Chapter XVI　War

August 1st, 1914.

“Dear Irène, dear Eve,

“Things seem to be going from bad to worse: we are expecting mobilization at any moment—I don't know if I shall be able to get away. Keep cool, be brave and calm. If there is no war, I shall come on Monday; if war comes, I shall remain here and send for you as soon as possible. Irène, you and I must try to make ourselves useful.”

August 2nd.

“Mobilization has begun and the Germans have entered France without a declaration of war. It will be difficult to get letters through for some time.

“Paris is calm and impressive in spite of the grief for the men going to the Front.”

August 6th.

“Brave little Belgium has not agreed to let them pass through without fighting. Everybody in France is hopeful that the struggle, though hard, will end in victory.

“Poland has been occupied by the Germans. What will remain of my country when they have finished with it? I have no news of my family.”

So wrote Marie to the children, who were on holiday in Brittany.

In Paris, Marie was extraordinarily alone. All her fellow-workers had gone to the war except one mechanic who had heart-disease and could not join up. Marie was ill and weak. But it did not enter her head to think of that or of the catastrophe that was happening to her work. She did did not follow the crowd of women who were offering to be nurses. As she had always done, she thought quickly and fiercely: where was there a gap to be filled with her work? The hospitals at the front, the hospitals behind the lines, were almost without X-ray appliances, were without that almost new and magic device by which a surgeon could see through men's flesh the shot or splinter of shell sitting fixed in the depths of a wound. X-rays had never been any business of Marie's; she had only been interested in them and had had a few lessons on them. That didn't matter. She would, with all speed, create X-ray stations. It took her only a few hours to make a list of all the X-ray apparatus available in Paris and get it distributed to the hospitals. Then she collected any scientists who could or would use it, and distributed them also. Paris was provided for.

But the wounded, pouring back, pouring back in their thousands, in ambulances from the front to field hospitals, what was to become of them? Marie did not hesitate. Time was everything. She turned for money to the U. F. de F. —the Union of the Women of France—and produced the first “Radiologic Car.” It was an ordinary motor-car with the electricity for the X-ray run off the engine. That travelling X-ray station went from hospital to hospital in the poor, shattered, beautiful Marne country, enabling all the wounded of the greatest battle of the war to be quickly examined, safely operated on, and many, many of them to be saved, who without it would have died. But before the battle of the Marne the Germans were fighting only a few miles from Paris. Would they get through? Would they take Paris? What ought Marie to do? Her children were alone in Brittany. Ought she to go to them? Ought she to go with the medical corps when they evacuated Paris? No. She was going to stay in Paris, whatever happened; because, as she put it, “Perhaps if I am on guard in the new buildings of the Pierre Curie laboratory the Germans will not dare to sack it; whereas if no one is there, for certain they will leave nothing.” Headstrong, unyielding Marie hated the mere thought of any flight. To be afraid was to help the enemy. Not for anything in the world would she give the enemy the satisfaction of entering a deserted Pierre Curie Institute! But if Marie wasn't leaving Paris, her one precious gramme of Radium had to go, and there was no one to escort it but herself.

She put on her black alpaca dust coat, packed her night things, and with a small, extraordinarily heavy packet of lead, took train for Bordeaux. Cramped on a wooden bench in the crowded train, with her Radium at her feet, she gazed out of the window at the fields under the burning early September sun and at the roads crowded with unending cars and carts fleeing always, fleeing to the west.

At Bordeaux, on the far western sea, Marie stood on the platform, hour after hour, with her little packet of lead still at her feet, the packet which was too heavy for a woman to carry and too valuable to be left alone. There were no porters and no taxis and no bedrooms. She smiled as she wondered if she would have to stand there all night. But she was rescued at last by a fellow-traveller, who helped to find her a bed and to house the Radium safely in a bank.

On the next morning she returned to Paris. In the evening she had been an unnoticed traveller in a mighty crowd of safety seekers, but in the morning she was stared at by a crowd who had collected to see the strange marvel of “the woman returning up there!” The woman returning up there was glad of the chance to tell them that there was no danger “up there,” that Paris would not fall, that its inhabitants would be in no danger. The woman returning up there, however, was hungry. She had had nothing to eat since the night before, and the troop train she was on merely crept towards Paris when it wasn't standing at ease in the fields. She was very glad of a bit of bread a friendly soldier gave her out of his haversack. And then when she reached lovely, threatened Paris, the joyful news came out to meet her that the enemy was held on the Marne.

Without a moment's rest, Marie rushed to the headquarters of the “National Help Society” to see what next she should do.

“Lie down, woman!” exclaimed its President, Appell, “Lie down and rest.'” She obeyed, but only while she discussed her future work. “With those great eyes of hers in her pale face,” said Appell, “she is nothing more than a flame.”

Then came the turn of the “little Curies.” Marie had two children in Brittany, but to the soldiers of France she was mother to the X-ray motor-cars that soon began to meet them everywhere as they were brought wounded from fighting. Marie fitted those cars out one by one at the laboratory and wrung from unwilling officials all they needed. She who had once been timid, bearded any lion in any den on behalf of her little Curies. She extracted “passes” from one, “pass- words” from another, visas from another— money from the rich, smart motor-cars from the kindly—“I'll return them,” said she, “if they are still returnable at the end of the war—I will indeed.”

A big Renault, more like a lorry than a car, she took for herself. Then began a life of outdoor adventure.

In her room in Paris the telephone bell rang. A big convoy of wounded needed an X-ray station. She went out to her car, painted grey for war with a big red cross; she carefully checked over her apparatus; then, while the soldier chauffeur filled up, she put on her dark coat, with red cross arm-band, and her soft, round, faded hat, and climbed into the seat beside the driver, with her old, yellow, cracked and sun-scorched leather bag. And then, at all the speed the slow old car could muster, she went, wind-whipped or rain-whipped, in the day or in the night, and without lights, into the war at places whose names are known for the fierceness of the fighting—Amiens, Ypres, Verdun.

Sentinels stopped them, enquired, passed them. The Renault found the hospital. Madame Curie chose her room and had the cases carried into it; then rapidly she put the apparatus together while others unrolled the electric cable that connected the car's dynamo with the apparatus. The chauffeur started up and Marie verified the current. Then she placed each thing in its right place, her protective gloves and glasses, her special pencils and lead wires for localising metal; then she darkened the room, with curtains if there were any or with bedclothes if there weren't. Meanwhile a second room had been got ready as a photographic dark room.

In half an hour from the time of her arrival, everything was ready, including the surgeon. Then began the long procession of the stretchers with the wounded; one after the other, one after the other, men in great pain, they came. Marie arranged her apparatus; the surgeon looked and saw among the shapes of bones or organs a dark fragment of this or that.

Sometimes an assistant wrote notes about the position of the metal at the surgeon's dictation for a later serious operation. Sometimes then and there the surgeon was able to operate and watch, while he worked, his pincers advancing into the wound and getting round some part of the bony skeleton to seize a piece of shrapnel.

The hours, and sometimes the days, passed. As long as there were wounded, Marie stayed in the dark room. Before she left the hospital, she had made her plans for installing a permanent X-ray theatre in it. In a few days, having moved heaven and earth to get it, she returned with the new apparatus and a new radiologist, whom she had conjured from nobody knew where.

In that way she personally installed 200 X-ray stations in hospitals, which, with her twenty cars treated more than a million wounded. That was great work for one woman.

But we mustn't fancy her, when she drove, always sitting beside a chauffeur in luxury on her front seat, protected from the weather. There were times when she had to do the driving and swing the mighty starting handle. She could congratulate herself when she hadn't more than two punctures, in a journey on those roads covered with splinters of every kind. She was often changing wheels with those same delicate, radium-burnt fingers in the terrible frost and wet that marked the war years. Sometimes she might be seen frowning a scientist's frown as she cleaned, most scientifically, an unfamiliar carburettor. Some-times she was doing porter's work, lifting heavy cases, when all men were in the fighting line.

Once she was angry! Her chauffeur, taking a curve too quickly, upset the car into a ditch and buried Marie under all the loose cases. Not that Marie mattered. It was the thought of what had happened to her delicate apparatus that made her furious. But she laughed aloud from under the cases when she heard the young man running round and round the car trying to catch a glimpse of her and asking, “Madame, are you dead? Madame, are you dead?”

Sometimes she forgot her breakfast or her dinner. Always she slept anywhere—in a bed if she could get one, under the stars if only they were available. It was natural to her, who had lived hard in her youth, to find herself a soldier of the Great War.

But that soldierly work was not all Marie's work. When She had time, she packed all the instruments in her old laboratory and had them taken to Pierre Curie's new laboratory. There she unpacked them and gradually fitted out the new home of science. She went to Bordeaux and brought back her gramme of Radium, and every week she “drew” its emanations from it, enclosed them in tubes and sent them for use to the hospitals.

With the tremendous increase of X-ray work, radiologists were needed. Marie taught and trained them in the new Radium Institute. Some of them were stupid and clumsy and hard to teach; but with infinite patience and sympathy she encouraged them and helped them, till they, too, could make a success of the delicate work. In that teaching she was helped by Irène, who was 17 by then. Irène had been studying radiology while still at the Sorbonne, and her mother had not thought her too young to work in the war hospitals.

In two years they trained 150 radiology nurses.

As if all that were not enough, Marie visited Belgian hospitals. Sometimes in hospitals where she was a stranger, fashionable ladies, who were nursing, mistook the shabby, poor-looking woman for a cleaner and treated her with scant courtesy. Marie didn't mind; she only felt more warmed and comforted by the charm of a certain nurse and a certain silent soldier who contentedly worked with her at d'Hoogstade: Elizabeth the Queen and Albert the King of the Belgians. She herself had lost all her cold distant manner and was just charming and infinitely gentle and encouraging with the wounded soldiers. She used to explain to the ignorant, scared peasants that her strange apparatus would not hurt them any more than a camera would. She was gay again.

She never spoke of herself, never said she was feeling tired, never felt frightened of shells falling round her. With all that work she went on daily, as if it were the most natural thing in the world.

But she longed for peace, longed for all that mad cruelty to come to an end! For her, with all the rest of the world, November 11th, 1918, was the happiest day that had been, when the cannon shot that marked the Armistice surprised her in her laboratory. Instantly she rushed out with her assistant, Mlle. Klein, to buy flags that the Institute might join in the glory. But there wasn't a flag in Paris! They had to make do with lengths of three colours which they sewed together. Then Marie took the old Renault and joined the wild throng in the streets, reckless of the fact that she had ten uninvited passengers on the wings and on the roof.

Who can guess the joy of the days that came after?

For Marie, it was not only her France that was free from the overwhelming terror, but her Poland also. Poland at last was free and in-dependent. She wrote to her brother:

“So we, ‘born in servitude and chained in our cradles,’ have seen the resurrection of our country.”

Chapter XVII　At Home

MARIE was at home again in a big old-fashioned flat on the Seine Quay side. The Seine has two islands in the heart of Paris: the Ile de la Cité, the ship-shaped isle, the oldest part of Paris, the old, with its sombre, beautiful and famous buildings; and the Ile St. Louis, old too and more lonely, where Marie lived on the Quai de Bethune. Two centuries before, the houses in the Rue de Bethune had been inhabited by dukes and gentlemen of the court. Marie's flat was a rambling place of corridors and many stairs. Her rooms were immense and lofty and empty. She had never learnt how to be rich or how to draw comfort around herself. Her few pieces of mahogany furniture stood about anyhow on the wide spaces of the slippery polished floor! She and Irène shivered and didn't notice it in the icy cold and bareness, but Eve spent her pocket money on attempts to make her own huge den cosy and elegant. One room was beautiful, Marie's study with its severe bookcases, its portrait of Pierre and its vase of flowers; and all the rooms had the beauty of light, for the windows were high and curtainless and they looked out on to the view that all the artists paint: the broad sunlit Seine with its busy little ships and colourful heavy barges and the towers of Notre Dame in the distance.

Marie had chosen the island for its loneliness and its quiet, but she seemed not to mind that, in fact, her house was full of noises. Eve's scales re-sounded on the piano hour by hour, a cat woke the echoes galloping down the corridors, the door bell clanged and the telephone rang through the emptiness, while the raucous syrens of the tugs came in from the river.

By eight o'clock every morning Marie's energetic, rapid footsteps, warned Irène and Eve that the busy day had begun. Any day for the next sixteen years was something like this: At eight-fortyfive three blasts of a motor horn told Marie that her little car was at the door. She hastily snatched her hat and coat and ran downstairs, because she would never think of keeping her chauffeur waiting more than three minutes. She began by having the handy man at the Institute to drive her, and when she took to a regular chauffeur, the poor man wept for grief that someone else should drive Marie. She drove across the Tournelle bridge and across the busy quays to the Latin quarter, where from the beginning of history, gay and rowdy students have lived in proverbial happiness and poverty and where, now-a-days, all the great learned institutes and buildings stand.

In the Rue Pierre Curie, Marie found herself at the entrance to the Institute of Radium. There was a crowd in the hall. Every morning there was a crowd in the hall and Marie called it the Soviet. Her students from this or that department always came to catch her before she went to her work, so that they should not trespass on her time, they said. They had a particular question to ask her or something to show her; or they hoped that Marie, overnight, had got out a problem for them. She often had. “Oh, Mr. So-and-So, your solution wouldn't work, but I have another for you…” Marie turned from one difficult piece of work to another, the crowd increased, each one bringing a difficult conundrum. Marie seemed not to mind what mental gymnastics they expected of her. Problems were often put to her in broken French or broken English, which added to the difficulty in hand. The Institute was quite a tower of Babel with all the languages of the East as well as all the tongues of the West. Marie tells a tale of her Chinese student who talked with her in English: he was so polite that even when she was wrong and he knew it, he had to agree with her and she had to use the very best of her brain to guess the silent contradiction which was at the back of his mind. She said that she was ashamed of her own manners in the presence of her Eastern students: “They are so much more civilized than we.”

The hall session often seemed unending and Marie would have to sit to it and, as there were no chairs, to sit on the stairs. It is a charming picture to think of her squatting on the lowest stair teaching her tall students at their feet. She was chief of the laboratory; she had read every book on anything to do with Radium in five languages; she was still inventing new techniques; she seemed to work by magic; her pupils could trust her guidance entirely. She was both bold and prudent.

One by one the students would go off to their particular experiments. Perhaps one who had something to show would take Marie with him; perhaps she would at last find herself free to go to her own laboratory and do her own work.

At mid-day she walked home to lunch but she still discussed Physics at the table with Irène. Eve sometimes felt out of it. Her mother and sister talked of BB prime and BB squared and as, in French, BB is pronounced bélé, which means baby, Eve was left wondering what a squared baby and a prime baby could possibly be.

But, in 1926, Irène married a brilliant young scientist called Joliot and Eve had the conversation to herself.

“Darling, you do the talking,” said Marie. “What are they doing in the world?” And Eve would talk to her about everything, for everything interested her, especially simple and childish things. She liked to hear how fast Eve drove, or what the baby said, when Irène's baby began to say things, or what people thought of the new Fascists.

“Ah!” said Marie, if by chance anyone praised a dictator, “I have lived under oppression. You haven't. You don't understand how happy you are to live in a free country.” And if anyone upheld the right of a Government to kill a rebel, she said: “You will never convince me that to guillotine Lavoisier served any purpose.”

After lunch the car would fetch her again and perhaps she would go to the flower market to buy her common garden flowers or wild ones if she could get them, for she never liked smart, greenhouse things. Or perhaps she had an appointment in the Luxembourg gardens with a very important personage, her baby granddaughter, Helène. She would sit and play at making sand-pies with her till it was time to go to the afternoon's session of the Academy of Medicine. There Marie was the only woman and her seat was next to her friend Dr. Roux, who had been Pasteur's most devoted disciple.

After the Academy, Marie went back to the laboratory and worked till dinner time on ordinary days; but sometimes till 2.0 in the morning if her experiments needed it.

Sometimes the seriousness of the place was disturbed by a tea party given in honour of some student who had become a doctor of science. Then scientific glasses became tea cups and glass rods served as spoons and the party closed with an address by Marie in which she congratulated the new doctor. The two happiest of those teas were those which celebrated Irène's doctorate and that of her husband, Frédéric Joliot. In 1934 those two made a great discovery, nothing less than artificial radio-activity. They bombarded aluminium and other substances with the rays of Radium and transformed them into new radioactive substances which had never been known before and which became sources from which Radium could be drawn. Scientists saw that a time might come when substances could be manufactured to do the work of Radium the rare. What a wonderful thing that would be, for across the garden, opposite the Radium Institute, was the building in which Radium was helping to cure cancer by the method known as Curietherapy. Radium was necessary and Radium was very rare.

Then there were the letters. Think of the letters of an important person! Fortunately a secretary opened the thousands of them— letters from thoughtless people asking for autographs, which they didn't get; letters asking foolish questions; letters from advertisers, from beggars. And in the great piles just a letter here and there that needed an answer.

Lastly, Marie had her lessons to give. Those were the things she hated. On a Monday and a Wednesday she was sick with nervousness from dawn till five o'clock, becaue she had to stand in the little amphitheatre and address some thirty students at once.

In those years she was threatened with blindness. The doctors told her that she must put up with being nearly blind for two or three years till she could have an operation. Probably they never dreamed what that meant to her. She wanted to work and she hated sympathy. Whatever happened, she did not want other people to know about her eyes. Eve had to book her glasses at the oculist's as those of Madame Carré. If she had a student's paper to correct, she made him bring it to her and then answer cleverly put questions on it, so that in that way she knew what he had written. She thought of every clever device to conceal her misfortune and the people who guessed pretended to notice nothing. That was to be truly kind. After her four operations she had to teach her eyes to work again. They would never work as they had worked, but her courage did not fail; she made them work.

But let us get back to Marie's day. We left her having late dinner with Eve. After dinner Eve had to go out and Marie, who was tired, lay on her sofa and watched her daughter dress. “Horrible heels, Eve! You will never make me believe that women were made for walking on stilts.”

“And what's this new fashion of bare backs? Bare in front is bearable, but these kilometres of bare back! Still the dress is pretty enough. Turn round and let me see how pretty you are.” Marie looked at her daughter with consternation: “I haven't any objection on principle to all this daubing. I know it has always been done. In ancient Egypt women invented worse things. I can say only one thing: I think it is hideous. You are cruel to your eyebrows and you daub your lips for no reason.”

“But, Mé, I really look better so.”

“Better! ! ! Listen, to console myself I shall come and kiss you in bed to-morrow morning before you have had time to put these horrors on your face.”

When Eve had gone, Marie, in her armchair, read a little poetry or a few pages of a favourite novel, but not for more than an hour. The floor was her place—the floor that gave her room to spread all her Physics papers around her and to work out her problems till two in the morning.

So Eve found her mother when she came in, a mother so absorbed in work that she did not notice her but went on counting, half aloud as she used to do at school and in Polish.

Chapter XVIII　Abroad

IT was May, 1920. The sun was hot. The chest-nuts in Paris were all in bloom, and Marie was, as usual, working. But an event was about to break in on her work; a most surprising event that she didn't expect in the least.

Marie never saw newspaper men, still less newspaper women. She hated being interviewed; she hated publicity. She had neat slips printed to say politely and firmly to strangers who wanted to meet her: “Madame Curie regrets…”

But people with Irish names who live in America sometimes have an odd little way of finding a right, irresistible word, and there was a certain Mrs. Meloney who had written to Marie: “My doctor father always used to say that it is quite impossible to exaggerate the littleness of human creatures. But for twenty years you have been great in my eyes, Madame, and I want to see you, only for a few minutes.” That was another way of saying: “Might a very little cat look at a queen?” and Marie, breaking all her own rules, said “Yes.”

So Mrs. Meloney waited on that May morning in Marie's tiny waiting-room at the Radium Institute, and this is how she described what happened:

“The door opened, and I saw come in a pale, timid woman with the saddest face I have ever seen. She had on a black cotton dress. Her splendid, patient, gentle face had the absent-minded look of people who study much. Suddenly, I felt that I was a mere intruder; I became even shyer than Madame Curie. I had been a professional reporter for more than twenty years and yet I couldn't manage to ask a single question of this defenceless woman in black cotton.”

It was Marie who set the reporter at ease by talking about America and Radium. She told her that America had fifty grammes of Radium, and she knew exactly how many grammes were in each town. “And how many has France?” asked Mrs. Meloney. “My laboratory possesses a little more than a gramme.”

“You have only a gramme of radium?”

“I? I haven't any. This gramme belongs to my laboratory.”

Then Mrs. Meloney began to speak of patents. She imagined, she said, that Marie must be drawing much money from those who used her methods of producing Raduim.

“Radium ought not to enrich anyone,” said Marie. “It is an element. It belongs to everybody.”

Mrs. Meloney must have felt then that the whole world ought to give Marie a present in return for what she had given the world. She said suddenly, “If you could choose out of the whole world the thing you would have, what would it be?”

Marie hesitated, “I need,” she said, “a gramme of radium to go on with my researches. But I can't buy it. Radium is too dear for me.”

It was then that Mrs. Meloney determined that America should give Marie Curie a gramme of Radium. She went home and tried to persuade ten rich women to give £3,000 each. But she could find only three. Then she turned from the few rich to the many poor. All the women of America should join together to give Marie the gift. In less than a year she wrote to Marie: “We have the money. Your Radium is yours.”

But America had grown excited over the collection. Soon all the girls and women had heard of the Madame Curie Radium Fund; everyone wanted to see Madame Curie. But Marie hated crowds. She did not want to go, but she had never before been offered so lovable a gift. Still she began to make excuses. She couldn't be separated from her daughters. That didn't worry hospitable America; they invited the girls, and told Marie that the gramme of Radium would be presented to her by the President himself.

So Marie, Irène and Eve packed all their clothes into one single trunk and set sail in the Olympic's most luxurious cabin, for America willed it so. France gave them a great send-off with a gala performance at the Opera, in which the greatest actors, Sarah Bernhardt, and the famous Guitrys, took part. Only the Atlantic refused to join in honouring Science; the ocean remained morose, dark and uncivilised, and encouraged Marie to dream with longing of the blue sunlit seas at home.

As the Olympic docked, Mrs. Meloney, who had travelled with her, brought Marie from her cabin to meet a real American welcome, and only those who have experienced it can imagine the warm-hearted sincerity of it. The crowd had been waiting five hours to greet her whom they named, “The benefactor of the human race.” It was summer; the skies were blue above the splendid white skyscrapers. The quay was colourful with the flags of Poland, France, and America. Students, girl-guides, three hundred women representing the Polish women of America, waved red and white roses before her. She sat, rather like a child trying to be good, in an armchair on the upper deck, while Mrs. Meloney took away her hat and her handbag and posed her for the photographers. “Your head to the right, please, Madame Curie.” “A little more this way please... !”

America went mad with welcome. The Americans were determined that the world should see through their eyes that a scientist is perhaps the greatest human-being. Their hearts were captured by Marie's love for pure science, by her scorn of profit, and by her conviction that to serve is the true purpose for which men live.

Nothing that they could invent to honour her was neglected. They wanted to welcome her everywhere and forgot the long distances of their great country. They offered her banquets where the guests were five hundred, and forgot the long hours. They offered her titles of honour by the bagful, and forgot that in her own country she refused them all. They asked her to university ceremonies and were surprised that she had no cap and gown. They offered her flowers grown especially for her, and forgot that she preferred them wild. Love is often like that; but Marie, though tired, understood. The only thing she could not tolerate was the magnificent university gown they made for her, for to expect her to wear silk was just a little too much, because silk irritated her fingers that Radium itself had injured.

Marie's first visits were to the women's colleges. Everywhere she went, girls in white made hedges to the roads or ran in immense clusters across fields to greet her carriage. And above the white masses were always the coloured streamers of the flags. At an immense gathering in New York the university women passed in long file before her, bowing and presenting alternately the Lily of France and the Rose of America. In another gathering of ambassadors and the great of many Lands, at which she was given the “Freedom of New York”, the most famous person after herself was Paderewski, whom long ago, when he was a struggling pianist, she had encouraged with her clapping.

Then came the great event: the presentation of the gramme of Radium.

The White House at Washington was prepared for the fête. The President of the United States and all the great people of America were there to meet Marie, but Radium itself was absent. It was too dangerous and too precious to sit about on tables and be handled by a president. It stayed safely in the factory and was present only by proxy. On a table in the east room during the ceremony stood a Radium casket containing tubes of imitation Radium.

At four o'clock the double doors were thrown open and the procession entered, Marie on the arm of President Harding.

In his address, the President reminded the guests that Marie was not only a great scientist, but a devoted wife and mother. She had done the daily work of a man and all her womanly duties in addition.

At the end of his speech, he gave her a rolled parchment, the deed of gift, and hung the tiny gold key of the real casket round her neck. Then, in the blue room, Marie sat while all the guests passed in procession before her and shook hands with Irène and Eve, because she herself was too tired.

So Marie possessed a gramme of Radium! By no means. On the evening before the ceremony, Mrs. Meloney had shown her the deed of gift and she had insisted, then and there, though it was late at night, that a lawyer should be sent for to give the gramme legally to her laboratory. When Mrs. Meloney suggested that the week after would do, Marie exclaimed: “I might die tonight!” From that evening her gramme was just something to work with which belonged to the laboratory.

There were other visits to make. America, full of penitence at having tired its guest, tried to spare her fatigue in every possible way. Sometimes they arranged for her to arrive at the station before the one at which she was expected, and when the excited people found out what had been done, there was a stream of cars along the road to meet the traveller. Sometimes Marie had to get out of the train on the wrong side, jump down to the rails and walk across them, which could not have been really restful. Sometimes Irène and Eve were accepted as their mother's understudies, and nobody smiled when staid professors spoke to sixteen-year-old Eve of her “magnificent discoveries” and “her lifetime of labour.”

But Marie was present herself when the Poles fêted her in Chicago. To them she was a symbol of their distant birthplace and her triumph was Poland's. Men and women, their faces wet with tears of joy, tried to kiss her feet or the hem of her dress.

On the Olympic, on which she sailed home at the end of June, was the Radium itself, locked in behind the complicated locks of the ship's safe. But in her letters, it was not of Radium she wrote, but of a little touch of gladness in her heart because she had been able to win just a little more American friendliness for France and Poland.

America's joy in her had taught Marie how much she meant to the great world. She realised that her mere name, her mere presence, could help the things she cared for and loved. So she began to travel more and face ceremonies and congresses. She became known the world over. She visited South America, Spain, England and Czechoslovakia. Even in China, though she did not go there, there was a portrait of her in a temple of Confucius side by side with the Buddhas and the Emperors of the Celestial Empire.

In all her travels she enjoyed the odd things she saw. She liked the fish that jump out of the water and fly through the air and, at the

Equator, it amused her that she lost her shadow, and she loved the wild flowers, new and old, that met her in strange places.

But apart from the things that she merely looked at and loved, there were the other loved things that she journeyed to fight for. Like everyone else who had served mankind, she hated war. She had been willing in war to do a soldier's work in defence of her country; but in peace, she was eager to serve in preventing future wars. She refused to take time from research to belong to Soceities, but she made one exception: she allowed herself to be nominated by the Council of the League of Nations as a member of the society of men and women who decided to use their brains to find ways of getting different nations to work together. That Society was called “The International Committee on Intellectual Co-operation.” Marie did not belong to it merely to talk. She set to work to do definite things. One was to get scientific people of all nations to use the same scientific terms and to make complete lists of all the scientific books and discoveries all the world over, so that every student could know what work had already been done.

Next, Marie wanted a scheme to help any scientific genius who might, in any nation, be too poor to develop its gifts. It is horrible waste, she thought, to throw away a genius. She gave all her strength to help to create a world in which freedom, peace and science were ever more and more. Now that the Radium Institute in Paris was working, Marie determined to build a Radium Institute in Warsaw. Her sister Bronia, who was in Poland, launched the appeal. All Poland was soon covered with placards; all the post-offices sold stamps with Marie's picture; postcards invited everyone to “buy a brick to build the Marie-Sklovodska-Curie Institute,” and, on them in Marie's writing, were the words: “My most ardent desire is the creation of a Radium Institute in Warsaw.”

1925, Marie was able to go to Warsaw for the foundation of the Institute. The President of the Republic laid the first brick, Marie the second. Laughingly, he asked her if she remembered the travelling pillow she had lent him when he was poor. She replied: “Yes, and you forgot to return it.” She remembered, too, that the famous actor who complimented her from the stage was none other than Monsieur Kotarbinski, for whom Manya had once plaited a crown of wild flowers.

But a Radium Institute was a queer place without Radium. Mrs. Meloney had again to persuade the United States to give Marie another gramme, and again Marie went to New York. On that occasion it was to thank the Americans in the name of Poland. She stayed at the White House and found it very amusing to see it full of elephants, large elephants, small elephants, minute elephants, white elephants. As a parting gift she was given two elephants, a little ivory one and an almost invisible one. Elephants were the badge of the governing party. With her two and the Radium, she returned to Warsaw to see the Institute begin its work of curing the sick.

As she had done when she was a little girl, she wandered by the great Vistula and wrote about it:

“The river winds, broad and lazy, gray near at hand and blue as heaven in the distance. Adorable sandbanks, sparkling in the sun, show here and there and mark the capricious course of the stream. At the edge of these banks, strips of more brilliant light show where the waters grow deep. I simply have to wander by these light-filled magnificent shores…There is a song which says: ‘In this Polish water there is such charm that those who love it once, love it for ever.’ To me that is true. This great river has a deep inexplicable fascination.”

Chapter XIX　Holiday

THERE was a place in Brittany. Pink granite cliffs and rocks ran out into a blue, clear sea that was always calm, because a reef of a thousand islands kept out the Atlantic tumult of the waves. There, in a dip among the rocks was Larcouëst, a group of fishermen's cottages, not even a village, a mere hamlet, where the Breton fishwives went out and in with their wide, white linen bonnets protecting their faces from the wind.

High up on the moor, in the clear path of all the winds and looking like a lighthouse, was Marie's little holiday home, a wisp of a little poor cottage with a glorious view. Marie was a nobody in Larcouëst. The king of the country was a little old hunchback man with smiling eyes behind spectacles, and the palace where he lived was a long, low cottage covered from ground to roof with virginiacreeper, wild red fuchsia, and travellers' joy. It stood in an orchard and was called Taschen-Vihan, which in Breton means “the little orchard field.” Its door was always open, except when the east wind blew, and all the old king's subjects—Marie and Irène and Eve and Frédéric Joliot and children and babies and scientists and writers—in fact all the people who loved him and everybody loved him, visited him all day long and never gave a thought to the fact that he was one of the most learned historians who ever lived, none other than Charles Seignobos whom everybody knows. He had discovered Larcouëst, and every summer the wisest, most learned people of Paris went to make holiday there.

Every morning, Marie in a washed-out linen hat, an old skirt, sandals and the black reefer jacket that all Larcouëstians wore, fishermen and ladies alike, used to take the steep path that led hither and thither down from her moor and ended among the flaming flowers of Taschen's garden.

“Good-morning, Madame Curie,” called Seignobos. “Good-morningt!” echoed the fifteen or so others who were lying about in the grass or the flowers, looking, in their queer rigout, like a company of gypsies.

Marie slung her rucksack on the ground and sat beside it. Larcouëst, like everywhere else, had its severe social distinctions; but they were of a different kind from those in most villages. In Larcouëst people of the lowest rank were called Philistines. They were simply strangers who didn't belong to Larcouëst. Next above them came the people whom you could just know, the Elephants. They were friends, but unfortunate landlubbers, people who were not as comfortable in and on the sea as they were on the land. They were to be pitied, but they could be improved. Above them came the honourable of the place, the Sailors, and then in distant, worship-able dignity, were the Crocodiles, those to whom all the arts of the sea were known. Not only could they swim, they could “crawl” and manage sails and oars among the stiffest currents. Marie had never been a Philistine and had little hope of ever being a crocodile. She had begun as an elephant and had risen to be a sailor.

At a word from Seignobos, the sailors of the day loosed from the fleet of two sailing boats and six rowing boats which were moored at the quay, the pinnace and the dinghy, and sculled them to the rock landing-stage.

“Aboard! aboard!” ordered Seignobos. “I'll row stroke, Madame Curie will row bow; Perrin and Borel to the oars, and Francis, you steer.”

The crews were all professors. The white and green boat went round in a circle, for one pulled too hard. The steersman called his oarsmen to attention: “Bow is not following stroke.” Marie blushed and timed her stroke. The sea rippled under the sun, and the mariners sang:

Three little boys sail for the isles!
Who sail with a boat-load of joys
For the isles, are three little boys. …

At the end of the third song, it was time to change the oars because stronger rowers were needed to take the boats through the current to Roch Vras, the violet-coloured desert island where the Larcouëstians bathed. The men took as their dressing-room the shore which they shared with the brown gulls; the women had a rock chamber carpeted with soft green grass.

Marie was first into the deep transparent water. She was a good swimmer even if she could not do the crawl. In the water she was young again, her gray hairs were hidden under her cap, and no-one could see her wrinkles. She was slender and graceful and quick and deliciously proud of her skill. “Aren't I much better than Borel?” she called to Irène, and Irène, who was no flatterer, could truthfully answer: “Oh much better, Mé. There is no comparison.”

After the bath, Marie sunbathed and ate a crisp little loaf. “It's a good life,” she would murmur, or, “Isn't it lovely?” No-one, not even Marie Curie, was allowed to say anything more about the beauty of Larcouëst. It was one of the things that were not done. Larcouëst was the loveliest place in the world. Everybody knew it and so it was not necessary to say so.

At mid-day the boats went home to the songs of the crews. Marie, bare-foot and bare-legged, her sandals in her hand, picked up her skirts and waded to the shore through the black mud where the white gulls sat in crowds.

The company lunched in their own homes, but most of them returned to Taschen at two to sail in the yacht Wild Rose. The yachts and the boats all belonged to Seignobos. Everything belonged to him, but he was one of those people who liked their possessions to be the property of all their friends. Marie did not sail; she found sitting in a sailing yacht too slow an occupation. Instead, she sat at home in her lighthouse correcting science papers; or she took her spade, her fork and her secateurs and gardened. Her reeds and brambles drew her blood; her unexpected rocks twisted her ankle, or she crushed her own fingers with her hammer; but she paid no attention to small matters. At six she bathed again and went to Taschen to keep the oldest old lady company and watch for the return of the Wild Rose. Its sails, golden in the setting sun, appeared just before dinner, and its wild happy crew came back to Taschen, the girls' hair decorated with the carnations Seignobos gave them each day from his garden.

After dinner everyone went back to Taschen through the everopen door. Perhaps they played games, simple games like word-making or charades. Sometimes there was a ball. An accordion played the music for old-fashioned dances, and everybody danced together—scientists and peasants, servants and masters.

Sometimes on fine nights, Marie and Irène and Eve went armin-arm for walks in the dark along mysterious, winding paths by the wine-dark sea. Did some sudden wind, bringing the booming of great breakers from beyond the reefs, remind Marie that, like the sea, her Radium was radiant yet dangerous? Larcouëst is near to Paimpol. The Larcouëstians played all day with a sunfit sea; but the men of Paimpol were the men of the Iceland fisheries who knew best the dark and bitter strangeness of the sea.

Every year in her holidays Marie played with the glittering, innocent sea. In her worktime, she played with Radium. She breathed in its rays. It burnt her hands, for she disdained the leaden shields which she made other people wear. It did strange, mysterious things with her blood. It puzzled the greatest doctors of France.

It was not till one summer day, July the 4th, 1934, when Marie Curie lay dead of an unknown illness at Sancellemoz in the mountains, that the doctors guessed that she had died from too great friendliness with her great discovery, Radium.

玛丽亚的孩子

有一个樵夫和他的妻子住在一座大森林前面，他们只有一个三岁的女儿。他们穷得连每天要吃的面包也没有了，不知道怎样才能养活自己的孩子。一天早晨，樵夫忧心忡忡地走出家门，到森林里干活。他正砍柴的时候，眼前忽然出现一个高大美丽的女子，头戴星光灿烂的冠冕，她对他说：“我是圣母玛丽亚，耶稣基督的母亲。你这么贫苦，把孩子给我吧，我要带走她，做她的母亲，照料她。”樵夫遵命，把孩子领来交给圣母玛丽亚，圣母玛丽亚就带着她到天上去了。在天堂里，小姑娘生活得很幸福，她吃糖面包，喝甜牛奶，穿的衣服是金子做的，小天使们和她一起玩。她长到了十四岁，有一天，圣母玛丽亚把她叫到跟前，对她说：“好孩子，我要做一次长途旅行，你要保管好开天堂十三扇门的钥匙。其中的十二扇门你都可以打开，进去看看里面的美妙景象，而唯独第十三扇门你不能打开！要当心，不要去开那扇门，不然就会大难临头。”小姑娘答应听她的话。圣母玛丽亚走后，她就开始看天国的住房：每天打开一处住所的房门，一直到十二所住房全看遍了。每一所住房里都坐着一个使徒，沐浴在一片灿烂的光辉里。看到所有这一切神奇美妙的景象后，小姑娘很高兴，一直陪伴她的小天使们也同她一样高兴。现在只剩下不许打开的那扇门了。她非常想知道那里面究竟藏着什么东西，她对小天使们说：“我不想把这扇门完全打开，也不进去，我只想把门开个小缝，往里面看上一眼。”

“啊，别开，别开！”小天使们说，“那是罪孽，圣母玛丽亚禁止你开这扇门，你开了会大难临头的。”小姑娘默不作声，她心中的好奇之火非但未熄灭，而且在啮噬着她的心，使她不得安宁。有一次，小天使们都到外面去了，她心想：“现在就我一个人在这里，可以进去看看，我进去看了谁也不会知道的。”她找出那把钥匙，一拿到手上，就把钥匙插进锁眼里，插进去后就转动钥匙。门一下子敞开，她看见烈火灵辉中坐着“三位一体”[1]。她站了一会儿，惊讶地打量着一切，随后用一根手指稍微接触一下火光，手指立刻变成了金色。她顿时惊恐万分，使劲关上门，拔腿就跑。她怎么也无法减轻心中的恐惧，一颗心怦怦直跳；无论她怎么擦洗，都无法去除手指上的黄金。

没过多久，圣母玛丽亚旅行归来了。她把小姑娘叫来，要她交回天国的钥匙。她递给她那串钥匙，圣母注视着她的眼睛，说：“你也开了第十三扇门了？”

“没有。”她回答说。圣母把手放在小姑娘心口上，感到她的心怦怦直跳，知道她违背她的戒律，开了那扇门，于是又问一遍：“你真的没打开过那扇门？”

“没有。”小姑娘再次回答。这时圣母玛丽亚看见她因为触到天火而变成金子的手指，知道她分明有罪过，便第三次问她：“真的没开过？”

“没有。”小姑娘第三次这样回答。

于是圣母玛丽亚说：“你不听我的话，并且还撒谎；你不配继续留在天堂。”

于是姑娘坠入了深沉的睡梦中，一觉醒来，发现自己已经躺在尘世荒野之中。她想喊，喊不出声音；想跑开，但无论向哪个方向跑，总被带刺的树篱拦住，无法穿越过去。她被困在荒野里，她站在一棵空心的古树下，只得把这棵树当作自己的住所。黑夜来临，她爬进树洞里面睡觉，暴风雨天气，她在里面躲避风雨。这是多么悲惨的生活！每当她想起在天堂里的时光，就觉得当时的生活多么美妙，想起天使们和她一同嬉戏，她就伤心痛苦。草根和森林里的野莓是她唯一的食物，还得费力去寻找。秋天，她收集树上掉下的坚果和树叶，把它们搬进树洞。坚果是她冬天的食物。下雪结冰，她就像可怜的小动物一样爬到树叶堆里，免得挨冻。不久她的衣服就破烂不堪，一块块地从身上掉下来。当太阳又温暖地照耀万物时，她爬出树洞，坐在古树前面，长长的头发遮蔽了她整个身子，如同一件长大衣。就这样过了一年又一年，她感受了人世的悲凉和苦难。

春天，树木又披上了新绿。有一天，国王在森林里打猎，追逐一只小鹿，小鹿逃到包围着那一片林中荒野的灌木丛里。国王下马，披荆斩棘，开出一条路。他终于穿过了灌木丛，看见一位美丽绝伦的姑娘坐在树下，一头金发遮住她的全身。国王静静地站着，非常惊讶，把她打量一番，然后问她说：“你是谁？为什么坐在这荒凉的地方？”可是她没有回答，因为她张不开口。国王又说：“你愿意跟我去我的王宫里吗？”她微微点一点头。国王把她抱到马上，骑马带她回家。一到王宫，就让她穿上美丽的衣裳，什么东西都给她，而且给的很多。虽然她说不了话，但她美丽又温柔，国王由衷地爱她，不久便同她结婚了。

大约一年以后，王后生了一个儿子。当天夜里，她独自一人躺在床上，圣母玛丽亚出现在她面前，说：“如果你肯讲实话，承认开了那扇禁止打开的门，我就让你能张开口，还给你说话的能力。如果你不肯悔过，顽固抵赖，我就带走你新生的婴儿。”王后这时能开口说话，她说：“不，我没打开过那扇禁止打开的门。”于是圣母玛丽亚从她怀里抱走了初生的婴儿。第二天早晨，孩子不见了，人们窃窃私语，说王后是吃人的妖精，杀了自己的亲生儿子。这一切她都听到了，但她无法辩白，不过国王非常爱她，不相信这些话。

一年后，王后又生了一个儿子。夜里，圣母玛丽亚又来到宫中找她，说：“如果你肯承认开过那扇禁止打开的门，我就把孩子还给你，让你能开口说话。可是，如果你不悔改，继续否认，我就把这个初生的婴儿也带走。”王后仍然说：“不，我没有开过那扇禁止打开的门。”圣母从她怀里抱走婴儿，带他飞上了天。第二个孩子又失踪了，人们早晨纷纷大声议论，说孩子是被王后吞了，大臣们要求治她的罪。但国王非常爱她，不愿相信有这回事，并且下令要大臣们绝口不提此事，违令者要处以死刑。

又过了一年，王后生了一个漂亮的女儿。圣母玛丽亚第三次夜里出现在她面前，说：“跟我走。”拉着她的手，领她上天堂看她那两个大孩子，他们正在玩地球仪，见了她都笑了。王后非常高兴，圣母玛利亚说：“你的心还那么硬吗？如果你承认开过那扇禁止打开的门，我就把这两个孩子还给你。”可是王后第三次的回答仍然是：“不，我没有开过那扇禁止打开的门。”于是圣母又让她落到尘世，并且带走了她的第三个孩子。

第二天早晨，事情传开了，所有的人们都大声呼喊：“王后是个吃人精，一定要将她判刑！”国王无法再拒绝大臣们的要求，于是对她进行审判。她既不能回答讯问，又不能为自己辩护，便被判处在火刑柱上烧死。木柴堆放好了，她被绑在火刑柱上，四周火焰开始熊熊地燃烧。这时，骄傲的坚冰融化了，悔恨震撼了她的心灵，她心里想道：“要是在临死前还能让我承认开过那扇禁止打开的门，那就好了！”就在这时，她忽然能开口说话了，于是她高声叫喊：“是的，玛丽亚，我开过那扇门！”霎时间，天上降雨浇灭了烈焰，在她的上方，射出一道光，圣母玛丽亚降临，怀里抱着初生的女婴，两个男孩站在她两边。她和蔼地对她说：“谁忏悔和承认自己的罪孽，谁就会得到宽恕。”她把三个孩子交给王后，让她又能开口说话了，并赐予她终生幸福。

[1]在基督教中把圣父、圣子、圣灵称为三位一体。

忠诚的约翰内斯

从前有一个老国王，得了重病，他想：“我看来好不了了。”便说：“叫忠诚的约翰内斯进来。”忠诚的约翰内斯是他最心爱的侍从，因为他一生对国王忠贞不渝，所以大家都这么叫他。约翰来到床前，国王对他说：“忠诚的约翰内斯，我觉得我快要死了，唯一不放心的是我的儿子，他还年轻，有时遇事缺乏主见。你要答应我，教给他必须知道的一切，当他的养父，否则我死不瞑目。”忠诚的约翰内斯回答说：“我决不离开他，一定忠诚地为他效劳，即使牺牲自己的生命也在所不辞。”老国王说：“那我死也放心了。”接着又说：“我死后你要带他看看这整座宫殿，看宫中所有房间、大厅、金库和金库里的全部珍宝，但是不要让他看长廊尽头的那个房间，因为房间里面藏有金屋公主的塑像，他要是看见她的塑像，会对她产生热烈的爱情，会晕过去，会因她而陷入极大的危险。你要保护他，不要让这种事情发生。”忠诚的约翰内斯听了国王的话，再次把手伸给他，国王不再说话，头往枕头上一靠就去世了。

将老国王安葬之后，忠诚的约翰内斯对年轻的国王讲了他向临终的老国王许下的诺言，他说：“我一定信守诺言，像对老国王一样对你忠诚，即使牺牲自己的生命。”服丧期结束了，忠诚的约翰内斯对年轻的国王说：“现在是你看一看你的遗产的时候了：我要领你看一看你父王的宫殿。”于是他领着年轻的国王上上下下转遍各处，让他看了所有的珍宝财富、豪华宫室，唯独没打开那间收藏着危险的塑像的房间。那塑像安放在一开门就能见到的地方，制作精美绝伦，令人感到那是真人、活人，世上再没有比她更美丽、更可爱的女子了。年轻的国王发现忠诚的约翰内斯总是从一扇门前径直走过，便说：“你为什么从不打开这扇门让我看？”

约翰内斯回答说：“这里面有些东西会吓着你。”

国王答道：“这座宫殿我都看完了，我很想知道里面有什么东西。”说着走过去用力推门。

忠诚的约翰内斯劝阻他说：“你父王临终前我答应过他，不让你看这房间里的东西，因为它会给你和我带来灾难。”

“啊，不！”年轻的国王回答，“我不进去，必遭毁灭，不亲眼见到它，我会日夜不得安宁。你不把门打开，我就不走。”

忠诚的约翰内斯见劝阻无效，便唉声叹气、心情沉重地从一大串钥匙里找出那把钥匙。他一打开门，就抢先跨进房间，想用自己的身体挡住国王的视线，让他看不见那尊塑像。可是有什么用呢？国王踮起脚尖，从他肩膀上方望去。当他瞥见那美艳绝伦、珠光宝气的少女塑像，一下子就晕倒在地上。忠诚的约翰内斯把他抱起来放在床上，满腹忧愁，他想：“大祸临头了，上帝啊，这该怎么办啊？”他给他灌葡萄酒，直至他恢复知觉。国王开口第一句话就是：“啊！那美丽的塑像是谁？”

“是金屋公主。”忠诚的约翰内斯回答说。

国王又说：“即便树上所有的树叶都是舌头，也说不尽我对她的挚爱，为了得到她，我愿付出我的生命。你是我最忠诚的约翰内斯，你必须帮助我。”

忠诚的臣仆想了很久，不知如何是好，因为仅仅要见公主一面，就很不容易。最后，他终于想出个办法，便对国王说：“公主身边的一切，桌子、椅子、盘碗酒杯，所有家用器皿，都是金子做的。你的宝物中有五吨黄金，可以拿出一吨来，让国中的金匠制作成各式各样的器皿用具，各式各样的飞禽走兽、珍稀动物，她一定会喜欢这些物件，我们就带着这些东西去碰一碰运气。”

于是国王召集全国金匠，命令他们日夜赶工，终于制成华美无比的精品。一切装船完毕，忠诚的约翰内斯换上商人的服装，国王同样乔装打扮，让人完全认不出他们。然后他们漂洋过海，航行了很久很久，终于来到金屋公主居住的城市。

忠诚的约翰内斯让国王在船上等他。他说：“说不定我会把金屋公主带来，因此你要把一切收拾得整整齐齐，把黄金器皿陈列起来，把整条船装饰得漂漂亮亮的。”说着，他把各种金器拣一些放在衣兜里，上岸直奔王宫。到了宫中庭院，只见一个美丽的姑娘站在井边，手提两只金桶打水。她提着晶亮晶亮的水要走的时候，一转身，看见一个陌生人，就问他是谁。他回答：“我是商人。”便打开衣兜让她看。她不禁叫起来：“啊，多美的金器啊！”她放下水桶，一件一件地仔细观赏。姑娘说：“我要让公主看看，她非常喜爱金器，会把您的金器全部都买下来的。”她拉着他的手，把他领进宫里，因为她是个侍女。公主见了这些金货，非常高兴，她说：“这些金器做得这么好，我要全都买下来。”但是忠诚的约翰内斯说：“我只是一个富商的仆人，我带到这儿来的珍宝，跟我主人的船上的比起来，算不了什么，他那些都是古往今来最考究、最贵重的金器。”她要他把所有的金器都拿出来，他说：“都搬出来要花好几天时间，东西太多了，要好几个大厅才能陈列得开，您宫里地方不够。”这番话更加激起了公主的好奇心和欲望，她终于说：“带我到船上去吧，我要亲自看看你家主人的珍宝。”

于是忠诚的约翰内斯领着公主向他们那条船走去，心里非常高兴。国王见她本人比那塑像还要美丽得多，乐得一颗心都快蹦出来了。她上了船，国王把她接进舱中；忠诚的约翰内斯留在舵手身边，下令开船离岸，他说：“把所有船帆都升起来，船要疾驶如飞，就像空中的鸟儿一样。”船舱里，国王向公主一件一件展示金器：金碗、金杯、金盆、金钵、黄金制作的飞禽走兽、珍稀动物。看完最后一件金器，她向商人道谢，准备回家，走到船舷，只见船已远离陆地，在大海上扬帆疾驶。“啊，”她失声惊呼，“我上当了，被人诱拐，落入商人手里，不如死了好！”国王握住她的手说：“我不是商人，我是个国王，出身高贵，不亚于你。我之所以设计诱骗你，是因为我太爱你了。当我初次见到你的塑像，我就晕倒在地。”金屋公主听了这话，感到宽慰，对国王渐渐起了爱慕之心，终于欣然同意做他的妻子。

他们在大海上航行，有一天，忠诚的约翰内斯坐在船头奏乐，看见空中飞来三只乌鸦。他便不再弹奏，聚精会神听乌鸦谈话，因为他精通鸟语。一只乌鸦叫道：“哎，他带金屋公主回家了。”

“是的，”第二只乌鸦说，“他还没得到她。”

第三只说：“他得到她了，她在船上，坐在他身边。”

第一只乌鸦又叫起来：“那有什么用！他们上岸时，会有一匹枣红马向他迎面奔来，说不定他要跃上马背，他一骑上马背，这匹马就驮着他奔上天空，他就永远见不到自己的未婚妻了。”

第三只乌鸦说：“那就没办法解救了？”

“啊，有办法，如果有另外一个人迅速骑上去，拔出马鞍上枪套里的火枪，射杀那匹马，年轻的国王就得救了。可是这法子谁知道！如果谁知道这法子，又告诉给国王，谁就会从脚趾头到膝盖变成石头。”

第二只乌鸦说：“我知道的还要多。杀了那匹马，并不等于年轻的国王就得到他的未婚妻了！他们一同走进王宫的时候，那里有一个大盆，里面放着一件做好了的结婚礼服，看上去像是金丝银线织成的，其实只不过是硫黄和沥青做成的，国王一穿上它，就会被烧成灰烬。”

第三只乌鸦说：“那就没办法解救了？”

“啊，办法是有，”第二只乌鸦回答说，“如果有人戴上手套，抓起礼服，把它扔进火里烧掉，年轻的国王就得救了。没用！没用！这法子谁知道！如果谁知道这法子，又告诉给国王，谁就会从膝盖到心脏半个身子都变成石头。”

第三只乌鸦说：“我知道的还要多。烧了结婚礼服，也还不等于年轻的国王就得到他的未婚妻了。婚礼之后，舞会开始，年轻的王后突然倒下，面色煞白，像死了一般，这时得有个男子把她抱起来，从她的右胸脯吸三滴血，再喷出来，否则她就会死掉。但是，如果有人知道这法子又泄漏出去，他从头顶到脚趾头全身就都会变成石头。”

三只乌鸦交谈完就飞走了。忠诚的约翰内斯什么都听明白了，他从此变得沉默寡言，暗自忧伤，因为，如果他不把听到的话告诉给主人，主人将遭到不幸；如果告诉他，自己必将丧命。终于，他还是对自己说：“我要救我的主人，即使为此毁了我自己。”

他们上岸的时候，果然真像乌鸦所说的那样，迎面奔来一匹枣红马。“太好了！”国王说，“就骑它回宫。”说罢就要上马，但忠诚的约翰内斯抢在他前面飞身上马，拔出枪套里的枪，打死了那匹马。那些不满忠诚的约翰内斯的侍从一起大叫起来：“这么漂亮的马竟然给杀了，真可恶！国王还想骑它回宫呢！”但国王说：“安静！让他去吧，他是我最忠诚的约翰内斯，他这么做一定有他的道理，谁知道呢！”

他们进宫，殿堂上有一个大盆，里面放着一件做好了的结婚礼服，外表看上去是金丝银线织成的。年轻的国王径直朝它走去，正要伸手去取，忠诚的约翰内斯推开国王的手，戴上手套，一把抓起礼服扔进火里烧掉了。那些侍从又叫嚷开了：“你们看，他居然把国王的结婚礼服给烧了！”但年轻的国王说：“谁知道这有什么好处！让他去吧，他是我最忠诚的约翰内斯。”

婚礼之后开始跳舞。忠诚的约翰内斯注视着王后的面庞，忽然，她面容苍白，倒在地上，像死人一样。约翰内斯一跃而起，奔上前去，把她抱起来，抱进一间房间，让她躺下。他跪下，从她的右乳房吮吸了三滴血，又喷了出来。她随即又能呼吸，恢复了过来。国王目睹这一幕，他不明白忠诚的约翰内斯为什么这样做，勃然大怒，高声说：“把他关进监牢。”

第二天早晨，忠诚的约翰内斯被判处绞刑，押赴刑场。当他站在绞刑台上将被处决的时候，他说：“要被处死的人都被允许讲一次话，我也有这个权利吗？”

“是的，”国王回答，“也给你这个权利。”

忠诚的约翰内斯说：“判我有罪是不公正的，我一贯对你忠心耿耿。”于是他讲了在海上听到的乌鸦的谈话，以及为了拯救主人，他必须做这一切。国王听了以后，大声喊道：“啊，我最忠诚的约翰内斯，赦免！赦免！快把他带下来。”可是忠诚的约翰内斯说完最后一句话，已经毫无生气，从台上摔下来，变成了石头人。

国王和王后为这件事非常难过。国王说：“啊，他这样忠心耿耿，我竟然恩将仇报！”他派人扶起石像，把它竖立在自己卧室的床边。每当望着这尊石像，他就哭泣说：“啊，我最忠诚的约翰内斯，要是能让你起死回生那该多好啊！”

过了一段时间，王后生了双胞胎，两个小男孩。小王子渐渐长大，他们是王后的开心果。有一次，王后上教堂去了，两个孩子坐在父亲身边玩儿，国王又满怀伤痛地望着石像叹息道：“啊，我最忠诚的约翰内斯，要是能让你起死回生那该多好啊！”

这时石像开口了，它说：“能，你能让我起死回生，只要你肯为此舍弃你最心爱的东西。”

国王大声说：“为了你，我愿舍弃我在世上拥有的一切。”

石像又说：“如果你亲手砍下你的两个孩子的头，把他们的血抹在我的身上，我就能重新获得生命。”

国王一听要他亲手杀死自己最心爱的孩子，惊骇异常，但他想到约翰内斯是为他而死的，便拔剑亲手砍下了两个孩子的头。当他用孩子的血涂抹了石像，石像立刻重获生机，忠诚的约翰内斯变成精神奕奕的活人，健康地站在他面前。他对国王说：“你的真诚应当获得报答。”他接上孩子们的头，用他们的血涂抹伤口，只一刹那，孩子就痊愈了，又活蹦乱跳，继续玩耍，好像什么事情都没有发生似的。国王心里非常高兴，他看见王后回来，让忠诚的约翰内斯和两个孩子躲在一个大柜橱里面。她一进门，国王就对她说：“你在教堂祈祷了吗？”

“祈祷了，”她回答，“可我心里总想着忠诚的约翰内斯，他为了我们，遭遇了这么大的不幸。”

国王说：“亲爱的妻子，我们可以使他重新获得生命，但要以我们的两个幼子为代价，我们必须牺牲他们。”

王后面色惨白，心中惊骇，但是她说：“我们应该这样做，为了报答他伟大的忠诚。”

国王很高兴她的想法和自己一样，他跑去打开柜橱，叫孩子们和忠诚的约翰内斯出来，国王说：“赞美上帝，他得救了，我们也没有失去我们的两个孩子！”并对她讲了事情的经过。从此他们一起过着幸福美满的生活，一直到老。

莴苣姑娘

从前有一个男人和一个女人，他们想要个孩子，可是很久都没有。后来，女人终于怀孕了，也许亲爱的上帝要让她如愿以偿了。他们家后面的房子有一扇小窗，从小窗往外看能看到一座豪华美丽的花园，芳草如茵，盛开着最美丽的花；但是这座一道高墙围着的花园，谁都不敢走进去，因为它属于一个法力广大的女巫，人人都惧怕她。有一天，女人站在那个小窗旁俯望花园，看见一圃非常美丽的莴苣，那么鲜嫩，青翠欲滴，引得她忽然产生想吃莴苣的强烈愿望。这渴望与日俱增，但她知道无法实现，因而日渐消瘦，面容苍白、憔悴。她丈夫吃惊地问道：“你怎么啦，亲爱的？”

“啊，”她回答，“如果我不能吃到我们家后面花园里长的莴苣，我就要死了。”

那个男人很爱她，心想：“无论付出什么代价，我也要给她弄点莴苣来。”他在暮色朦胧中翻过围墙，跳进巫婆的花园，匆匆忙忙拔了一个莴苣，带回来给妻子。她马上拿它做凉菜，吃得一干二净。她觉得莴苣味道好极了，第二天馋得更厉害。丈夫要让她安宁，还得再去一趟花园。于是他又在暮色朦胧的时候爬墙过去，这时，他看见老巫婆就站在自己面前，吓一大跳。

“你胆子不小啊！”她目露凶光，说：“敢做贼到我花园里偷我的莴苣，我得叫你知道我的厉害。”

“啊！”他回答说，“请你宽恕我吧，我实在是迫不得已，我的妻子从窗口看到你的莴苣，她馋得厉害，不让她吃点儿，她真的会死的。”巫婆怒气渐消，对他说：“真是像你所说的那样，我就让你拿莴苣，要多少拿多少。只是我有个条件：你得把你妻子生的孩子给我。我会像妈妈一样照料他，孩子的生活差不了。”那男人心里害怕，一口答应了。他的妻子一分娩，老巫婆就去了，她给孩子取名叫莴苣，把孩子带走了。

莴苣长成了天底下最漂亮的女孩子。她十二岁那年，巫婆把她锁在森林中一座塔楼里。这塔既没有楼梯，也没有门，只塔顶上有一个很小很小的窗户。

巫婆要上塔楼，就往塔下一站，大声喊：

莴苣，莴苣，
放下你的头发，我要上去。

莴苣有一头长长的细如金丝的美丽秀发，她听到巫婆的叫声，就解开辫子，缠绕在一个窗钩子上，把头发放下四米来长，让巫婆爬上去。

几年以后，一位王子骑马路过森林，从塔旁走过的时候，听见有人在唱歌，歌声是那么美妙动人，王子不由驻足倾听。这是莴苣姑娘在孤寂中为了打发时光，扬声歌唱。王子想上去找她，却找不到塔楼的门。这座塔没有门。他只好回家，但这歌声深深地打动了他的心，他天天到森林里去听莴苣姑娘唱歌。一天，他站在一棵树后面，看见一个巫婆走上前去，听见她叫喊：

莴苣，莴苣，
放下你的头发，我要上去。

莴苣姑娘听了，放下发辫，巫婆爬了上去。“既然这是上塔的梯子，我也要碰碰运气。”第二天天快黑的时候，他走近塔，大声喊：

莴苣，莴苣，
放下你的头发，我要上去。

不一会儿，头发垂下来，王子登上了塔。

莴苣姑娘看见一个男人进塔向她走来，起初非常害怕，因为她从来没有见过男人。但王子十分亲切地和她攀谈，向她诉说她的歌声如何使他深受感动，他如何寝食难安，非要亲自见她一面不可，莴苣姑娘的恐惧消失了，他问她愿不愿意嫁给他，她见他年少英俊，心想：“他会比戈特尔老太太还爱我。”便答应了，把自己的手放在他的手里。她说：“我愿意跟你一起走，但是我不知道怎样才能下去。你以后再来，都带一卷丝线吧，我要编个软梯，编好了，我就能下塔了，然后你再扶我上马。”他们约定直到出走之前，他每天晚上都来看她，因为老太婆白天来。这事巫婆丝毫也没有察觉，直到有一天，莴苣姑娘对她说：“请你告诉我，戈特尔太太，这是怎么回事，我觉得把你拉上来比把那位年轻的王子拉上来要费劲得多，他一眨眼就到我身边了。”

“好啊！”巫婆叫嚷起来，“你这个坏孩子，说的什么话！我还以为已经使你与世隔绝了呢！原来你骗了我！”大怒之下，她抓住莴苣姑娘美丽的发辫，在左手腕缠绕几圈，右手抄起一把剪刀，咔嚓几下，剪断了头发，美丽的发辫落在地上。她还狠心地把可怜的莴苣姑娘带到一处荒野，迫使她在那里过着极其艰辛痛苦的生活。

莴苣姑娘被赶走的当天晚上，巫婆把剪下的发辫的一端牢牢系在塔里的窗钩上，王子一喊：

莴苣，莴苣，
放下你的头发，我要上去。

她就往塔下放发辫。王子登上塔发现他心爱的莴苣姑娘不在塔上，只见老巫婆一双恶毒的眼睛死死盯着他。“啊哈，”她讥笑王子，大声说，“你要找你的心上人，但美丽的小鸟儿已经不在窝里，也不歌唱了，猫把她叼走了，我还要挖掉你的两只眼睛，叫你永远休想再看见她！”王子心中痛楚万分，绝望之中跳下高塔。他落在荆棘丛中，虽然保住了性命，双眼却被刺瞎了。他盲目地在森林里流浪，吃的是树根、野莓，终日为失去他最心爱的女子而哭泣悲伤。他在愁苦困顿之中这样流浪了几年，终于来到莴苣姑娘和她生的孪生兄妹一起艰难度日的荒野。他听到有人说话，那声音是那么熟悉，他径直走过去，待他走近，莴苣姑娘认出他来，扑到他身上痛哭了起来。她的两行清泪湿润了他的眼睛，它们又变得清澈明亮，恢复了从前的视力。他带他们回到他的王国，受到热烈的欢迎，他们幸福愉快地一起生活了很久很久。

三片蛇叶

从前有一个穷人，没有钱养活自己的独生子。儿子说：“亲爱的爸爸，你这么贫困，我还拖累你，我还是自己出去挣口饭吃为好。”父亲为他祝福，非常悲伤地和他告别。这时，一个强国的国王正在征战，年轻人去从军为国王效力。当他随部队开赴战场时，前线正在打仗，形势十分危急，他周围的战友纷纷在弹雨中倒下了。虽然指挥官还在，但剩下的人都想逃跑，这时年轻人挺身而出，激励他们，高呼道：“我们决不能让祖国沦亡！”战士们随他一同冲入敌阵，狠狠打击了敌人。国王听说由于他战争才取得了胜利，便提升他，使他位居所有人之上，并给他大批珍宝，使他成为了国中的首富。

国王有一个女儿，非常美丽，但是也很奇特。她立下誓言，要娶她的男人必须答应她，如果她先死，他便要陪她一同入葬。“如果他真心爱我，我死了他还活着干吗？”她这样说。反过来说，如果他先死，她也同样给他陪葬。这奇异的誓言把所有的求婚者都给吓跑了，但年轻人被她的美貌迷住了，不顾一切地向国王请求和她结婚。“你知道你得答应什么条件吗？”国王说。

“如果她死了我还活着，”他回答说，“我得同她一起被葬入坟墓。但我非常爱她，不在乎这点危险。”于是国王同意他们结婚，并为他们举行了隆重的婚礼。

他们在一起过了一段幸福愉快的生活，后来，年轻的公主得了重病，没有一个医生能医好她的病。公主死了，年轻的驸马想起曾经许下的诺言，害怕自己被活埋在陵墓里面，但他已经没有退路：国王下令卫兵把守所有宫门，他已无法逃避等待着他的命运。到了公主的尸体被移进王室陵墓的那一天，他也被带了下去，随后墓门被锁上，还加了门闩。

墓室里，灵柩旁边有一张桌子，桌上有四盏灯、四个长面包、四瓶葡萄酒。这些食物吃完了，他就得饿死。他悲痛地坐在那里，每天只吃一点面包，喝一口酒，尽管如此，仍然感到死神日益逼近。他茫然地望着前面，忽然看见拱形墓室的墙角爬出一条蛇，越来越接近尸体。他想蛇是要去咬尸体的，便拔出剑来，说：“只要我还活着，就不许你碰她。”说着，挥剑把它斩为三段。不一会儿，从墙角又爬出一条蛇，看见那蛇死了，躺在那里，就往回跑，很快叼着三片绿叶爬过来。它把三段蛇身拼接在一起，在每处伤口贴上一片绿叶。死蛇动了，活了，两条蛇一起跑掉，撂下三片绿叶在地上。不幸的年轻人在一旁看到这整个过程，忽然想到，能使死蛇复活的叶子是否对人也能有所帮助呢？于是他捡起叶片，拿一片叶子放在公主嘴上，另外两片放在她的眼睛上。他刚放完，死者脉管里的血液便开始流动，苍白的面孔变得红润起来。她又能呼吸了，睁开眼睛问道：“上帝啊，这儿是什么地方？”

“你和我在一起，”他回答，接着向她叙述了事情的经过，以及他如何又使她死而复生。他让她吃点面包，喝点酒，她又有力气了，便站起来，走到门口，使劲敲门，大声呼喊，让卫兵听见去报告国王。国王亲自下来开门，看见两人都神采奕奕、身体健康，为他们渡过难关感到欣慰。年轻的驸马拿了那三片蛇叶，把它交给一个侍从，说：“细心保存好它们，随时带在身边，说不定有什么灾难时还用得着它们。”

那女人死而复生之后，心理却发生了变化，似乎她对她丈夫的情爱全都已从心中消失殆尽。过了一些时候，他要乘船渡海去探望父亲，他们登上了一条船，她全忘了她丈夫把她从死神手中救出来时所明示的伟大的爱和忠贞，竟然对船夫产生了恋情。一天，驸马躺着睡觉时，她把船夫叫来，自己抓住沉睡的丈夫的头，船夫抓住他的脚，把他抛下了大海。干完这无耻勾当，她对船夫说：“现在我们回去吧，就说他半路上死了。我一定要在我父亲面前夸奖你，让他同意我和你结婚，让你继承王位。”这一切，那个忠诚的侍从看在眼里，他悄悄地解开了系在大船上的一条小船，划船去寻找主人，和背信弃义者分道扬镳。他捞起死者，把随身携带的三片蛇叶分别贴在他的嘴唇和双眼上，凭着蛇叶神奇的力量，他复活了。

他们俩竭尽全力日夜划船，小船疾驶如飞，比大船还先到老国王那里。国王看见他们独自回来，感到奇怪，问他们出了什么事。当他听到他女儿的罪恶行径，他说：“我不相信她会做出这样的坏事，不过事情很快就会真相大白。”他命令他们两人藏在密室，不许见任何人。不久大船到达，那个邪恶的女人带着忧伤的表情出现在国王面前。国王说：“你怎么自己一个人回来了？你的丈夫呢？”

“啊，亲爱的爸爸，”她说，“我非常悲伤地回来，我丈夫在航行途中突然生病死了，多亏好心的船夫帮助，不然我就惨了。我丈夫去世时他也在场，他可以把一切讲给你听。”国王说：“我要叫死人再活过来。”他打开密室，唤两个人出来。那女人一见她丈夫还活着，像遭了雷击，跪下去求饶。国王说：“这是不能宽赦的！他甘愿与你同死，给你第二次生命，你却趁他熟睡害死他，你应该罪有应得。”于是公主和她的帮凶被送到一条凿穿孔的船上，推到了海里，他们很快就在波涛中沉没了。

灰姑娘

一个富人的妻子病了，她觉得自己快要死了，便把她的独生女儿叫到病床前，对她说：“亲爱的孩子，你要永远虔诚、善良，上帝会永远保佑你的，我也会从天上俯望你，与你同在。”说完，她闭上眼睛去世了。姑娘天天去她母亲坟上哀哭，她的心地一直保持着善良、虔诚。冬天来临，雪如一方白布披罩在坟上。当春天的阳光又把它的光辉洒下来的时候，那富人又讨了一个老婆。

这女人带着两个女儿进家门，她们脸蛋又白又俊，但她们的心又狠又黑。前妻的可怜的女儿日子很不好过。“蠢丫头也和我们一起坐在屋里？”她们说，“她要吃饭得靠自己去挣！滚出去，你这厨房的丫头！”她们拿走她的漂亮衣服，给她穿一件旧灰褂子和木屐。“瞧这骄傲的公主打扮的德行！”她们叫着，笑着，把她带到厨房。她得从早到晚干重活，天不亮就得起床，挑水、生火、做饭、洗衣服。两个妹妹还想出种种点子作弄她、嘲笑她，她们把豌豆和扁豆倒在炉灰里，叫她再把它们一粒粒拣出来。晚上，她干活干得很累了，没有床让她睡觉，她只好躺在炉灶旁的灰土里。因为她总是浑身灰土，样子很脏，她们就管她叫“灰姑娘”。

有一次，父亲要去赶年市，问两个继女要什么东西。一个说要“漂亮的衣裳”，另一个说要“珍珠和宝石”。“你呢，灰姑娘，”父亲说，“你想要什么？”

“爸爸，在你回家的路上，请你折下第一根碰到你的帽子的树枝，把它带来！”于是他为两个继女买了漂亮的衣服、珍珠和宝石；骑马回家穿过一片绿色灌木林的时候，一根榛树的枝条碰着他，他的帽子掉在地上，他就折下这榛树枝，带回家去。到了家里，他给了继女所要的东西，给了灰姑娘那根榛树的枝条。灰姑娘对他表示感谢，把那根树枝种在母亲的坟上。她哭得十分伤心，泪水掉在泥土上，浇灌着榛树的枝条，这枝条生长成了一棵美丽的小树。灰姑娘每天三次去那棵树下哭泣、祈祷，每次树上总停着一只白色的小鸟，她想要什么，一说出口，小鸟儿就把她希望得到的东西扔下来送给她。

有一次，国王要举行为期三天的舞会，邀请全国年轻美貌的姑娘参加，让他的儿子从中挑选一个未婚妻。灰姑娘的两个异母妹妹听说她们也被邀请参加，非常高兴，便大声对灰姑娘说：“给我们梳头、擦鞋、结好鞋扣，我们要去王宫参加舞会。”灰姑娘遵命照办，但她哭了，因为她也很想一起去参加舞会。她请求继母允许她去。“灰姑娘，”继母说，“你浑身灰土，这么脏还想去参加舞会？你没有衣服又没有鞋，还想跳舞？”但她仍不断恳求，终于，继母说：“我把一碗扁豆倒在炉灰里，要是你能在两小时内把扁豆都拣出来，就让你去。”灰姑娘从后门走进花园，叫道：“温顺的小鸽子、小斑鸠，天空中所有的小鸟儿，请你们都来帮我拣豆子。”她唱道：

好的豆拣进碗里，
坏的豆吞进肚里。

于是从厨房的窗户飞进来两只小白鸽，接着飞进来几只小斑鸠，后来天空中所有的小鸟儿都叽叽喳喳地飞来了，落在灰堆的周围。小鸽子点着头，开始一粒一粒地拣豆，其他鸟儿也开始一粒粒地啄着，把好的豆统统拣进碗里。不到一个钟头，它们就拣完豆，又飞走了。灰姑娘高高兴兴地把一碗豆给继母端去，满以为她会让她去参加舞会了。但继母说：“不行，灰姑娘，你没有好衣服，没法跳舞。你只会让人笑话。”灰姑娘哭了，继母说：“要是你能在一个钟头内把两碗满满的扁豆从灰堆里拣出来，拣得干干净净，就让你一起去。”她想，这是灰姑娘永远无法做到的。继母把两碗扁豆倒在炉灰里，姑娘从后门走进花园，叫道：“温顺的小鸽子、小斑鸠，天空中所有的小鸟儿，请你们都来帮我拣豆子”。她唱道：

好的豆拣进碗里，
坏的豆吞进肚里。

于是从厨房的窗户飞进来两只小白鸽，接着飞进来几只小斑鸠，后来天空中所有的小鸟儿叽叽喳喳地都飞来了，落在灰堆的周围。小鸽子点着头，开始一粒一粒地拣豆，其他鸟儿也开始一粒粒地啄着，把好的豆统统拣进碗里。不到半个钟头，它们就拣完豆，又飞走了。姑娘高高兴兴地把豆子给继母端去，满以为她会让她去参加盛会了。继母却说：“什么都帮不了你的忙。你不能去，因为你没有好衣裳，无法跳舞；你去了，我们会为你感到丢人现眼的。”说罢，她转过身去，背对着灰姑娘，带上她那两个骄傲的女儿匆匆走了。

现在家里没有别人了，灰姑娘来到母亲坟前的榛树下哀求：

小树啊，你摇一摇，晃一晃，
把金子银子撒在我身上！

鸟儿给她抛下一件金丝银线织成的衣裳和一双用丝绸和银线缝制的舞鞋。她匆匆忙忙穿上那件衣裳去参加舞会。她穿着金色衣裳是那么漂亮，她的两个妹妹和继母都认不出她来，以为她是一位外国的公主。她们根本就想不到会是灰姑娘，以为这会儿她正坐在家里拣扁豆，浑身脏兮兮的。王子向灰姑娘走过来，握着她的手，和她跳舞。他只和她跳舞，不和别人跳，他握着她的手不放。如果有人来请灰姑娘跳舞，他就说：“这是我的舞伴。”

灰姑娘一直跳舞跳到晚上。她要回家了，王子说：“我送你回去。”因为他要看看这位美丽的姑娘是谁家的。灰姑娘到了家门口，便从王子身边逃走，一跃跳进了鸽房。王子等她父亲回来，告诉他那位不知姓名的姑娘跳进了鸽房。老头子心想：“莫非是灰姑娘？”他只好给王子拿来斧子和锄头，让他劈开鸽房。可是里面没有人。回到家里，只见灰姑娘穿着她那身脏衣服躺在灰堆上，壁炉架上点着一盏暗淡的小油灯。原来灰姑娘很快就从鸽房后面跳下来，跑到小榛树那儿，脱下漂亮的衣裳，放在坟上，鸟儿又把它收走了，她这才又穿上旧灰褂子，坐在了灰堆旁边。

第二天，盛会重新开始，父母和两个异母妹妹都走了，灰姑娘来到榛树下说：

小树啊，你摇一摇，晃一晃，
把金子银子撒在我身上！

鸟儿又扔下一件比前一天还要华丽得多的衣裳。当她穿着这件衣裳出现在盛会上时，人们见她这么美丽，都很惊奇。王子一直在等着，她一来，王子就握着她的手，只和她一个人跳舞。如果有人来请灰姑娘跳舞，他就说：“这是我的舞伴。”到了晚上，她要走了，王子尾随在她身后，想看她会走进哪一座房子。但她一下子跳开，跑到了屋后的花园里。花园里有一株美丽的大树，枝头挂着鲜美的梨子。王子等她父亲回来，对他说：“那位不知姓名的姑娘从我身边跑了，我想她上了梨树。”父亲心想：“莫非是灰姑娘？”他让人拿斧子来，砍倒梨树，可是树上一个人也没有。他们到厨房去，看见灰姑娘身上穿着灰褂子，像往常那样躺在灰堆上。原来她早就跳下梨树，把美丽的衣裳还给小榛树上的鸟儿，自己又穿上了灰褂子。

第三天，父母和妹妹走后，灰姑娘又去她母亲坟上，对小榛树说：

小树啊，你摇一摇，晃一晃，
把金子银子撒在我身上！

于是鸟儿给她扔下一件衣裳、一双舞鞋，那衣裳华美无比，光辉夺目，真是举世无双，那双舞鞋整个儿都是金子做的。她穿了这身衣裳来到舞会上，所有的人都惊奇得不知道该说什么好。王子只和她一人跳舞，如果有人来请灰姑娘跳舞，他就说：“这是我的舞伴！”

到了晚上，灰姑娘要走了，王子要陪她回去，她很快跑了，他追不上她。但王子预先设下一个计策，叫人把所有台阶全都涂上沥青；灰姑娘跑下台阶时，左脚的舞鞋被沥青粘住了。王子把它捡起来，发现它小巧、精美，整个儿都是金子做的。第二天早晨，他带上这只鞋去见那个富商，对他说：“我要娶能穿上这只金鞋的女子做妻子。”继母的两个女儿都很高兴，因为她们的脚很好看。大姐拿了鞋到房里试穿，母亲站在一旁观看。可是她的脚趾头太大，鞋太小，穿不进去，母亲递给她一把刀，说：“把脚趾剁下来，当上王后就用不着走路了。”姑娘剁下脚趾头，硬把脚塞进金鞋里去，咬紧牙关，强忍疼痛，去见王子。王子拿她当自己的新娘子，扶她上马，带她回去。经过坟墓的时候，小榛树上的两只鸽子高声啼鸣：

回头瞧瞧，回头瞧，
鞋里面鲜血流淌，
鞋儿太小，鞋太小，
家里那个才是真新娘。

王子瞥一眼她的脚，一见鲜血涌流，便拨转马头，把假新娘送回家去，说这位不是真的新娘，要她的妹妹来穿金鞋。妹妹走进房间，很幸运地把脚趾头伸进了鞋里，可是脚后跟太大，套不进去。母亲递给她一把刀，说：“把脚后跟剁一块下来，当上王后就用不着走路了。”姑娘剁下一块脚后跟，硬把脚塞进金鞋里去，咬紧牙关，强忍疼痛，去见王子。王子拿她当自己的新娘子，扶她上马，带她回去。经过坟墓的时候，小榛树上的两只鸽子高声啼鸣：

回头瞧瞧，回头瞧，
鞋里面鲜血流淌，
鞋儿太小，鞋太小，
家里那个才是真新娘。

王子瞥一眼她的脚，只见鲜血从鞋子里面涌出来，把白色的长袜染成了一片血红。他便拨转马头，把假新娘送回家去，说：“这位也不是真的新娘，你们再没有别的女儿了吗？”

“没有了，”老头子说，“家里就还有我已故的前妻生的一个可怜的灰姑娘，她不可能是新娘子。”王子要他把她叫来，母亲却说：“不用了，她太脏，见不得人。”可是王子无论如何要见一见她，他们只得让灰姑娘出来。灰姑娘把手和脸洗得很干净，然后出来，向王子鞠躬，王子把金鞋递给她。她坐在一只小板凳上，脱下脚上笨重的木屐，穿上金鞋，这鞋就像是为她的脚定做的。她站起来，王子看着她的面庞，马上认出她就是那个和自己跳过舞的美丽的姑娘，他大声说：“她就是真的新娘！”继母和两个妹妹又惊又气，脸色煞白。王子扶灰姑娘上马，带她回宫。他们经过坟墓的时候，小榛树上的两只鸽子高声啼鸣：

回头瞧瞧，回头瞧，
鞋里没有鲜血了，
鞋儿不小，鞋不小，
他领真的新娘子回家了。

叫完了，两只白鸽双双飞下枝头，停在灰姑娘肩上，一只在左边，一只在右边，停落不走了。

王子要举行婚礼了，灰姑娘那两个虚情假意的姊妹也来奉承，想和她同享幸福。新婚夫妇上教堂去，大妹妹走在右边，小妹妹走在左边；这时，两只鸽子啄掉了她们一人一只眼睛。她们随即向门外奔去，大的在左边，小的在右边。鸽子又啄掉了她们另一只眼睛。她们凶狠又虚伪，受罚做瞎子一直到死。

霍勒太太

从前，有个寡妇她有两个女儿，一个美丽又勤快，一个丑陋又懒惰。但她更爱那个又丑又懒的，因为那是她的亲生女儿，家里所有的活都叫另一个去做，她成了家里的灰姑娘。这个可怜的女孩得天天坐在当街的一口水井旁边纺线，一直纺到手指流血。

有一天，鲜血染红了纺锤，她拿着纺锤弯腰探进水井，要把它洗干净，不料纺锤从她手中掉到井里去了。她哭着跑回去向继母诉说这件不幸的事情。狠心的继母责骂她说：“是你让纺锤掉到井里去的，你得把它捞上来！”

小姑娘回到水井旁边，不知怎么办才好。她心里害怕，就跳进井里找纺锤。她在水里失去了知觉，醒来时发现自己正躺在一片美丽的草地上，阳光明媚，草地上盛开着成千上万朵鲜花。小姑娘在草地上朝前走，来到一个烤面包炉旁边；满满一炉子面包喊叫着：“喂，把我抽出去，把我抽出去，我快烤煳了！我早就烤熟了！”小姑娘走过去，用面包铲把面包一个个都取出来。她又继续往前走，来到一棵果实累累的苹果树下，苹果树冲她喊：“喂，摇晃我，摇晃我，树上的苹果都熟了。”小姑娘摇晃苹果树，苹果雨点般纷纷坠落。她一直摇晃到树上一只苹果也没有了才停下，接着又把地上的苹果捡起来，放在一起，然后继续往前走。最后她来到一座小房子前面，一位老太太探出头朝外面张望，小姑娘见她牙齿特别大，心里害怕，转身就要跑开。老太太在她背后喊：“你害怕什么呢，好孩子？待在我这儿吧！如果你肯把家里的活儿都做得很好，你会过上好日子的。只是得注意好好整理我的床铺，使劲抖被子，抖得羽绒飞起来，那样，世上就会下雪了。我是霍勒太太。”老太太对她说话很和气，小姑娘不再害怕了，便答应留下来替她做事。她无论做什么事情，都做得让老太太满意，总是使劲抖她的被子，抖得羽绒像雪花似地四处飞舞。她干活勤快，在老太太那儿生活得很好，从没听过一句骂她的话，天天又烧又炖，吃得很好。

小姑娘在霍勒太太那儿住了一段时间，心里渐渐感到悲伤，起初自己也说不清哪儿不对劲儿，后来才知道是想家了。虽然她在这里的生活比在家里好千百倍，但她还是想家。最后她对霍勒太太说：“我想家想得厉害，在您这里的生活很好，但我不能再住下去了，我必须回去，和我家里的人在一起。”霍勒太太说：“你想回家去，我很高兴，你一直这么忠心地为我服务，我要亲自送你上去。”说罢，她拉着小姑娘的手，领她走到大门口。门开了，小姑娘正好站在大门下面，这时忽然落下一阵很大的金雨，金子全都粘在了她身上，她浑身上下都是黄金。“你一直那么勤快，这是你应得的。”霍勒太太说，把原先掉到井里的纺锤还给她。接着，大门关上了，小姑娘又回到那离继母家不远的地方。

她走进院子的时候，蹲在井上的公鸡叫起来：

喔喔！喔喔！
咱们的金姑娘回来了！

小姑娘进屋去见继母，因为她全身都是金子，所以受到了继母和妹妹的热情接待。

小姑娘讲了她亲身经历的一切，继母听罢，很想让她那个又丑又懒的女儿也有这一份福气。于是，丑姑娘只得坐在水井旁边纺线。为了使她的纺锤染上鲜血，她把手伸进荆棘树篱，自己扎破手指，然后把带血的纺锤扔进水井，自己跟着跳了下去。同她那勤劳美丽的姐姐一样，她来到一片美丽的草地，沿着同一条路往前走。她走到烤面包炉旁边，面包又叫喊：“喂，把我抽出去，把我抽出去，我快烤煳了！我早就烤熟了！”懒姑娘回答说：“我才不乐意把自己弄脏呢。”说完继续往前走。不一会儿，她走到苹果树前，苹果树喊叫着：“喂，摇晃我，摇晃我，树上的苹果都熟了。”她却回答说：“说得轻巧，苹果掉下来还不砸我的脑袋？!”她只管往前走。

她到了霍勒太太的房子前面，因为听说过她的牙齿很大，所以她并不害怕，马上答应做她的女仆。

第一天她强打精神，干活勤快，霍勒太太要她做什么，她就去做，因为她想着霍勒太太会送她许多许多金子。可是第二天她就开始偷懒，第三天更懒，早晨赖在床上不起来。她不给霍勒太太整理床铺，这本是她分内该做的；也不把被子抖得羽绒纷飞。不久，霍勒太太就厌烦了，不要她做工了。懒姑娘乐不可支，满心以为金雨就要来了。霍勒太太同样领她到大门口，她站在大门下面的时候，落下的不是金雨，而是满满一锅沥青。“这是你做工的报酬。”霍勒太太说完便关上了大门。

懒姑娘回家来，浑身上下都是沥青，井上的公鸡见了她，大叫起来：

喔喔！喔喔！
咱们的脏姑娘回来了！

沥青牢牢地粘在她的身上，一直到死也洗不掉。

七只乌鸦

有一个男人有七个儿子，他很想要个女儿。终于有一天，他的妻子又怀孕了，生下一个女孩。他们非常高兴，可是孩子瘦小、身体虚弱，需要行紧急洗礼。父亲派一个儿子赶快去井边打水作洗礼用，其他六个也都跟着一起去，人人争着要第一个把水打上来，结果把水桶掉到井里去了。他们站在那里，不知该怎么办好，谁都不敢回家。左等右等孩子们总也没回来，父亲不耐烦了，说：“他们一定是玩得忘了，这些坏孩子！”他怕女孩没来得及行洗礼就死了，一气之下，大声说：“我要这些小子都变成乌鸦。”话音刚落，就听见头顶上传来一阵鸟儿飞行的声音，他抬头仰望空中，只见七只像煤炭一样黑的乌鸦飞掠过去。

父母再也无法收回咒语，虽然失去七个儿子十分伤心，但他们那个心爱的小女儿身体渐渐变得强壮起来，而且出落得一天比一天美丽，多少也给他们一些安慰。很长时间她甚至不知道自己曾经有好几个哥哥，因为父母很小心地避免在她面前提起他们，一直到有一天偶然听到人们议论，说这女孩子是很漂亮，但就是因为她，她的哥哥们才遭遇不幸。她听了很难过，回去问父母究竟她有没有哥哥，他们在哪里？父母再也不能继续瞒着她了，但他们说这是天降灾难，并非她的过错。可是这女孩天天为此心里难过，认为自己有责任去解救她的哥哥们。她终日坐立不安，后来悄悄离家出走，决心走遍天涯海角，无论如何也要找到哥哥们的踪迹，把他们解救出来。她随身只带了一枚父母的小戒指作纪念，一个长面包充饥，一壶水解渴，一把累了能坐一坐的小椅子。

她不停地走，走得很远很远，几乎走到了世界的尽头。她去找太阳，太阳太热，非常可怕，还吃小孩子。她赶紧逃走，跑去找月亮，可是月亮太冷，又很凶残，见了她，说：“我闻到人肉味儿了。”她赶忙离开，去找星星，星星都待她很和气、很友好，每一个都坐在自己的特别的小椅子上。晨星站起来，给她一只雏鸡腿，说：“你的哥哥们在玻璃山中，没有这只雏鸡腿，你就打不开玻璃山的锁。”

姑娘接过雏鸡腿，用一小块布仔细包好，又继续走，走了很久，终于走到了玻璃山。山门锁着，姑娘要取出雏鸡腿，打开布包一看，里面是空的，好心的星星赠送的礼物丢了。现在她该怎么办呢？她要解救她的哥哥们，可是没有打开玻璃山的钥匙。善良的小妹妹拿出一把小刀，切下自己一根小指头，把它塞到大门里去，幸运地打开了大门。她进入大门，迎面走来一个小矮人，说：“我的孩子，你找什么？”

“我找我的哥哥们——七只乌鸦。”她回答。小矮人说：“乌鸦先生们不在家，你如果要等他们就进来吧。”说着，小矮人端来盛放乌鸦的食物的七张小盘子和七只小酒杯，小妹妹从每个盘子里拿一小块面包吃，从每只杯子里喝小一口酒。她把她随身携带的小戒指放在最后一只小酒杯里。

忽然，她听到空中一阵鸟鸣声和风声，小矮人说：“乌鸦先生们回来了。”他们回来要吃要喝，找他们的小盘子、小酒杯。他们一个接一个地说：“谁吃了我小盘子里的东西？谁喝了我小酒杯里的酒？是人的嘴碰过的。”第七只乌鸦小酒杯里的酒快喝完了，小戒指滚向他的嘴边，他看见了，认出这是父母的戒指，他说：“上帝保佑，如果我们的小妹妹来了，我们就得救了。”姑娘听到这个愿望，就从门后走出来，于是七只乌鸦恢复了人形。他们互相拥抱、亲吻，高高兴兴地回家去了。

三根金发的魔鬼

从前有一个贫穷的女人生了一个儿子，儿子出生时身上裹着胎膜，有人就预言他十四岁时会娶公主做妻子。过了不久，国王到村里来，谁都不知道他是国王，他问起村里有什么新闻，人们就回答说：“前几天这里的一个女人生了一个带胎膜的孩子，据说这种人做什么事情都能成功。有人还预言他十四岁那年会娶国王的女儿做妻子。”国王心地狠毒，听了这预言很生气，他去找孩子的父母，装出和气的样子，说：“你们是穷人，把孩子交给我吧，我会照料他的。”起初他们不愿把孩子交给他，但陌生人出了一大笔钱，他们想：“他是个幸运儿，总会逢凶化吉的。”终于同意把孩子给他。

国王把孩子放在一个盒子里面，骑马带着他来到一条很深的河边，把盒子扔到河里，心想：“我帮助我女儿摆脱了一个不受欢迎的求婚者。”但是这盒子没有下沉，它像一只小船一样在水上漂流，也没有一滴水灌进盒子里。它漂流到离国王的京城两英里的地方，那里有一座磨坊，盒子搁浅在磨坊的堤坝边上。碰巧一个磨坊的伙计看见了它，就用钩子把它钩过来，以为得到了大宗财宝，打开一看，却是一个健康活泼的漂亮男孩躺在里面。他把孩子给磨坊主夫妇送去，他们没有孩子，便很高兴地说：“这是上帝赐予我们的。”他们精心抚养这个弃儿，他渐渐长大，各方面品德都很好。

有一天，国王为了避雷雨走进磨坊，他问磨坊主夫妇，那个高个子少年是不是他们的儿子。“不，”他们回答说，“这是一个弃儿，十四年前躺在一个盒子里漂流到堤坝边上，磨坊的伙计把他从水里钩上来的。”国王知道这孩子不是别人，正是他扔到水里的那个幸运儿，就说：“你们两位好心人，能不能让这个孩子送一封信给王后？我要赏他两块金币。”

“国王的命令，一定照办。”他们回答完就叫男孩准备启程。国王给王后写了一封信，信里说：“送这封信的男孩子一到，就把他杀了、埋掉，这一切在我回来之前都要办好。”

男孩带了这封信启程，但他迷了路，晚上走到一座森林里去了。黑暗中他看见一个小小的亮光，径直朝它走去，走到一座小房子跟前，便走了进去。屋里只有一个老太婆独自坐在火堆旁边。她看见少年进来，吃了一惊，说：“你从哪里来，要到哪里去？”

“我从磨坊来，”他回答说，“我要去找王后，给她送一封信；可是我在森林里迷了路，想在这里住一夜。”

“你这可怜的孩子，”老太太说，“你跑到强盗窝里来了，他们一回来，就会杀死你。”

“谁要来就来吧，”少年说，“我不怕，我累得再也走不动了。”说着，他躺在一条长凳上睡着了。不久，强盗们回来了，怒气冲冲地问道，躺在那里的陌生人是谁。“啊，”老太太说，“这是个纯洁无辜的孩子，在森林里迷了路，我可怜他，把他收留下来，他有一封信要交给王后。”强盗们拆开信看，信里说，这男孩一到，就要马上把他杀了。这些硬心肠的强盗起了怜悯之心，强盗首领把信撕了，另写一封，信里说，这男孩一到，就要他马上和公主结婚。他们让他在长板凳上安安静静地睡到第二天早晨，交给他那封信，又给他指了正确的路。王后收到信件，看了以后，就照信里吩咐的那样，下令举行盛大豪华的婚礼，公主和幸运儿结婚了。因为这少年英俊又友善，公主和他在一起生活得很快乐、很满意。

过了一段时间，国王回到王宫，发现预言应验了，幸运儿已经和他的女儿结了婚。“这是怎么回事？”他说，“我在信里下的命令不是这样的。”王后把信递给他，叫他自己看里面写了些什么。国王看了信，发现信被人换了。他问年轻人叫他送的那封信哪儿去了，为什么他把另一封信送来了。“我一点儿也不知道，”他回答说，“信一定是我那天夜里在森林里睡着的时候被人调换的。”国王勃然大怒说：“不能让你这么容易得手。谁要得到我的女儿，就得从地狱里取来魔鬼头上的三根金发；你能把我要的东西给我拿来，就可以继续和我女儿做夫妻。”国王希望以此永远甩掉他。但幸运儿却回答：“我会拿到金发的，我不怕魔鬼。”说完，他就告别众人，踏上了旅途。

他沿着大路走到一座大城市，城门口的卫兵盘问他能干什么活，知道些什么。“我无所不知，无所不晓。”幸运儿回答说。

“那你可以帮我们一个忙，”卫兵说，“告诉我们，为什么我们市集广场上的井往常能喷涌出葡萄酒，现在连一点儿水都没有了？”

“你们会知道的，”他回答说，“你们等着吧，等我回来。”他继续往前走，来到另一座城市，那里的城门卫兵又问他能干什么活，知道些什么。“我无所不知，无所不晓。”幸运儿回答说。

“那你可以帮我们一个忙，告诉我们，为什么我们城里的一棵树往常能长出金苹果，现在却连叶子也不长了？”

“你们会知道的，”他回答说，“你们等着吧，等我回来。”他继续往前走，来到一条大河边。他要过河，摆渡的船夫问他能干什么活，知道些什么。“我无所不知，无所不晓。”幸运儿回答说。

“那你可以帮我个忙，”船夫说，“为什么总得我摆渡来摆渡去，老是没有人来接替我？”

“你会知道的，”他回答说，“你等着吧，等我回来。”

过了河，他就找到了进入地狱的大门。地狱里面黑黝黝的，粘满煤烟，魔鬼没在家，他的老祖母坐在一张宽大的安乐椅上。“你来干什么，年轻人？”她对他说，样子一点儿也不凶。“我要魔鬼头上的三根金发，”他回答说，“要是拿不到，我就会失去我的妻子。”

“你的要求太过分了，”她说，“要是魔鬼回家发现了你，你就没命了。不过我可怜你，我要看看能不能帮你点忙。”她把他变成一只蚂蚁，说：“爬到我的裙子折缝里来，你在这里很安全。”

“好的，”他回答，“这样很好，不过还有三件事情是我很想知道的：为什么往常喷涌出葡萄酒的一口井变干涸了，现在连水也没有？为什么往常结出金苹果的一棵树，现在连叶子也不长了？为什么一个摆渡的船夫总是摆渡来摆渡去，也没有一个人来替换他？”

“这是些很难的问题，”她回答说，“你一定要安安静静待着，不要出声，我拔魔鬼三根金发的时候，你要注意听他说些什么。”

晚上，魔鬼回家。一进家门，他就觉得空气不纯净。“我闻到有人肉味，”他说，“这里情况不对头。”他在所有犄角旮旯察看、寻找，什么也没有找到。老祖母骂他：“我刚才才打扫过，把所有的东西整理好了，你现在又给我翻腾得乱七八糟；无论什么时候你鼻子里都总能闻到人肉味！坐下来吃你的晚饭吧！”他吃完了，喝过了，累了，头枕在老祖母怀里，要她给他抓虱子。不久，他睡着了，出气很粗，直打呼噜。老祖母揪着一根金发，拔下来放在一边。“哎哟！”魔鬼叫喊起来，“你干什么呀？”

“我做了个噩梦，”老祖母回答说，“就揪了你的头发。”

“梦见什么了？”魔鬼问。

“我梦见市集广场上有一口井，往常它喷涌出葡萄酒，现在干涸了，连水也流不出来，这是什么缘故？”

“哼，他们哪能知道！”魔鬼回答说，“井里一块石头下面有一只癞蛤蟆；把它打死，葡萄酒就又流出来了。”老祖母又给他抓虱子，他又睡着了，鼾声震得窗户颤动起来。老祖母拔了他第二根头发。“哎哟，你干什么？”魔鬼生气地喊叫。“别发火，”她回答说，“我做梦呢。”

“又做什么梦了？”他问。

“我梦见一个王国里有一棵果树，往常都结金苹果，现在连叶子也不长了。这是什么原因？”

“哼，他们哪能知道！”魔鬼回答说，“有一只耗子在咬树根；把它打死，这棵树就还能长出金苹果，如果还让它继续咬下去，这棵树就会完全枯死。别再拿那些梦来烦我了，我睡着你要再把我弄醒，我就给你一个耳光。”老祖母答应他，又给他抓虱子，他又睡着了，打起呼噜。她揪住他的第三根头发，拔了出来。魔鬼跳起来，大喊大叫，要和她算帐，老祖母又一次使他的气消下来，说：“要做噩梦，谁有什么办法！”

“你又做什么梦了？”他问，毕竟很好奇。

“我梦见一个摆渡的船夫诉苦说，总是他摆渡来摆渡去，也没人去替换他。这究竟是怎么一回事？”

“哼，这笨蛋！”魔鬼回答说，“如果有人要过河，他只要把船篙往那人手里一塞，那人就得摆渡，他不就自由了？”老祖母已经拔了他三根金发，三个问题也都回答了，她就让魔鬼安安稳稳地一觉睡到天亮。

魔鬼走了以后，老太太把蚂蚁从裙子皱褶里面拿出来，让幸运儿恢复了人形。“给你这三根金发，”她说，“魔鬼回答三个问题时说的话你都听见了吧？”

“是的，”他回答说，“我都听见了，我会牢牢记住的。”

“忙已经帮了，”她说，“你现在可以走了。”

他感谢老太太在危难中给予他帮助，让他离开地狱。这一切办得这么顺利，他很高兴。到了摆渡的船夫那儿，船夫要他兑现诺言，回答问题。“先把我摆渡到对岸，”幸运儿说，“我就告诉你怎样解脱。”到了对岸，他把魔鬼的主意转告船夫说：“如果又有人来，要坐渡船到对岸，你只要把船篙放在他手上就行了。”他继续往前走，来到那棵不长果实的树所在的城市，卫兵也要他回答问题。他把从魔鬼那儿听到的告诉他，说：“杀死那只咬树根的耗子，这棵树就会再结出金苹果。”卫兵感谢他，酬谢他两只驮满黄金的驴子，跟随在他后面。最后，他来到那座水井干涸了的城市。他把魔鬼说的话告诉卫兵：“井里一块石头下面有一只癞蛤蟆，你们得把它找出来，打死它，井就会涌出很多很多葡萄酒。”卫兵感谢他，也赠送他两只驮着黄金的驴子。

幸运儿终于回到家里，回到妻子身边，他的妻子和他重逢，听他说一切都很成功，心里非常高兴。他给国王送去他所要的魔鬼的三根金发，国王看见四只驴子驮着黄金，高兴得不得了，说：“现在所有的条件都满足了，你可以永远和我的女儿在一起了。不过，亲爱的女婿，请你告诉我，这么多黄金是哪儿来的？这可是巨大的财富啊！”

“我曾经渡过一条河，”他回答说，“这些黄金就是我从那儿带来的，那儿河岸边没有沙子，都是黄金。”

“我也可以拿一些吗？”国王贪婪地问。

“您想拿多少就拿多少，”他回答，“河上有个摆渡的船夫，您让他把您摆渡过去，到了对岸，您就可以装满您的袋子了。”贪心的国王急忙上路，到了河边，挥手让船夫把他摆渡过去。船夫过来，叫他上船，到了对岸，他把船篙塞在国王手里，自己跳上岸走了。从此国王不得不在那儿摆渡，这是对他的罪孽的惩罚。

“他还在摆渡吗？”

“应该还在，因为大概没有一个人从他那儿接过船篙。”

裁缝在天堂里

一个晴朗的日子，亲爱的上帝要去天堂的花园，所有使徒和圣徒都随他前往，天堂里就只留下圣彼得一人。上帝命令他，在他外出期间不许放任何人进来，于是圣彼得站在大门口守卫。不久，有人敲门。圣彼得问谁在外面，要干什么。“我是一个诚实的穷裁缝，”一个细嗓子回答说，“请求放我进去。”

“不错，真的，”圣彼得说，“你就像上了绞刑架的小偷一样老实，你给人家裁衣服偷人家的衣料。你不能进天堂，主不许我在他外出期间放任何人进来。”

“请你可怜可怜我吧，”裁缝大声说，“自己从桌上掉下去的小块布不是我偷的，也不值一提。请看，我走路一瘸一拐的，走得脚上起了泡，我无法再往回走了。求你放我进去吧，再次的活我都肯干。抱孩子，洗尿布，擦洗孩子们在上面玩的板凳，补小孩衣裳，我都愿意做。”圣彼得动了恻隐之心，把天堂的大门给瘸裁缝开了一条缝，让他那干巴瘦小的身体刚好能挤进去。他必须一声不响地在门后的墙角静静待着，上帝回来时别让他看见，惹他生气。裁缝当时听从了他的吩咐；可是圣彼得一到门口去，他就站起来，满怀好奇地到处溜达，看这看那，最后他来到一个地方，那里有许多又好看又贵重的椅子，当中有一把纯金的扶手椅，装饰着闪光的宝石。这把椅子比别的椅子高得多，椅子前面还有一只金色的小凳子做踏脚。这就是上帝在的时候坐的扶手椅，他一坐在这把椅子上，就能看见人间发生的一切事情。裁缝站着看这把椅子，默不作声地看了好一会儿，因为他喜欢它超过其他的一切。他终于控制不住自己的好奇心，便登上小凳子，在扶手椅上坐下。于是他看到人间发生的一切，看见一个丑陋的老太婆在一条溪边洗衣服，把两条纱巾藏起来。裁缝怒不可遏，抄起金脚凳从天上往人间扔下去打那个年老的女窃贼。可是他无法把金脚凳再收回来，便悄悄溜下扶手椅，仍旧回到门后面，坐在自己原先待着的地方，好像什么事情也没有发生似的。

上帝带着天堂的随从回来了，他虽然没看见门后的裁缝，但他坐上扶手椅时，发现踏脚凳没了。他问圣彼得脚凳哪儿去了，圣彼得也不知道。上帝又问他，放什么人进来没有。“除了一个裁缝，什么人我都我没放进来，”圣彼得回答说，“那是一个走路一瘸一拐的裁缝，他现在还在门后头待着。”上帝把裁缝叫到他跟前，问他有没有拿走凳子，拿到什么地方去了。“主啊，”裁缝高高兴兴地回答说，“我看见一个老太婆洗衣服的时候偷了两条纱巾，我很生气，就把凳子扔下去打她。”

“啊，你这无赖，”上帝说，“我要是像你这样审判，你早就该受惩罚了，我的椅子、凳子、扶手椅也早就没了，甚至连火钳也没了，统统都得扔下去打尘世的罪人了。你不能继续留在天堂，必须离开这里，到哪儿去，你看着办吧！这里除了我，谁都无权惩罚别人。”

圣彼得只好把裁缝带到天堂外面。裁缝因为鞋子破了，双脚净是水泡，就拿了一根棍子拄着，向“等候室”走去，里面坐着虔诚的士兵在玩乐。

自动上菜的小桌子、金驴子和跳出口袋的棍子

很久很久以前有一个裁缝，他有三个儿子和一只山羊。那只山羊，因为他们都吃它的奶，所以每天都得被牵到草地上去，吃很好的草料。儿子们轮流干这活。有一天，老大牵羊去教堂墓地，那里有许多鲜美的青草，他让羊儿吃草，自己在附近跳来跳去。傍晚该回家时，他问道：“羊儿，吃饱了没有？”羊儿回答：

我吃得很饱，
一片叶子也不再要，咩——咩——

“那就回家吧！”年轻人说，把它牵进羊圈拴牢了。“怎么样，”老裁缝问，“羊吃够草料没有？”

“哦，”老大回答说，“吃得很饱，它一片叶子也不想再吃了。”父亲要证实一下，自己到羊圈里来，他抚摸那可爱的山羊，问它：“羊儿，你吃饱了没有？”山羊回答说：

我怎么能吃饱？
我跳过几道小沟，
一片叶子也没见到，咩——咩——

“太不像话了！”裁缝大声喊叫起来，他跑上去对老大说：“喂，你这撒谎的家伙，你叫羊饿着，还说它吃饱了！”怒气冲冲地拿起墙上的尺子打他，把他赶跑了。

第二天轮到老二放羊，他在花园篱笆旁边找到一个地方，那儿的草长得很好，羊把草都吃光了。傍晚要回家时，他问：“羊儿，吃饱了没有？”羊儿回答：

我吃得很饱，
一片叶子也不再要，咩——咩——

“那就回家吧。”年轻人说，把它牵进羊圈拴牢了。“怎么样，”老裁缝说，“羊吃够草料没有？”

“哦，”老二回答说，“吃得很饱，它一片叶子也不想再吃了。”父亲不放心，自己到羊圈里来，他问：“羊儿，你吃饱了没有？”山羊回答说：

我怎么能吃饱？
我跳过几道小沟，
一片叶子也没见到，咩——咩——

“这个坏蛋！”裁缝大声喊叫，“让这么好的牲畜挨饿！”跑上去拿尺子打老二，把他赶出家门。

现在轮到第三个儿子放羊了，他要把事情办好，找了一处枝叶葱茏的灌木丛，让羊去吃。傍晚要回家时，他问：“羊儿，吃饱了没有？”羊儿回答：

我吃得很饱，
一片叶子也不再要，咩——咩——

“那就回家吧。”年轻人说，把它牵进羊圈拴牢了。“怎么样，”老裁缝说，“羊吃够草料没有？”

“哦，”老三回答说，“吃得很饱，它一片叶子也不想再吃了。”父亲信不过，自己到羊圈里来，他问：“羊儿，你吃饱了没有？”这阴险的畜生回答说：

我怎么能吃饱？
我跳过几道小沟，
一片叶子也没见到，咩——咩——

“啊，撒谎的混蛋！”裁缝大声喊叫，“一个个都这么坏，这么不负责任！你们再不能拿我当傻瓜了！”他气极了，跑上去拿尺子狠狠地抽可怜的小伙子的背，打得他只好从家里逃走。

现在就只剩老裁缝自己一个人和山羊在一起了。第二天早晨他去羊圈，对羊爱抚一番，说：“来，我可爱的小动物，我要亲自带你去吃草。”他牵羊去绿色篱笆那儿，去吃蓍草和羊平时爱吃的东西。“这回你可以随心所欲地吃个够了。”他对它说，让它吃草吃到傍晚。他问：“羊儿，吃饱了没有？”羊儿回答：

我吃得很饱，
一片叶子也不再要，咩——咩——

“那就回家吧。”裁缝说，把它牵进羊圈拴牢了。走了几步，又转过头来，说：“这回你可吃得够饱的了！”不料山羊对他也没好到哪里，叫道：

我怎么能吃饱？
我跳过几道小沟，
一片叶子也没见到，咩——咩——

裁缝一听，愣住了，也明白了他赶走三个儿子的无理。“等着瞧吧，”他喊叫着，“你这忘恩负义的畜生，赶走你还算便宜你了！我要给你做个记号，叫你没脸见正直的裁缝。”他匆忙跑上楼拿刮胡子刀，给山羊的头抹肥皂，把山羊头剃得像他的手掌一样没一根毛。他觉得用尺子揍它太赏它脸了，就去拿鞭子狠狠抽它，抽得它狂奔逃命。

裁缝孤孤单单待在家里，非常伤心，很想要他的儿子们回来，可是没人知道他们的下落。原来老大在一个细木匠那儿当学徒，他勤奋不懈地学习，满师以后，要去漫游，师傅送他一张小桌子。这张小桌子表面看上去并没有什么特别的地方，木头也是普普通通的木头，但是它有个很好的性能。你把它放好了，说：“小桌子，上菜吧！”这顶呱呱的小桌子马上就铺上干净的小台布，摆上一只盘子，旁边放置餐刀、叉子，还有几盘煎烤烧炖的菜肴、一大杯红葡萄酒，谁看了心里都会乐开花。年轻的木工心里想：“这够我受用一辈子了！”就高高兴兴地去各处漫游了，饭店好坏、有没有什么吃的，他都不放在心上。高兴时，他根本不进饭店，而是在田野上，在森林里，在草地上，高兴在哪儿就在哪儿，取下背上的小桌子，摆在面前，说：“上菜吧！”心里想吃什么，就都有了。他最后想回到父亲那里，他想父亲大概已经怒气全消，看到自动上菜的桌子，也许会很乐意接纳他。他在回家的途中，晚上来到一家客店，里面坐满了客人。他们招呼他，邀请他和他们一起吃，否则恐怕不容易得到什么吃的东西。“不用了，”细木匠回答说，“你们就这么点儿吃的东西，我怎么好意思吃呢？还是我请诸位吧！”他们哈哈大笑，以为他在和他们开玩笑。他在房间正中摆好他那张小木头桌子，说：“小桌子，上菜吧！”转眼间，桌上就摆满了客店老板拿不出来的香味扑鼻的美馔佳肴。“亲爱的朋友们，请用餐吧！”客人们看他真的请吃饭，也就不等他再说第二遍，都坐过来，举起刀叉狼吞虎咽起来。最使他们惊奇的是，一碗菜吃完了，马上又有满满的一碗自动上来。老板站在墙角看这玩意儿，不知该说什么好，心里想道：“我这客店倒很需要一个这样的厨师。”木匠和他的客人一直闹腾到深夜才上床睡觉，木匠将那神奇的小桌靠墙放着。老板睡不着，一个劲儿地转脑筋，忽然想起在他堆放破烂的小屋里有一张旧的小桌，样子和这张一模一样。他悄悄去取来，拿它调换神奇的小桌。第二天，木匠付了住宿费，收拾好桌子上路，根本想不到桌子被人调换了。中午时分，他回到父亲那里，父亲见他回来，非常高兴。“亲爱的孩子，你学了什么？”父亲对他说。

“爸爸，我是个细木匠了。”

“这手艺好啊，”父亲说，“你在各处漫游，带什么东西回来了？”

“爸爸，我带的最好的东西是这张桌子。”裁缝从各方面把小桌子打量一番，说：“你做的这张桌子可不是什么精品，这是一张又旧又差的小桌子。”

“这是一张自动上菜的桌子，”儿子回答说，“我把它放在地上，叫它上菜，桌上马上就会有很好的菜肴，还有令人开心的葡萄酒。你去请所有的亲朋好友来高高兴兴地美餐一顿吧，小桌子会让他们吃个够的。”客人来了，他把小桌子放在房间正中，说：“小桌子，上菜吧！”可是小桌子毫无动静，桌上什么东西也没有，和别的听不懂人话的桌子没什么两样。这时，可怜的木匠发现桌子被人调换了，站在那儿，羞愧难当，好像自己是个说谎话的人似的。亲友们取笑他一番，回家去了，什么也没吃，什么也没喝。父亲又拿出布料来继续做裁缝活，儿子去一个师傅那儿做工。

二儿子在一个磨坊主那儿当学徒。学徒期满时，师傅说：“你干得很好，我要送你一头特别的驴子，它不拉车，也不驮口袋。”

“那它究竟能派什么用场呢？”年轻人问。

“它会吐出金子，”磨坊主回答说，“你把它放在一块布上，嘴里念‘布列克勒布列特’，这顶好的牲口就会给你吐金币出来，前面后面一起吐。”

“是个好东西啊！”年轻人说，谢过师傅，就带上驴子去远游了。他需要金子的时候，只要对驴子说“布列克勒布列特”，金币就像雨一样落下来，他只需把它们捡起来就是了。无论他到哪里，总是要最好的东西，越是昂贵的，他越喜爱，因为他的钱袋总是满满的。他在各处看了一段时间以后，心里想：“得去看看父亲，带着这头金驴回去，他会忘了恼怒，好好待我的。”他来到把他哥哥的小桌子给调换了的那家客店，手里牵着驴子，老板要接过这牲口，把它拴起来，没想到年轻人说：“不麻烦你了，我自己把驴子牵去牲口棚拴着吧，我得知道它在哪儿。”店主认为一个需要自己照管驴子的人，吃不起多少东西，所以，当年轻人从口袋里掏出两块金币，要他只管把好酒好菜给他端来的时候，他好生奇怪，不由睁大了眼睛，跑去找他能搞到的最好的东西。吃完了饭，客人问该付多少钱，老板想多敲些竹杠，就说还得再给几个金币。年轻人一摸口袋，金币已经完了。“请稍等片刻，老板先生，”他说，“我去取了金币就来。”顺手把桌布带走。老板莫名其妙，心里好奇，悄悄跟在他后面。因为客人把牲口棚的门插上了，他就从门缝里偷看，只见客人把桌布铺在驴蹄下面，口念“布列克勒布列特”，这牲口就前面后面都吐出金子，金子雨点一般地落在地上。“哎呀呀，了不得，”老板说，“金币一会儿就铸好了！有这么个钱袋子倒是不赖啊！”客人付了钱，倒头就睡，老板却偷偷溜进牲口棚，牵走铸金币的能手，把另一头驴子拴在那儿。第二天一大早，年轻人牵了驴子就走，以为那就是他的金驴子。中午时分，他回到父亲家里，父亲见他回来，非常高兴。“你当了什么了，我的儿子？”老头子问。

“当了磨坊伙计，亲爱的爸爸。”他回答道。

“你在各处漫游，带什么东西回来了？”

“只有一头驴子，别的什么也没有。”

“驴子这里多的是，”父亲说，“要是有一只好山羊更好。”

“不错，”儿子回答说，“不过这不是一头普通的驴子，这是金驴子，我只要说一声‘布列克勒布列特’，这顶好的牲口就会在一块布上吐出一大堆金币。你去把所有的亲戚都请来，我要让他们都成为富翁。”

“这，我就太高兴了，”裁缝说，“以后我就不用那么辛苦地缝制衣服了。”他赶快跑去叫亲戚们来。他们一到齐，磨坊伙计就请他们让开点儿地方，在地上铺一块布，把驴子牵进房间。“现在请大家注意了！”他说完就念起“布列克勒布列特”，可是，掉下来的不是金币，并且这牲口根本不懂他那门艺术，因为不是每一头驴子都有那种本事。可怜的磨坊伙计拉长了脸，明白自己上当了，他请求亲戚们原谅，最后亲戚们走了，跟来的时候一样贫困。无奈，老头子只得又拿起针线，年轻人只得又去给一个磨坊主干活。

老三给一个车木师傅当学徒，因为这门手艺需要很高的技巧，所以他学习的时间要更长一些。他的两个哥哥写信告诉他说他们多么倒霉，客店老板如何在他们快到家的前一天晚上骗走了他们顶好的宝物。车木工学成后要去漫游，因为他做得很好，师傅送他一个口袋，说：“口袋里有一根短棍。”

“口袋我可以背着，对我很有用，短棍放在口袋里有什么用？只是增加分量罢了。”

“我这就告诉你，”师傅回答说，“如果有人欺负你，你只要说‘短棍，从口袋出来吧！’这短棍就会跳出来，跳到人们中间，兴高采烈地在他们背上跳舞，叫他们八天动弹不得，要等到你说‘短棍，回口袋里去吧！’它才停下。”小伙子谢过师傅，背起口袋走了。遇到有人侮辱他，要和他动手，他就说：“短棍，从口袋出来吧！”棍子就从口袋里跳出来，不管他们穿着外衣还是背心，没等他们脱下来，上去就一顿狠揍，而且速度很快，人家还没看清楚是怎么回事就挨揍了。黄昏时分，年轻的车木工来到他的两个哥哥受骗上当的那家客店。他把背包放在面前的桌子上，便讲开了他在各地看到的稀奇古怪的事情。“不错，”他说，“有人大概见到一张会自动上菜的小桌子、一头金驴子和诸如此类的东西：这些都是好玩意儿，我不小看它们，可是要跟我得到的、现在就在我口袋里的宝贝比起来，那都算不了什么。”老板竖起耳朵听着，“老天爷啊，这会是什么宝贝？”他想，“口袋里没准儿装的都是宝石，这东西也该归我，好事成三嘛！”到了睡觉的时候，客人在凳子上躺下，把他的口袋垫在脑袋底下当枕头。老板觉得客人睡熟了，走过去轻轻地小心翼翼地拉一下口袋，看能不能抽出来换上另一个枕头。车木工早就等着这一手，老板大着胆子正要偷梁换柱的当儿，车木工喊一声：“短棍，从口袋出来吧！”短棍马上跳出口袋，飞到老板身上，狠狠揍他，打得他大喊饶命。他叫喊得越响，短棍应和着他叫喊的节拍打他的背，打得越狠，最后他筋疲力尽，倒在地上。车木工问他：“你不交出自动上菜的小桌子和金驴子，就还得挨揍。”

“啊，别打了，”老板低声下气地说，“我心甘情愿退还所有的一切，只求你快让这魔棍回到口袋里去吧！”车木伙计说：“且饶你一回，你要使坏可得当心！”说罢，喊一声“短棍，回口袋里去吧！”让棍子歇歇。

第二天，车木工带着自动上菜的小桌子和金驴子回到父亲家里。裁缝又再见到儿子，非常高兴，问他在外地都学了些什么。“亲爱的爸爸，”他回答说，“我当了车木工了。”

“这是需要很高技术的手艺。”父亲说，“你在各处漫游，带什么东西回来了？”

“一件很贵重的东西，亲爱的爸爸，”儿子回答说，“一根短棍，在口袋里。”

“什么？!”父亲叫喊起来，“一根短棍！从哪棵树上都能砍一根短棍，还值得这么费事老远地带来！”

“这可不是那种普通的棍子，亲爱的爸爸，我一说‘短棍，从口袋出来吧’，棍子就跳出来，狠狠地打那个对我不怀好意的人，直打得他躺在地上求饶才罢休。那个客店老板偷走我哥哥们的自动上菜的小桌子和金驴子，你看，我用这棍子把这两样东西都要回来了。现在你把他们叫来，也把所有亲戚都请来，我要宴请他们，还要让他们的口袋装满黄金。”老裁缝真不敢相信，但他还是把亲戚们都请来了。车木工在房间里铺上一块布，把金驴子牵进来，对他的哥哥说：“亲爱的哥哥，现在你对它说吧！”磨坊工人说：“布列克勒布列特。”霎时间，金币像暴雨一般倾泻在布上，一直到大家再也拿不动了，金驴子才停止吐金币。（我看得出来，你也很想当时能在场。）之后，车木工拿出小桌子，说：“亲爱的哥哥，现在你对它说吧！”木匠刚说出：“小桌子，上菜吧！”桌子已经铺好，摆满了最漂亮的碗碟。善良的裁缝从来没在他家里办过这么丰盛的酒席，所有的亲戚都一起待到深夜，大家都非常快乐。裁缝把针线锁起来，把尺子和熨斗放在柜子里面，和他的三个儿子一起过着美满幸福的生活。

山羊哪里去了，那只使裁缝赶走他的儿子的有罪的山羊？我这就跟你讲。它被剃了光头，没脸见人，钻到狐狸的洞穴里躲了起来。狐狸回家时在黑暗中看见迎面一对亮闪闪的大眼睛，吓得转身就跑。遇见熊，狐狸很慌张，熊问道：“狐兄，你怎么了，脸色这么难看？”

“唉，”狐狸答道，“一只凶猛的野兽占据了我的洞穴，一对火眼直瞪着我。”

“咱们这就去把它赶跑。”熊说着和狐狸一起来到洞穴，往里面张望，见了那一双火眼，熊也胆怯，转身就跑，不想和那头恶兽打交道。蜜蜂遇见熊，看它神色不对，便说：“老熊，你满脸懊丧的样子，你的高兴劲儿丢到哪儿去了？”

“你说得轻巧，”熊回答说，“一头凶猛的野兽蹲在狐狸家里，我们没法子把它赶跑。”

“我很同情你，老熊，”蜜蜂说，“我是个可怜的弱小的生物，你们在路上都不肯正眼看我一下，可我相信我能帮你们的忙。”它飞进狐狸洞里，停在山羊剃得精光的脑袋上，狠狠蜇它，蜇得山羊跳起来，咩咩地狂叫着，发疯似地窜了出去，到现在谁也不知道它究竟跑到哪里去了。

死神教父

有一个穷人有十二个孩子，他得夜以继日地工作，才能养活他们。当他的第十三个孩子出生时，他想不出什么办法能摆脱困境，就跑到大路上去，想找他遇到的第一个人当教父。他遇到的第一个人是上帝。上帝已经知道他的心事，对他说：“可怜的人啊，我同情你，我要给你的孩子行洗礼，我要照顾他，使他在人间生活幸福。”

穷人说：“你是谁？”

“我是上帝。”

“那我就不请你做教父了，”那人说，“你只把好处给富人，让穷人挨饿。”穷人这么说，因为他不知道上帝把财富和贫困分配得多么明智。于是他从上帝那儿走开了。

这时魔鬼向他走过来，说：“你寻找什么？如果你愿意让我做你的孩子的教父，我要给他很多很多金子，还给他世上所有的快乐。”

穷人问：“你是谁？”

“我是魔鬼。”

“那我就不请你做教父了，”那人说，“你欺骗人，还诱惑人。”他继续走，这时，瘦腿的死神向他大步走来，说：“让我做教父吧！”

“你是谁？”

“我是死神，我对所有人一视同仁。”

穷人说：“你正合适，你带走富人，也带走穷人，不厚此薄彼，就请你做教父吧！”

死神回答说：“我要让你的孩子富有并且出名，谁和我交朋友，亏待不了他。”

穷人说：“下星期天就行洗礼，你要准时来。”死神果然去了，堂堂皇皇地当了教父。

男孩长大了，有一天，教父来叫他一起出去，把他带到森林里，指给他看生长在那儿的一种草，说：“现在要你领受教父送你的礼物。我要让你成为一位著名的医生。如果你去给一个病人看病，每次你总能见到我。如果我站在病人脑袋旁边，你就尽管说，你能让他恢复健康，给他一些这种草药，他就好了；如果我站在病人的脚边，这人就是我的，你就得说，什么办法都没用了，世界上没有一个医生能救活他。但是你要当心，不许违背我的意志乱用药，否则你就要遭殃。”

不久，年轻人就成了世上最著名的医生了。“他只要看一下病人，就知道病情如何，知道病人能够恢复健康，还是必死无疑。”人们都这样谈论他，从老远的地方来请他去给病人看病，给他很多金子，不久，他就成了富翁。有一次，国王病了，叫他去问能不能治好。他来到病床前，看见死神站在病人脚边，病人必死无疑了。“我骗一下死神，”医生心里这样想，“他自然会恼火，不过我是他的教子，他会睁一只眼闭一只眼的。我要冒一次险。”他便抱起病人，把他调转过来，这样，死神就在他的脑袋旁边了。他又给他一些草药，国王经过调养，恢复了健康。死神来找医生，面色阴沉凶狠，用手指指着他威胁道：“你欺骗我！这一次我饶了你，因为你是我的教子。但是，如果你胆敢再愚弄我，我就要你的命。”

过不多久，国王的女儿得了重病。国王就只有这个孩子，他日夜哀哭，哭瞎了双眼。他下令宣布：谁能医治好她的病，就招他为驸马，并且让他继承王位。医生来到公主的床前，看见死神站在公主脚边。他本应记得他的教父的警告，可是公主的非凡美貌和做她的丈夫的福分使他迷了心窍，把一切顾虑全都抛到九霄云外去了。他顾不上看死神向他投去的愤怒的目光和高高地举起来威胁他的干枯的拳头，把公主抱起来，把她的头放在她的双脚原先的位置，再给了她一些草药。公主很快变得双颊红润，重新获得了生命的活力。

死神发现自己第二次受骗，大步流星地向医生走去，说：“你完蛋了，现在轮到你了。”说着，用他那冷冰冰的手牢牢抓住医生，医生无法反抗，只好随着他下地狱。在那里，他看见万点烛光，一排排望不到尽头，有的光点很大，有的不大不小，有的很小。每时每刻都有一些烛光熄灭，又有一些点燃起来，看上去好像小火焰在不停地跳过来跳过去似的。“你看，”死神说，“这就是人类的生命之火。大的烛光是属于孩子们的，不大不小的是中年夫妇们的，小的烛光是白发老人的。不过有些孩子和年轻人的烛光很小，也是常有的事。”

“告诉我，哪个是我的烛光？”医生说，心里以为他的生命的烛光还挺大。死神指着一小截快烧完了的蜡烛头说：“你看，这就是。”

“啊，教父，”医生吓坏了，说，“给我点一支新的吧，求求你，让我能享受生活，做国王，做美丽的公主的丈夫。”

“我不能，”死神回答说，“得先有一支蜡烛熄灭，才能点一支新的。”

“那就把旧的接在新的上面，旧的点完了，新的接着点。”医生请求说。死神做出愿意满足他的愿望的样子，拿了一支新点燃的大蜡烛过来，但他为了报复，在接蜡烛的时候故意让那蜡烛头掉下去熄灭了。医生立马栽倒在地上，他自己落到死神手里了。

六只天鹅

有一天，一个国王在一座大森林里打猎，他兴致勃勃地追逐一只猎物，他的随从都被他抛在了后面。夜晚来临，他停下环顾四周，发现自己迷路了。这时他看见一个老太婆摇晃着脑袋向他走过来。这是一个巫婆。“亲爱的太太，”他对她说，“你能告诉我怎么走出这森林吗？”

“啊，没问题，国王陛下，”她回答说，“我可以告诉你，不过有一个条件如果你不能答应我，你就永远无法走出森林，只能饿死在这里。”

“请问是什么条件？”国王问。

“我有一个女儿，”老太婆说，“她很漂亮，世上很难再找到第二个像她这么漂亮的女子，她完全配得上做你的妻子。如果你愿意娶她做王后，我就指给你走出森林的路。”

国王心里害怕，就答应了。老太婆领国王到她的小屋，她的女儿就坐在屋子里的火炉旁边。她迎接国王，好像她正等待他到来。他看出她很漂亮，但是并不喜欢她，他注视她的时候，心里总暗暗感到恐惧。他把这姑娘抱上马后，老太婆给他指路，国王回到王宫，举行了婚礼。

国王曾经结过一次婚，他的第一个妻子生了七个孩子，六个男孩和一个女孩。国王爱他的孩子超过世上的一切。现在他担心继母会虐待他们，就把他们送到森林深处一座孤零零的宫殿里去住。这宫殿的位置非常隐蔽，很难找到，如果不是一个聪明的女人送给他一个神奇的线团，他自己也无法找到。他把这线团往面前一扔，那团线就自己展开，为他指引道路。国王经常去探望他的孩子们，这引起了王后的注意。她很好奇，想知道国王独自一人去森林里究竟干些什么。她给他的侍从们很多钱，他们向她泄漏了那个秘密，并且告诉她只有那团线能指明道路。她心中无法平静，直至探明国王把那线团保存在什么地方，然后她做了几件白绸子小衬衣，把一种魔力缝到了里面去。原来她跟她母亲学过巫术。一次，国王出去打猎，她就带上小衬衣走进了森林，线团给她带路。孩子们远远地看见有人来，以为是他们亲爱的父亲来看望他们，兴高采烈地跑来迎接。她往他们头上每人扔过去一件小衬衣，小衬衣一碰着他们的身体，他们就变成了天鹅，越过森林上空飞走了。王后快活地回家，以为国王前妻的孩子都被她处置了。可是那女孩没有和她的哥哥们一起跑去迎接，王后对她一无所知。第二天，国王回来，要去看望他的孩子们，但他只见到小姑娘一个人。“你的哥哥们呢？”国王问。

“啊，亲爱的父亲，”她回答说，“他们到别处去了，只留下我一个人在这里。”她向国王叙述她的哥哥们如何变成天鹅，从森林上空飞走，她让国王看她在院子里捡到的他们掉下的羽毛。国王非常难过，但他没想到这坏事是王后干的。他担心小姑娘也会给掳走，要带她一同回去。但她害怕继母，便请求国王允许她再留在森林里过一个夜晚。

可怜的姑娘心里想：“我不能在这里久留，我要去找我的哥哥们。”黑夜降临，她向森林深处走去，走了一整夜，第二天继续走，一直走到累得再也走不动了。她看见山坡上有一个小屋，她爬上去，发现一间小房间，里面有六张小床，但她不敢躺在小床上，而是爬到一张小床下面，躺在坚硬的地面上，想在那里过夜。夕阳快要西沉的时候，她听见一阵风声，看见六只天鹅从窗外飞进来。天鹅们落在地上，互相往身上吹气，吹掉身上所有的羽毛，身上的天鹅皮就像一件衬衣一样脱下来了。小姑娘望着他们，认出是她的哥哥们，非常高兴，就从床下爬出来。哥哥们见了小妹妹，也非常高兴，但他们的欢乐为时短暂。“你不能在这里久留，”他们对小妹妹说，“这是一个强盗窝，他们回来一发现你，就会把你杀掉。”

“你们就不能保护我吗？”小妹妹问。

“不能，”他们回答说，“因为我们每天晚上只有一刻钟时间能脱掉天鹅皮，恢复人形，过了这一刻钟我们就又变成天鹅了。”小姑娘哭了，她说：“那你们就没法解脱了吗？”

“啊，难啊，”他们回答说，“我们变回人形条件非常苛刻，那就是，六年的时间里，你不许说话，不许笑，在这段时间里你还得为我们用紫箢缝制六件小衬衣。只要从你的嘴里说出一个字，就前功尽弃。”哥哥们说完这话，一刻钟的时间已经过去，他们又变成天鹅飞出了窗外。

但是小姑娘下了坚定的决心，即使付出生命的代价，也要拯救她的哥哥们。她离开小屋，走到密林深处，爬到一棵树上坐下来，在那里度过一夜。第二天早晨，她出去采集紫箢，开始缝衣。她不可以和任何人说话，她也没有兴致笑，她坐在那儿，专心致志地工作。她在那里度过了很长时间。有一天，那个国家的国王到这森林里打猎，国王的猎人们来到姑娘坐着的那棵树下。他们大声问她：“你是谁？”但她不回答。“你下来吧，”他们说，“我们不会欺负你的！”她只是摇头，仍不开口。猎人们继续问她，她把她的金项链扔下来给他们，心里想，这样他们就会满足了。可是他们仍不罢休。她又把她的腰带扔给他们，还是无济于事。她又扔下她的袜带，就这样把身上穿戴的一件一件扔下去，最后只剩下一件小衬衣。猎人们仍不肯走，他们爬到树上，把姑娘抱下来，带她到国王跟前。国王问：“你是谁？你在树上做什么？”她不回答。国王用他会的所有语言问她，她始终像鱼一样默不作声。但她很美丽，国王动心了，深深地爱上了她。他用他的大衣裹着她的身体，把她抱上他的马，带她回宫。他让人给她穿上华丽的衣裳，她容光焕发、光彩照人，但她一句话也不说。他把她抱起来放在桌旁，和他坐在一起，他非常喜爱她那谦逊文静的仪态，他说：“我就要娶你，除了你，世上任何人我都不娶。”几天以后，他和她结婚了。

国王的母亲是个凶狠的老婆子，她不满意这桩婚事，说年轻的王后的坏话。“谁知道这丫头是哪里来的，”她说，“话也不会说，她配不上国王。”一年后，王后生了第一个孩子，老婆子把孩子抱走，趁王后熟睡时在她嘴唇涂抹上血迹，接着跑去向国王告状，说她是个吃人精。国王不信，不能容忍别人伤害她。她还是一直坐着缝制小衬衣，对其他事情一概不闻不问。第二年，王后又生了一个漂亮的男孩，虚伪的婆婆又故伎重演，国王难以决断是否应该相信他母亲的话。他说：“她极为虔诚而善良，不致于做出这种事来。她不会说话，无法为自己辩护，否则她必定能证明自己是清白无辜的。”可是，当老婆子第三次偷走初生的婴儿，又去告王后的状的时候，王后还是没有说一句话为自己辩白，国王很无奈，只好把她交给法庭，法庭判处用烈火将她处死。

执行处决的那一天，同时也就是不许她说话不许她笑的六年的最后一天，她即将把她亲爱的哥哥们从巫术的魔力中解救出来。六件小衬衣缝制好了，只是最后一件小衬衣还缺左边的袖子。她被带上火刑场的柴堆时，她把那些小衬衣放在胳膊上，快要点火的时候，她站在柴堆上举目环顾，只见六只天鹅破空飞来。她知道她获救的时刻临近了，她的心儿激动、欢欣。天鹅嗖嗖地向她飞来，低低地围在她身旁，让她能把衬衣抛给它们。它们一碰到衬衣，身上的天鹅皮就掉了，她的哥哥们一个个恢复了人形，生气勃勃而又英俊，只有最小的哥哥还缺左臂，背上长着一只天鹅的翅膀。他们互相拥抱、亲吻。国王十分惊愕，王后走到国王跟前，开口说：“亲爱的丈夫，现在我可以说话了，我要向你说明：我被人诬告了，我是清白无辜的。”她向他揭穿老婆子的谎言，是她抱走她的三个孩子，把他们藏了起来。孩子们被送到了国王那里，国王很高兴。恶婆婆受到了惩罚，她被送到柴堆上烧成灰烬。国王、王后和王后的六个哥哥一起幸福安宁地生活了很多很多年。

金鸟

古代有一个国王，他的宫殿后面有一座美丽的花园，园中有一棵能结出金苹果的树。苹果熟了的时候，是数了数的，可是第二天就发现少了一只。国王得到报告，下令每天夜里都要有人在树下看守。国王有三个儿子，夜幕降临时，他派大儿子到花园去，半夜时分，他熬不住睡着了，第二天早晨又少了一只苹果。第二夜该二儿子去看守，他也好不了多少：钟敲十二点时，他睡着了，早上发现又少了一只苹果。现在轮到第三个儿子了，他也做好了准备，但国王不怎么信得过他，以为他可能还不如他的两个哥哥；不过最终还是准许他去了。这年轻人躺在树下，他醒着，不让睡意控制自己。钟敲十二下时，他听见空中传来“嗖嗖”的响声，月光下看见飞来一只鸟儿，浑身羽毛金光闪耀。鸟儿落在树上，它正要啄下一只苹果，年轻人向它射了一箭。鸟飞走了，但那支箭射中它的羽毛，一根金羽毛落到地上。年轻人把它捡起来，第二天送去给国王看，向他讲述夜间看到的情景。国王召集他的大臣，人人都说像这样的羽毛一根就比整个王国还要宝贵。“既然这羽毛这么珍贵，”国王宣称，“只有一根远远不够，我要整只金鸟，无论如何都要得到它！”

于是大王子启程去找金鸟，他自以为很聪明，找到它不成问题。他走了一段路，看见一只狐狸蹲在森林边上，他举起火枪向它瞄准。狐狸大叫：“别开枪，我要给你出个好主意。你要去找金鸟，今天晚上你将走到一个村庄，那儿有两家客店彼此隔街相对。一家灯火明亮、热闹非凡，这一家你可别进去，要进另一家客店，虽然它看起来破败、冷清。”

“这么愚蠢的畜生还能给我出什么好主意！”王子心里想着，就扣动扳机，但没打中，狐狸竖起尾巴飞快跑进森林。王子一路走下去，傍晚来到两家客店隔街相望的村子，一家客店里有人在唱歌跳舞，另一家却冷冷清清，一副寒碜相。“要是放着这家热闹的客店不住，”他想，“去住那穷酸客店，我就真是个傻瓜了。”他便走进那家热闹的客店，在那里花天酒地，把金鸟儿、父王和所有忠告、教诲统统忘了。

过了一段时日，左等右等，总不见大儿子回来，二王子就启程去寻找金鸟。他像大王子一样，也遇见了狐狸，狐狸给他出个好主意，但他听不进去。他走近那两家客店，他哥哥站在传出喧嚣声的那家客店窗前呼唤他。他抵挡不住诱惑，便进去尽情享乐。

又过了一段时间，小王子也要出去试试运气，父亲不让他去。“这是白费力气，”他说，“他还不如他哥哥，怎么能找到金鸟？要是遇上什么不幸，他也毫无办法；三兄弟就数他最无能。”但国王被他吵得心神不宁，最后也只好让他走了。那只狐狸又蹲在森林边上，求他饶命，同时要给他忠告。小王子心地善良，说：“放心吧，小狐狸，我不伤害你。”

“我不会让你后悔的，”狐狸回答说，“你骑在我的尾巴上，这样能快一点到。”小王子刚骑上去，狐狸就飞奔起来，越过种种障碍，毛发在风中嗖嗖作响。他们来到那座村庄，小王子下来，他接受狐狸的忠告，径直走进那家寒碜的小客店，安安静静地在那里过了一夜。第二天早晨他走到田野上，狐狸已经蹲在那里，它说：“我还要告诉你该怎么办。你一直朝前面走，最后你会走到一座宫殿前面，那里躺着一大群士兵，你不用管他们，他们都在睡觉、打呼噜。你从他们中间穿过去，径直走进宫殿，穿过所有房间，最后你就到了一间挂着一个木鸟笼的房间，金鸟就在那木鸟笼里。旁边有一个空的华丽的金鸟笼，那是放在那儿当摆设的，你可得当心别把金鸟从那个难看的鸟笼里拿出来放进华丽的鸟笼里去，否则你会遭殃的。”说完这一席话，狐狸又翘起尾巴，让王子骑上去：狐狸飞奔起来，越过种种障碍，毛发在风中嗖嗖响。到了王宫一看，果然一切全跟狐狸说的一模一样。王子走进那房间，金鸟蹲在木鸟笼里，旁边还有一个金鸟笼；三只金苹果随便地放在地上。他想：“让这只美丽的鸟儿待在又平常、又难看的鸟笼里，太可惜了！”便打开鸟笼，捉住金鸟，把它放到金鸟笼里面。就在这一瞬间，金鸟一声尖叫，士兵们醒了，冲进来把他捉进监牢。第二天早晨，他在法庭受审，因为他对一切供认不讳，便被判处死刑。但是，国王说可以饶他不死，不过有一个条件：如果他能把那匹跑得比风还快的金马找来给他，他还可以赏赐他金鸟。

王子上路了，但他唉声叹气，心中悲伤，叫他到哪儿去找金马呢？忽然，他看见他的老朋友狐狸蹲在路旁。“你看，”狐狸说，“你不听我的话，事情搞糟了。不过你要振作起来，我还要关照你，告诉你怎么找到金马。你一直朝前走，就会走到一座宫殿那儿，金马就在马厩里。马厩前面躺着几个马夫，他们都睡着了在打呼噜，你可以从容不迫地把马牵出来。不过有一点你要注意：要给那匹马装上用木料和皮革做的马鞍，不能给它装上金马鞍，否则你会遭殃的。”说罢，狐狸翘起尾巴，王子骑上去，狐狸飞奔起来，越过种种障碍，毛发在风中嗖嗖作响。一切果然和狐狸说的一模一样。他走进金马所在的马厩，但当他要把次的马鞍放在马背上的时候，他想：“如果我不给他安上一副和他般配的鞍子，那就太辱没这匹好马了。”金马鞍刚碰着马背，那马一声长嘶，众马夫醒了，捉住年轻人，把他投入监狱。第二天，法庭判处他死刑，但国王允诺饶他一命，并把金马赠送给他，条件是如果他能把美丽的公主从黄金宫殿里带出来的话。

年轻人心情沉重地踏上旅途，幸运的是，他很快就见到了忠实的狐狸。“我本该叫你吃些苦头才是，”狐狸说，“不过我同情你，我要再一次帮助你摆脱困境。这条路直通黄金宫殿，晚上你就到那儿了。夜深人静时，美丽的公主要去浴室洗浴。她一进去，你随即跟上去给她一个吻，她就会跟你走，你就可以把她带走了。只是千万不能让公主和她父母告别，否则你就要遭殃。”说罢，狐狸翘起尾巴，王子骑上去，狐狸飞奔起来，越过种种障碍，毛发在风中嗖嗖响。到了黄金宫殿，情况果然像狐狸说的那样。他等到午夜时分，人们全都沉沉入梦了，美丽的少女走进浴室，他立即冲上去吻了她一下。她说，她愿意和他一起走，但她流着眼泪恳求他允许她和她父母告别。起初他不同意她的请求，但她哭得越来越伤心，还跪在他脚下哀求，他终于让步了。可是，公主刚走近她父亲床前，他就醒了，宫中所有人都醒了，他们把王子抓起来，关进监狱。

第二天早晨，国王对他说：“你的命完了，如果你在八天内能把在窗前挡住我的视线的那座山铲走，就饶你不死，还要把我女儿嫁给你。”王子开始不停地挖山，七天过后，他看自己挖得太少，所干的活加起来和没干也差不多，十分伤心，不再抱什么希望了。第七天晚上狐狸来了，说：“你那么不听劝告，不值得我帮助。不过，你就睡觉去吧，我替你干活。”第二天早晨他一觉醒来，望着窗外，那座山已经不见了。年轻人兴高采烈地跑去向国王报告事情办好了，不管国王愿意不愿意，他只得遵守诺言，把女儿许给他。

于是王子带上公主一起上路，走了没多久，忠实的狐狸来找他们，说：“最好的你虽然有了，但是金马还得和金殿公主在一起。”

“怎样才能得到金马呢？”王子问。

“我来告诉你，”狐狸回答说，“你先带着美丽的公主去见派你去金殿的国王。他一定非常高兴，愿意把金马牵出来送给你。你立即骑上马，俯身伸手向所有的人们告别，最后向美丽的公主告别时，你抓住她的手，一下子把她拉上马，远走高飞，没有人能追上你，因为金马跑得比风还快。”

一切顺利完成了，王子带上美丽的公主骑着金马走了。狐狸并没留下，它对王子说：“现在我还要帮你得到金鸟。快到关着金鸟的宫殿的时候，你让公主下马，我来保护她。你骑着金马进宫去。他们见了，一定非常高兴，会把金鸟给你拿出来。鸟笼一到了你手里，你立刻飞奔回来找我们，接走你的公主。”计策成功了，王子正要带着他的宝贝骑马回家，这时，狐狸说：“我帮了你的忙，现在该你报答我了。”

“你想要什么？”年轻人问。

“我们到了那座森林里面，你就开枪把我打死，砍下我的脑袋和爪子。”

“这不是忘恩负义嘛！”王子说，“我绝不能这样待你。”

狐狸说：“如果你不愿意这么做，我只好离开你。不过在我走之前，我还要给你一个忠告。两件事你要当心：不要买绞架上的肉，不要坐在水井旁边。”狐狸说罢，跑进森林里去了。

年轻人心里想：“这真是只奇特的动物，净是些古怪念头。谁会去买绞架上的肉！还有，我从来也没想过要在水井旁边坐一下。”他带着美丽的公主继续骑马往前走，又来到他的两个哥哥待着的那个村子。那里人声鼎沸，人群熙熙攘攘。他问出什么事了，有人告诉他要吊死两个人。他走近一看，原来是他的两个哥哥，他们干尽了坏事，花光了所有钱财。他问能不能放了他们。“如果您肯花钱赎他们，当然可以，”人们回答说，“可是您花钱买这两个坏蛋干什么呀？”他想也不想一下，就付钱赎了他们；两人获释，三兄弟结伴同行。

他们来到当初遇见狐狸的那座森林，太阳很毒，森林里清凉舒适，两个哥哥说：“我们在水井旁边坐下休息一会儿，吃点东西，喝点水吧。”小王子同意，说话间不知不觉就在水井旁边坐下，丝毫没料到会有什么危险。两个哥哥从后面把他推到井里，带着公主、金马和金鸟回家去见他们的父王。“我们不仅带回金鸟，”他们说，“还把金马和金殿公主都抢过来了。”大家喜气洋洋，但金马不吃草，金鸟不唱歌，公主坐着只是哭泣。

小弟弟并没有死。幸亏那井是口枯井，他摔在绵软的苔藓上，没有受伤，可是没法出来。这次又是那只忠实的狐狸救他脱险，它跳下井，责骂他忘了它的忠告。“我不能丢下你不管，”它说，“我要帮你重见天日。”它叫小王子紧紧抓住它的尾巴，然后把王子拉上去。“你还没有完全脱离危险，”狐狸说，“你的两个哥哥还不能确定你已经死了，他们派兵把这片林子包围了起来，你一露面，就会被他们杀死。”这时恰巧有个穷人坐在路边，王子和他换穿衣服，用这个办法回到国王宫中。没有一个人认出他，可是鸟儿又开始歌唱，马儿又开始吃草，美丽的公主也不再哭了。国王纳闷地问道：“这是怎么回事？”公主说：“我不知道，但是我原来那么伤心，现在我非常快乐。我觉得是我真正的未婚夫回来了。”尽管那两个哥哥威胁她，如果她泄漏什么，就要将她处死，她还是把发生的一切事情原原本本讲给了国王听。国王命令把王宫里所有的人都带来见他，小王子也来了，他衣衫褴褛，像个穷人，但公主一眼就认出他来，搂着他的脖子。那两个邪恶的哥哥被抓住处死，他和美丽的公主结婚了，并被指定为国王的继承人。

可怜的狐狸后来怎么样了？很久以后，有一天，王子又到森林里去，狐狸遇见他，说：“你希望得到的一切，现在你都有了，可是我的苦难还没有尽头，你是完全有能力解救我的。”它再次恳求王子射死它，砍下它的头和爪子。王子照它说的做了，刚刚做完，狐狸马上变成一个人，此人正是美丽的公主的哥哥，他终于解除了身上的魔法而获救。他们一生再没有什么痛苦，生活得非常幸福。

蜂王

有一次，两个王子出去冒险，竟过起放荡荒唐的生活，根本不再回家。叫作“小笨蛋”的最小的王子动身去找他的哥哥，终于找到他们，他们却嘲笑他，说他头脑这么简单，还想去闯世界，他们两个聪明得多，尚且不行。他们三人一起往前走，来到一个蚂蚁穴跟前。两个哥哥要捅蚂蚁穴，看小蚂蚁如何惊恐地搬运蚁卵，小笨蛋却说：“让小蚂蚁安宁吧，我不能容忍你们打扰它们。”他们继续往前走，来到一个湖边，湖面上游着许多鸭子。两个哥哥要捉几只来烤，小笨蛋不同意，说：“让小鸭子安宁吧，我不能容忍你们杀死它们。”他们来到一个蜂窝旁边，蜂窝里蜂蜜多得顺着树干往下流淌。两个哥哥要在树下点把火，熏死蜜蜂，好取走蜂蜜。小笨蛋又制止他们说：“让小蜜蜂安宁吧，我不能容忍你们烧死它们。”三兄弟终于来到一座宫殿，那里马厩里立着的都是石马，也看不见一个人影。他们穿过所有大厅，一直走到尽头一扇门前，门上挂着三把锁，门正中有个小窗，可以看到屋里。他们看见一个白发苍苍的小老头坐在一张桌子旁边。他们喊他一声，又喊一声，他都听不见，喊第三声时，他才站起来开锁，走出来。但他不说一句话，只领他们在一张摆着丰盛食物的桌旁坐下。吃喝完毕，老头儿又领他们去各自的卧室。第二天早晨，那个白发苍苍的小老头来找大王子，打手势把他领到一座石碑前面，碑上写着三件事，办好这三件事宫殿就能被解除魔法。第一件事是森林里苔藓下面藏着公主的一千颗珍珠，要在日落之前把它们都找出来，如果缺一颗，找珍珠的人就要变成石头。大王子去找了一整天，到日落天黑，才找到一百颗珍珠。结果像石碑上所写的那样，他变成了石头。第二天，二王子去冒险，他比老大也好不了多少，找到的不超过二百颗，他也变成了石头。最后轮到小笨蛋去苔藓里面找，但是找珍珠谈何容易，进展极其缓慢。他坐在一块石头上哭开了。正哭着，他救过命的蚂蚁王率领五千蚂蚁来了，不一会儿，这些小动物就把珍珠都找了出来，堆成了一堆。第二件事是要把公主卧室的钥匙从海里捞出来。小笨蛋来到海边，他救过命的那几只鸭子游过来，潜入海底，取出钥匙。第三件事是最难的，那就是要从睡着的三个公主当中找出那位最年轻、最可爱的公主。但是她们三个长得一模一样，毫无差别，只是入睡前吃过不同的甜食：大公主吃了一块糖，二公主吃了一点糖浆，小公主吃了一满勺蜂蜜。这时，受小笨蛋保护才没被烧死的蜂王来了，它把三个人的嘴都检查一遍，最后停在吃过蜂蜜的公主嘴上，这么一来，王子就认出要找的人来了。魔法已经破除，所有的人们都从酣睡中被解救出来，早先变成了石头的，也都恢复了人形。小笨蛋和最年轻可爱的公主结婚了，老国王去世后，他当了国王。他的两个哥哥也和公主的两个姐姐结了婚。

金孩子

从前在一间小屋里住着一个穷人和他的妻子，除了一间小屋，他们一无所有，靠捕鱼为生，勉强度日。有一天，丈夫坐在水边撒网，捕到一条浑身金色的鱼。他正十分惊奇地打量这条鱼的时候，鱼儿开口说话了：“听着，渔夫，把我放回水里去，我就把你的小屋变成一座宫殿。”渔夫回答说：“如果我一点吃的都没有，宫殿对我有什么用？”金鱼继续说：“吃的也会安排好的，宫殿里会有一个柜子，你一打开，里面有一些碗盛着最好的菜肴，你要多少，就有多少。”

“如果这样，我可以帮你这个忙。”

“好，”金鱼说，“不过有个条件：你不许告诉世界上任何人，不管是谁，你的幸福是怎么得来的。只要说出一个字，一切就都没了。”

于是渔夫把这条神奇的鱼儿又放回水里，便回家去。他原先小屋所在的地方，现在耸立着一座大宫殿。他瞪大了眼睛观看，走进宫殿，看见妻子身上穿着美丽的衣裳，坐在一间豪华的房间里。她十分愉快地说：“丈夫，怎么一下子成这样了？我真高兴。”

“是啊，”她丈夫说，“我也很高兴，我肚子饿极了，给我拿点儿吃的吧。”

“什么也没有，”妻子说，“在这新房子里面我什么也找不着。”

“这不难，”丈夫说，“我看见那边有个大柜子，你去把它打开。”她一打开柜子，里面有糕点、肉、水果和葡萄酒，让人看了喜上心头。妻子非常高兴地叫了起来：“心肝儿，你还想要什么？”他们坐下来一起吃喝。吃饱了，妻子问道：“你说，这些财富都是哪儿来的？”

“唉，别问了，”丈夫说，“我不能说，我要是对谁说了，我们的幸福就完了。”

“好，”她说，“不该我知道的，我也不想知道。”但这并不是她的真心话。她日夜心神不安，折磨她丈夫，刺激他，直到他无法忍耐，终于说出他逮着一条神奇的金鱼又放了它，这一切都是那金鱼给的。这话刚说出口，富丽堂皇的宫殿连同那个大柜子立刻就不见了，他们又坐在原先的渔民小屋里了。丈夫又得重操旧业捕鱼去。但他福星高照，又捕到那条金鱼。“听着，”鱼儿说，“如果你再放我到水里，我就把那座宫殿连同装满红烧油炸食物的柜子一起还给你。不过你不得泄露是谁给的，不然的话，一切都会再丢掉的。”

“我会小心的。”渔夫回答说，把鱼儿放回水里。家里一切又恢复了早先的豪华气派，妻子对重新获得幸福十分高兴，但好奇心使她不得安宁，过了几天，她又问起这事的来龙去脉。丈夫沉默了一段时间，最后她又整得他一气之下，把秘密泄露了出来。刹那间，宫殿不见了，他们又坐在旧渔民小屋里了。“都是你闹的，”丈夫说，“现在我们又得挨饿了。”

“啊，”妻子说，“我如果不知道财富的来路，宁可不要，否则我心里总不踏实。”

丈夫又去捕鱼，过了一段时间，他偏偏又第三次捕到那条鱼。“你听我说，”鱼儿说，“我看我几次三番落在你手里，真是命中注定；把我带回你家吧，把我切成六块，两块给你妻子吃，两块给你的马吃，两块埋在地里，这样，你会有福的。”渔夫把鱼儿带回家，照它说的办理。埋在地里的两块鱼肉后来长成了两朵金百合，马儿生了两只金马驹，渔夫的妻子生了两个孩子，浑身上下全是金的。

两个孩子渐渐长大，长得又高大又英俊，百合花、马驹和他们一同长大。他们说：“父亲，我们要骑上金马到世界上走走。”父亲忧心忡忡地回答说：“要是你们走了，我又不知道你们的情况，我怎么能受得了呢？”孩子们说：“家里有两朵金百合花，可以看到我们的情况：花儿鲜美，我们就健康；花儿枯萎，我们就有病；如果它们耷拉下来，就是我们死了。”他们骑马来到一家客店，里面有许多人，看见这两个兄弟，就笑起来，嘲弄他们。一个金孩子听了他们嘲笑，受了羞辱，不愿去闯世界了，又回到父亲身边。另一个继续往前走，来到一座大森林。他要骑马过去，人们对他说：“你不能去，森林里面有很多强盗，他们会打你的主意，他们见你和你的马都是金的，会打死你的。”但他没有被吓住，他说：“我非过去不可。”他拿了几张熊皮，把自己和马完全包裹起来，不露出一点金子，便放心大胆地骑马进森林。走了一小段路，就听见树丛里面有响动，有人在说话。有人在一侧喊：“这儿有一个人！”另一侧又有人喊：“放他走吧，这是个懒汉，穷得跟教堂里的耗子一样，没什么油水，对我们有什么用处！”就这样，金孩子幸运地穿过森林，没受到伤害。

有一天，他来到一座村庄，看见村里有个非常美丽的姑娘，他想，世上再不会有比她更漂亮的少女了。他非常爱她，便走到她跟前对她说：“我真心爱你，你愿意做我的妻子吗？”那姑娘也很喜欢他，便应允了，说：“好的，我愿意成为你的妻子，终生对你忠诚。”于是他们举行了婚礼；正当他们沉浸在最大的欢乐中的时候，新娘子的父亲回到家里，看见他女儿结了婚，感到很惊奇，他说：“你的新郎在哪里？”人们把金孩子指给他看，这时金孩子还裹着一身熊皮。父亲见了怒气冲冲地说：“决不能叫一个懒汉娶走我的女儿。”他要把他杀了。新娘子苦苦求父亲说：“他已经是我的丈夫，我从心底里爱他。”一直说到父亲怒气渐消。但他仍然存着这个念头，第二天一早起床，就要去看女儿的丈夫是不是一个衣衫褴褛的下贱乞丐。他往屋里张望，只见床上躺着一个英俊的男子，浑身金色，脱下的熊皮扔在地上。他退回去，心里想道：“好在我怒气消了，我几乎犯下大错。”

金孩子在做梦，梦见他外出狩猎，追逐一只美丽的鹿；早晨醒来，他对他的新娘子说：“我要出去打猎。”她感到害怕，请求他不要去，她说：“你很可能要遇到大灾难的。”但他回答说：“无论如何我必须去。”他随即站起来，前往森林，不多一会儿，一只骄傲的鹿果然出现在他眼前，完全像梦中的情景一样。他端起猎枪要射击，但那只鹿跑了。他在后面紧追。越过沟渠，穿过树丛，追了一整天，并不觉得疲乏；但在夜晚，鹿在他的眼前消失了。金孩子环顾周遭，他面前是一座小屋，里面坐着一个女巫。他敲门，一个老妈妈出来问道：“这么晚了，你到这大森林里来干什么？”

他说：“你看见一只鹿没有？”

“看见过，”她回答说，“我认得那只鹿。”随她从屋里出来的一只小狗冲他狂吠。“给我安静，你这混蛋，”他说，“再叫，我射死你。”女巫听了，怒喝一声：“什么，你要打死我的小狗！”马上将他变成了一块石头，躺在地上。他的新娘子等着他，老是不见他回去，心里想：“我心里害怕，心情沉重，他一定出事了。”

在家里，另一个兄弟站在金百合花旁边，突然有一株耷拉下来了。“上帝啊，”他说，“我的兄弟大难临头了，我必须前去，或许我能解救他。”他跨上金马，策马奔入他的兄弟变成石头躺着的那座大森林。老巫婆从她的房子里走出来大声和他说话，也想迷惑他，但他不走近前去，只说：“如果你不把我的兄弟救活，我就把你射死。”尽管她很不乐意，也只得用手指去摸石头，他的兄弟立刻恢复了人形，活过来了。两个金孩子重逢，他们都很高兴，互相亲吻、拥抱，一起骑马离开森林，一个去找他的新娘子，一个回到父亲身旁。父亲见了他说：“我知道你救了你的兄弟了，因为金百合一下子又挺立起来，继续开花了。”他们生活得非常快乐，一直到他们生命的终点。

穷人和富人

在古代，上帝还在人间漫游的时候，一天晚上，他感到疲乏了，还没能找到住宿的地方，黑夜已经来临。他站在路上，前面有两座房子彼此相对，一座又大又漂亮，另一座又小又寒酸。那座大房子是一个富人的，小房子是一个穷人的。

上帝想：“我到富人家去不会给他添麻烦，我要在他家里过夜。”富人听见敲门声，打开窗户问陌生人有什么事，上帝回答说：“我只请求有个地方睡觉。”

富人把行路人从头到脚打量一番，见上帝衣着朴素，不像口袋里有很多钱的样子，便摇头说：“我不能接待你，我的房间都装满草和种子，如果谁来敲我家的门，我都让他住宿，我自己就该成叫花子了。你去别处找住的地方吧。”说完，使劲关上窗户，让上帝干站着。

于是上帝转过身来向那座小房子走去。才敲一下门，穷人已经把门打开，请旅行者进去。“请在我家过夜吧，”他说，“天已经黑了，今天你不能再赶路了。”上帝听了很高兴，走进屋里到他跟前。穷人的妻子向他伸出手欢迎他说，他们没什么东西，请他随便凑合着用；如果需要什么，他们会很乐意提供。说完话，她把土豆放在炉火上，煮土豆这工夫，她去挤羊奶，打算用这点羊奶就着土豆吃。食物摆上了餐桌，上帝和他们一同坐下，一同用餐。他觉得这简单的食物味道很好，因为餐桌上有愉快的笑容。吃过晚饭，到了该睡觉的时候，女人悄悄把丈夫叫到一旁说：“亲爱的丈夫，你听我说，我们今天铺个草垫子睡一夜吧，让那个可怜的行路人在我们床上睡觉，能休息得好些。他走了一整天路，一定很累了。”

“这样很好，”他回答说，“我就让他在大床上休息。”说着，他就去跟上帝说，如果他不介意，就请他在他们的床上躺下，好好歇一歇腿脚。上帝不肯占用两个老人的卧床，但经不起他们恳请，终于同意睡他们的床，他们自己就在地上用干草打地铺。第二天早晨，天还没大亮，他们就起来了，拿出他们最好的东西给客人做早点。太阳照进窗户，上帝起床后，又同他们一起用餐。吃过早饭要上路了，上帝站在门口，转过身子说：“你们心地这么善良又这么虔诚，说出你们的三个愿望，我要使你们的愿望实现。”穷人说：“我愿能永远快乐幸福，我们俩人在世上活着的时候都健康无病，每天都有面包吃，不致挨饿；除了这三件事，我不知道还该希望得到什么。”上帝说：“这房子旧了，你不想要一所新的吗？”穷人说：“啊，如果还能得到一所新房子，我太高兴了。”于是上帝满足了他们的愿望，把他们的旧房子变成了一座新房子，再一次祝福他们，然后继续上路了。

天大亮了，富人起床，把头探出窗外，看见对门往日破旧小屋所在的地方，立起一座崭新的漂亮的红砖房，窗户明亮。他瞪大眼睛，喊妻子过来，说：“你说，这是怎么回事？昨天还是破旧的小屋，今天就变成一座漂亮的新房子了。快过去问问是怎么回事。”富人的妻子过去详细询问穷人，穷人讲给她听：“昨天晚上有一个走远路的人来投宿，今天早晨临走时他答应满足我们三个愿望：一是永远快乐幸福，二是从此健康无病，三是衣食不成问题，最后还给了我们一座漂亮的新住宅。”富人的老婆赶紧跑回去跟她丈夫讲这一切的来由。她丈夫说：“我真该死，我真该杀，早知道就好了！那个陌生人先到这里来过，是我把他撵走的。”

“唉，你呀，”老婆说，“快骑马追，还能追上那人，你得让他也满足你的三个愿望。”富人听从这好主意，策马狂奔，追上上帝。他言辞谦卑恳切，说没能立即让他进屋，请他不要见怪，因为他还没找到大门钥匙时，他已经走了。回来时请他一定到他家去。“好，”上帝说，“如果我回来，就这么办。”于是富人问，能不能像对待他的邻居那样，也满足他三个愿望。可以，亲爱的上帝说，他能办到，不过这对他没什么好处，他倒是什么都不祈求最好。但富人认为，只要能实现，他就要寻找那能给他带来幸福的东西。亲爱的上帝说：“骑马回家吧，你说的三个愿望都会实现。”

富人如愿以偿，骑马回家，开始琢磨该提些什么愿望好。他一动脑筋，手放掉缰绳，马撒欢跳跃起来，一再打断他的思路，他根本无法集中精神思考。他拍拍马的脖颈说：“安静点儿，利泽！”但马儿还是很不听话，末了他火了，暴躁地大声喊道：“那我就要你的命！”话音一落，砰的一声，他摔下来，马躺在地上动弹不了，死了。就这样，他实现了自己的第一个愿望。但他为人吝啬，不肯扔掉马鞍，便取下它来，扛在肩上，现在只能徒步走了。“我还有两个愿望，”他以此自我安慰。他在沙地上慢慢地走，时当正午，烈日烘烤，热得他心中烦躁；马鞍压得他后背疼痛，他还没想好该祈求什么。“即使祈求得到世上所有的帝国和珍宝，”他自言自语，“以后还会想要这样那样的东西，这一点现在我就很清楚；我要一劳永逸地解决问题，使我往后根本不需要再祈求什么才好。”他叹口气又接着说：“是啊，如果我是个巴伐利亚[1]农夫，也让说三个愿望，那就好办了：第一希望有很多啤酒，第二要有足够他喝的啤酒，第三还要一大桶啤酒。”有时他觉得想到合适的要求了，过一会儿又觉得那个愿望毕竟太微不足道。他脑子里想他老婆这会儿可真舒服，待在家里，坐在凉爽的房间里吃好吃的东西。这念头使他十分恼火，竟不自觉地说出：“我要她在家里坐在这马鞍上下不来，省得我驮着它！”他一说完最后一个字，背上的马鞍顿时不见了，他知道他的第二个愿望也已经实现了。这时他觉得热得难受，奔跑起来，想独自坐在他的房间里想出些伟大的东西作为他最后的愿望。可是到家一打开房门，他的老婆在房间正中坐在马鞍上没法下来，又哭又叫。他说：“别着急，我要发愿让全世界的财富都归你所有，你就好好坐着吧。”她骂他是笨蛋，说：“我坐在马鞍上下不来，全世界的财富对我有屁用；你发愿让我坐上去，就得把我再弄下来！”不管他愿意还是不愿意，他都得说出第三个愿望，让他的妻子能从马鞍上下来；这个愿望很快就实现了。富人除了气恼、辛苦和辱骂，什么也没有得到，还损失了一匹马。而穷人夫妇过着愉快、平静而虔诚的生活一直到老。

[1]联邦德国南部的一个州，旧译巴威略，慕尼黑是其首府。

会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟

从前有一个男人要去做一次长途旅行，临别的时候他问他的三个女儿，要他给她们带些什么东西。大女儿要珍珠，二女儿要钻石，三女儿却说：“亲爱的父亲，我想要一只会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟。”父亲说：“好的，如果能够找到，就给你。”于是他和三个女儿一一吻别，然后上路。待到他要踏上归途的时候，他给两个女儿买了珍珠和钻石，可是寻遍了所有地方，都找不到会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟，他心里十分难过，因为小女儿是他最心爱的孩子。他沿着一条路走进一座森林，森林深处有一座宫殿，宫殿近旁有一棵树，他看见这棵树的树梢上有一只小百灵鸟在唱歌、跳舞。“嗨，你来得正是时候。”他说，心里非常高兴，就叫仆人爬上去逮那小鸟儿。仆人刚走近那棵树，只见树下跳起一只狮子，抖动鬣毛，大吼几声，震得林木枝叶乱颤。“谁要想偷走我的会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟，”狮子吼叫道，“我就吃掉他。”那男人说：“我不知道这只鸟儿是你的，为了弥补我的过错，我愿意以重金自赎，只求你不害我性命。”狮子说：“说什么都救不了你的命，除非你答应把你一进家门第一个遇见的人或物送给我。如果你愿意这么做，我就送你一条命，这只小百灵鸟也送给你的小女儿。”那男人拒绝，说：“最先遇见我的可能是我的小女儿，她最爱我，我回家她总是跑过来迎接我。”仆人心里害怕，他说：“你最先遇见的也不一定就是你的女儿，也许是一只猫或是一只狗。”主人被他说服了，接过那只会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟，答应狮子把最先遇见的给它。

他踏进家门时，第一个前来迎接他的，不是别人，正是他最心爱的小女儿。她跑过来吻他、拥抱他，当她看见他给她带来那只会唱歌会跳舞的小百灵鸟，她高兴极了。但她的父亲高兴不起来，他哭了，说：“我最亲爱的孩子，这只小鸟儿是用了高昂的代价买来的，我不得不答应一只狂野的狮子，把你给它，他会撕碎你、吃了你的。”他把事情经过原原本本告诉了她，叫她不要去，要发生什么事情，就让它发生好了。但女儿安慰他，说：“亲爱的父亲，你既然答应了，就要信守诺言，我要去，我会让狮子平静下来的，我会再回来看你。”第二天早晨她问清楚了路，和家里人告别后便沉着地走进森林。那只狮子本是个王子，被人施了魔法，白天是狮子，他手下那些人也都变成狮子，夜间他们全都恢复原先的人形。她到达时受到亲切热情的接待，被领进王宫。夜幕降临，狮子变成一个美男子，他们举行了隆重的婚礼，夜间醒着，白天睡觉，日子过得非常快乐。有一天，他说：“明天你父亲家里举行盛宴，庆祝你的大姐结婚，如果你想去，就叫我的狮子领你去。”她说她很想去看看她父亲，于是她在众狮子陪同下回去了。回到家里，大家都非常高兴，因为他们全都以为她已被狮子撕碎，早已不在人世。她跟他们讲她的丈夫多么漂亮，她的生活多么美满。她和家人待在一起，一直到婚礼结束，才重返森林。二女儿结婚时，又邀请她参加婚礼，她对她的狮子丈夫说：“这一次我不自己一个人去了，你得和我一起去。”但是狮子说，这样做对他非常危险，因为，那儿燃烧的灯火，只要有一线灯光映照到他身上，他就会变成一只鸽子，就得和鸽子一起飞七年。“啊，”她说，“放心跟我去吧，我会小心保护你，不让你接触到一点灯光。”于是他们一同前往，把他们的小孩子也一起带去了。她让人在那里建造一座大厅，造得十分坚固厚实，透不进一丝光线，准备在点燃婚礼灯烛的时候，让他待在里面。可是门是用新木头做的，裂开了一条细小的缝隙，谁都没有察觉。婚礼十分隆重，但当新郎新娘从教堂回来，人们高举无数火炬、灯烛经过大厅时，一丝细如毫发的火光照在王子身上，光线一碰到他，霎时间，他就变成了鸽子。她又进去找他的时候，看不见他了，只见那儿有一只白鸽。鸽子对她说：“我必须在世上飞七年：我会每七步流下一滴鲜红的血，掉下一根白色羽毛，让它们给你引路，如果你跟踪找我，你就能解救我。”

说罢，鸽子飞出门外，她紧跟在它后面，它每七步流下一滴鲜红的血滴和一根洁白的羽毛，为她引路。她不停息地走着，走到遥远的远方，不看周围景物，也不休息。快满七年的时候，她很高兴，以为他们不久便可获救，其实还差得远呢。一天，她正走着，没有羽毛掉下来，也没有鲜血滴下来，她抬眼仰望，已不见白鸽的踪影。她想，人无法帮助她，于是上天去找太阳，对太阳说：“你照进所有缝隙，照耀在所有峰巅之上，你可曾看见一只飞翔的白鸽？”

“没有，”太阳说，“我没有看见白鸽，不过我送你一个小盒子，你如有危难就打开它。”她谢过太阳，继续向前走，直至夜晚降临，明月当空。她问月亮：“你整夜照着所有田野和森林，你可曾看见一只飞翔的白鸽？”

“没有，”月亮回答说，“我没有看见白鸽，不过我送你一颗鸡蛋，十分困难的时候就把它打破。”她谢过月亮，继续往前走，直至夜风渐起，吹拂着她。她问夜风：“你在所有林木上方吹拂，从一切树叶底下吹过，你可曾看见一只飞翔的白鸽？”

“没有，”夜风说，“我没有看见白鸽，不过我可以问问东风西风和南风，也许它们见过它。”东风和西风来了，它们都没有看见，但南风说：“我见过那只白鸽，它飞到红海去了，它到了那里又变成狮子，因为七年时间已经过去。雄狮在红海边和一只龙形怪兽搏斗，那龙形怪兽是一位公主中了魔法幻化成的。”夜风接着对她说：“我给你出个主意。你去红海海滨，红海右岸生长着高大的芦苇，你把它们数一数，砍下第十一根芦苇，用它拍打龙形怪兽，狮子就能制服它，它们两个就都能恢复人形。然后你看一下周围，你会看见巨雕格拉夫[1]兀立在红海之滨，你和你的丈夫赶快跃上巨雕的背，它会载你们飞越海洋，返回家乡。我送你一个胡桃，飞到红海当中的时候，把它扔下去，它很快就会浮上来，从水里会长出一棵巨大的胡桃树，让格拉夫停在上面休息；如果它得不到休息，它就没有足够的力气载你们飞越红海；如果你忘了扔下胡桃，它就会把你们扔下大海。”

于是她前往红海，夜风告诉她的，她都找到了。她数海边的芦苇，砍下第十一根，用它拍打龙形怪兽，狮子把它制服了，它们两个立时恢复了原先的人形。可是，先前被变成龙形怪兽的公主一解除魔法，就抱起年轻人坐上格拉夫的背，带着他远走高飞。这时那跋涉万里的可怜女子，又孤零零地独自一人，她坐在地上哭泣。但她终于振作起来，说：“风吹得到的地方，我都要去，只要还有公鸡在啼叫，我就要去寻找，直至找到他为止。”她又走了很远很远的路，终于来到他们两人居住的宫殿。她听说不久要举行一次盛宴，那时他们就要结婚了。她说：“上帝还会帮助我的。”便打开太阳送她的小盒子，里面有一件衣裳，像太阳那样光华灿烂。她把它拿出来，穿着它上宫殿去，所有的人，连新娘子也惊奇地望着她。新娘子非常喜爱这件衣裳，她想，这可以做她的新婚礼服，便问她那衣裳是不是要卖？“用金钱财富来买，不卖，”她回答说，“如果用血肉来买，就卖。”新娘子问这话是什么意思。她说：“让我在新郎睡觉的房间睡一夜吧。”新娘子不肯，但又很喜欢那件衣裳，终于允许了，却叫侍仆给王子喝一杯安眠药酒。到了夜间，王子睡了，她被人领进房间。她在床前坐下，说：“我跟随你七年，到太阳那里、到月亮那里、到东南西北风那里打听你的消息，还帮助你战胜龙形怪兽，难道你就完全把我遗忘了吗？”王子睡得很深沉，只觉得外边似有风吹过枞树林的飒飒声。第二天天刚亮，她就又被人领出去，不得不交出她那件金衣裳。连这办法也无济于事，她伤心地走到外面一片草地上，坐下来哭泣。这时候，她忽然想起还有月亮送给她的一颗鸡蛋，她把它敲破，从里面出来一只母鸡和十二只小鸡儿，浑身都是纯金的，小鸡在周围跑来跑去，叽叽喳喳，过一会儿又钻到母鸡翅膀底下，真是一幅世上最美不过的图画。她站起来，在草地上赶着小鸡儿往前走，直至公主从窗口看见它们。她非常喜欢这些小鸡儿，立即问她卖不卖。“用金钱财富来买，不卖；如果用血肉来买，就卖。让我在新郎睡觉的房间再睡一夜吧。”新娘子答应了，她还想像前一天夜晚那样欺骗她。但当王子上床时，他问他的侍从昨天夜间喃喃的低语声和飒飒声是怎么回事。侍从把事情原原本本对他讲了，说他昨晚奉命给王子喝一杯安眠药酒，因为有一个可怜的姑娘悄悄在他房间里面过夜，今天夜里又要他再给他喝一杯。王子说：“把酒泼在床边。”入夜，她又被领进王子的卧室，她一开始诉说她那伤心的往事，王子立即从她的声音认出是自己的爱妻，他跳起来大声说：“现在我才真正得救了，以前我就像在梦中一样，那个外国公主对我施了魔法，使我忘了你，但是上帝及时地解除了她对我的迷惑。”于是俩人连夜悄悄离开王宫，因为他们害怕公主的父亲，他是一个魔法师。他们坐在巨雕格拉夫背上，巨雕驮着他们飞越红海，飞到中途，她扔下胡桃。霎时间生长出一株巨大的胡桃树，巨雕停在树上休息，然后载他们回家。在家里，他们见到他们的孩子长得又高大又漂亮，从此他们过着快乐的生活，一直到死。

[1]传说中的怪兽，其外形为鹰头狮身，有双翼，爪如钩。

牧鹅女

从前有一个年老的王后，丈夫已去世多年，她有一个美丽的女儿。女儿长大了，许给远方一位王子。临近婚期，新娘需动身到外国去，老王后为她收拾了许多贵重的器物，首饰、酒杯、金银和珠宝，总之，凡是帝王家公主陪嫁中应有的宝物，无不尽有，因为老王后非常疼爱她女儿。她还给公主一名侍女，要她一起骑马，把新娘送交给新郎本人。公主和侍女每人得到一匹马，公主的马叫法拉达，是一匹会说话的马。离别时，老母亲到她卧室取出一把小刀，划破手指，流出鲜血；她拿一小块白布接在下面，在白布上滴下三滴血，她把白布交给女儿，说：“亲爱的孩子，保存好，路上你会用得着的。”

于是母女俩伤心地离别了。公主把那一小块白布藏在胸前，骑上马去找她的未婚夫。走了一个钟头，她又热又渴，对侍女说：“你下马，用给我带的杯子舀些溪水，我要喝水。”侍女说：“你要是渴了，就自己下马去趴在溪边喝水，我不想给你当奴婢。”公主渴极了，只好下马，去溪边弯腰喝水，没能用上那只金杯。她说：“啊，上帝！”这时三滴血回答说：“如果你母亲知道了，她的心可要碎了。”可是公主谦和容让，什么也没说，又骑上马。她们又走了几里路，天很热，太阳毒辣辣的，没多久她又渴了。她们正来到一条河边，公主又叫侍女：“你下马去，用我的金杯盛些水给我喝。”她早忘了侍女那些没好气的话了。这回侍女更加傲慢地说：“要喝你就自己去喝，我不想做你的奴婢。”公主渴极了，便下马趴在河岸上哭泣：“啊，上帝！”三滴血又回答说：“如果你母亲知道了，她的心可要碎了。”她趴着喝水，上身探出在河面上，藏在胸前那块有三滴血的白布掉进水里，顺水漂走了，公主由于心里十分害怕，没有发现。但侍女看见了，并且为自己能控制公主而感到高兴，因为公主一旦失去那三滴血，她也就变得软弱无力了。公主又要骑上她那匹叫法拉达的马的时候，侍女说：“我骑法拉达，你骑我那匹劣马！”公主只得忍气吞声。侍女接着又用更严厉的话命令公主脱下皇家的服饰，穿上侍女的衣服，最后还要她对天起誓，在王宫里对任何人都绝口不提此事；若不起誓，就要当场杀死她。这一切，法拉达都看见了，注意到了。

于是侍女跨上法拉达，而真正的新娘却骑着劣马，她们就这样一直走到王宫。她们的到来使大家非常高兴，王子朝她们快步走来，把侍女从马上抱下来，以为这就是他的妻子，领着她走上阶梯，真正的公主却得在下面站着。老国王在窗边观察，看她待在庭院里，长得清秀、娇嫩又非常美丽，随即去王子房间里问新娘带来的站在庭院里的那个女子是谁。“是我半路上找来做伴的；请给她找个什么活干，省得她没事光闲站着！”可是老国王没什么工作可给她做，就说：“有个少年在牧鹅，她可以去帮帮他。”牧鹅少年名叫小屈尔德，真新娘得帮他牧鹅。

不久，假新娘对年轻的王子说：“亲爱的丈夫，请你帮我个忙！”他回答说：“我一定照办。”“请你叫一个屠夫来，砍下我骑来的那匹马的马头，因为它在路上惹我生气。”原来她害怕法拉达说出她对待公主的实情。现在事情落到这一步，法拉达眼看活不成了，真公主也听到了消息，她暗地里许诺屠夫一笔钱，让他给她办一件事。城里有一个阴暗的大城门，每天早晨她都要赶鹅从那里经过，她要屠夫把马头挂在这阴暗的城门下，让她能时常见到它。屠夫答应照办，砍下马头，把它牢牢钉在阴森的城门下面。

清晨，她和小屈尔德赶鹅出城，从城门下走过时，她说：

啊，法拉达，你挂在这里！

那马头回答说：

啊，公主，你在这儿牧鹅，
如果你母亲知道了，
她的心可要碎了。

她默不作声，走出城门，到了草地上，她坐下来，打开一头纯金的头发，小屈尔德见了，喜欢她亮丽的头发，要去拔几根下来。于是她说：

吹吧，风儿，快快吹，
吹掉小屈尔德的帽子，
让他快跑去追，
等我梳好、编好辫子，
再让他戴上帽子。

立刻刮起一阵大风，把小屈尔德的帽子刮到老远的地方，他赶紧去追帽子。他回来时，公主已梳完、编好发辫，他一根头发丝也没能拿到。小屈尔德生气了，不和她说话；他们就这么放鹅，直到天黑才回家。

第二天早晨，他们从阴森的城门下走过，少女说：

啊，法拉达，你挂在这里！

法拉达回答说：

啊，公主，你在这儿牧鹅，
如果你母亲知道了，
她的心可要碎了。

到了田野上，她又坐在草地上开始梳理她的头发，小屈尔德跑过来，伸手要抓，她赶快念：

吹吧，风儿，快快吹，
吹掉小屈尔德的帽子，
让他快跑去追，
等我梳好、编好辫子，
再让他戴上帽子。

于是风吹起来，刮走他头上的帽子，刮得远远的，小屈尔德只得追过去；公主的头发他一根也没抓着。他们继续放鹅，直到天黑。

晚上，他们回家后，小屈尔德就去找老国王，说：“我再也不和那个女孩子一起牧鹅了！”

“为什么？”老国王问。

“唉，她惹得我整天不高兴。”老国王要他讲他们之间发生了什么事情。小屈尔德说：“每天早晨，我们赶着鹅群从阴暗的城门下经过，那儿城墙上挂着一只马头，她对那马头说：

啊，法拉达，你挂在这里！

那马头回答说：

啊，年轻的公主，
你在这儿牧鹅，
如果你母亲知道了，
她的心可要碎了。”

小屈尔德又讲了牧鹅草地上的事，讲他如何在风中追他的帽子。

老国王叫小屈尔德第二天仍照常去牧鹅，他自己天一亮就坐在阴暗的城门后面，听她怎么和法拉达的头说话。接着又尾随他们到郊外，躲在草地上一棵矮树后面。不久，他亲眼看见牧鹅女和牧鹅少年赶着鹅群走来，过一小会儿，她坐在地上，散开一头灿然生辉的金发。她随即又说：

吹吧，风儿，快快吹，
吹掉小屈尔德的帽子，
让他快跑去追，
等我梳好、编好辫子，
再让他戴上帽子。

于是刮起一阵风，卷走小屈尔德的帽子，让他跑得很远，姑娘静静地梳理头发，编好发辫，这一切老国王都看在眼里。随后他悄悄回去了。晚上，牧鹅女回到家里，老国王把她叫到一旁，问她为什么这样行事。“我不能告诉你，我也不能对任何人诉苦，因为我曾经对天发过誓，那时候我不发誓，就要被杀死。”老国王逼迫她，使她不得安宁，但他无法从她口中得到一点东西。于是他说：“如果你什么也不肯对我说，那就对这里的这个铁炉诉诉你的苦吧！”说完，他就走了。她爬进铁炉里，号啕大哭，把心里话尽情倾诉出来：“我被所有的人抛弃了，我本是个公主，坏心肠的侍女强迫我脱下我身上穿戴的王家服饰，叫我当牧鹅女，干下贱的活。如果我的母亲知道了，她的心可要碎了。”老国王就站在铁炉烟囱旁边，她说的每一句话，他都听得清清楚楚。他又走进去，叫她从炉子里面爬出来，给她换上王室的衣裳，原来她是个绝代佳人。老国王把他儿子叫进来，向他讲清楚他的新娘子是个假新娘，那人只不过是个侍女；当过牧鹅女、站在这里的这个才是真的新娘。年轻的国王看见她有这样的美貌和品德，非常高兴，吩咐大摆宴席，邀请所有人及好朋友赴宴。新郎坐在最上面，旁边是公主，侍女在另一侧，但是侍女的眼睛花了，没认出那个穿戴得一身珠光宝气的女子是谁。他们吃了饭菜喝了酒，兴致很好，老国王说一个谜题让侍女回答，说有个女人如此这般欺骗她的主人，老国王乘机把事情经过全部讲出来，问道：“这个女人应当如何处置？”假新娘说：“把她脱光衣服，塞进一只内壁钉着尖尖的铁钉的大桶里去，用两匹马拉着这桶在街上跑来跑去，直到她死了为止。”老国王说：“那个女人就是你，你已经给自己做出判决，就照你的判决处置吧。”判决执行后，年轻的国王和他的真正的妻子结婚，两人一同和平幸福地治理他们的国家。

乌鸦

从前有一个王后，她有一个小女儿，小女儿还很小，还要人抱着。有一段时间孩子很淘气，不论母亲说什么，她都不肯安静。王后不耐烦了，她看见乌鸦绕着宫殿飞，便打开窗户说：“你要是变成乌鸦飞走，我才清静呢！”这话刚说出口，孩子已经变成一只乌鸦，从她怀里飞出窗外去了。那乌鸦飞进一座幽暗的森林，在里面待了很久很久，父母听不到一点她的消息。后来有一个人走进森林，听见乌鸦的叫声，顺着声音找去，走到近处，乌鸦说：“我原本是一个公主，被人施了魔法，但是你能解救我。”

“要我做些什么呢？”他问。她说：“你继续往森林深处走去，就会找到一所房子，里面有一个老太婆，她会给你吃的，给你喝的，但你一点儿都不能品尝；要是你吃了点什么，喝了点什么，就会沉睡不醒，无法救我。屋后花园里有一棵大橡树，你要站在那里等我。三天里我每天中午两点乘马车来这里找你，第一天拉车的是四匹白马，接着是四匹红马，最后是四匹黑马；如果你沉睡不醒，我就无法得救。”那男人许诺做她要求的一切。乌鸦却说：“啊，我现在就已知道你是救不了我的，你会吃老太婆给你的东西。”那男子许诺不论食物还是饮料，他都绝不碰它。但他一走进那所房子，老太婆就迎着他走过来，说：“可怜的人啊，你疲惫不堪了，快来休息一会儿，吃点东西，喝口酒吧。”

“不，”那男人说，“我不想吃，也不想喝。”但她总劝他，不让他安宁，她说：“如果你不想吃，那就从酒杯里喝一口吧，一口酒算不了什么。”他终于被说动了，喝了。下午快到两点的时候，他去花园里，在老橡树的大树根上等候乌鸦。他站在那里，突然感到非常疲乏，支持不住，便躺下打算休息一会儿。他并不想睡觉，可是刚一躺下，眼睛就自己闭上，他睡着了，睡得很死，任世上无论什么都不能把他叫醒。午后两点，乌鸦乘坐四匹白马拉的马车前来，但她神色非常悲伤，她说：“我知道他会睡着的。”当她来到花园，他仍躺在老橡树的大树根上熟睡。她从马车上下来，走到他身边，摇晃他，呼唤他，他都不醒。第二天中午时分，老太婆又来了，给他带来食物和饮料。他不肯接受。但她老是缠着他，使他无法安宁，劝了他很久，他终于又从酒杯里喝了一口酒。快两点的时候，他去到花园里，踏上老橡树的树根，等候乌鸦到来，忽然感到异常疲惫，四肢支持不住，毫无办法，只好躺下，又陷入深沉的睡眠。乌鸦乘四匹红马拉的马车驶来，神色十分悲伤，她说：“我知道他会睡着的。”她走到他身旁，但他躺着睡熟了，叫不醒他。第三天老太婆说：“这是怎么回事？不吃不喝，是不是想寻死？”他回答说：“我不想吃喝，也不被允许吃喝。”但她把一碗食物和一杯葡萄酒放在他面前，香味扑鼻，使他无法抗拒；他喝了一大口葡萄酒。时候到了，他走到花园老橡树树根上等候公主，感到比前两天更疲倦，躺下睡得很死，就像一块石头。两点钟的时候，乌鸦乘四匹黑马拉的马车前来，马车和所有的一切全都是黑色的。她神色十分悲伤地说：“我知道他会睡着的，他救不了我。”她走到他身边，他躺在那里，睡得很深沉。她摇晃他、喊他，都无法把他叫醒。于是她把一块面包放在他身旁，又放上一块肉，最后是一瓶葡萄酒。这三样东西他想吃多少，就吃多少，永远不会变少。末了，她又从自己手指上褪下一枚刻着她的名字的金戒指，把它戴在他的手指上。最后放上一封信，信里写着她给他的东西，并说这些东西是永远用不完的。她在信里写道：“我十分明白，在这里你是无法救我的，如果你还想救我，就到大河山的金宫去，在那里你能救我，这一点我很清楚。”她把这些东西给了那个男人，然后上车，向大河山的金宫驶去。

那人醒来，知道自己睡着了，心里很悲哀，他说：“毫无疑义，她现在坐车走了，我没能拯救她。”这时，他身边的那些东西映入他的眼帘，他读那封写着事情经过的信。他站起来，要去大河山金宫，但不知道大河山金宫在什么地方。他浪迹四方，过了很长时间，后来来到一座森林，走了十四天还没能走出森林，已经又是夜晚，他疲惫不堪地躺在一丛灌木旁边睡着了。第二天继续走，晚上他又想在一丛灌木旁边躺下，却听见呼喊号叫的声音，无法入睡。到了上灯的时候，他看见一点灯光闪烁，便站起来尾随灯光前行，来到一所房子跟前。一个巨人站在房前，房子因而显得很小。他在心里暗想：如果径直往屋里走去，巨人看见了，很容易丢了性命。但他终于壮起胆子走上前去。巨人看见他，说道：“你来了，很好，我很久没吃到一点东西了，我要马上把你当晚饭吃掉。”

“这样不好，”那人说，“我可不喜欢让人吃掉，如果你要吃的，我有的是，保证让你吃个饱。”

“真是这样，”巨人说，“你就不必担心了。我是因为什么吃的东西都没有，才想吃你。”于是他们走到桌旁坐下，那人取出永远不变少的面包、肉、葡萄酒。“这个我很喜欢！”巨人说，吃得非常痛快。吃完饭，那人问巨人：“你能告诉我大河山金宫在哪里吗？”巨人说：“我要查看我的地图，所有城市、村庄，所有房屋，我的地图上都有。”地图放在他的房间里，他拿出来，找大河山的金宫，但地图上没有。“没关系，”他说，“我的柜橱顶上还有几张更大的地图，我们可以找找。”可是那些地图上也没有。那人要继续往前走，巨人请他再等几天，等他外出取食物的兄弟回家。巨人的兄弟回来后，他们问他大河山的金宫在哪里，他回答说：“等我吃饱了，我就在地图上找找。”吃完饭后，他带他们到他的房间，可是在他的地图上也没能找到它，他又拿了一些别的旧地图来不停地查找，终于找到了大河山的金宫，但它却在好几千里外。“我怎样才能到那里去呢？”那人问。巨人说：“我有两个钟头时间，我把你背到金宫附近，就得回家给我们的孩子喂奶。”说着巨人背起那人，走到离金宫约有上百小时路程的地方，他说：“剩下的路你一个人走应该没问题了。”说罢，便往回走。那人日夜赶路，终于来到大河山的金宫。但金宫坐落在一座玻璃山上，中了魔法的公主坐在她的马车里围绕金宫兜圈，然后进宫。他看见她，心里非常高兴，要上山去找她，但无论他怎么走法，总是从玻璃山上滑下来。她可望而不可即，他心中十分悲伤，对自己说：“我要留在这儿的山下等她。”于是他建造一间小屋，在里面住了整整一年，天天看见她在山上乘车出行，始终无法上山找她。

有一天，他从小屋里面看见三个强盗在打斗，他冲他们大声喊道：“上帝保佑你们！”强盗听见喊声，停下不打了，可是他们看不见人，便又打起来，互相往死里打。他又喊一声：“上帝保佑你们！”他们又住手不打了，环视周围，不见有人，又继续恶斗。这时他第三次喊：“上帝保佑你们！”心里想：得去看看这三个究竟是怎么回事，于是走出去问他们为什么厮打。一个说他得到一根棍子，用它打门，门就开；一个说他得到一件斗篷，披在身上就能隐身；第三个说他捉到一匹马，骑上它哪儿都能去，也能登上玻璃山。他们不知道应该共同保管这些东西，还是各自使用自己的。那人听了，说：“我想和你们换这三件东西，我虽然没有钱，但是有一些比金钱更有价值的东西！不过我得先试一试，看你们说的是不是真话。”于是他们让他骑上马，给他披上斗篷，把棍子放在他手里，他有了这三件东西，他们就看不见他了。他狠狠揍了他们一顿，大声说道：“你们这些懒汉，这就是你们该得到的，满意了吧？”随即策马奔上玻璃山。山上宫门紧闭，他用那棍子击打宫门，大门立即打开。他走进宫殿，踏上台阶，一直来到高高的殿堂。公主坐在殿堂上，她面前有一只金杯，盛满了葡萄酒。她看不见他，因为他身上披着隐身斗篷。当他走到她跟前，把她送他的戒指从手指上褪下来，扔进酒杯里，发出响声。公主大声说：“这是我的戒指，要来救我的男人一定在这里。”人们寻遍了整座宫殿，找不到他，原来他已经走出金宫，跨上马，抛下斗篷。人们奔到金宫大门口，看见了他，高兴得欢呼起来。于是他下马，把公主拥在怀里，她吻他，说：“现在你救了我，我们明天就举行婚礼吧！”

聪明的农家女

从前有一个贫穷的农夫，他没有土地，只有一所小房子和一个独生女儿。女儿说：“我们最好请求国王给我们一块荒地。”国王听了他们贫困的情况，送了一块草地给他们。女儿和父亲去翻地，想种点粮食之类。那块地快翻完了，从地里掘出一个纯金的臼。“你听我说，”父亲对女儿说，“我们的国王非常仁慈，送给我们这块地，我们得把臼送给他表示感谢。”女儿不同意，她说：“父亲，我们有臼，没有杵，还得去找杵，所以不要声张为好。”但父亲不肯听她的话，带上金臼去见国王，说是他在荒野找到的，为对国王表示敬意，请他收下。国王接过臼，问还找到什么别的没有？农夫回答说：“没有。”国王说，他得把杵拿来。农夫说他们没发现杵。可是没用，就像是说给风听似的。他被关进监牢，要他拿出杵来，才会放他出去。仆役天天给他送水和面包，蹲监牢的人得到的就是这些。他们听见农夫不停地哭喊：“唉，要是听我女儿的话就好了！”仆役去见国王，说犯人不吃也不喝，不停地哭喊：“唉，要是听我女儿的话就好了！”国王叫仆役把犯人带来，亲自问他为什么老是哭喊，“你女儿到底说了些什么？”

农夫答道：“她说我最好不要送臼来，要送也得等找到杵再送。”

“你真有这么一个聪明的女儿，就叫她来见我。”于是他女儿来见国王。国王问她是不是当真那么聪明，说要给她出一个谜，她若能猜中，就和她结婚。她马上说可以，她能猜中。国王说：“你到我这里来，不穿衣服，不赤裸身子，不骑马，不乘车，不从路上来，也不从路外来，如果你能做到，我就娶你为妻。”女儿回去，脱得赤条条一丝不挂，她没穿衣服；拿一张大渔网，坐在渔网里面把自己包起来，她没有赤裸身子；她雇了一头驴，把渔网绑在驴尾巴上，让驴子拖着渔网和她一起走，她没骑马，也没乘车；驴子走在车辙上，她只双脚大脚趾着地，不在路上，不在路外。她这样前去，国王说她猜中了，满足了一切要求，于是把她父亲从监牢释放出来，娶她为妻，命令她管理王室的一切财富。

过了几年，有一次国王去阅兵，刚巧有农夫卖完木材，他们的车停在王宫前面，有的车是公牛拉的，有的车是马拉的。有一个农夫有四匹马，其中一匹生了一只小马驹，小马驹跑到一辆车前面，在两头公牛之间躺了下来。农夫聚拢来，开始争吵，摔东西，大声喧哗。有公牛的农夫想要小马驹，说马驹是公牛生的；另一个农夫说不对，是他的马生的小马驹，小马驹是他的。吵吵嚷嚷的声音传到国王那里，国王传下口谕：小马驹躺在谁那儿，它就是谁的。于是有牛的农夫得到了小马驹，可马驹确实不是他的。另一个农夫走了，为失去小马驹而哭泣，而诉苦。他听说王后也是穷苦农户出身，十分仁慈，于是去见王后，请求她帮助他要回他的马驹。王后说：“可以，如果你答应我不说是我说的，我就告诉你该怎么办。明天一大早，国王检阅卫队，你在他一定要经过的大路上站住，拿一张大渔网，不停地做出撒网打鱼、抖渔网，好像打了满网鱼的样子。”她还告诉他如果国王问话，他应如何回答。于是农夫第二天就站在一块干地上撒网打鱼。国王经过时看见了，派传令兵去问那个傻瓜在干什么。农夫回答说：“我在打鱼。”传令兵问，这里并没有水，怎么能打鱼。农夫说：“两头公牛会生一匹小马驹，我在干地上也能打鱼。”传令兵回去向国王报告，国王把农夫叫去，问这话是不是他自己想出来的，要他马上说出是谁教他的。农夫不说是谁教的，只是翻来覆去说上帝保佑！这话是他自己想出来的。他们把他放在一捆干草上拷打很长时间，直至他供认是王后教他的。

国王回到家里，对王后说：“你为什么对我这么虚伪？我要把你休了，你的美好时光结束了！你从哪里来，还回哪里去，回到你的农夫小屋去吧。”但他仍允许她带走一件她认为最可爱、最美好的东西，作为别离的礼物。她说：“好吧，亲爱的丈夫，如果你这样命令，我也愿意遵命照办。”说着，便扑过去抱住他亲吻，说要同他告别。她叫人送来效力很强的安眠药酒，和国王饮酒道别。国王喝一大口，她只呷了一点儿。国王很快睡着了，睡得很深沉。她叫来一名侍役，用一条洁白美丽的亚麻床单把国王包裹起来，叫侍役把他抬进停在宫门前的一辆马车里，她驾着马车回家了，回到她那小小的农舍。她把他放在她的床上，他日夜熟睡，醒来时望着周围，说：“上帝啊，这是什么地方？”他呼唤侍从，但这里一个侍从也没有。他的妻子终于来到床前，说：“亲爱的国王，你曾经命令我，要我带走宫中一件我最心爱、最美好的东西，除了你，再没有什么是我认为更美好、更心爱的，所以我把你带回来了。”国王眼睛里饱含热泪，他说：“亲爱的妻子，你是我的，我是你的。”他把她又带回王宫，和她重新举行婚礼。他们很可能直到如今还在人世。

三只小鸟

大约一千多年前，这片土地上有许多小国的国王，其中有一个国王住在科伊特山上。那国王非常喜欢打猎。有一天，他带猎人走出王宫，山下有三个姑娘在放牛，她们看见国王和众多随从，年长的姑娘指着国王对另外两个说：“喂！喂！我就要和这个人结婚，不嫁给别人。”山那边的另一个姑娘指着国王右边一个人回答说：“喂！喂！我就要和这人结婚，不嫁给别人。”年纪最小的女孩指着国王左边一个人说：“喂！喂！我就要和这人结婚，不嫁给别人。”他们是国王的两个大臣。她们这些话国王都听到了。打猎归来后，国王把那三个姑娘叫来，问她们昨天在山下说些什么。她们不说。国王问年长的姑娘，是不是想嫁给他，她说是的；两个大臣也问了另外两个妹妹并娶了她们。她们姐妹三人全都容貌清秀可人。王后尤其美丽，她有一头亚麻色的秀发。

两个妹妹婚后一直没有生育。有一次，国王要出去旅行，因为王后正怀孕在身，为了使她快乐，便叫她们来陪伴她。他走后王后生了一个男孩，一生下来，身上就有一颗红痣。两个妹妹心生嫉妒，商量要把这漂亮的男孩扔到河里。她们把他扔进河里时（我想是威悉河[1]西段），一只鸟儿飞上天空唱道：

你会不会死去，
变成一束百合花，
以后才能知道：
这是你吗，勇敢的男孩？

两人听了，十分害怕，慌忙跑开了。国王回来，她们对国王说，王后生了一只狗。国王说：“上帝做事，总有道理。”

一个渔夫住在河边，他把小男孩从河里捞出来，孩子还活着，恰巧他的妻子不生孩子，就把孩子收养了起来。一年后，国王再次出门旅行，王后又生了一个男孩，两个恶毒的妹妹又把孩子扔进河里；那只小鸟又飞上天空唱道：

你会不会死去，
变成一束百合花，
以后才能知道：
这是你吗，勇敢的男孩？

国王回来，她们对他说，王后又生了一只狗，国王仍然说：“上帝做事，总有道理。”恰好这个小男孩又被渔夫从河里捞起来收养了。

国王又出去旅行，王后生了一个女孩，两个虚伪的妹妹又把这孩子扔进河里。小鸟儿又飞上天空唱道：

你会不会死去，
变成一束百合花，
以后才能知道：
这是你吗，勇敢的女孩？

国王回来后，她们告诉国王说，王后生了一只猫。国王大怒，把王后投入监狱。王后在狱中度过了很多年。

孩子们渐渐长大，有一天，大孩子和别的男孩一起出去钓鱼，那些男孩不愿意和他待在一起，他们说：“你这弃儿，滚开吧！”他很伤心，问老渔夫这是不是真的。渔夫告诉他，是他有一天打鱼时把他从水里捞上来的。男孩说要去找亲生父亲。渔夫挽留他，但他无论如何一定要走，最后渔夫只好答应了。于是他起身上路，连续走了几天，终于来到一条大河边，有一个老太婆在那里打鱼。“你好，老妈妈。”男孩说。

“你好。”她回应道。

“你要很长时间才能钓到一条鱼吧？”

“你大概要找很久才能找到你的父亲。你怎么过这条河呢？”老太婆说。

“是啊，这只有上帝知道。”老太婆把他背过河去。他寻找了很久，一直没能找到父亲。过了一年，第二个孩子要离开家里去找他的哥哥。他走到河边，遇到的情形和他的哥哥完全一样。现在只有小女孩独自一人留在家里，她想念两个哥哥，终日哭泣，最后也请求渔夫让她去寻找她的哥哥。她也来到那条大河边，她对那个老太婆说：“你好，老妈妈。”

“你好。”老婆婆说。

“上帝保佑你打到鱼。”老太太听了这话，态度变得十分和蔼可亲，把她背过河去，并给她一根树枝，对她说：“沿着这条路一直走下去，我的孩子，当你从一只大黑狗旁边走过去的时候，不要惊慌，你静静地走过去，不要出声，不要笑，不要看它。然后你会来到一座大宫殿前，宫殿大门敞开着，你让这树枝掉在门槛上，穿过宫殿，从另一头出来；那儿有一口古井，井上长着一棵大树，树上挂着一个鸟笼，笼里关着一只鸟，你把它拿下来，再从古井里取一杯水，然后带着这两件东西从原路回来，也带上门槛上的树枝，再次从那只大黑狗旁边走过的时候，用树枝打狗的脸，可是要小心，务必打到它的脸上，然后再回到我这儿来。”一路上她遇到的情形和老太婆所说的完全一样。回来的路上她遇见她的两个哥哥，他们互相寻找，已经寻遍了半个世界。他们一块儿走到黑狗躺着的路旁，她打中了狗的脸，于是那只狗变成一个英俊的王子，随他们一起来到河边。老婆婆还在河边，看见他们都回来了，非常高兴，把他们一个个背到河对岸，她也离开了，因为她自己也获救了。大家都回到老渔夫那里，欢聚一堂，非常高兴，他们把鸟儿挂在墙上。

但是二儿子不愿在家休息，他拿了一张弓出去打猎，累了，就取出笛子吹奏一曲。正巧国王也在打猎，听见了笛声，便走过去，遇见了年轻人。国王问：“是谁允许你在这里打猎的？”

“哦，没有谁允许。”

“你是谁家的孩子？”

“我是渔夫的儿子。”

“渔夫没有儿子啊。”

“你要是不信，就跟我一起去。”国王前去问渔夫，渔夫向他详述一切，这时墙上的鸟儿开始唱道：

母亲孤零零，
关在监牢里，
啊，高贵的国王，
他们是你的好儿女。
两个恶毒的妹妹，
要害死你的孩子，
把他们抛进深深的河里，
渔夫发现他们在水里。

大家听了，都很吃惊。于是国王把鸟儿、渔夫和三个孩子带回王宫，下令打开监狱，接出王后，她身染重病，十分憔悴。她的女儿让她喝几口古井水，她又神采奕奕，恢复了健康。两个恶毒的妹妹被烧死，公主和那位获救王子结了婚。

[1]威悉河在德国北部下萨克森州境内，经不莱梅北流至不莱梅哈芬入海。

两个漫游者

山和谷不相遇，好人和坏人会碰面。有一天，一个鞋匠和一个裁缝在漫游途中走到一起来了。裁缝是个小个子男人，总是心情愉快。他看见鞋匠迎面走来，看他的工匠背囊就知道他是干哪一门手艺的，他冲着他唱一支讽刺小曲：

给我缝好鞋缝，
给我拉紧鞋线，
鞋帮涂上沥青，
牢牢钉上鞋钉。

鞋匠听了受不了，脸上酸溜溜的，像喝了醋似的，一副要和小裁缝拼命的架势。小裁缝却笑了，把自己的酒瓶递给鞋匠，说：“我没有恶意，喝口酒吧，消消气。”鞋匠喝了一大口，脸上的乌云就消散了。他把酒瓶还给裁缝，说道：“我喝了一大口，人说喝得很多，但不说喝得厉害。我们一起漫游好吗？”

“很好，”裁缝回答说，“如果你想去大城市的话，那里有活干。”

“我也正想去大城市，”鞋匠说，“在小镇赚不到什么钱，乡下人更喜欢光脚丫子走路。”于是他们一起继续漫游，像雪地里的黄鼠狼一样，不停地移动双脚朝前走。

时间他们两个有的是，就是没有什么吃的。他们到了一个城市，就到处走走，探望同行。因为小裁缝性情爽朗愉快，又长着俊俏的红扑扑的腮帮，人人都乐意送给他些东西，运气好的话，师傅的女儿还会在家门口给他一个吻，送他上路。又和鞋匠会合的时候，他背包里的东西总要比鞋匠多些。性情阴郁乖僻的鞋匠拉长了脸说：“人越无赖越是有福。”小裁缝却又是笑又是唱歌，无论得到什么东西，全都和鞋匠分享。他口袋里如果有几枚银币叮当响，就下饭馆，高兴得拍桌子，拍得酒杯在桌上跳起舞来，他这人正是：“钱赚得容易花得也快。”

他们漫游了一段时间，来到一座大森林附近，通往京城的路就穿过这座森林。人走的小路有两条，一条要走七天，另一条只要走两天，但他们谁也不知道哪一条是近路。两个漫游者坐在橡树下商量该带些什么东西，带吃几天的面包。鞋匠说：“不能光想顺利的情况，我要带七天吃的面包。”

“什么！”裁缝说，“像头驴子那样背着七天吃的面包？那就连转过头看看周围都不行了。我依靠上帝，别的事我不管。我口袋里的钱，夏天和冬天都一样好用，可是面包天热就会干巴，还会发霉。带够吃的面包就行了，不要带太多。我们怎么就找不到近路呢？带两天吃的面包就行了。”于是俩人各自买自己吃的面包，然后走进森林去碰运气。

森林里面静悄悄的，像教堂里面一样。没有风吹树叶沙沙响，没有溪水潺潺，没有鸟儿鸣啭，没有阳光透过树枝的浓荫照射进来。鞋匠一声不吭，沉甸甸的面包压得他满头大汗，汗水从他闷闷不乐的阴沉的脸上往下流淌。裁缝的兴致很好，他跳来跳去，拿一片树叶吹哨子，要不就唱一支小曲，心里想道：“天上的上帝看我这样快乐，一定会很高兴。”这样过了两天，第三天裁缝的面包吃完了，还没有快要走出森林的模样，裁缝的心猛往下沉，但他并未因此丧失勇气，他信赖上帝，相信自己会有好运。第三天晚上他饿着肚子躺在一棵树下，早晨又饿着肚子爬起来。第四天也是如此。鞋匠坐在一棵倒下的树上吃饭，裁缝只能瞧着他干瞪眼。他向鞋匠讨一小块面包，鞋匠讥笑他说：“你一向那么快活，现在也可以尝一尝不快活是什么滋味。早晨唱歌唱得太早的小鸟儿晚上会被老鹰叼走的。”一句话，此人没有同情心。可是第五天早晨，裁缝爬不起来了，他疲乏无力，几乎说不出一句话；他的脸颊苍白，双眼血红。鞋匠对他说：“今天我要给你一块面包，但是要把你的右眼挖出来。”不幸的裁缝要活命，没有办法，他双眼泪流，然后抬起头来，铁石心肠的鞋匠用一把锋利的刀子把他的右眼挖了出来。这时裁缝想起从前他在储藏食物的房间偷吃甜食以后母亲说过的话：能吃多少就吃多少，必须忍受就得忍受。他吃完以高昂的代价换来的面包后，又站起来继续走，忘记了他的不幸，并且安慰自己说，他有一只眼睛就能够看清楚了。但到了第六天，他又饥肠辘辘，一颗心几乎都要碎了。晚上，他躺倒在一棵树旁边，第七天早晨他已经没有力气爬起来，死到临头了。鞋匠说：“我要行善事，再给你一次面包，但不能白给，得挖掉你另一只眼睛。”裁缝这才认识到自己生活的轻率，请求亲爱的上帝宽恕他，他说：“你要怎么干，就动手吧，我要忍受我必须忍受的；但是，你好好想一想，我们的主不是每时每刻都在审判，另外一个时刻会到来的，那时候你对我的暴行就会得到报应。我没有对不起你的地方，我有好日子过的时候，我和你分享我的所有。我的手艺需要我一针一针地缝，如果我没有眼睛，无法缝纫，我就只能乞讨度日。我要是瞎了，你可不能把我一个人扔在这里，那我就得饿死了。”鞋匠的心里已经没有上帝，他拿起刀，把裁缝的左眼挖出来，然后拿一块面包给他吃，递给他一根棍子，牵着他走。

日落时分，他们走出森林，森林附近的田野上立着一个绞架。鞋匠领着盲裁缝走到那里，让他躺下，就自己走了。不幸的裁缝非常疲劳，又疼又饿，他睡着了，睡了整整一夜。晨光熹微中，他醒了，却不知道自己身在何处。绞架上吊着两个可怜的罪人，这两人头顶上都蹲着一只乌鸦。这时，一个吊死鬼说“：兄弟，你醒了吗？”

“醒了。”另一个说。“那我告诉你件事，”第一个又开口说，“昨天夜里从我们头顶绞架上落下的露水，拿去洗眼，会使人重见光明。要是盲人们知道这样能重新获得视力，有些人恐怕还不信呢。”裁缝听了，拿起毛巾按在草上，沾湿露水，揩擦眼睛。吊死鬼说的话，果然应验了，裁缝的眼窝里立刻重现一对清新健康的眼睛。没过多久，裁缝看见太阳从山后面升起，在他面前的平原上，就是伟大的京城，华丽的城门，上百座塔楼，塔尖上的金球和十字架开始闪亮。他能分得清树上的每一片树叶，看得见飞掠而过的鸟儿和在空中跳舞的蚊子。他从口袋里取出一根缝衣针，当他和从前一样把线穿过针眼，他的心里真是乐开了花。他跪在地上，感谢上帝赐予他的恩惠，做了晨祷，也没忘记为那两个像大钟的钟摆一样在风中摇摆、互相碰撞的罪人求祈。接着他背上行李，不久就忘了所遭受的苦难，唱着歌吹着口哨继续往前走。

他首先遇到一匹棕色马驹在田野上自由地欢蹦乱跳。他抓住马鬃毛，正要跃上马背，骑马进城，马驹求他放了它，说：“我还太年幼，像你这么轻的裁缝骑上来也会压断我的脊背，放了我吧，等我长壮实了，也许将来可以报答你。”

“去吧，”裁缝说，“我看你也是个顽皮的小子。”他用树枝抽一下马背，小马驹尥蹶子撒欢，跃过树篱和壕沟，向着原野奔去。

从昨天起，小裁缝就没吃过一点东西。“阳光虽然充满我的眼睛，”他说，“但是我的嘴里没有面包。我一定不放过最先碰到的勉强能吃的东西。”这时，一只鹳神态庄严地从草地上阔步走来。“停一下！停一下！”裁缝喊道，抓住它的腿，“我不知道能不能吃你，可是我饿极了，别无选择，我得剁下你的脑袋，把你烤了。”

“别这么干，”鹳回答说，“我是能给人类带来大益处的圣鸟，谁都不伤害我。要是你放了我，我下次会报答你的。”

“那就走吧，长腿老弟。”裁缝说。鹳鸟飞起来，垂下一双长腿，从容飞走了。

“怎么办？”裁缝自言自语，“我越来越饿，肚子越来越空。现在我要是碰上什么，准叫它没命。”这时他看见池塘里游过来几只小鸭。“你们来得正是时候。”他说着逮住一只，正要拧断它的脖子，躲在芦苇里的一只老母鸭游过来，张大鸭嘴，恳求他怜悯它亲爱的孩子们。“你想一想，”老母鸭说，“如果有人要把你抓走，干掉你，你母亲会多么悲伤！”

“别说了，”善良的裁缝说，“领走你的孩子吧。”说着，把捉住的小鸭又放回水中。

他回过身来，面前是一棵半空的树，野蜂在那里飞进飞出。“我做了好事，马上就要获得报答了，”裁缝说，“蜂蜜会使我恢复精力。”但是蜂王出来威胁他说：“如果你碰一下我们，毁坏我们的蜂巢，我们的刺会像千百支烧红的针扎进你的皮肉里去。但是，你如果让我们安安生生过日子，走你的路，以后我们会报答你的。”

小裁缝看出这里也搞不出什么名堂。“三只碗是空的，第四只也是空碗，这顿饭真差劲。”他饿着肚子，拖着疲惫的身体进城，那时正好是吃午饭的时候，饭馆里已经为他准备好了饭菜，他一坐下，马上就能吃饭。吃饱了，他说：“现在我也要干活了。”他在城里各处转悠，找到一位师傅，很快也就找到一个不错的工作。因为他的手艺学得很好，不久就出名了，大家都要找小裁缝定做新衣服。他的名声一天比一天响亮。“我的技术虽然不能再提高了，还是一天比一天更棒。”终于，国王任用他为宫廷裁缝师。

世上的事就有这么凑巧：就在同一天，他原来的漫游伙伴——鞋匠，也当上了宫廷鞋匠。鞋匠看见裁缝，一见他又有了一双健康的眼睛，心里很不是滋味。“没等他来报复我，”他在心里暗自想道，“我得先设计除掉他。”但是，设计害人的，会自己遭殃。傍晚，鞋匠收工后，暮色苍茫中悄悄溜去见国王，说：“国王陛下，裁缝是个狂人，胆敢说他能找到古代遗失的金王冠。”

“这太好了。”国王说，叫裁缝第二天早晨去见他，命令他去把金王冠再找回来，否则就永远离开这个城市。“哦，”裁缝心里想，“这混蛋真会编。闷闷不乐的国王要我干谁也干不了的事，我何必等到明天，今天就出城去算了。”于是他捆好行李，出了城门，却为他不得不放弃幸福，离开这个他过得不错的城市而感到惆怅。他来到结识鸭子的那个池塘，那只老母鸭正在岸边用鸭嘴梳理羽毛，当初他把小鸭子还给了老母鸭，这时老母鸭一眼就认出他来，问他为什么这么垂头丧气。“要是你知道我碰到什么事，你就不会感到奇怪了。”裁缝回答说，向她讲自己的遭遇。“如果就是这件事，”老母鸭说，“我们可以想办法。金王冠掉到水里去了，现在就在水底，我们很快就把它捞上来，你在岸边铺开手绢等着好了。”老母鸭带着十二只小鸭潜入水中，五分钟以后，她又浮上来，用鸭翅架着金王冠，十二只小鸭游在她的周围，用他们的鸭嘴帮助托着金冠。鸭子游到岸边，把王冠放在手绢上。你简直想不到那王冠有多么美丽！太阳照射在王冠上，光芒闪耀，犹如数十万颗红榴石。裁缝把手绢的四角打上结，提去见国王，国王大喜，把一条金项链挂在裁缝脖子上。

鞋匠一计不成，又生一计。他去找国王说：“国王陛下，裁缝又口出狂言，说这整座王宫，连同里面所有的东西，能挪动的和不能挪动的，里里外外，他都能用蜡复制出来。”国王把裁缝叫去，命令他把整座王宫，连同里面的所有东西，能挪动的和不能挪动的，里里外外，都用蜡复制出来，如果他做不到，或者就只差墙上一根钉子，都要把他终生监禁在地牢里。裁缝心想：“越来越令人讨厌，谁能受得了？”行李包往背上一甩，走人。走到那棵空心树下，他坐下，低垂着头。蜜蜂飞出来，蜂王问他，他那么歪着脑袋，是不是脖子僵硬了。“啊，不是，”裁缝回答说，“是别的事情使我心情不舒畅。”便把国王要他办的事讲了一遍。蜜蜂们开始互相在一起嗡嗡叫了一阵，蜂王说：“你只管回家去吧，明天这个时候带一大块布来这里，一切就都解决了。”裁缝回去，蜜蜂飞去王宫，从敞开的窗户飞进宫里，爬到所有犄角旮旯里面把一切都看得一清二楚，然后飞回去，用蜂蜡[1]做出王宫的模型，速度之快，简直像眼看着它长起来一样。当天晚上，便已大功告成。第二天裁缝来了，整座华丽的宫殿立在那里，墙上一根钉子也不少，屋顶一片瓦也不缺，娇嫩洁白，气味香甜如同蜂蜜。裁缝小心翼翼地用布把它包起来，送去给国王；国王无比惊奇，把它摆在最大的厅堂，为此他送给裁缝一所石砌的大房子。

鞋匠仍不肯罢休，第三次去见国王，他说：“国王陛下，裁缝听说王宫里没有喷泉，他竟敢说庭院正中应该有一个一人高的喷泉，像水晶一样晶莹清亮。”国王把裁缝叫去，说：“如果明天在我宫中庭院里没有水柱喷涌出来，像你许诺的那样，刽子手就要在那个院子里使你矮下去一头。”可怜的小裁缝不假思索赶紧跑出城门，因为这一次会要他的命，泪水沿着他的脸颊往下滚滚流淌。他正十分伤心地走着，先前被他放了的那匹小马驹向他奔跑过来。小马驹已经长成一匹漂亮的棕色骏马。“现在是时候了，”骏马对他说，“我要报答你的恩惠。我知道你需要什么，马上就能对你有所帮助。只管骑上来吧，我的背载得了两个你这样的人。”裁缝又有了勇气，他跃上马背，马儿往城里迅跑，直奔王宫，绕王宫驰骋三圈，疾若闪电，三圈跑完，便霍然倒在地上。就在此时，随着一声骇人的巨响，王宫庭院正中的一块土地飞到空中，像一只圆球飞出宫外，紧跟着升起一股水柱，有骑在马上的人那么高，清澈明净有如水晶，阳光开始在喷泉上舞蹈。国王看了，惊奇得站起来，当着众人的面去拥抱小裁缝。

但是，好景不长。国王有许多女儿，可是没有儿子。恶毒的鞋匠第四次去见国王，对他说：“国王陛下，裁缝仍然非常狂妄自大，眼下他竟敢说，如果他愿意的话，可以从天上给国王陛下送一个儿子来。”国王把裁缝叫去说：“如果你在九天内让人给我送一个儿子来，我就把我的大女儿给你做妻子。”小裁缝心里想：“酬劳自然可观，好让人卖力干；可是樱桃树太高了，要是我爬上去摘樱桃，踩在脚下的树枝折断了，我就得摔下来。”回到家里，他盘腿坐在工作台上沉思对策。“不行，”末了，他大声说，“我要走，在这里日子过不安宁。”他捆好行李，匆匆出城。走到草地上，看见他的老朋友，鹳，像一位哲学家在那里来回踱步，时而停下脚步，仔细观察一只青蛙，末了把它一口吞下去。鹳走上前来向他问候，他说：“我看见你背着背囊，为什么你要离开这个城市？”裁缝向鹳诉说他无法满足国王对他的要求，并哀叹自己倒霉。“别为这事愁白了头发，”鹳说，“我要帮你摆脱困境。我老早就给城里送襁褓中的婴儿，我也可以从井里带个小王子出来。你回家去吧，放宽心不要烦恼。九天后你到王宫里去，那时我也要去。”小裁缝回家，他准时到王宫里去。不久，鹳飞来敲窗户，裁缝给他开窗，长腿老弟小心翼翼地进来，迈着庄严的步伐走过光滑的大理石地面。他嘴里叼着一个像天使般漂亮的孩子，那孩子朝向王后伸出一双小手。裁缝接过孩子，把他放在王后怀里，她抱着他亲吻他，高兴得不知怎么才好。鹳飞走前，从肩上拿下一个旅行袋递给王后。里面有好些纸袋，装着彩色甜豌豆，分给小公主们。大公主没得到一粒豌豆，却得到快乐的裁缝做她的丈夫。“我觉得就像是中了头彩，”裁缝说，“我母亲说得有理，她总说：谁信赖上帝，又有好运气，谁就不会失败。”

鞋匠不得不给裁缝做他举行婚礼时跳舞穿的鞋，随后他得到命令，要他离开京城，永远不许再回来。他沿着通往森林的路走去，走到绞架那儿。由于激怒、愤懑和天气炎热，他疲惫不堪地倒在地上，闭上眼睛，正想睡觉，吊死鬼头顶上的两只乌鸦高声叫着扑下来，啄掉了他的双眼。他莫名其妙地跑到森林里去，一定是饿死在里面了，因为后来再没有一个人看见过他，也没人听到过他的消息。

[1]蜜蜂腹部的蜡腺分泌的蜡质，是蜜蜂造蜂巢的材料。通称黄蜡。

明亮的太阳会揭露这件事

一个裁缝伙计在各处漫游，靠自己的手艺为生。有一次他找不到活干，穷得一文不名，吃不上饭。这时他在路上碰见一个犹太人，他想，犹太人身上一定带着很多钱，便把上帝抛到九霄云外，径直朝那犹太人走过去，说：“拿钱出来，不然打死你。”那犹太人说：“饶了我吧，我没钱，我身上总共只有八分钱。”裁缝说：“你有钱，还不拿出来！”然后对犹太人拳脚交加，一顿痛打，直打得犹太人气息奄奄，眼看就要没命了。犹太人临死的时候，说了最后一句话：“明亮的太阳会揭露这件事的！”说完，他就死了。裁缝伙计翻他的口袋找钱，真像犹太人说的，他身上只有八分钱。他把那犹太人提起来，扛到一丛灌木后面，又继续漫游，干他的手艺活谋生去了。他旅行了很久，后来来到一座城市，在一个师傅那儿干活。师傅有个漂亮的女儿，他爱上了她，同她结了婚，他们的婚姻美好而幸福。

很久以后，他们已经有了两个孩子，岳父岳母双双去世，他们自己理家。一天早晨，丈夫坐在窗前桌子旁，妻子给他端来咖啡，他把咖啡倒在小碟上，正要喝的时候，太阳照在咖啡上，反光在墙上来回闪动，变幻成小圈圈。裁缝看着它说：“是啊，它很想揭露，可是不能够！”女人说：“唉，亲爱的丈夫，你说什么呀？你这话是什么意思？”他回答说：“我不能告诉你。”女人又说：“如果你还爱我，就得告诉我。”她说了许多好话劝他，说这事决不会让别人知道，她闹得他很不安宁。终于，他向她讲了：许多年以前，他在漫游途中如何穷困潦倒，一文不名，打死了一个犹太人，那个犹太人在临死的痛苦中说，明亮的太阳会揭露这件事的！现在太阳似乎很想揭露，在墙上闪动，变化出小圈圈，但是它做不到。之后，他又特意请求妻子千万不要告诉别人，否则他就没命了。他的妻子也答应了。可是，他一埋头干活，她就跑去找她的教母，悄悄告诉她这件事，又叮嘱她不要再告诉别人；不到三天时间，全城都知道了这件事情。裁缝上了法庭，被判处死刑。明亮的太阳毕竟还是揭露了这件事情。

蓝灯

从前有一个士兵，他为国王忠诚效劳了许多年，但当战争结束，这个士兵因为多处受伤，不能再在军中服务，国王就对他说：“你可以回家了，我不需要你了；你再拿不到什么钱了，因为只有能为我服务的人才能得到薪饷。”士兵不知道自己该靠什么维持生活，他满腹忧愁地离开，走了一整天，傍晚走进一座森林。暮色四合时，看见一点灯光，他朝灯光走去，来到一座房屋跟前，里面住着一个巫婆。“请你给我一个睡觉的地方，给我一点吃的喝的，”他对巫婆说，“我饿极了渴极了。”

“啊哈！”她回答说，“谁肯给一个散兵游勇东西啊？不过我要发善心，只要你能照我的要求去做，我就收留你。”

“你要我做什么？”士兵问。“明天你给我的园子翻地。”巫婆说。士兵答应了，第二天竭尽全力地干，天黑了还干不完。“我看，”巫婆说，“你今天是没法再干下去了，我愿意留你再住一夜，但是明天你得给我劈一车柴，劈得很细。”这活士兵干了一整天，晚上，巫婆建议他再住一夜：“明天你只需要替我办一件小事：我家后面有一口干涸的古井，我的灯掉井里去了，这盏灯发蓝光，不熄灭，你给我拿上来就行了。”第三天，老婆子带他到井边，叫他坐在一只大篮子里面下井去。士兵找到了蓝灯，发个信号，让她把他再拉上去。巫婆把他拉上来，快到井沿的时候，她伸手下去，要拿他手里的蓝灯。“不，”他说，看出她不怀好意，“我得双脚踩着地面，才能给你这盏灯。”巫婆一听，怒不可遏，又让他掉进井里，自己走了。

可怜的士兵摔在潮湿的井底，倒没受伤，蓝灯还一直亮着，但这对他有什么用？他明白自己难逃一死了。他很悲伤地坐了一会儿，无意中手伸进口袋，发现烟斗还在，烟锅里还装了半锅烟丝。他想，这是最后一点享受了，便拿出烟斗，就着蓝灯点上烟，抽起来。井里烟雾弥漫，这时，一个黑色小矮人站在他的面前，问道：“主人，你命令我做什么？”

“我能命令你干什么呢？”士兵答道，十分惊奇。

“你要我做什么事，”小矮人说，“我都必须办好。”

“好，”士兵说，“那你就先帮助我离开这口井。”小矮人拉着他的手，领他穿过地下通道，可是他并没忘记带上那盏蓝灯。一路上矮人指给他看巫婆收罗和储藏的财宝，士兵拿了尽可能多的黄金。到了地面上，他对小矮人说：“现在去把老巫婆绑了送上法庭。”不久，老巫婆骑在一只公猫背上，撕心裂胆地嚎叫着一阵风似地疾驰过去，又过不久，小矮人回来了，说：“事情都办完了，巫婆已经绞死了。”矮人又问：“主人，你还有什么命令？”

“现在不要你做什么，”士兵回答说，“你可以回家了，不过我一叫你，你得马上就到。”

“不用叫我，”小矮人说，“你只要在蓝色灯火上点着你的烟斗，我马上就出现在你的眼前。”说罢，他就在士兵眼前消失了。

士兵回到他原来那座城市，住进一家最好的旅馆，定做漂亮的衣服，然后吩咐旅馆老板替他布置一间房间，要尽可能的华丽。房间布置好了，士兵住进去，唤来小矮人，说：“我忠诚地为国王效劳，他却把我打发走，让我挨饿，现在我要报复。”

“要我干什么呢？”小矮人问。

“等到夜深人静，公主在床上睡着了，你把她背到我这里来，我要她给我当使女。”

小矮人说：“对我来说，这事容易，对你可是很危险的，一旦查出来，后果不堪设想。”

钟敲十二下的时候，士兵的门突然开了，小矮人背着公主进来。“啊哈，你来了？”士兵大声说，“快去干活！去拿扫帚打扫房间。”房间打扫完了，他把她叫到他坐的圈椅跟前，冲着她伸出双脚说：“给我脱靴子。”随后他把靴子朝公主脸上掷去，公主还得把靴子拾起来，擦干净，擦得锃亮。无论他叫她做什么，她都默默去做，并不抗拒，眼睛半睁半闭。鸡叫头遍的时候，小矮人又把她背回王宫，放在她的床上。

第二天早晨，公主起床后去见她的父亲，跟他说她做了一个怪梦：“一个人背着我像闪电般快地跑过几条街道，把我带到一个士兵的房间，我得给他当使女，伺候他，扫地、擦皮靴，什么下贱活都得干。这只是一个梦，可是我很累，像真干了那么多活那样累。”

“这梦也许是真的，”国王说，“我给你出个主意：把你的口袋铰一个小窟窿，口袋里装满豌豆，如果有人再把你带走，豌豆洒在路上，就留下线索了。”国王说这话的时候，小矮人正隐身在旁边，这些话他一句不漏都听见了。夜里，睡着的公主又被背着经过街道的时候，虽然豌豆从口袋里漏洒出来，但是不能提供什么线索，因为足智多谋的小矮人已经事先在所有街道上都洒了豌豆。公主又得干使女的活干到鸡叫。

第二天早晨国王派人四处寻找线索，但是无济于事，因为所有街道上穷人的孩子们都在捡豌豆，他们说：“昨夜天上掉下豌豆了。”国王说：“我们必须想个别的办法，你上床睡觉的时候不要脱鞋，再到那里，你把一只鞋藏在屋里；我有办法找到它。”小矮人听到了这个诡计。晚上，士兵又要他把公主弄来，他劝士兵打消这个念头，他说无法破这个诡计，一旦在他房间里找出那只鞋来，他就要遭殃了。“照我说的去做。”士兵回答说。第三天夜晚公主又得像使女一样干活，她被背回去之前，把一只鞋藏在了床下。

翌日早晨，国王在全城搜查他女儿的鞋；鞋在士兵房间里找到了。在此之前，士兵听从小矮人的请求，跑出城外，但他很快就被追上，抓进了监牢。逃跑时他忘了带上他最好的东西：蓝灯和黄金，口袋里只有一枚金币。他被铁链锁着，站在牢房窗边，看见他的一个伙伴走过。他敲窗玻璃，那人走过来，他对他说：“我在旅馆里落下一个小包，劳驾请你给我捎来，我给你一块金币。”那伙伴跑去，带来他所要的东西。士兵独自一人待着的时候，便在蓝灯上点着烟斗，叫黑色小矮人来。“不必惊慌，”小矮人对他的主人说，“他们押你去哪里，你就跟他们去哪里，不管发生什么事情，只要带着蓝灯，就没问题。”第二天对士兵进行审判，他虽然并没有干什么坏事，法官还是判处他死刑。他被押赴刑场的时候，请求国王给予他一个最后的恩典。“什么恩典？”国王问。

“准许我在路上抽一锅斗烟。”

“你可以抽三锅斗烟，”国王回答说，“但别以为我会饶你一命。”士兵于是抽出烟斗，就着蓝灯点燃了烟，几个烟圈升上来后，小矮人已经站在那里，手里拿着一根短棍，说：“主人命令我干什么？”

“把那些混账法官和他们的差役统统给我打倒在地，对那个待我刻薄的国王也别客气。”小矮人闪电一般地来回奔跑跳跃，谁一碰着他的棍子，谁就倒下，一动也不敢再动。国王害怕了，连声求饶，为了保住性命，他把王国交给士兵，并把女儿嫁给了他做妻子。

草驴

从前有一个猎人去森林里打猎。他满怀喜悦地一路走去，拿一片树叶在嘴上吹口哨，这时来了一个相貌丑陋的老太婆，和他搭话说：“你好，亲爱的猎人，你很快活，可是我又饿又渴，施舍给我点儿什么吧。”猎人可怜这老太婆，便伸手去口袋里拿出点东西给她。要走的时候，老太太拦住他说：“你听我说，亲爱的猎人，你心地善良，我要送你一件礼物：你一直走下去，过一会儿你就会看见一棵树，树上有九只鸟在互相争夺一件外衣。你用猎枪朝它们正中射击，那件外衣就会掉下来，同时也会有一只鸟被打死掉下来。你要把外衣拿了，这是一件如意衣；披在肩上，只要你想去哪里，眨眼间就到哪里。你把那只死鸟的心取出来，整个儿吞咽下去，每天早晨你一起床，都会看见在枕头下面有一块金子。”

猎人感谢女预言家，心里想：“她许诺给我的是美妙的东西，但愿能够实现。”走了百步左右，听见头顶上树枝间有鸟叫声，抬头一看，只见一群鸟用鸟嘴和脚爪在拉扯一件衬衣，鸣叫着，互相争夺，似乎哪只鸟都想把它据为己有。“咦，”猎人说，“奇怪，事情真是像老太太说的那样。”他从肩上取下猎枪，瞄准鸟群正中射去，毛羽纷飞。众鸟高声鸣叫着飞逃而去，一只鸟被射死，掉了下来，外衣也落在地上。猎人照老太婆吩咐的那样，剖开鸟，取出鸟心，一口吞了下去，带上外衣回家了。

第二天早晨，他睡醒的时候，忽然想起老太婆的预言，他想看看是否应验。一提起枕头，就看见一块金子在闪光，翌日又有一块，从此以后，每天起床时都是如此。他积攒了一堆金子，可是后来他想：“如果我老是在家里待着，这么多金子有什么用？我要出门去见识见识外面的世界。”

于是他告别父母，背上猎人的背包和猎枪，出门远游。有一天，他穿过一座茂密的森林，森林尽头的平原上，在他眼前出现一座壮观的宫殿。一个老妇人站在宫殿的一扇窗畔，旁边有一个绝色少女俯望窗外。这老妇人是个巫婆，她对她的女儿说：“从森林里出来一个人，这人身上有一件神奇的宝贝，我们得把它骗到手，我亲爱的心肝女儿，我们拥有它更合适。他肚子里有一颗鸟心，因此，他的枕头下面每天早晨都有一块金子。”她对那姑娘讲那鸟心是怎么回事，以及如何设骗局引他入壳，最后怒目威胁她说：“你若不听我的话，就叫你遭殃。”猎人走近了，看见那少女，他对自己说：“我游历了很长时间，现在我要到这富丽堂皇的宫殿里面休息一下，钱我有的是。”真正的原因是：他看中了那位千娇百媚的少女。

他走进屋里，受到亲切的迎接，有礼的款待。不久，他迷上了巫婆的女儿，只是看着她的眼睛，别的什么都不想，凡是她要求的，他都乐意做。老巫婆说：“现在我们必须得到那鸟心，他丢了它，自己也不会知道。”她调制一种饮料，烧好了，倒在一只酒杯里，叫姑娘端去给猎人喝。姑娘说：“亲爱的，为我的健康干了这杯。”他接过酒杯，喝了下去，很快就吐出了鸟心。姑娘偷偷把它捡起来，自己吞下去，因为老巫婆要她这么干。从此猎人在他的枕头下面再也找不到金子了，金子出现在姑娘的枕头下面，老巫婆每天都去那儿取。猎人痴心迷恋着姑娘，什么也不想，只想和姑娘一起消磨时光。

老巫婆又说：“鸟心我们有了，也得把他身上的如意衣拿来。”姑娘回答说：“让他留着那件如意衣吧，他已经失去财富了。”老婆子生气了，说：“这件外衣可是世上难得的神奇玩意儿，我非把它搞到手不可。”她把计谋告诉姑娘，并说如果不听她的话，就叫她大吃苦头。姑娘只好照老太婆的主意去做，靠在窗口，目望远方，仿佛十分悲伤。猎人问：“你这么伤心地站在这里，是为什么？”

“啊，我的心肝，”她回答说，“对面有一座宝石山，那里生长珍贵的宝石。我非常想要宝石，一想起来，就感到悲伤。可是，谁能去取宝石呢！只有飞鸟能飞到那里去，人是永远不能的。”

“如果你只是为此而忧伤，”猎人说，“我可以很快就解除你心中的烦恼。”说罢，他搂着她，让如意衣也盖着她的身子，发愿要去宝石山。眨眼的工夫，他们两人已经坐在宝石山上。四面八方都是宝石的闪光，看着这般景象着实赏心悦目，他们搜集起最美丽、最珍贵的宝石。由于老太婆施了巫术，猎人眼皮变得沉重起来。他对那姑娘说：“我累得站不住了，我们坐下休息一会儿吧。”他们坐下，他的头枕在她怀里睡着了。他一睡熟，她就脱下他披在肩上的如意衣，披在自己肩上，拿起宝石，发愿回家去了。

猎人一觉醒来，发现情人欺骗了他，把他独自一人留在了荒山野岭。“啊，”他说，“世上竟有这么无情无义的人！”他坐在那里，心中痛楚而忧虑，不知如何是好。这座山是属于野蛮残暴的巨人的，他们住在山上干他们的事。猎人在那里没待多久，就看见三个巨人大步流星走过来。他躺下装作睡得很死。巨人过来，一个踢他一脚说：“什么东西在这里！”第二个巨人说：“踩死他。”第三个不屑地说：“不值得费这力气！让他活好了，他在这儿待不住的，要是他再往高处爬，爬到山顶上，云就会抓住他，把他带走。”他们说着话走过去了，猎人却记住了他们说的话，等他们走远了，他就爬到了山顶上去。在那儿坐了一会儿，飘来一朵云，攫住他，带着他在天上飘了一段时间，然后徐徐降落在一片有围墙围着的大菜园里面，他轻轻地落在大白菜和别的蔬菜之间的地面上。

猎人环顾周围，说：“要是有点吃的就好了，我饿极了，很难再走下去。可是这里看不见苹果、梨和别的水果，到处都只有蔬菜。”最后他想，实在没办法，可以吃莴苣，莴苣虽然味道不是特别好，但可以充饥提神。于是他挑了一棵漂亮的吃起来，刚吞下几口，就有一种很奇异的感觉，觉得自己完全变了，长出四条腿，一个大脑袋，两只长耳朵，他惊恐地发现自己变成了一只驴子。因为他还是感到饿得厉害，多汁的莴苣正合他的口味，他便贪婪地吃个不停。终于他吃到另一种莴苣，才吞咽下一点，就再度觉得自己的身体起了变化：他恢复了原先的人形。

于是猎人躺下睡觉，消除疲劳。第二天早晨醒来，他摘了一棵坏莴苣，一棵好莴苣，心里想：“这东西会帮助我收回我的宝物，惩罚无情无义之人。”他把莴苣带在身上，爬过围墙，去找他的情人的宫殿。走了几天，他很幸运地找到了。于是他迅速把自己的面孔弄成褐色，他的母亲即使见了他，也未必能认出他来。他走进宫殿里面请求借住一夜。“我非常疲惫，”他说，“实在走不动了。”巫婆问他：“你是谁，你是干什么的？”他回答说：“我是国王的使节，国王派我去寻找太阳底下生长的最可口的莴苣。我非常幸运，找到它了，把它采摘了带在身上，可是骄阳似火，我担心娇嫩的莴苣会枯萎了，真不知道还能不能带回去。”

老太婆听说有可口的莴苣，馋涎欲滴，她说：“亲爱的老乡，让我尝一尝珍奇的莴苣吧。”

“当然可以！”他回答说，“我带了两棵，可以给你们一棵。”他打开背包，把那棵坏莴苣递给她。巫婆毫无戒心，馋得直流口水，就自己跑去做菜。做好了，等不及摆上餐桌，先拿了几片塞进嘴里；一咽下去，马上失去了人形，变成一头母驴，跑到院子里去。使女来到厨房，看见做好的莴苣，要把它端上餐桌，半路上照例忍不住要先尝个鲜，吃了几片，立刻就见神效，也变成一头母驴跑到院子里找老巫婆做伴去了，盛莴苣的碗掉在地上。在此期间，猎人陪伴美丽的姑娘坐着，老是没人端莴苣来，她又很想尝尝，便说：“不知道莴苣在哪儿了。”猎人心里想：看来是那菜起作用了，就说：“我去厨房问问。”他走下去，看见两头母驴在院子里乱跑，莴苣掉在地上。“不错，”他说，“这两个罪有应得。”他把剩下的菜捡起来放在碗里，给那姑娘送去。“为了不让你久等，”他说，“我亲自把这美味食物给你端来了。”她吃了，也像那两个一样马上失去了人形，变成一头母驴跑到院子里去。

猎人洗完脸，变成母驴的那几个人都能认出他是谁了，他走到院子里，说：“你们无情无义，现在该受报应了。”他把她们三个拴在一条绳上，赶到一座磨坊去。他敲窗户，磨坊主探出头来，问他有什么事。“我有三只很凶的畜生，”他回答说，“我不想再留着它们了。你如果想要它们，我可以付给你钱，你要多少就给你多少，只要你照我要求的那样喂它们草料，对待它们就行。”磨坊主说：“为什么不呢？你要我怎样对待它们？”猎人说，那头老母驴，也就是老巫婆，一天得打它三次，给它吃一次草料；那头小母驴，就是那个使女，一天打一次，给它吃三次草料；那最小的母驴，就是那个姑娘，一天给它吃三次草料，不要打它，因为他毕竟不忍心让这姑娘挨打。之后，他就回到宫殿，他需要的一切那里都有。

过了几天，磨坊主来告诉他说，一天光挨打只吃一次草料的老母驴死了。“其余两头母驴，”他继续说，“虽然没死，一天吃三次草料，但它们都很伤心，恐怕也活不长久了。”猎人起了怜悯之心，怒气消了，对磨坊主说，要他还把驴子赶来。两头驴子来了，他拿好莴苣给它们吃，让它们重新恢复人形。那美丽的姑娘在他的面前跪下说：“啊，我最亲爱的人，请你原谅我对你做的坏事，这些都是我母亲逼我做的，是违背我的本心的，因为我真心爱你。你的如意衣挂在一个柜橱里，我喝一帖吐药，就把鸟心吐出来还给你。”这时猎人的想法变了，他说：“你留着吧，反正都一样，因为我要娶你做我的忠实的夫人。”他们举行了婚礼，在一起过着愉快的生活。

三兄弟

从前，有个男人有三个儿子，他的全部财产就是他住的那所房子，三个儿子都想在他死后得到这所房子。父亲对这三个儿子都很疼爱，他不知道该如何做才能不偏不倚。他不肯卖掉房子，因为它是祖上传下来的，否则，卖房子的钱就可以给他们平分了。最后他想出一个办法，便对儿子们说：“你们都去外面走走，试试运气，各人学一门手艺，回来以后，谁最有本事，房子就给谁。”三个儿子都同意了。老大要当给马蹄钉铁掌的工匠，老二想当理发师，老三却想当个击剑师。他们定了一个回家重聚的日子，就出门去了。说也凑巧，他们各自都找到高明的师傅，学到了真本事。铁匠给国王的马钉马掌，他想：“毫无疑问，我准能得到那所房子。”理发师净给体面的老爷先生们刮胡子，他也想：“这房子准定归我无疑了。”剑士一身伤痕累累，但他咬紧牙关，并不懊恼，因为他心里想：“若怕受剑伤，永远得不到房子。”

到了预定的日期，三兄弟又在父亲那儿团聚。他们不知道怎样才能得到显示技艺的最好机会，便坐在一起商议。正在这时，忽然一只兔子越过田野向这边跑来。“好，”理发师说，“它来得正是时候。”他拿起脸盆、肥皂，打好肥皂沫，等兔子一到跟前，在它迅跑如飞之时，给它抹皂液，修剪出一副短胡子，还没划破一点皮。“我很满意，”父亲说，“其他人如果没有更出色的本领，房子就归你了。”没过多久，一个老爷坐着马车疾驰而来。蹄铁匠说：“爸爸，现在请你看看我的手艺。”他向马车跃去，取下疾奔中的马的四个马蹄铁，钉上四个新的，那马一直不停地奔跑。“你是个了不起的人，”父亲说，“你的手艺和你弟弟的一样好，我不知道该把房子给谁了。”老三说：“爸爸，让我也试一试吧。”这时正好下起雨来，他抽出剑飞快舞起来，护住头顶，没有一滴雨点落在他的身上；雨越下越大，后来成了瓢泼大雨，他的剑也越舞越快，身上始终没有被雨水打湿，竟像是坐在屋里一样。父亲见了，惊讶地说：“你的本事最了不起，房子是你的了。”

两个哥哥都遵守原先的约定，对父亲的决定表示赞同。三兄弟相亲相爱，仍旧一起住在这房子里，做他们的手艺活。他们技艺高超，人又机灵，因此挣了很多钱。就这样，三兄弟一起过着愉快的生活，直到晚年。后来病死了一个，另外两个悲伤得生了病，不久也都去世了。因为他们机灵聪明，彼此十分友爱，三兄弟被合葬在一座坟墓里。

跳舞跳破了的鞋

从前有一个国王，他有十二个女儿，长得一个比一个漂亮。她们一起睡在一个大厅里，一张张卧床并排摆着。晚上，她们上床后，国王亲自来锁门，还上了门闩。可是第二天早晨他开门时，总是发现女儿们的鞋跳舞跳破了，谁也不知道这是怎么回事。于是国王发出通告：谁能三天三夜时间探查出她们夜间在哪里跳舞，就可以从她们中间挑选一个作妻子，并可在他去世后继承王位；但若报名后三天三夜查不出来，他也就活不成了。不久便有一位王子前来冒险一试。他受到殷勤接待，晚上被人领到紧挨着大卧室的一间房间里去。他的床铺就在那房间里面，他得留神她们去哪里跳舞；为了不让她们背地里耍什么花招，或跑到别处去，大卧室的门敞开着。

可是王子觉得眼皮铅一样的沉重，他睡着了，第二天早晨他睡醒的时候，十二个公主都已经跳过舞了，她们的鞋底子都跳舞跳破了。第二夜、第三夜也是如此，那个王子被毫不留情地砍掉了脑袋。后来又有许多人报名来干这种冒险的事，他们一个个全都丢了性命。碰巧有个穷当兵的受了伤，不能在军中服役，在前往国王所在的城市途中遇见一个老妇人，她问他要去哪儿。“我自己也不知道，”他说，又开玩笑接着说，“我倒很想去探查探查那些公主在哪里跳舞跳得鞋都跳破了，将来好当国王。”

“这并不难办，”老妇人说，“你不能喝晚上给你端去的酒，要装出熟睡的样子。”接着，她又给他一件外衣，说：“披上它，谁也看不见你，你就可以悄悄尾随那十二个人了。”那当兵的得到这个好主意，竟认真起来，下决心以求婚者的身份应征去见国王。他像别人一样受到很好的接待，穿上了王室的服装。晚上快就寝的时候，有人带他进入卧室，他正要上床，大公主给他送来了一杯酒，他事先在下巴底下系了一块海绵，一滴酒也没喝，全都倒在海绵上。他躺下，过一会儿，发出像睡熟的人那样的鼾声。十二个公主听见，都笑了，大公主说：“这个人分明是来送死啊。”随后她们都起来打开衣箱、柜橱，取出华丽的衣裳，照着镜子打扮，跳来跳去，为就要去参加舞会感到十分高兴。只有年纪最小的公主说：“不知道是什么缘故，你们都这么高兴，可我有一种异样的感觉，觉得会有祸事。”

“你是个小傻瓜，”大公主说，“总是前怕狼后怕虎。你忘了有多少王子在这儿待过，都不管用？这个大兵我不给他安睡药酒喝，他也会睡得像死人一样。”她们全都打扮整齐了，才去看一眼那个当兵的。他双目紧闭，一动不动，她们认为不会有问题了。于是大公主走过去敲几下她的卧床，那张床就陷入地下去，她们由大公主领头鱼贯从那入口进去。那个当兵的把这一切都看在眼里，他不再犹豫，披上他那件外衣紧跟在小公主后面也下去了。还没下完梯级，他不小心踩着了小公主的裙子，小公主吓了一跳，大叫：“谁？谁拽我的裙子？”

“别冒傻气了，”大公主说，“你是给钩子挂了一下。”她们全都走完了梯级，到了地底下，走在一条奇妙的林荫道上，那里的树叶都是银的，闪烁放亮。当兵的想：“得拿点东西作凭证。”便折了一枝树枝，树上咔嚓一声响，小公主又喊：“不对头，你们听见响声了吗？”大公主说：“那是在鸣枪庆贺，因为我们很快就能把王子们解救出来了。”接着她们来到另一条林荫道上，那里的树叶都是金的。最后走到第三条林荫道上，那里的树叶都是晶莹的钻石，当兵的从后面两条林荫道上各折了一枝树枝，每次咔嚓一声响，都吓得小公主发抖，但大公主都说这是欢庆的枪声。她们一直走到一条大河畔，河边有十二条小船，每一条小船里有一位英俊的王子在等候着她们。他们每人接一位公主到自己的船上，当兵的和小公主登上同一条船。船上那个王子说：“不知道为什么今天这船沉得多，我得用尽全身力气划船才能前进。”

“怎么会这样呢，”小公主说，“大概是天热的缘故吧，我也觉得心里烦躁。”河对岸有一座美丽的宫殿，灯火辉煌，宫中响起鼓点和喇叭的欢快的音乐声。他们划船过河，走进宫殿，每位王子和自己的心上人共舞；那当兵的也一块儿跳舞，但没人看得见他。哪个公主手里拿着一只盛着葡萄酒的酒杯，他就把这杯酒喝了，公主把酒杯端到唇边时，那已是一只空酒杯。小公主感到惊恐，但大公主不让她声张。她们一直跳舞跳到凌晨三点，鞋底都跳破了，只好停下。众王子划船送她们过河，这一次那当兵的在前面坐上大公主那条船。公主们在河岸边和王子们告别，答应夜里还要再去。她们踏上阶梯的时候，那个当兵的跑在前面，躺倒在床上，十二个公主疲惫地慢悠悠爬上来时，他又大声打鼾，公主们听了说：“这个人坏不了我们的事。”于是她们脱下美丽的衣裳，放到一边，把跳舞跳破了的鞋放在床下，然后躺下睡觉。第二天早晨当兵的什么也不说，他准备再跟着去看看这种稀罕事，第二夜第三夜他都随公主们前往。一切都同第一夜一样，每次她们都要跳舞跳到鞋破方休。第三次那当兵的拿了一只酒杯作为凭证。到了该他去回复国王的时候，他把三根树枝、一只酒杯藏在身上，去见国王，十二个公主站在门后听他说些什么。国王问：“我的十二个女儿夜间在哪里跳舞跳破了鞋？”他回答说：“和十二个王子一起在一座地下宫殿里跳舞。”他接着报告事情经过，并拿出物证。国王叫公主们出来，问她们当兵的所说的是不是事实，她们见事情已经暴露，抵赖毫无用处，只好全部承认。随后国王问他想要哪个公主做妻子，他回答说：“我年纪不小了，把大公主许配给我吧。”于是当天举行婚礼，国王允诺自己去世后由他继承王位。但是被施了魔法的王子们还不能得到解救，得过了同公主们跳舞一样多的夜晚的天数才行。

黑白新娘

一个女人带自己的亲生女儿和继女去野外割喂牲畜的草料。上帝变成一个穷人向她们走来，问她们：“要去村里该怎么走？”

“你要想知道，”母亲说，“就自己找去。”女儿补上一句：“怕找不着路，就雇个指路人。”继女说：“我领你去，跟我来吧。”亲爱的上帝对那母女俩很生气，转过身去，背对着她们，诅咒她们，让她们像黑夜一样乌黑，像罪恶一样丑陋。但上帝对继女很仁慈，和她一道走，快进村的时候，上帝为她祝福，并且说：“我要满足你三个愿望，你挑三个说吧。”于是姑娘说：“我愿能像太阳一样美丽纯洁。”很快她就变得如同白昼一样耀眼美丽。“我希望有一个永远不会空的钱袋。”亲爱的上帝也给了她，但他又说：“不要忘了最好的东西。”她接着说：“第三件，我希望我死后能上永恒的天国。”上帝也答应了她，最后亲爱的上帝和她告别了。

继母和她的女儿回到家里，发现她们两人变得像煤炭一样乌黑，又丑陋不堪，继女却又白皙又漂亮，对继女更加怀恨在心，一心想要加害于她。那继女有一个哥哥，名叫雷吉纳尔，她很爱她的哥哥，把发生的一切全都告诉了他。有一次雷吉纳尔对她说：“亲爱的妹妹，我要给你画一张像，这样我就总能看见你，因为我非常爱你，每时每刻都想见到你。”她回答说：“不过我请你别让人看见这张画像。”于是他画了一张妹妹的肖像，挂在他的房间里面。他是国王的马车夫，所以他住在王宫里。他天天站在妹妹肖像跟前，感谢上帝赐予他亲爱的妹妹幸福。这时恰巧他所效劳的国王的王后去世了，王后生前美貌非凡，简直找不到能和她相比的女子，国王对王后的去世深感悲痛。

宫中侍从发觉国王的车夫天天站在那幅美丽的肖像前面，他们妒忌他，便向国王报告。国王下令把画像给他拿去，他一看这画中人酷似他那已故的王后，只是比王后还要美丽，便热恋上了她。他把车夫传来，问他这画中人是谁。车夫说是他的妹妹，国王便决定娶她做妻子，给车夫马车、马匹和华丽的金衣裳，派他去把自己选中的未婚妻接来。雷吉纳尔带着使命到达的时候，他的妹妹很高兴，黑姑娘嫉妒她的幸福，非常生气，对她母亲说：“你的那些能耐都哪里去了？也不能给我带来这样的幸福。”

“别嚷嚷，”老婆子说，“我就给你想办法。”她施展巫术，使车夫变成半瞎，看东西一片模糊，再把白姑娘的耳朵堵上，使她成了半聋。随后他们登上马车，身穿王室华丽服装的新娘子先上车，接着是继母和她的女儿，雷吉纳尔坐在车夫座上驾车。走了一程，车夫大声说：“我的小妹子，遮蔽好身子，别让雨水打湿了你，别让风吹尘土弄脏了你，要漂漂亮亮到国王那里去！”

新娘子问：“我亲爱的哥哥说什么？”

“啊，”老婆子说，“他叫你把金衣裳脱下来给你妹妹穿。”她就脱下来给那黑姑娘，黑姑娘把自己一件破旧的灰褂子给她。马车载着她们继续朝前走，过一会儿，哥哥又大声说：“我的小妹子，遮蔽好身子，别让雨水打湿了你，别让风吹尘土弄脏了你，要漂漂亮亮到国王那里去！”

新娘子问：“我亲爱的哥哥说什么？”

“啊，”老婆子说，“他叫你把金帽子摘下来给你妹妹戴。”她把金帽拿下来给黑姑娘戴上，自己没帽子戴了。他们继续朝前走了一会儿，哥哥又大声说：“我的小妹子，遮蔽好身子，别让雨水打湿了你，别让风吹尘土弄脏了你，要漂漂亮亮到国王那里去！”

新娘子问：“我亲爱的哥哥说什么？”

“啊，”老婆子说，“他叫你往车外面看一看。”这时候马车正在过一座桥，桥下是一条很深的河。新娘子站起来，半个身子探出车外，那两人使劲一推，她掉进河里去了。就在她沉没在河里的那一瞬间，从水面上浮起一只雪白雪白的鸭子，顺流游下去。哥哥根本毫无察觉，驾车将她们送进宫里，把黑姑娘当作他的妹妹交给国王，还以为那个人真是他的妹妹，因为他眼前一片模糊，只看见金衣裳闪闪发光。国王一见自己想望中的新娘子奇丑无比，非常生气，下令把车夫扔进一个养着毒蛇的土坑里。老巫婆有一套诱惑国王的办法，她施巫术使国王眼睛昏花，使得他把她们留在宫里，甚至让他觉得她女儿还不错，真的和她结了婚。

一天晚上，就在黑新娘坐在国王怀里的时候，一只白鸭从下水道游到御膳坊，对小厨师说：“请烧把火，小兄弟，好让我烘干毛羽。”

小厨师照办，给它在炉灶上生了火，鸭子蹲在炉灶旁摇晃着身子，梳理羽毛。它这么舒适地蹲着，问道：“我哥哥雷吉纳尔在干什么？”

小厨师回答说：“他被关在土坑里，和毒蛇在一起。”

鸭子又问：“黑姑娘在家里干什么？”

小厨师回答说：“她暖暖和和地坐在国王怀里。”

鸭子说：“上帝啊，可怜可怜吧！”又从下水道游出去了。

第二天晚上鸭子又来了，还是问同样的问题，第三天晚上又来一次。小厨师实在不忍心，便去见国王，向他报告一切。国王要亲自查明情况，就在第二天晚上前来御膳坊，鸭子从下水道口探出头来，他就拔剑斩断鸭脖子，鸭子一下子变成美丽非凡的姑娘，和她的哥哥画的像一模一样。国王高兴极了；她全身湿漉漉地站在那里，国王叫人送来华贵的衣裳，让她更衣。之后，她向国王讲述她如何中了奸计，最后被推到河里，她首先请求把她的哥哥从蛇洞里放出来。国王满足了这个请求之后，走近老巫婆待着的房间，问她，做了如此这般事情的人该当如何处置，并讲了发生的事情。老巫婆的脑子乱了，毫无察觉，她说：“应该脱光这个女人的衣服，把她放在一个钉着钉子的大木桶里，让马拉着那木桶到处跑。”后来就完全按照这个办法处置了老巫婆和她的黑女儿。国王和洁白美丽的新娘子结了婚，并奖赏了她忠诚的哥哥，使他成为一个富有又受人尊敬的人。

希梅里山

从前有两个兄弟，一个富有，一个贫穷。富人什么也不给穷人，穷人只好靠做谷物买卖勉强维持生活；有时他的日子很艰难，甚至不能让老婆、儿子吃上面包。一天，他推着手推车穿过森林的时候，看见一座寸草不生的大山，因为他从来没看见过这座大山，就停下来惊奇地看着它。他站在那里，只见十二个身高马大的粗野的男人走了过来，他以为这是一伙强盗，就赶紧把他的车子推到树丛里去，自己爬上一棵树，等着看要发生什么事情。那十二个大汉走到山前，大声喊道：“塞姆希山，塞姆希山，开门！”秃山很快从中间分开，十二个大汉走了进去，他们一到里面，山又合上了。过一会儿，山开了，大汉们出来，背上都驮着沉重的口袋。他们走到阳光下，说：“塞姆希山，塞姆希山，关门。”山迅速合拢，再也看不出这座山的入口，那十二个人走了。等到他们完全从穷人的视线中消失，穷人才从树上爬下来，他很想知道山腹里面究竟隐藏着什么神秘的东西。于是他走上前去，说：“塞姆希山，塞姆希山，开门！”果然山门大开。他走进去，原来整座山就是一个装满金银的洞穴，里面还有好多堆珍珠和闪光的宝石，像谷物那样堆放着。那穷人完全不知道该怎么办，不知道自己是不是可以拿点珠宝回去。后来他把口袋装满了金子，珍珠和宝石原封不动放着。他从山里出来后，依样画葫芦，说：“塞姆希山，塞姆希山，关门！”山合上了，他便推着手推车回家。现在他不用发愁了，他可以用金子给妻子和孩子买面包，还能买葡萄酒，生活得很愉快。他为人正直，并乐善好施，经常帮助穷人。钱用完了，他去跟他哥哥借一只木桶，又去拿一次金子，但那几堆珠宝他从不碰一下。他第三次想去拿点金子，又向他哥哥借木桶。那富人早就嫉妒他的财产，嫉妒他家过的好日子，不明白他兄弟的财富哪儿来的，要借木桶干什么。于是想出一个计策，在桶底涂上沥青，归还木桶时，发现里面粘着一块金币。富人马上去找他弟弟，问：“你用木桶量什么？”

“谷物和大麦。”弟弟说。哥哥给他看那枚金币，威胁他说，如果不对他讲真话，他就去法院告他。于是他把事情经过向富人全盘托出。富人马上叫人套一辆马车赶去，想好好利用这个机会，把所有宝贝统统运回来。他到了山前，大声喊道：“塞姆希山，塞姆希山，开门！”山分开了，他走进去。所有金银珠宝统统在他眼前，很长时间他不知道该先拿什么才好，最后他尽可能多地装宝石，装到他快背不动为止。他要把它们运出来，但因他全部心思念念不忘珠宝，竟忘了山名，他大声喊叫：“希梅里山，希梅里山，开门。”可是这山不叫这名字，山纹丝不动，依然锁闭着。他害怕了，越想脑子越乱，所有那些金银珠宝都帮不了他一点忙。晚上，山门开了，十二个强盗进来，看见他在里面，强盗们哈哈大笑，大声说：“好小子，我们终于逮着你了，你来过两次，你以为我们不知道？我们没抓你就是了，第三回你可跑不了了。”他大叫：“以前来的不是我，是我弟弟！”不管他说什么，不管他怎么恳求饶命，强盗还是砍下了他的脑袋。

小驴子

从前有一个国王和一个王后，他们很富有，事事称心如意，唯一的缺憾就是没有孩子。王后为此日夜哀叹，她说：“我就像一块什么都不长的庄稼地。”上帝终于满足了她的愿望，但孩子出生的时候，看着不像个小孩，倒像一头小驴子。母亲看见了，号啕痛哭，说她宁愿压根儿就没有孩子，也不要一头驴子，说要把它扔进河里喂鱼。但是国王说：“不，既然上帝把他给了我们，他就是我的儿子，我死后就由他戴王冠、继承王位。”于是驴子被养起来，渐渐长大，耳朵也长得高高的，笔直地竖起来。这驴子生性快活，到处跳来跳去，尤其喜爱音乐。他去找一个著名的乐师，对他说：“把你的技术教给我，让我弹奏琉特[1]能像你弹奏的那么动听。”

“啊，亲爱的少爷，”乐师回答说，“你会觉得很困难的，你的手指太大，并不特别适合弹奏，我担心琴弦会断。”可是无论他怎么推托都无济于事，小驴子就是要学弹奏琉特。他学琴有恒心，又勤奋，最后竟弹得像他的老师一样出色。有一天，这位年轻少爷一边散步一边沉思，走到一口水井旁边，他往井里一看，明亮如镜的水面上映出他那驴子的身影，他伤心极了，决心到广阔的世界去，随身只带一个忠实的伙伴。他们四处漫游，最后来到一个王国，统治这个王国的老国王有一个美貌非凡的独生女儿。小驴子说：“我们就在这里停留一下吧。”他敲城门，大声叫道：“有一个客人来访问，请开门让他进城。”城门不开，他就坐下，取出琉特，用他的两只前蹄弹奏起来，弹奏得非常美妙动听。守城的士兵瞪大了眼睛，跑去向国王报告说：“有一只小驴子在城门外弹奏琉特，他弹奏得很好，和熟练的乐师没什么两样。”

“那就把这个乐师给我叫进来吧。”国王说。小驴子一进去，所有的人都笑这个琉特演奏家。他被安排和仆人坐在一起吃饭，小驴子不乐意，他说：“我不是一头驴圈里普普通通的驴子，我是一头高贵的驴。”他们说：“既然如此，你去和武士们坐在一起吧。”

“不，”他说，“我要坐在国王身边。”国王笑了，兴致很好地说：“好，就准了你的要求，小驴子，到我身边来吧。”驴子在他身边坐下后，他又问：“小驴子呀，喜欢我的女儿吗？”小驴子转过脑袋，凝视着公主，点点头说：“太喜欢了，我还从来没见过这么漂亮的人儿呢。”

“那么你也应该坐在她的身边。”国王说。“我正求之不得。”驴子说，便坐在她身边吃喝起来，举止倒还挺文明得体。这只高贵的小动物在国王宫廷里待了一段时间以后，心里想：“这一切有什么用呢，到头来还不是得回家？”他悲伤地低垂着脑袋，走到国王跟前，就要告辞。国王却很喜欢他，说：“小驴子，你怎么啦？你看上去很悲伤，留在我这儿吧，你要什么，我给你。你要金子吗？”

“不。”小驴子说，摇摇脑袋。

“你要珠宝和装饰品？”

“不。”

“你要我的半个王国？”

“哦，不。”

“我要是知道怎么能让你快乐就好了，”国王说，“你要我的美丽的女儿做妻子？”

“对，对，”小驴子说，“我就是想要她。”一下子变得快活起来，因为这正是他心里所希望的。国王满足了他的要求，为他们举办了盛大豪华的婚礼。晚上，新郎新娘被领进洞房，国王想知道小驴子是不是也懂得温柔、有礼，便派一个侍从藏在那里。洞房里只有他们两人了，新郎插上门闩，扫视一下周围，相信只有他们两人在场，一下子脱下驴皮，一个英俊的王族子弟赫然站在那里。“你看我是谁？”他说，“你说我配不上你吗？”新娘子高兴极了，吻他，从心坎里爱他。天刚破晓，他跳起来，又套上那一身驴皮，谁也想不到驴皮里面是个何等样的人物。国王很快也来了，说：“嗨，小驴子又欢蹦乱跳了！”他对他的女儿说，“你没能嫁给一个人，一定很伤心吧？”

“哦，不，亲爱的父亲，我非常爱他，我觉得他是世界上最漂亮的男人，我要和他过一辈子。”国王觉得不可思议，这时，藏在洞房里的那个侍从来了，详尽地向国王报告了情况。国王说：“这绝不可能是真的。”

“那么明天晚上您亲自去守夜，您就会亲眼看见，国王陛下，您只要拿掉他的皮，把它扔进火里，他就会现出原形。”

“你的计策很好。”国王说。晚上，他们睡着以后，他悄悄溜进去，走到床前，月光下看见一个高贵的年轻人躺在床上，脱下的驴皮扔在地上。他把驴皮拿走，命人在外面生起一堆大火，把驴皮扔进火里，亲自守在旁边，看它烧成灰烬。他想看看新郎丢了驴皮怎么办，便彻夜不眠，细听有什么动静。年轻人睡醒了，晨光初露，他起床，正要套上驴皮，可是哪儿也找不到它了。他吃惊不小，又伤心又害怕地说：“看来我只好逃走了。”他走出来，国王站在门口，说：“我的儿子，你匆匆忙忙要去哪里？你有什么心事？留在这里吧，你是一个漂亮的男子，不要离开我，我要把我的半个王国给你，我死后整个王国都给你。”

“我希望良好的开端也能有良好的结局，”年轻人说，“我留在您这里。”于是老人给他半个王国，一年后国王去世，他拥有了整个王国。他的父亲去世后他又得到一个王国，享尽荣华富贵。

[1]一种弹拨乐器，状若琵琶，弹奏时置于膝盖上。

雪白和玫瑰红

有一个贫穷的寡妇孤单地住在一间小草屋里，房前有个花园，花园里有两株小玫瑰树，一株开白花，一株开红花。寡妇有两个孩子，像那两株玫瑰树一样，一个叫雪白，另一个叫玫瑰红。她们两个又虔诚又善良，热爱劳动，勤勉不息，真是世上少有；只是雪白比玫瑰红还更娴静、更温柔。玫瑰红更喜欢在草地上、田野上蹦蹦跳跳，寻找花朵，捕捉夏天的鸟儿；雪白则留在家里陪伴母亲，帮她料理家务，没什么事做的时候，就读书给她听。两个孩子相亲相爱，一起出去，总是手挽着手。如果雪白说：“我们不分开。”玫瑰红就回答说：“只要活着，我们就不分开。”母亲补上一句：“一个人有什么必须要和另一个人分。”她们常常在森林里跑来跑去，收集草莓；动物不伤害她们，倒和她们很亲近：小兔子从她们手上吃白菜叶，狍子在她们身边吃草，小鹿欢快地跳跃，小鸟儿停在枝头唱它们会唱的歌。她们没有发生过意外事故：如果她们在森林里长久逗留，夜幕降临，她们便并肩躺在苔藓上睡到第二天早晨，母亲知道了，并不为她们担忧。一次，她们在森林过夜，当朝霞唤醒她们的时候，她们看见一个俊美的孩子，穿一身洁白、闪亮的衣裳，坐在她们睡处的旁边。那孩子站起来，友爱地望着她们，一句话也没说，就走进了森林里。她们环顾周遭，发现自己睡在深渊的边缘，如果在黑暗中再走几步，就一定会掉下去。母亲告诉她们，那一定是守护好孩子的天使。

雪白和玫瑰红把母亲的小草屋收拾得非常整洁，让人朝屋里一望，就感到赏心悦目。夏天，玫瑰红料理家务，每天早晨母亲睡醒之前，她就把一束花放在母亲床前，每株小玫瑰树都有一朵玫瑰花在里面。冬天，雪白生火，把锅吊在火钩上，那口锅是青铜做的，被擦得非常干净，像黄金似地亮光闪闪。晚上雪花飞舞的时候，母亲说：“雪白，去把门闩闩上！”然后她们在炉灶旁坐下，母亲戴上眼镜，诵读一本大书，两个姑娘一边听着，一边纺线；一只小羊躺在她们身边，一只小白鸽蹲在她们背后的一根杆上，把头埋在翅膀底下。

一天晚上，她们这么和和美美地一起坐着，有人敲门，好像要求进屋。母亲说：“玫瑰红，快去开门，大概是个行路人想要投宿。”玫瑰红去拔门闩，心想这是一个可怜的男人；但不是，是一只熊把它那肥胖的黑乎乎的脑袋拱进门里。玫瑰红一声惊叫，后退几步；小羊咩咩叫，小白鸽扑打着翅膀，雪白躲在母亲的床后头。熊开口说话了，它说：“你们别害怕，我不会伤害你们的，我冻得半死，只想在你们这儿暖和暖和。”

“你这只可怜的熊，”母亲说，“在火旁边躺下吧，可要当心，别烧着你的毛皮。”她又大声说：“雪白，玫瑰红，出来吧，熊不会伤害你们，它说的是实话。”她们出来了，小羊和小鸽子也慢慢地靠拢过来，不怕它了。熊说：“孩子们，给我把毛皮上的雪拍打下来吧。”她们取来扫帚，把熊的皮扫干净；熊伸开四腿躺在火炉旁边，呼噜呼噜地哼哼，又高兴又舒服。不久，她们和它熟了，就戏弄这个笨拙的客人。她们扯熊的毛，踢它的背，把它推过来，推过去，或者用榛树枝抽它，熊哼叫，她们就笑。但熊心甘情愿让她们戏耍，只是在她们对它太恶作剧时，它就大叫：“让我活命吧，孩子们：雪白、玫瑰红，你们快打死你的求婚者了！”

睡觉的时间到了，别人都上床睡觉去了，母亲对熊说：“上帝保佑，你在炉灶旁边躺着不动，就不用担心寒冷和坏天气了。”天蒙蒙亮，两个孩子就开门放它出去，它踏着雪走进森林。从此，每天晚上熊在固定的时间来，躺在炉灶旁，让孩子们尽情戏耍；她们对它也习惯了，总要等到这黑色伙伴来了，才去闩门。

春天来了，大地一片葱绿，一天早晨，熊对雪白说：“现在我得走了，整整一个夏天都不能回来了。”

“亲爱的熊，你要去哪里？”雪白问。

“我得去森林里守护我的宝物，不让它们被凶恶的小矮人抢走。冬天大地冻硬了，他们只能待在地下，钻不出来。可是现在，大地被太阳晒得解冻了，晒得暖和了，他们就钻出来寻找、盗窃。不管什么东西，一旦落入他们手里，藏在他们洞中，就不容易重见天日了。”雪白对这次离别感到十分难过，她给熊拔门闩，熊挤出门时，被门钩卡住，撕下一块皮来，雪白似乎看见金子的闪光，但又不能十分肯定。熊急急忙忙跑了，转眼间消失在树林里面。

过了一段时间，母亲叫孩子们去森林里拣柴禾。她们看见野外有一棵大树被砍倒了放在地上，树干旁边的杂草中有个东西跳来跳去，但不知道是什么。走近一看，原来是一个小矮人，长着一张苍老而又憔悴的脸，长着长极了长极了的雪白的胡须。胡须末端夹在树缝里，小矮人就像一只拴在绳上的小狗那样跳来跳去，不知怎样才能摆脱困境。他瞪大两只火红的眼睛朝姑娘们大声喊叫：“你们站在这儿干什么！不能过来帮我一把吗？”

“你这是怎么回事，小矮人？”玫瑰红问。

“好奇的蠢鹅，”小矮人回答，“我要劈开树，拿小块木头去厨房烧火。我们不像你们这些粗鲁贪婪的人，吞食那么多东西，我们就只需要一点儿菜，烧大块木头一会儿就烧糊了。我已经把楔子打进木头里面，看来万事如意，可是这块该死的木头太滑溜，突然蹦出来，树干很快合拢，我来不及抽出我的漂亮的白胡须；胡须夹在树缝里，我没法走开。你们两个脸蛋光滑白嫩的蠢孩子还在笑！呸，真可恶！”

孩子们费尽力气，也没法把胡须拔出来，它夹得太紧了。“我去喊几个人来。”玫瑰红说。

“疯疯癫癫的傻丫头，”小矮人愤愤地说，“谁要你们去叫人？你们两个我看就太多了。你们就想不出好一点的办法吗？”

“别急，别急，”雪白说，“我有办法了！”她从口袋里取出小剪刀，铰断胡须的末端。小矮人一获得自由，马上抓住一只藏在树根之间、装满金子的口袋，一边提出来，一边叽里咕噜自言自语：“没教养的东西，把我的威严的胡须剪掉了一段！魔鬼会惩罚你们的！”说着，把口袋往背上一甩，也不再看孩子们一眼，掉转头就走了。

过些时候，雪白和玫瑰红要钓几条鱼做一道菜。她们走近小溪边，看见一个大蝗虫似的东西在水边蹦跶，好像要往水里跳。跑近前去，认得是那个小矮人。“你要去哪儿？”玫瑰红问，“该不是要下水吧？”

“我才不那么傻呢，”小矮人大声喊叫，“你们没看见吗，该死的鱼要把我拉下水！”原来小矮人坐在那儿钓鱼，很不幸，风一吹，他的胡须和钓竿的渔线纠缠在一起，这时刚巧有一条大鱼咬食，衰弱的矮人没有力气把鱼拉出水面。鱼占了上风，把矮人拉过去。尽管矮人拼命抓住草根，但却无济于事，不得不被鱼的游动所左右，随时有被拖下水去的危险。姑娘们来得正是时候，她们把他紧紧拉住，设法让胡须和渔线分开，但是不行：胡须和渔线紧紧缠在一起。没有别的办法，只好取出小剪刀，剪掉一小截胡须。矮人见了，冲她们高声怒骂：“你们两个淘气鬼，毁坏人家的容貌，太不像话了！你们剪掉我的胡须末端，还嫌不够，现在又把我最好的部分剪掉，我真没脸见我的家里人了。你们快跑开吧，跑得掉了鞋底才好！”说完，他去拿放在芦苇里面的一口袋珍珠，一句话也不多说，拖了就走，转过一块石头后面，就不见了。

不久，母亲叫两个女孩进城买针线、绳子和带子。她们走的路经过一片旷野，旷野上随处零零散散地堆放着大块岩石。她们看见一只大鸟在空中飞翔，在她们头顶上缓慢盘旋，越飞越低，后来便向不远处的一块岩石俯冲下去，随即听到一声凄厉的哀号。她们跑过去，见那情景，大吃一惊，老鹰抓住了她们的老相识——那个矮人，要把他攫走。两个好心肠的孩子马上紧紧拽住那小矮人，同老鹰拉来拉去，争夺了很长时间，才使老鹰放开它的猎物。矮人受到惊吓，定了定神后，用尖锐刺耳的声音喊道：“你们就不会对我小心点儿吗？你们又拉又拽，把我薄薄的衣服都扯碎了，弄出许多窟窿眼来，真是笨手笨脚的蠢丫头！”说完，提起一口袋宝石，又钻进岩石下边他的洞里去了。两个小姑娘已经习惯了他的忘恩负义，继续走她们的路，去城里买东西。回家时她们还从那片旷野走过，把那个矮人吓了一跳，矮人那时正把一口袋宝石倒在一块干净的地方，他没想到天这么晚了，还会有人来。夕阳照在亮晶晶的宝石上，色彩斑斓的宝石毫光四射，富丽无比，引得孩子停下脚步观赏。“你们站在这里张大嘴巴看什么？!”矮人大喊大叫，发灰的脸气得变成朱砂一样红。他还要继续骂下去，忽听得一声咆哮，从森林里窜出一只黑熊来。矮人大惊，跳了起来，但他来不及钻进洞里，熊已经到他身边。他吓得要死，大声喊道：“亲爱的熊先生，饶了我吧，我情愿把我所有的珍宝统统给您，您看看这里这些美丽的宝石吧。请您饶我一命，我一个又矮小又瘦弱的人对您有什么意思？还不够塞您的牙缝。这两个邪恶的女孩倒是您的两块嫩肉，像雏鹌鹑一样肥肥的。上帝保佑，您把她们抓去吃吧。”熊不听他胡说，抬起熊掌，一下就把那坏家伙打得再也不能动弹。

两个小姑娘跑了，熊在后面喊她们：“雪白，玫瑰红，别害怕，等等我，我要和你们一起走！”她们听出它的声音，站住了，熊来到她们身边，熊皮忽然脱落，眼前站着一个美男子，全身衣服都是金子做的。他说：“我是一个王子，那个邪恶的矮人偷了我的珠宝，又施了魔法，把我变成一只野熊在森林里奔跑，直到他死后我才能得救。现在他已得到应有的惩罚。”

雪白和王子结婚，玫瑰红和王子的弟弟结了婚，他们一起分了矮人聚敛到他洞中的大批珠宝。老母亲安宁幸福地和她的孩子们一起生活了好多年。她把两株玫瑰树移栽到她的窗前，它们年年开出美丽的玫瑰花，白玫瑰和红玫瑰。

玻璃棺材

谁都不能说一个穷裁缝就成不了大事，不能获得崇高的荣誉。只要他找对了门路，别的都无所谓，重要的是要有好运气。有一次，一个乖巧灵活的小裁缝出门漫游，走进一座大森林，在森林里迷了路。夜幕降临，他没有别的办法，只得在这可怖的寂寥中寻找睡觉的地方。柔软的苔藓自然是不错的床褥，只是害怕有野兽，他无法安宁，最后只好决定在树上过夜。他找了一棵高高的橡树，一直爬到树梢，谢天谢地，多亏他身上带着熨斗，否则刮过树梢的风准得把他卷走。

他哆哆嗦嗦，惊恐不安地在黑暗中度过了几个钟头，看见不远处有一点灯光，他想，那儿一定有人家，到那儿去要比在树上待着好些，便小心翼翼地从树上爬下来，朝灯光走去，来到一座用芦苇和灯芯草编成的小屋前面。他大胆地敲门，门开了，灯光下，他看见一个头发花白的小老头，身上穿的衣服是用五颜六色的碎布拼接起来的。“你是什么人，你要干什么？”小老头粗声粗气地问道。“我是一个穷裁缝，”他回答说，“黑夜里独自一人在这荒野，恳求您收留我，让我在您的茅草屋住一夜吧。”

“走你的路去吧，”老头子说，口气很不友好，“我不和流浪汉打交道。你去别处找个地方住吧。”说完就要回屋里去，裁缝紧紧揪住他的衣角哀求他，这老头看上去样子凶狠，其实心地不坏，他心软了，把裁缝带进屋里，给他吃的，又把房间一角一个不错的铺位给他睡觉。

疲乏的裁缝不需要人哄就睡得很香甜，要不是一阵喧闹声把他从睡梦中惊醒，他还想不到该起床呢。猛烈的嘶鸣和咆哮声穿过薄薄的墙壁传到屋里来。裁缝也不知道哪儿来的胆量，跳起来匆忙穿上衣服就往门外跑，只见一只大黑牛和一只美丽的鹿在小屋附近猛烈搏斗。它们怒气冲冲地向对方扑过去，大地被它们踹得颤抖起来，它们的嘶鸣和咆哮在空中震荡，斗了多时，仍然不分胜负。终于，鹿把它的角插进对手的肚子里去，随着一声骇人的吼叫，黑牛扑倒在地上，又挨了鹿几下猛击，黑牛断气了。

裁缝一直在吃惊地观战，那只鹿飞快向他跳去，他还是站着不动，没等他拔腿逃跑，鹿角已经把他叉了起来。那只鹿迅跑如飞，越过田野、山谷、草地和树林，他来不及多想，双手紧紧抓住鹿角，听天由命。他觉得就像在飞似的。那只鹿终于在一块岩壁前停下，轻轻放下裁缝。裁缝已经半死不活，好长时候才清醒过来。鹿一直站在他身边，等他恢复好些了，它用鹿角使劲推岩壁上的一道门。门被推开了，从门内喷出火焰，蒸汽随之而来，使他看不见那只鹿。裁缝不知该朝哪个方向走，该怎么办，才能离开这蛮荒之地，重新回到人群中去。他犹豫不决地站在那儿，这当儿，他听见岩石里面有一个声音向他呼唤：“进来吧，不要害怕，我不会伤害你的。”他虽然犹疑，却由于受一种神秘力量的驱使而听从了那个声音的召唤，便穿过铁门，走进一个宽敞的大厅。大厅的天花板、墙壁和地板都是用打磨得亮光闪闪的方方正正的石头砌成的，每一块方石上都刻着他不认识的符号。他十分惊奇地观察这一切，正想抽身退出，又听见那声音对他说：“踏上大厅正中那块方石，你就有福了。”

他的胆量已经大到敢于遵照那命令行事。那块方石在他脚下慢慢下沉。他又站稳脚跟的时候，环顾四周，那是一个大厅，大小和上面那个大厅完全一样，但是可供观赏、令人赞叹的东西还更多。墙上刻有若干深凹的处所，里面有透明的玻璃器皿，装满有颜色的酒精或充满淡蓝色烟雾。大厅地面上相对而立的两口大玻璃箱立即激起他的好奇心。他走近其中一口玻璃箱跟前，看见里面有一座宛如宫殿的美丽的建筑，周围有农庄、畜厩、仓廪诸如此类的东西。一切都很小，但精雕细刻，又极精确，似乎出自艺术家之手。

如果他不是又听见那声音的话，他的眼睛还会继续欣赏这些稀世珍品，无暇他顾。那个声音要他转过身子，去看对面的玻璃箱。他看见玻璃箱里躺着一位美貌绝伦的少女，感到无比惊奇。那少女如在睡梦中，长长的金黄色发丝犹如一袭大衣包裹着她的全身。她双眼紧闭，但她生机盎然的面色和因她的呼吸而来回飘动的带子都令人毫不怀疑她是活人。裁缝端详这位美人，心跳不止，忽然，她睁开眼睛，看见他在身旁，惊喜万分。“苍天有眼，”她大声说，“我就要获得解放了！快，快，快救我出这牢狱：你只要把这玻璃棺材上的闩子推开，我就得救了。”裁缝毫不犹豫，遵命照办，她很快掀开玻璃盖，走了出来，迅速去大厅角落，用一件肥大的外衣把全身包裹起来。随后她在一块石头上坐下，叫那年轻人走上前去，在他的嘴上印下一个亲昵的吻，之后，她说：“我盼望已久的解放者，是仁慈的上天引导你来到我这儿，结束我的苦难。我的苦难到头之日，就是你的幸福开始之时。你是上天指定的我的丈夫，注定要获得我的爱情，拥有人世间的一切财富，无扰地在欢乐中度过一生。坐下，让我把我的遭遇讲给你听：

“我是一位富有的伯爵的女儿，我年幼时父母就去世了，遵照父母的遗愿，把我托付给我哥哥，由他抚养我长大成人。我和哥哥亲密无间，志趣相投，我们两人决定永远不结婚，一直到死，永远相依为伴。我们家中向来不乏社交活动：时常有邻居、友人来看望我们，我们对所有的来宾都竭力殷勤招待。一天晚上，一个骑马的陌生人来到我们的伯爵府第，他说他来不及赶到下一个住宿地点，请求借宿。我们友好地接受了他的请求。晚餐席间和他的交谈以及他在谈话中穿插讲述的故事，使我们感到异常愉快。我哥哥非常喜欢他，请他在我们家里多住几天，他略表推辞，便同意了。直至夜深，我们才散席。客人被领去一个房间，我很疲累，赶快去柔软的床上躺下。我刚微微入睡，就被一阵细微而动听的音乐唤醒。我不知道是哪儿来的音乐，正要叫唤睡在隔壁房间的侍女，这才惊讶地发现，犹如梦魇压迫我胸脯，一种陌生的力量使我失去语言能力，我连一点细微的声音也发不出来了。我在夜间的灯光下，看见那个陌生人穿过两道紧锁着的门走进我的房间里来。他向我走过来，说他施了魔法，用优美动听的音乐把我唤醒，现在亲自穿过重重锁闭的门，就是为了向我求婚。我非常讨厌他施行魔法，根本不屑给予回答。他一动不动地在那里站了好一会儿，很可能是在期待得到一个对他有利的决定。后来见我始终沉默不语，他便恼怒地宣称他要报复，而且会有办法惩罚我的傲慢，说完便离开房间走了。这一夜，我极度不安，天快亮时才蒙眬入睡。醒来后我赶紧去找哥哥，要告诉他发生的事情，可是在他的房间里没能找到他，仆人告诉我，拂晓时分他骑马和那陌生人一起打猎去了。

“我马上预感到事情不妙，迅速穿好衣服，叫人给我的坐骑备好马鞍，向森林疾驰而去，只有一个仆人跟随我。途中，仆人和马一起摔倒，马腿折断，他不能随我一同去了。我马不停蹄地继续赶路，几分钟后，看见那个陌生人用绳子牵着一只美丽的鹿向我走过来。泪水从这只鹿的一双大眼睛里滚滚而下。我问他把我哥哥弄到哪里去了，他怎么弄到这只鹿的。他哈哈大笑，不回答我的问话。我愤怒至极，拔出手枪，对准这坏蛋射击，可是子弹从他的胸膛反弹回来，射进我的马的脑袋。我摔倒在地上，随后陌生人念念有词，我就失去知觉了。

“我又恢复知觉的时候，发现自己在这地下墓穴的一个玻璃棺材里面。那个魔法师又出现一次，说他把我的哥哥变成了一只鹿，把我的宫殿和属于宫殿的一切缩小了，锁在另一个玻璃棺材里面，把我的手下人变成烟雾封在了玻璃瓶里面。如果我现在肯顺从他，让他称心如意，他很容易就可以使一切恢复原先的状况，只要打开器皿，一切就都会恢复本来的自然形态。我照旧不理会他。他不见了，让我躺在我的牢狱里，陷入了深沉的睡眠。时常有些幻景飘入我的梦中，其中一个使我感到安慰的梦，是梦到一个年轻人来解救我。今天我睁开眼睛，看见了你，我知道我的梦就要圆了，请你帮助我实现我梦中所见的一切。首先要把装着我的宫殿的玻璃箱搬到那块宽大的石板上来。”

石头一承受重压，便载着少女和年轻人一起升高，穿过地板上的孔洞到上面的大厅上来，在这里，他们不费事就到外面来了。姑娘打开箱盖；看着宫殿、房屋、农庄以极快的速度自行伸展开来，恢复到原先的大小，真是无比奇妙。他们随即回到地下洞穴，把充满烟雾的瓶子都搬到石头上运上来。姑娘一打开瓶塞，蓝色烟雾喷涌出来，变成活生生的人，姑娘认得这些就是她的仆人和手下人。当她的哥哥杀死那个变成大黑牛的魔法师，恢复了人形，从森林里走出来的时候，她更高兴得不得了。就在这一天，姑娘依照她的承诺，在祭坛前面和幸运的裁缝结为夫妻。

女水妖

从前有一个磨坊主，和妻子一起过着快乐的生活。他们有钱，有田产，一年比一年富裕。可是一夜之间，不幸降临：当初他的财富增长迅速，如今一年年急遽减少，到头来磨坊主连他自己住的磨坊都很难说是他的了。他忧虑重重，白天干了一天活，夜里躺在床上，辗转反侧，无法安宁。

有一天，天还没亮他就起来，想到外面去散散心。他走过磨坊水堤，朝阳正射来第一道旭光，他听见水塘里有哗哗的水声，回头一看，只见一个美貌女子从水里缓缓升起来。被她娇嫩的双手拢住的长长的头发越过她的肩膀，从两侧流泻下来，遮住她白皙的身躯。他很清楚这是池塘里的女水妖，由于害怕，他不晓得自己该逃走还是该站住不动。女水妖温柔的声音叫着他的名字，问他为什么这样悲哀。磨坊主起初默不作声，后来听她说话十分和气友善，便鼓起勇气，向她讲述以前他的生活多么幸福富裕，现在多么贫困，自己也不知道该怎么办才好。“你放心，”女水妖回答说，“我能使你比从前更富裕、更幸福，只是你得答应把你家里刚生下来的给我。”

“除了生个小狗、小猫，”磨坊主心里想，“还能生什么？”便答应了她的要求。女水妖又沉下水去，磨坊主心情愉快，充满信心地快步走回磨坊。他还没到家里，使女就走出门口朝他大声喊，说他有喜事了，他的妻子给他生了一个男孩。磨坊主像触了电似的站住。他明白了：狡猾的女水妖早已知道，骗他上当。他低着头走到妻子床前，妻子问他：“这个男孩这么漂亮，你怎么不高兴？”他把遇见女水妖和他答应女水妖的事向她讲了。“如果失去孩子，”他接着说，“幸福和财富有什么用？我该怎么办呢？”对此，前来贺喜的亲戚也想不出什么好办法。

在此期间，磨坊主家又福星高照了。不管他做什么，总能成功，箱子、柜子仿佛自己装满了似的，一夜之间，柜橱里的钱多起来了。没过多久，他的财富就比以前还要多。但他并不快活：对女水妖的许诺使他心中痛苦。每当他走到水塘边，总担心女水妖会从水里冒出来向他讨债。他严禁男孩走近水塘边。“你要小心，”他对孩子说，“你一碰到水塘的水，就会有一只手伸出来抓住你，把你拖下水去。”然而时光流逝，年复一年，女水妖没再出现，磨坊主心里才踏实下来。

那男孩长成了小伙子，跟随一个猎人学艺，学成归来，成了一个精明能干的猎人，村里的老爷雇用了他。村子里有一个美丽率真的姑娘，猎人很喜欢她，老爷知道了，送给他一所小房子。两人举行了婚礼，倾心相爱，过着安宁幸福的生活。

有一天，猎人追赶一只鹿。那只鹿从森林里奔逃到旷野上，猎人紧追不舍，终于一枪把它撂倒在地上。但他没察觉自己就在那危险的水塘附近，取出猎物的内脏后，他双手沾满了血，便走去水塘边洗手。他的手刚伸进水里，女水妖就升上来，伸出湿淋淋的臂膀，笑着搂住他，把他拖下水去，波浪很快就淹没了他的头顶。

到了晚上，猎人没有回家，他的妻子担心他，就跑出去找他，以前他常跟她讲起他必须提防女水妖暗算，不敢走近水塘边，所以她已有出事了的不祥预感。她匆匆赶去水塘，看见猎人的袋子放在岸边，她已不再怀疑是不是大祸临头了。她悲痛万分，绞着双手，呼喊至爱的亲人的名字，然而无济于事；她又跑到水塘对岸呼唤他，狠狠咒骂女水妖，还是没有任何回答。池水如镜，平静无波，水底下只有月亮的半张脸一动不动地仰望着她。

可怜的妻子仍不离开水塘。她绕着它一圈又一圈地快步疾走，有时默不作声，有时发出一声激烈的呼喊，有时口中低声喃喃，绝不休息。最后她终于精疲力尽，倒在地上睡着了，睡得很深沉。不一会儿她就做了一个梦。

她梦见自己在巨大的岩石之间向上爬，心里惊惧万分；荆棘、藤蔓钩她的脚，雨打着她的脸，风吹乱她长长的头发。她爬上山顶，映入眼帘的是截然不同的另一番景象。天蓝蓝的，柔风轻拂，地缓缓下沉，在一片姹紫嫣红鲜花怒放的葱绿草地上，有一座干净的草屋。她走过去推开草屋的门，一个白发老妇人坐在屋里，向她和蔼地招手。就在这时，这个可怜的女人醒了。天已经亮了，她决定立即遵从梦中的指引。她艰难地爬上山顶，一切和夜里梦中所见一样。老妇人亲切接待她，指着一张椅子叫她坐下。“你找到我这孤寂的草屋，一定有不幸的遭遇。”老妇人说。女人含泪向她讲述了她的遭遇。“你放心吧，”老婆婆说，“我会帮助你，给你一把金梳子。你要耐心等待，等到圆月升上天空，那时你就去坐在池塘边上，用这把梳子梳你的长长的黑发，梳完了，把梳子放在池塘岸边，你就会看见要发生的事情。”

女人回去等待月圆，觉得时间过得很慢。一轮明月终于升上天空，她走出家门，来到池塘边坐下，用金梳子梳理她长长的黑色的头发，梳完了，把梳子放在池塘岸边。不久，哗啦一声，从水深处掀起一股波浪，卷到岸边，卷走了金梳子。很快，过了大约金梳子沉到水底所需要的那么长时间，水面分开了，猎人的头冒了出来。他不说话，悲哀地凝视着他的妻子。就在这一瞬间，第二股波浪哗啦啦卷过来，盖住猎人的脑袋。一切都消失了，池塘又平静如初，只有圆月的面庞在池面上闪光。

女人绝望地回家，梦中她又见到老婆婆的草屋。第二天早晨她再次上路，向智慧的老妇人诉说她的苦难。老婆婆给她一支金笛，说：“你要耐心等待，等到圆月再升上天空，你就去坐在池塘边上，用这支金笛吹奏出一首美妙的曲子，吹完了，把笛子放在池塘岸边，你就会看见要发生的事情。”

女人照老婆婆说的去做。笛子刚放在池塘岸边，哗啦一声，从水深处掀起一股波浪，卷到岸边，卷走了金笛。池水随即分开，不仅仅猎人的头，而且他的半个身子都露出了水面。他充满渴望地朝她张开双臂，但是第二股浪头喧嚣而来，盖住他，又把他拖下水去。

“啊，”不幸的女子说，“我只见到我至爱的亲人一面，就又失去了他，这有何用？”她的心里又充满了哀伤，但她第三次来到老婆婆那座草屋。智慧的老妇人给她一个金纺车，安慰她说：“不是所有的事情都做完了，你要耐心等待，等到圆月再升上天空，那时你就带上这辆纺车去坐在池塘边纺线，纺一满轴，纺完了，把纺车放在池塘岸边，你就会看见要发生的事情。”

女人完全照此办理。圆月一升上天空，她就把金纺车搬到池塘边辛勤纺线，直到亚麻纺完，线轴缠满了线。她刚把金纺车放在岸边，水深处响起比前两次都更厉害的喧嚣声，一阵大浪汹涌而来，卷走了纺车。随即，猎人的头和全身随着一股涌起的水柱一起升上来。他迅速跳到岸上，拉着妻子的手一起逃跑。可是，他们才走了一小段路程，整个池塘的水汹涌澎湃，发出惊心动魄的咆哮，迅猛地冲向广阔的原野。两个逃亡者看见死期已近在眼前。惊恐中，妻子向老婆婆呼救，就在这一瞬间，他们变了，她变成一只蛤蟆，他变成一只青蛙。洪水淹到他们身边，淹不死他们，但冲散了他们俩，把他们冲到很远很远的地方。

水退了，他们两个接触到干的土地，又都恢复了原先的人形。但谁都不知道另一个人在什么地方。他们生活在陌生人中间，人们对他们的家乡一无所知。他们只好以牧羊谋生，长年累月赶着羊群，穿过田野和森林，心中充满悲伤和思念。

又一年春回大地，两人在同一天出来放羊，他们偶然走近了彼此。他看见远远的山坡上有一群羊，便赶着羊群到那儿去。他们在一个山谷里相遇，两人谁都没有认出对方来，但他们都为不再孤独一人而高兴。从此他们天天一起放羊，他们说话不多，但心情愉快。一天晚上，皓月当空，羊儿都已睡了，牧羊人从口袋里取出笛子，吹了一支优美而哀伤的曲子。一曲终了，他发现牧羊女在伤心地哭泣。“你为什么哭泣？”他问道。“啊，”她回答说，“我最后一次用笛子吹奏这支曲子，看见我至爱的亲人从水里冒出头来的时候，天上也是这样的满月。”他凝视着她，仿佛一下子去掉了遮眼布：他认出了他的妻子；当月光照在他的脸上，她也认出了他。他们拥抱、亲吻。他们是否幸福，那就不用问了。

矮人的礼物

一个裁缝和一个金匠结伴漫游。一天傍晚，太阳下山后，他们听到远远地传来音乐声，越来越清晰；那乐声很不寻常，非常优美，他们听了，便忘记一切疲劳，继续快步往前走。月亮升起来了，他们走到一座小山前，看见山上有一群矮小的男人和女人手拉着手，正围成圆圈跳舞。矮人们非常快乐地舞蹈，边舞边唱极动听的歌，这就是方才漫游者听到的音乐。人群正中间坐着一位老者，他比其他人稍高一些，身穿一件色彩斑斓的外衣，一副斑白的长须飘垂胸前。两人停下脚步，惊讶不已地观看舞蹈。老者招手要他们进去，众小矮人欣然让出一个入口。金匠是个驼背，天下的驼子胆子都很大，金匠也是如此，他先走进矮人圈里；裁缝开始有点胆怯，站着不动，后来看那场景十分有趣，便壮起胆子，随后跟了进去。跳舞的圆圈迅速又围拢起来，小矮人们继续且歌且舞，他们的舞跳得极其狂野。老者取下腰带上佩带的一把大刀磨起来，磨得足够锋利的时候，老者回头看两个陌生人。两人心里害怕，他们还没来得及多想，老者就抓住金匠，迅捷无比地把他的头发、胡须剃得精光，接着对裁缝也如法炮制。他们的恐惧心理消失了。做完这事，老者亲切地拍拍两人的肩膀，好像是要表示：他们顺从地听凭他摆布，做得不错。他用手指指着堆放在边上的一堆煤，打手势要他们把煤装满他们的口袋。两人遵命照办，虽然并不明白要这些煤有什么用处。之后，两人便继续往前走，要找个过夜的地方。他们进了山谷，附近的修道院钟敲十二下，霎时间歌声沉寂，一切消失得无影无踪，月光下的小山分外寂静。

两个漫游者找到一家旅店，躺在干草铺上，身上盖上自己的衣服。因为十分劳累，忘了把煤块先拿出来。沉重的东西压着手和脚，所以他们醒得比平常早。一掏口袋，简直不敢相信自己的眼睛，原来他们装的不是煤块，而是纯金，头发、胡须也原样长着，毫发无损。现在他们俩都成了富人了。金匠生性贪婪，口袋装得更满，比裁缝还多一倍。但他贪心不足，还想要更多。金匠向裁缝建议再多住一天，晚上再去找山上的小老头要更多财宝。裁缝不愿去，他说：“我已经够多了，心满意足了。我这就当师傅去，娶我那舒服的东西（他这样称呼他的恋人），我是个幸福的男人了。”但他为了让金匠高兴，同意在那儿再多待一天。晚上，金匠想尽量多装些，还在肩上搭了几条口袋，然后上山。和前一天夜里一样，他看见小矮人们且歌且舞，那老者又把他剃得精光，示意他去取煤。他毫不犹豫，把他所有的口袋都装得满满当当，心里美滋滋地回去，盖上衣服睡觉。“金子压得再厉害，”他说，“我也能忍受。”终于，他怀着明天一早醒来就是个大富翁的甜蜜梦想睡着了。他一睁开眼睛就赶紧起床，检查口袋，可是不论掏多少次，掏出来的都是黑黝黝的煤块，他惊呆了。“我还有昨天夜里得到的金子。”他想，便拿了出来，看到那些东西也都变成了煤块，大吃一惊。他举起沾满煤屑的手拍打额头，觉得整个脑袋光溜溜的，连胡须一根也没了。但他的厄运并未到此为止，到这时他才发现，除了背上隆起的驼包之外，他的胸前还长出一块同样大小的肉团。他知道这是对他的贪婪的惩罚，便放声大哭起来。好心的裁缝被他的哭声吵醒了，尽力安慰这不幸的人，裁缝说：“我们是漫游的伙伴，你就留在我身边吧，一起分享我的财富。”裁缝信守诺言，可怜的金匠却得一辈子带着两坨肉团，用帽子遮盖他那光秃秃的脑袋。

鼓手

一天晚上，一个年轻鼓手独自走在田野上，他走到一个湖边，看见岸上有三块白色亚麻布。“多么精细的亚麻啊，”说着，他便捡一块放在自己口袋里。回到家里，他也没再想起捡到的东西，就上床睡觉去了。刚要入睡，恍惚听见有人在叫他的名字。凝神细听，一个轻柔的声音在呼唤他：“鼓手，鼓手，醒来吧。”漆黑的夜里，他看不见人，只觉得有个人影在他的床前来回移动。“你要干什么？”他问。

“你昨晚在湖边拿走了我的衬衣，”那声音回答说，“请你把它还给我。”

“告诉我，你是谁？”鼓手说，“我就还你。”

“啊，”那声音回答说，“我是一个强国的公主，落入一个巫婆手里，被困在玻璃山上。每天我必须和我的两个姐妹一起在湖里洗浴，丢了衬衣我就无法飞回去。我的姐妹已经飞走了，我还不得不留在这里。求求你把我的衬衣还给我吧。”

“不要着急，可怜的孩子，”鼓手说，“我很乐意还给你。”他从口袋里取出那块亚麻布，在黑暗中递给她。她一把抓住，就要匆匆离去。“等一等，”他说，“说不定我能帮助你。”

“你要帮助我，就得上玻璃山，把我从巫婆手里救出来。但是你无法去玻璃山，即使到了山前，也爬不上去。”

“我要做什么，就一定能做到，”鼓手说，“我同情你，我什么都不怕，就是不知道要去玻璃山该走哪条路。”

“去玻璃山的路穿过一座大森林，森林里有吃人的巨人，”她回答说，“我只能讲这些，不能再多说了。”随后，他听见她飞走了。

鼓手天亮就起身，挂上鼓，毫不畏惧地径直走进森林。走了一会儿，没看见巨人，他想：“我得把睡懒觉的家伙叫醒。”就把鼓挂在身前，一通鼓打得树上的鸟儿惊叫着飞起来。很快就有一个躺在草里睡觉的巨人站起来，就像一棵枞树那么高。“你这个小家伙，”巨人向鼓手喊道，“我睡得正香，你为什么在这里敲鼓，把我吵醒？”

“我后面还有几千人要来，”鼓手回答说，“我敲鼓是为了给他们引路。”

“他们来我的森林里干什么？”巨人问。

“他们来干掉你，清除森林里像你一样的怪物。”

“哎呀呀，”巨人说“，我踩死你们还不是像踩死蚂蚁一样容易？”

“你以为你对付得了他们？”鼓手说，“你弯腰去抓一个人，他就逃走，躲起来；你躺下想睡觉，他们就从所有的树丛里出来，爬到你身上。他们个个腰带上掖着一把钢锤，要用它来砸你的天灵盖。”巨人心里懊恼，他想：“和这些狡猾的人斗，最后我恐怕要吃亏。我能卡住狼和熊的咽喉，却对付不了蚯蚓。”他说：“听着，小家伙，你撤回去吧，我向你承诺：将来我不会找你和你的伙伴麻烦，如果你还有什么愿望，就告诉我，我想做一点让你高兴的事情。”

“你腿长，比我走得快，”鼓手说，“把我背到玻璃山吧，我就给我的人发个信号，让他们撤退，这次不让他们给你找麻烦了。”

“来吧，小虫子，”巨人说，“坐在我的肩膀上，你要去哪儿，我就背你去哪儿。”巨人把他提起来放在肩上，鼓手在上面尽兴地打鼓，巨人还以为他是在发信号让其他人撤退呢。过一会儿，又一个巨人站在路旁，把鼓手从第一个巨人肩上拿下来，放在自己衣服的纽扣眼里。纽扣像盆那么大，鼓手紧紧扒住纽扣，快乐地朝四下里张望。途中他们又见到第三个巨人，他把鼓手接过去，放在他的帽檐上。鼓手在上面走来走去，目光越过树梢远眺前方，看见蔚蓝色的远方有一座山，他笑了，心想，这一定就是玻璃山了。果然不错。那巨人又走几步，便到了山脚下。巨人把他放下来，鼓手要求把他背到玻璃山上去，巨人摇摇头，嘟囔了几句，就回森林里去了。

可怜的鼓手站在山下，山极高，仿佛三座山摞在一起似的，玻璃山光滑如镜，他要上山，却不知道如何才能上去。他开始爬山，但总是劳而无功，一而再、再而三地滑下来。“我要是一只鸟儿就好了。”他想。可是这么企盼有何用呢？他也没能长出翅膀来。他束手无策站在那儿，看见不远处有两个男人在激烈争吵。他朝他们走去，原来是为了一个马鞍发生争执，马鞍就在他们跟前的地上放着，两人都想据为己有。“你们真傻，”他说，“为一个马鞍争吵不休，又没有马骑。”

“这马鞍很值得一争，”两人中的一人说，“谁坐在这马鞍上，他即使到世界的尽头，只要他说出愿望，眨眼间就到了。它本是我们共有的，现在该轮到我骑在马鞍上了，可他却不让。”

“我能很快调停这起纠纷，”鼓手说着，走了一段路，把一根白色的棍子插在地上，走回来后说：“现在你们就朝那目标跑去，谁先到，谁就先骑。”那两人发足狂奔，没等他们跑多远，鼓手翻身骑上马鞍，说他要上玻璃山，还不到翻掌的工夫，人已经在那里了。玻璃山上有一块平地，平地上有一座年久的石屋，石屋前面有一个大鱼塘，鱼塘后面是一片黝黑的森林。他看不见人，看不见动物，四外静寂，只有风吹过树木的沙沙声，云几乎贴着他的头顶飘走。他走到门前敲门，敲了三次，才有一个褐色面皮、红眼睛的老婆子来开门；她长长的鼻子上架着一副眼镜，目光锐利地看着他，问他要干什么。“让我进去，供我食宿。”鼓手回答说。

“可以，”老婆子回答说，“不过你得做三件事。”

“没问题！”鼓手回答说，“我生来不怕干活，再重的活也不怕。”老婆子让他进去，给他饭吃，晚上让他睡一张很好的床铺。早晨，他睡醒了，老婆子从她干瘪的手指上脱下一枚顶针，递给鼓手，说：“现在去干活，用这枚顶针把外面池塘里的水舀干，入夜之前必须干完，而且池塘里所有的鱼都要按不同品种大小顺序排好。”

“这是个罕见的工作。”鼓手说着，去池塘动手舀水。整整舀了一上午也毫无起色。用一枚顶针舀一口大池塘的水，即使舀一千年，能有什么结果？中午时分，他想：“全都白费力气，干不干还不是一个样？”他不干了，坐下来。这时屋里走出来一位姑娘，把一个盛着午饭的篮子放在他跟前，说：“你坐在这里这么悲哀，是病了吗？”他望着她，看见她非常美。

“啊，”他说，“第一个工作我就完不成，其他的工作怎么办呢？我是出来找一位公主的，她说她住在这里，可我没见到她。我想继续往前走。”

“留在这里吧，”姑娘说，“我要帮助你摆脱困境。你累了，把你的头枕在我怀里睡吧。你睡醒了，事情也就做完了。”鼓手没等她再说第二遍。他一闭上眼睛，姑娘就转动如意戒指，说：“水升上来，鱼儿出来。”立时，池水犹如一片白雾升上高空，和其他云朵一起飘走，鱼儿喘着粗气蹦到岸上，自行按照不同种类和大小排列整齐。鼓手醒来，看见大功告成，惊奇不已。姑娘却说：“有一条鱼不跟同类排在一起，自己单独待着。老太婆今天晚上来，看见一切都照她的要求做了，如果她问：‘这条鱼怎么单独在这儿？’你就把鱼朝她脸上扔去，说：‘这条鱼是给你的，老巫婆。'”

晚上，老婆子来了，她问了那句话，鼓手就把鱼往她脸上扔过去。她装作没看见的样子，却目露凶光盯着他看。

翌日早晨，老婆子说：“昨天的活你干得太容易了，我得给你重一点的活。今天你要把整座森林的树都砍倒，把木头劈了，码成六尺高的柴垛，晚上必须全部做完。”她给他一把斧、一把锤和两个楔子。但斧是铅斧，锤和楔子都是白铁做的。他一砍树，斧刃就卷了，锤子、楔子都砸瘪了。他束手无策。中午，姑娘又带了食物来安慰他。“你的头枕在我怀里，”她说，“睡吧，睡醒了，事情也就做完了。”她转动她的如意戒指。顷刻间，整座森林里的树全都哗啦啦倒了，木头自己劈成小块木柴，自行堆成六尺高的柴垛，仿佛有眼不可见的巨人在完成这工作似的。鼓手醒了，姑娘说：“你看，木柴堆成方木柴垛，只剩下一根树枝。老太婆今天晚上来，如果她问这树枝是怎么回事，你就用这树枝打她，说：‘这树枝是给你的，老巫婆。'”

老婆子来了，她说“：你看，这活多容易干呀，这树枝是给谁的？”

“给你的，老巫婆。”他回答说，拿起树枝打了她一下。但她装作什么也没感觉到的样子，冷笑着说：“明天早晨你把所有木柴堆成一个柴堆，点火把它烧了。”

拂晓时分他就起床，开始搬运木柴。可是，就他一个人怎么能把整个森林的木柴都弄到一块儿呢？工作没有进展。在危难之际，姑娘没有离开他：中午她给他带来菜肴，吃完饭后，他把头枕在她的怀里睡着了。一觉醒来，整个柴堆烈火熊熊地燃烧，火舌上冲云霄。“注意听我说，”姑娘说，“巫婆来时，会叫你做各种各样事情，不要害怕，她要你做什么，你都毫不畏惧地去做，她就丝毫伤害不了你；如果你害怕了，大火就会烧着你、吞噬你。到最后，你一切都做完了，就双手抓住她，把她抛入火海。”

姑娘走了，老婆子悄悄过来。“唉，真冷！”她说，“这儿有堆火烧着，暖和我这把老骨头，我觉得挺好。不过那儿有块木头没有燃烧，你去给我拿出来。做了这事，你就自由了，想去哪里，就可以去哪里。快去吧！”鼓手不假思索，跃进火海，火焰没伤害他，甚至没烧掉他一根毫毛。他把那块木头拿出来，放在地上。那木头一接触地面，马上变了：鼓手面前站着的，正是危难中给予他援手的美丽的姑娘，鼓手从她的一身流金焕彩的丝绸衣裳认出这就是他要找的公主。但是老婆子狞笑着说：“你以为你得到她了，其实你还没有得到她。”她正要朝公主扑过去，把她拖走，鼓手双手抓住老婆子，把她高高举起来，抛进熊熊燃烧的火焰，火焰吞没了她，火焰似乎为吞噬了一个巫婆而感到欢欣。

公主望着鼓手，见他是个英俊少年，想到他冒着生命危险来救她，便向他伸出手，说：“你为了我甘冒一切危险，我也愿意为你做一切事情。如果你答应对我忠实，我愿做你的妻子。我们有的是财富，我们拥有巫婆在这里所聚敛的，已足够了。”她把他领进屋里，那里有许多箱子柜子，装满珍宝。他们放着金银不拿，只带上宝石。她不愿在玻璃山上再逗留更长时间，鼓手对她说：“你和我一起坐在我的马鞍上，我们就会像鸟儿一样飞下山去。”

“我不喜欢旧马鞍，”她说，“我只要转动一下如意戒指，我们就到家了。”

“好，”鼓手回答说，“我们就发愿去城门口。”转眼间他们已在那里了。鼓手说：“我要先去我父母家里，告诉他们情况，你就在这原野上等我，我很快就回来。”

“啊，”公主说，“我请求你多加小心，到家后不要吻你父母的右面颊，否则你会忘记一切，我就得孤零零独自一人留在原野上了。”

“我怎么会忘记你呢？”鼓手说，许诺他很快就回来。

当他踏进父母的家，没有人知道他是谁，他的变化很大，因为他在玻璃山上度过的三天已是世上漫长的三年。他说了自己的身份，他的父母高兴得扑过去搂着他的脖子，他心里非常激动，忘了姑娘的嘱咐，亲吻了父母的双颊。他在父母的右脸颊印上了一个吻，有关公主的一切记忆就全都消失了。他把口袋里的东西都掏出来，将一大把非常大的宝石放在桌上。父母简直不知道该如何处置这些财富。于是父亲建造一座豪华宫殿，若干花园、草地，几座树林环绕宫殿周围，仿佛住在里面的是一位王侯。宫殿竣工了，母亲说：“我给你挑选了一个姑娘，三天后就举行婚礼。”父母想要的一切，儿子全都赞同。

可怜的公主在城门口站了很久，等待年轻人回去。到了晚上，她说：“他一定吻了他父母的右脸颊，把我忘了。”她心中充满悲伤，希望住在冷清的林中小屋，不愿再回到她父王的宫廷。她每天进城去，从他的家门口走过，他见到她几次，但已不认得她了。终于她听到人们说：“明天他要举行婚礼了。”她说：“我要试一试，看我能不能再次赢得他的心。”到了新婚首日晚会时，她转动她的如意戒指，说：“我要一件拥有太阳一样光辉的衣裳。”这衣裳立刻放在了她的面前，光芒耀眼，仿佛纯系太阳的光线织成的。宾客全都到齐了，她走进大厅。人人都对这件美丽的衣裳惊奇不已，而最感惊奇的则是新娘子。因为美丽的衣裳是她最大的快乐，她便走近那陌生女子身旁，问她是否愿意把这件衣裳卖给她。“用钱买不行，”她回答道，“不过，如果第一夜能让我待在新郎睡觉的房门口的话，我愿意卖。”新娘子无法抑制自己的欲望，便答应了，但她在酒里掺进安睡药水，新郎晚间喝了，睡得非常深沉。夜阑人静时，公主蹲在卧室门前，推开一点门缝，朝屋里说道：

鼓手，鼓手，你听我说，
难道你完全忘了我？
忘了玻璃山上你我坐在一起？
忘了我从巫婆手里救过你？
忘了你和我握手矢志忠贞不渝？
鼓手啊，鼓手，你听我说。

然而一切都无济于事，鼓手沉睡不醒，到了早晨，公主没能如愿以偿，只得离去。

第二天晚上，她转动如意戒指，说：“我要一件银白如月的衣裳。”她穿着柔美如月光的衣裳参加晚会，又激起新娘子的贪欲，允许公主在卧房门前度过第二个夜晚。夜深人静时她大声说道：

鼓手，鼓手，你听我说，
难道你完全忘了我？
忘了玻璃山上你我坐在一起？
忘了我从巫婆手里救过你？
忘了你和我握手矢志忠贞不渝？
鼓手啊，鼓手，你听我说。

可是鼓手喝了安睡药酒，睡得昏昏沉沉，无法唤醒。早晨，她又伤心地回到她的林中小屋。但鼓手府第中的人们听到了陌生姑娘的哀诉，对新郎谈起此事，他们还告诉他，他不可能听见什么，因为他们在他的酒里倒进安睡的药了。第三天晚上，公主转动如意戒指，说：“我要一件如同星光闪烁的衣裳。”当她穿着它在晚会上露面时，新娘子见它远比前两件衣裳更为绚丽华贵，激动极了，她说：“我无论如何要得到它。”和以前一样，姑娘要求获准在新郎卧室门前过夜。临睡前给新郎端来了酒，新郎不喝，把它泼在床后。屋子里全都安静下来了，他听见一个温柔的声音呼唤他：

鼓手，鼓手，你听我说，
难道你完全忘了我？
忘了玻璃山上你我坐在一起？
忘了我从巫婆手里救过你？
忘了你和我握手矢志忠贞不渝？
鼓手啊，鼓手，你听我说。

鼓手忽然恢复了记忆。“啊，”他喊道，“我怎能如此无情无义？原因是，我心里一高兴吻了我父母的右面颊，这一吻使我完全迷糊了。”他跳起来，拉着公主的手，把她领到他父母床前。“这才是我真正的新娘，”他说，“如果我娶另一个，就要铸成大错了。”父母听说了事情的全部经过，便同意了。于是大厅中又再点燃灯烛，召来鼓乐，邀集亲朋，极尽欢乐地举行真正的婚礼。那几件漂亮的衣裳归第一个新娘所有，作为对她的补偿，她也感到满意。

Godfather Death

A poor man had twelve children and was forced to work night and day to give them even bread. When therefore the thirteenth came into the world, he knew not what to do in his trouble, but ran out into the great highway, and resolved to ask the first person whom he met to be godfather. The first to meet him was the good God who already knew what filled his heart, and said to him,“Poor man, I pity you. I will hold your child at its christening, and will take charge of it and make it happy on earth.”

The man said,“Who are you?”

“I am God.”

“Then I do not desire to have you for a godfather,”said the man;“you give to the rich, and leave the poor to hunger.”Thus spoke the man, for he did not know how wisely God apportions riches and poverty. He turned therefore away from the Lord, and went farther.

Then the Devil came to him and said,“What do you seek? If you will take me as a godfather for your child, I will give him gold in plenty and all the joys of the world as well.”

The man asked,“Who are you?”

“I am the Devil.”

“Then I do not desire to have you for godfather,”said the man;“you deceive men and lead them astray.”He went onwards, and then came Death striding up to him with withered legs, and said,“Take me as godfather.”

The man asked,“Who are you?”

“I am Death, and I make all equal.”

Then said the man,“You are the right one, you take the rich as well as the poor, without distinction; you shall be godfather.”

Death answered,“I will make your child rich and famous, for he who has me for a friend can lack nothing.”The man said,“Next Sunday is the christening; be there at the right time.”Death appeared as he had promised, and stood godfather quite in the usual way.

When the boy had grown up, his godfather one day appeared and bade him go with him. He led him forth into a forest, and showed him a herb which grew there, and said,“Now shall you receive your godfather's present. I make you a celebrated physician. When you are called to a patient, I will always appear to you. If I stand by the head of the sick man, you may say with confidence that you will make him well again, and if you give him of this herb he will recover; but if I stand by the patient's feet, he is mine, and you must say that all remedies are in vain, and that no physician in the world could save him. But beware of using the herb against my will, or it might fare ill with you.”

It was not long before the youth was the most famous physician in the whole world.“He had only to look at the patient and he knew his condition at once, and if he would recover, or must needs die.”So they said of him, and from far and wide people came to him, sent for him when they had any one ill, and gave him so much money that he soon became a rich man. Now it so befell that the King became ill, and the physician was summoned, and was to say if recovery were possible. But when he came to the bed, Death was standing by the feet of the sick man, and the herb did not grow which could save him.“If I could but cheat Death for once,”thought the physician,“he is sure to take it ill if I do, but, as I am his godson, he will shut one eye; I will risk it.”He therefore took up the sick man, and laid him the other way, so that now Death was standing by his head. Then he gave the King some of the herb, and he recovered and grew healthy again. But Death came to the physician, looking very black and angry, threatened him with his finger, and said,“You have overreached me;this time I will pardon it, as you are my godson; but if you venture it again, it will cost you your neck, for I will take you yourself away with me.”

Soon afterwards the King's daughter fell into a severe illness. She was his only child, and he wept day and night, so that he began to lose the sight of his eyes, and he caused it to be made known that whosoever rescued her from death should be her husband and inherit the crown. When the physician came to the sick girl's bed, he saw Death by her feet. He ought to have remembered the warning given by his godfather, but he was so infatuated by the great beauty of the King's daughter, and the happiness of becoming her husband, that he flung all thought to the winds. He did not see that Death was casting angry glances on him, that he was raising his hand in the air, and threatening him with his withered fist. He raised up the sick girl, and placed her head where her feet had lain. Then he gave her some of the herb, and instantly her cheeks flushed red, and life stirred afresh in her.

When Death saw that for a second time he was defrauded of his own property, he walked up to the physician with long strides, and said,“All is over with you, and now the lot falls on you,”and seized him so firmly with his ice-cold hand, that he could not resist, and led him into a cave below the earth. There he saw how thousands and thousands of candles were burning in countless rows, some large, others half-sized, others small. Every instant some were extinguished, and others again burnt up, so that the flames seemed to leap hither and thither in perpetual change.“See,”said Death,“these are the lights of men's lives. The large ones belong to children, the half-sized ones to married people in their prime, the little ones belong to old people; but children and young folks likewise have often only a tiny candle.”

“Show me the light of my life,”said the physician, and he thought that it would be still very tall. Death pointed to a little end which was just threatening to go out, and said,“Behold, it is there.”

“Ah, dear godfather,”said the horrified physician,“light a new one for me, do it for love of me, that I may enjoy my life, be King, and the husband of the King's beautiful daughter.”

“I cannot,”answered Death,“one must go out before a new one is lighted.”

“Then place the old one on a new one, that will go on burning at once when the old one has come to an end,”pleaded the physician. Death behaved as if he were going to fulfill his wish, and took hold of a tall new candle; but as he desired to revenge himself, he purposely made a mistake in fixing it, and the little piece fell down and was extinguished. Immediately the physician fell on the ground, and now he himself was in the hands of Death.

The Wolf and the Man

Once on a time the fox was talking to the wolf of the strength of man; how no animal could withstand him, and how all were obliged to employ cunning in order to preserve themselves from him. Then the wolf answered,“If I had but the chance of seeing a man for once, I would set on him notwithstanding.”

“I can help you to do that,”said the fox.“Come to me early tomorrow morning, and I will show you one.”The wolf presented himself betimes, and the fox took him out on the road by which the huntsmen went daily. First came an old discharged soldier.“Is that a man?”inquired the wolf.

“No,”answered the fox,“that was one.”Afterwards came a little boy who was going to school.“Is that a man?”

“No, that is going to be one.”At length came a hunter with his double-barrelled gun at his back, and hanger by his side. Said the fox to the wolf,“Look, there comes a man, you must attack him, but I will take myself off to my hole.”The wolf then rushed on the man. When the huntsman saw him he said,“It is a pity that I have not loaded with a bullet,”aimed, and fired his small shot in his face. The wolf pulled a very wry face, but did not let himself be frightened, and attacked him again, on which the huntsman gave him the second barrel. The wolf swallowed his pain, and rushed on the huntsman, but he drew out his bright hanger, and gave him a few cuts with it right and left, so that, bleeding everywhere, he ran howling back to the fox.“Well, brother wolf,”said the fox,“how have you got on with man?”

“Ah!”replied the wolf,“I never imagined the strength of man to be what it is! First, he took a stick from his shoulder, and blew into it, and then something flew into my face which tickled me terribly; then he breathed once more into the stick, and it flew into my nose like lightning and hail; when I was quite close, he drew a white rib out of his side, and he beat me so with it that I was all but left lying dead.”

“See what a braggart you art!”said the fox.“You throw your hatchet so far that you can not fetch it back again!”

The Old Man and His Grandson

There was once a very old man, whose eyes had become dim, his ears dull of hearing, his knees trembled, and when he sat at table he could hardly hold the spoon, and spilt the broth upon the table-cloth or let it run out of his mouth. His son and his son's wife were disgusted at this, so the old grandfather at last had to sit in the corner behind the stove, and they gave him his food in an earthenware bowl, and not even enough of it. And he used to look towards the table with his eyes full of tears.

Once, too, his trembling hands could not hold the bowl, and it fell to the ground and broke. The young wife scolded him, but he said nothing and only sighed. Then they bought him a wooden bowl for a few halfpence, out of which he had to eat.

They were once sitting thus when the little grandson of four years old began to gather together some bits of wood upon the ground.“What are you doing there?”asked the father.“I am making a little trough,”answered the child,“for father and mother to eat out of when I am big.”

The man and his wife looked at each other for a while, and presently began to cry. Then they took the old grandfather to the table, and henceforth always let him eat with them, and likewise said nothing if he did spill a little of anything.

Simeli Mountain

There were once two brothers, the one rich, the other poor. The rich one, however, gave nothing to the poor one, and he gained a scanty living by trading in corn, and often did so badly that he had no bread for his wife and children. Once when he was wheeling a barrow through the forest he saw, on one side of him, a great, bare, naked-looking mountain, and as he had never seen it before, he stood still and stared at it with amazement. While he was thus standing he saw a twelve great, wild men coming towards him, and as he believed they were robbers he pushed his barrow into the thicket, climbed up a tree, and waited to see what would happen. The twelve men, however, went to the mountain and cried,“Semsi mountain, Semsi mountain, open,”and immediately the barren mountain opened down the middle, and the twelve went into it, and as soon as they were within, it shut. After a short time, however, it opened again, and the men came forth carrying heavy sacks on their shoulders, and when they were all once more in the daylight they said,“Semsi mountain, Semsi mountain, shut yourself;”then the mountain closed together, and there was no longer any entrance to be seen to it, and the twelve went away. When they were quite out of sight the poor man got down from the tree, and was curious to know what really was secretly hidden in the mountain. So he went up to it and said,“Semsi mountain, Semsi mountain, open,”and the mountain opened to him also. The he went inside, and the whole mountain was a cavern full of silver and gold, and behind lay great piles of pearls and sparkling jewels, heaped up like corn. The poor man hardly knew what to do, and whether he might take any of these treasures for himself or not; but at last he filled his pockets with gold, but he left the pearls and precious stones where they were. When he came out again he also said,“Semsi mountain, Semsi mountain, shut yourself;”and the mountain closed itself, and he went home with his barrow. And now he had no more cause for anxiety, but could buy bread for his wife and children with his gold, and wine into the bargain. He lived joyously and uprightly, gave help to the poor, and did good to every one. When, however, the money came to an end he went to his brother, borrowed a measure that held a bushel, and brought himself some more, but did not touch any of the most valuable things. When for the third time he wanted to fetch something, he again borrowed the measure of his brother. The rich man had, however, long been envious of his brother's possessions, and of the handsome way of living which he had set on foot, and could not understand from whence the riches came, and what his brother wanted with the measure. Then he thought of a cunning trick, and covered the bottom of the measure with pitch, and when he got the measure back a piece of money was sticking in it. He at once went to his brother and asked him,“What have you been measuring in the bushel measure?”

“Corn and barley,”said the other. Then he showed him the piece of money, and threatened that if he did not tell the truth he would accuse him before a court of justice. The poor man then told him everything, just as it happened. The rich man, however, ordered his carriage to be made ready, and drove away, resolved to use the opportunity better than his brother had done, and to bring back with him quite different treasures. When he came to the mountain he cried,“Semsi mountain, Semsi mountain, open.”The mountain opened, and he went inside it. There lay the treasures all before him, and for a long time he did not know which to clutch at first. At length he loaded himself with as many precious stones as he could carry. He wished to carry his burden outside, but, as his heart and soul were entirely full of the treasures, he had forgotten the name of the mountain, and cried,“Simeli mountain, Simeli mountain, open.”That, however, was not the right name, and the mountain never stirred, but remained shut. Then he was alarmed, but the longer he thought about it the more his thoughts confused themselves, and his treasures were no more of any use to him. In the evening the mountain opened, and the twelve robbers came in, and when they saw him they laughed, and cried out,“Bird, have we caught you at last! Did you think we had never noticed that you had been in here twice? We could not catch you then; this third time you shall not get out again!”Then he cried,“It was not I, it was my brother,”but let him beg for his life and say what he would, they cut his head off.

The Nail

A merchant had done good business at the fair; he had sold his wares, and lined his money-bags with gold and silver. Then he wanted to travel homewards, and be in his own house before nightfall. So he packed his trunk with the money on his horse, and rode away. At noon he rested in a town, and when he wanted to go farther the stable-boy brought out his horse and said,“A nail is wanting, sir, in the shoe of its left hind foot.”

“Let it be wanting,”answered the merchant;“the shoe will certainly stay on for the six miles I have still to go. I am in a hurry.”In the afternoon, when he once more alighted and had his horse fed, the stableboy went into the room to him and said,“Sir, a shoe is missing from your horse's left hind foot. Shall I take him to the blacksmith?”

“Let it still be wanting,”answered the man;“the horse can very well hold out for the couple of miles which remain. I am in haste.”He rode forth, but before long the horse began to limp. It had not limped long before it began to stumble, and it had not stumbled long before it fell down and broke its leg. The merchant was forced to leave the horse where it was, and unbuckle the trunk, take it on his back, and go home on foot. And there he did not arrive until quite late at night.“And that unlucky nail,”said he to himself,“has caused all this disaster.”

The more haste the less speed.

The Peasant and the Devil

There was once on a time a far-sighted, crafty peasant whose tricks were much talked about. The best story is, however, how he once got hold of the Devil, and made a fool of him.

The peasant had one day been working in his field, and as twilight had set in, was making ready for the journey home, when he saw a heap of burning coals in the middle of his field, and when, full of astonishment, he went up to it, a little black devil was sitting on the live coals.“You do indeed sit upon a treasure!”said the peasant.

“Yes, in truth,”replied the Devil,“on a treasure which contains more gold and silver than you have ever seen in your life!”“The treasure lies in my field and belongs to me,”said the peasant.

“It is yours,”answered the Devil,“if you will for two years give me the half of everything your field produces. Money I have enough of, but I have a desire for the fruits of the earth.”The peasant agreed to the bargain.“In order, however, that no dispute may arise about the division,”said he,“everything that is above ground shall belong to you, and what is under the earth to me.”The Devil was quite satisfied with that, but the cunning peasant had sown turnips. Now when the time for harvest came, the Devil appeared and wanted to take away his crop; but he found nothing but the yellow withered leaves, while the peasant, full of delight, was digging up his turnips.“You have had the best of it for once,”said the Devil,“but the next time that won't do. What grows above ground shall be yours, and what is under it, mine.”

“I am willing,”replied the peasant; but when the time came to sow, he did not again sow turnips, but wheat. The grain became ripe, and the peasant went into the field and cut the full stalks down to the ground. When the Devil came, he found nothing but the stubble, and went away in a fury down into a cleft in the rocks.“That is the way to cheat the Devil,”said the peasant, and went and fetched away the treasure.

译者序

从独立战争到南北战争，一般被称为美国的浪漫主义文学时期。在这个时期，涌现了一批文学史上的重要人物，如华盛顿·欧文、詹姆斯·库柏、纳撒尼尔·霍桑、爱伦·坡和惠特曼等。他们不仅推动了美国文学的发展，也为世界文学增色不少。尤其是华盛顿·欧文更是独领风骚，起着开拓者的作用。他的创作震惊了美国文坛，也在英国文坛掀起了轩然大波，令“老大哥”英国文学家们刮目相看，称他为“美国文学之父”。

华盛顿·欧文（1783—1859）是苏格兰裔的美国人，其父年轻时从苏格兰迁居纽约，在纽约发了大财，家境富裕。欧文受哥哥的影响，自小酷爱文学，博览群书，最叫他陶醉的是彭斯、拜伦、司各特等英国浪漫主义作家的作品。1802年，19岁的欧文在《早晨纪事报》上发表了几篇书信体散文，崭露头角。1804年，他走出国门到欧洲旅行（这是他的第一次欧洲之旅），游历了法国、英国和意大利等国，历时两年，深为辉煌的欧洲文化而激动，写下了大量的旅行笔记。1815年，他第二次到欧洲去，一住就是十七年，先是经商，后供职于美国驻英使馆。1842—1846年，他三度赴欧，出任驻西班牙公使。粗略计算，他在青壮年时期，在欧洲居住了长达二十一年之久。在此期间，他跑遍了英、法、德、意、西等国，还拜访过司各特、萨克雷等著名作家。与刚刚建立不久的美利坚合众国相比，欧洲有着灿烂的历史和悠久丰富的文化，具有震撼人心的力量。从某种角度来说，欧文虽是“美国文学之父”，却又是“欧洲文学之子”。在这一点上，欧文是一种象征，象征着美国文学对欧洲文学的继承、发展和创新。

欧文著述颇丰，有历史小说、人物传记等，而他最擅长的是札记、散文、随笔、故事之类随心所欲的自由文体。1809年，他出版了第一部作品《纽约外史》。这部小说以诙谐幽默的笔调抨击了荷兰殖民者的残忍和狡诈，对受到不公正待遇的土著人深表同情。这是一部具有独特风格的诙谐之作，充分显露出欧文的幽默才能。《纽约外史》出版后，欧文成为纽约文坛风靡一时的人物。1820年，他在英国出版了《见闻札记》，更使他成为在欧洲为美国文学赢得声誉的第一人。此书并非鸿篇巨制，只是一本包括34篇散文、故事、杂感的文集，其中包含着作者对欧洲文明的敬仰之情，也表现了美国人的幽默诙谐，因而受到欧美广大读者的欢迎，成为美国文学的开山之作。

《见闻札记》中，以短篇小说《瑞普·凡·温克》最为著名。该小说的创作受德国民间故事《睡皇帝》启发。故事的背景是荷兰殖民地时期的美国乡村。在一个僻静的小村庄里住着一个叫瑞普·凡·温克的农夫，过着游游荡荡的悠闲日子，唯一不顺心的是“家有悍妇”。为了躲避“悍妇”的辱骂，他独自到附近的山里去打猎，不期遇到了当年发现了哈德逊河的哈德逊船长及其伙伴，在喝了他们的仙酒后，就睡了一觉。醒后下山回家，才发现时间已过了整整二十年。旧日的景象不复存在，自己所熟悉的小村庄彻底改变了容颜，寂静被打破，到处是演说、传单和竞选。瑞普终于知道，他现在已由英王的臣民变为“合众国的一个自由的公民”。一切都是那么陌生。唯一叫他感到庆幸的是，那个折磨得他生不如死的彪悍妻子被一个小贩气死，“妇人专政”终于结束了。瑞普做了一场梦，而美国则产生了翻天覆地的变化。他摆脱了“妇人专政”，而美国摆脱的却是“英国专政”。一个重大的历史事件，一次剧烈的革命性转折，竟被欧文以轻轻松松的一场梦给交代了。以轻松幽默的笔调反映沉重的历史——这是欧文创作的一个显著特征，不得不令人佩服。

1877年，清朝官员张德彝出访英国时，观看了根据欧文的《瑞普·凡·温克》改编的戏剧。回国后，张德彝在出访记录中记述了对它的感受。三十年后，晚清著名翻译家林纾将欧文的《见闻札记》翻译成中文，取名《拊掌录》。林纾在序中说：“欧文气量宏广，而思致深邃而便敏，行文跳踊变化，匪夷所思。其雅趣高情……又博古，广哀遗典，叩以所有，无不立应。”

《睡谷的传说》也是《见闻札记》中一个影响力非常大的故事。睡谷是真实存在的地点，位于哈德逊河畔，这个故事以欧文拜访睡谷时听到的传说为基础创作。睡谷当中雾气腾腾、阴气逼人，据说巫师给这儿施了妖术，让居民们的大脑受到控制，连走路也晕晕乎乎如在梦中。当地居民最为津津乐道的都是些惊悚的鬼怪故事和传说。其中无头骑士的故事流传最广。传说在美国独立战争时期的一次战役中，一个黑森州骑兵的头被炮弹打飞了。死后，他的阴魂常在夜里骑马飞奔，到战场上去寻找自己的头颅。这篇故事将幻想和现实融于一处，营造出一种诡异而怪诞的气氛，对愚昧和残暴进行无情的鞭挞。

《睡谷的传说》自问世后，即受到广大读者的喜欢，其诡谲的气氛、离奇的情节，更是受到许多戏剧家、影视导演的青睐。1922年即被搬上银幕，此后又有多个影视版本相继面世，其中不乏影响力深远之作，如1999年由蒂姆·波顿指导、约翰尼·德普主演的电影。2013年由福克斯电视台制作的电视剧《沉睡谷》融合了《睡谷的传说》和《瑞普·凡·温克》两个故事的背景，并在睡谷实地拍摄。目前已经播放了三季，第四季正在制作当中。

除了这两个故事，本书还精选了欧文另外几篇同样精彩的短篇小说——《鬼新郎》《魔鬼和汤姆·沃克》《阿拉伯占星家的传说》以及《摩尔人遗产的传说》。

《鬼新郎》以跌宕起伏的故事情节吸引住读者的注意力，歌颂友谊与爱情，对美国文学的影响十分深刻。《魔鬼和汤姆·沃克》情节有点类似歌德的《浮士德》，讲的是一个人为了达到自己卑鄙的目的，不惜把灵魂出卖给魔鬼。《阿拉伯占星家的传说》里，欧文利用一个流传很广的传说，揭露了侵略成性的统治者阿本·哈布兹残忍而荒淫的面目，以及道貌岸然、以哲人自居的占星家的卑鄙丑恶的灵魂。在《摩尔人遗产的传说》里，欧文塑造了朴实勤劳、见义勇为的卖水贩子佩雷吉尔，还以辛辣的笔锋刻画出了贪婪暴戾的市长及警察的丑恶嘴脸，将这些人放在一处进行比较，以期达到扬善抑恶的目的。

1859年11月28日，欧文心脏病发逝世。当年12月的麻省历史学会会议之上，他的朋友，诗人朗费罗这样赞扬欧文对于美国文学的巨大推动和促进作用：“我们对于他身为一个作家的荣誉感到自豪，不过最不能忽略的，他最值得我们感激的，是他在文学的历史上为我们国家赢得的名声和地位。”

方华文

作于苏州大学

2016.6.24

瑞普·凡·温克

下面的故事是在已故的迪德里克·尼克博克(1)的遗稿里发现的。尼克博克生前是纽约的一位老绅士，对该省的荷兰殖民史颇感兴趣，醉心于研究该省原始定居者后裔的风土人情。不过，他的历史研究并不是仅仅查阅资料，更是深入民间、了解民情。因为，凡是他感兴趣的题目，资料都少得可怜，但他发现民间的那些老人，尤其是老太太，知道许许多多民间传说——这些传说对发掘真实的历史弥足珍贵。每当他看到一户地地道道的荷兰人家安居于屋顶低矮的农舍，在浓荫如盖的梧桐树的遮掩下过着与世隔绝的日子，便如获至宝，将其视为印满古旧文字的珍稀卷册，投注以狂热的激情加以研究。

在这些研究的基础上，他编写了该省的历史书，反映荷兰总督执政时的那段如烟的往事，几年之后得以出版。对于书中的文学特色，人们看法不一，众说纷纭，实不相瞒，至今非议之声仍不减当年。此书的最大优点在于它的严谨和精确，虽问世之初也曾被质疑过，但后成定论，现已成为公认的权威史书，观点被纳入所有的史料。

这本书出版后不久，老绅士便辞世了。他已驾鹤西去，此刻说句遗憾的话也不至于有损他的形象——也许，他应该从事分量更重的研究。不过，话又说回来，人各有志，各有各的兴趣所在。此书固然时不时会令邻人的目光黯淡，叫一些朋友伤感（对于这些人，他怀有真诚的敬意和深沉的爱），但人们忆及他的错误和愚蠢，感到“悲哀多于愤怒”。人们不由会想到，他的初衷绝不会是想给别人带来伤害，也不会是想得罪任何人。不管评论家对他有什么样的看法，老百姓一般都对他颇有好感，而民意是值得尊重的；特别是一些面包师，他们甚至会把他的肖像印在新年蛋糕上，使他得以不朽于人间，其效果几乎等同于将他的肖像印在了滑铁卢奖牌或安妮女王的硬币上。

瑞普·凡·温克

迪德里希·尼克博克的遗作

啊，沃登，撒克逊人的天神，
有了你才有了沃登节这一星期三，
真理我将永铭心间，
直至我入土为安那一天……

——卡特赖特(2)

乘船在哈德逊河逆流而上，你肯定能记得卡茨基尔山，那是庞大的阿巴拉契亚山脉的一支断脉，位于大河的西岸，巍峨绵延，直插霄汉，鹤立鸡群般屹立于周围的景物之间。季节更迭，天气变幻，甚至每一小时的流逝，都会令山的色彩、山的形态发生变化。当地的主妇们，不论远近，都会将那山当作精确的晴雨表观看。天气晴好时，群山的颜色或蓝或紫，傍晚时分，雄浑的山影则映衬在清澈的天幕上。有时，他处万里无云，而高山之巅却轻雾缭绕。在落日的余晖中，像一顶璀璨的皇冠闪射出异彩。

乘船人放眼望去，可以看见美丽的群山脚下有一座村庄，村子里炊烟袅袅，农家的木屋顶掩映在一片树木中，而就在那儿，山的蓝色与山跟前的新绿交融在了一起。这是一个小村子，历史非常悠久，是在该省草创期由一些荷兰殖民者所建，大约正值好心的彼得·斯泰弗森特(3)（愿他的灵魂安息）开始执政之时。几年前这儿还矗立着几所最初的定居者居住的房屋，是用从荷兰运来的小块黄砖建造的，有格子窗和三角墙的面脸，屋顶上装着风向标。

就在这个村子里，就在这儿其中的一所房子里（说老实话，此房由于年代久远和风雨剥蚀，已经破烂不堪），曾经住着一个生性淳朴、性格温和的人，名叫瑞普·凡·温克。那是多年以前的旧事了，当时该地还属于大不列颠帝国治下的一个省。他是凡·温克一族的后代，其祖先在彼得·斯泰弗森特执政的骑士时代以骁勇善战著称，曾追随彼得围攻过克里斯蒂娜要塞。不过，他祖先的那种刚勇好斗的性格却几乎连一点都没有遗传给他。如我刚才所言，他是一个生性淳朴、性格温和的人；不仅如此，他还是个心地善良的邻居和对老婆百依百顺的“妻管严”丈夫。说实话，后一种情况的出现是由于他柔顺的性格，他也因此赢得了大家普遍的爱戴——男人在外边温和友好，平心静气地待人，都是家里有个母老虎把他调教出来的。这些男人的脾性，毫无疑问，都是在家里苦难的熔炉里千锤百炼，才变得百伶百俐、游刃有余了。看起来，要教人养成忍耐和坚忍的美德，床帷内的训导抵得过天下所有的循循善诱。因此，从某些方面来说，娶一个母老虎当妻子，也可以说是一种挺不错的福气。若依此理，瑞普·凡·温克便是洪福齐天了。

情况的确如此。村子里所有的贤妻良母都很喜欢他（女性一般都喜欢柔顺的男人），当他家出现争执时，则一边倒地站在他的一方，晚上唠嗑时谈及两口子的争执，毫无例外地都会把罪责归到凡·温克太太身上。村童们也喜欢他，见他走近，会高兴得喊叫起来。他跟孩子们一道玩耍，给他们做玩具，教他们放风筝和射弹球，还给他们讲很长很长的关于鬼怪、巫婆和印第安人的故事。他一出现在村头村尾，身边就会有一大群孩子簇拥，有的扯住他的衣摆，有的爬到他背上，无所顾忌地用各种办法拿他寻开心；就连附近的狗亦喜欢他，见了他叫都不叫一声。瑞普的性格中最大的缺陷，是对一切有益的劳动均具有不可克服的厌恶。这不可能是源于他缺乏持之以恒或坚持不懈的毅力。因为他可以坐在一块湿漉漉的石头上，拿着一根像鞑靼人的长矛似的又长又重的钓竿，钓上一整天鱼，哪怕没有一条鱼来咬饵，他也不会丧气，不会说一声牢骚话。他会肩扛一杆鸟枪，耗费好几个小时穿树林过沼泽，上山坡下峡谷，只为了打几只松鼠或野鸽子。谁家需要帮忙，他一定会出手相助，再累的活都不会在乎；乡间举办剥玉米或者筑石墙的活动，他历来都是头一个到场。村妇们经常支使他，叫他干些她们自己那不太听话的丈夫不愿意干的零碎活儿。总而言之，除了干自己家的活，任何人叫他帮忙他都乐意。至于料理自家的事务，耕种自家的农田，他则觉得比登天还难。实际情况是：他公开宣称说耕种自家的田纯粹是白费气力。他家的几亩薄田是整个地区最倒霉的农田，不管种什么，不管怎么种，都会出乱子。他家的篱笆墙经常倒塌；他家的牛不是走失便是跑到菜地里偷菜吃；他家农田里的野草总是比别家的长得快；每当他走出房门去田里干活，老天爷总会挑这个时候下雨。眼见得祖上留下的田产在他手里一英亩一英亩地少下去，最后只剩下了一块地种点玉米和马铃薯，而这块地仍然是附近一带顶顶差劲的。

他的几个孩子衣衫褴褛，像是没人管的野孩子。他的儿子小瑞普是个淘气包，长得像他，穿他的旧衣服，恐怕将来的生活习惯也会跟他一样。平时常见这小家伙屁颠屁颠跟在母亲的身后，像小马驹跟随着老马，穿着父亲丢掉的一条灯笼裤，用一只手费劲地往上提着，仿佛一位贵妇人在下雨天提着长长的裙裾。

好在瑞普·凡·温克属于那种乐天派，生就糊里糊涂、浑浑噩噩的性情，随遇而安地过日子，粗粮细粮无所谓，只要不费心思、不费气力，有吃的就行。他宁可只有一个便士而挨饿，也不愿为一个金镑去工作。假如叫他自己选择，他情愿吹着口哨轻松度日，心满意足地度过一生。可是他老婆却不停地在他耳边唠叨，怪他游手好闲，对家里的事不上心，把一个家都给毁了。不分早晨、中午还是夜间，她的责难之声不绝于耳，如果他胆敢还嘴或者有冒犯的举动，定会招来连珠炮似的训导和铺天盖地的抱怨。对于这类家训，瑞普只有一种办法，由于经常使用，逐渐成了习惯，那就是：耸耸肩、摇摇头、两眼看天，一声也不吭。可是，这种办法每一次都会招来老婆新一轮的发作，令他不得不撒丫子跑路，跑到门外去避难——说老实话，对于一个“妻管严”丈夫而言，这是唯一的退路了。

瑞普在家里的唯一追随者就是他那条名叫“狼”的狗，此狗和他一样惧怕女主人。凡·温克太太把他俩视为一对游手好闲的伙伴，甚至看“狼”的时候眼里会露出恶狠狠的神情，认为它是诱使它的主人整天出门游荡的罪魁祸首。其实，“狼”也具有一条可敬的狗所应有的全部精神，它跟任何出没于林中的动物一样勇敢——不过，哪一种勇气能抵挡得住一个女人那喋喋不休、恶言恶语的可怕舌头呢？一旦进入家里的房门，它就会垂下脑袋，尾巴拖地或者夹在两腿之间，胆战心惊的，一副马上就要上绞刑架的样子，不时拿眼偷窥凡·温克太太。后者只要举起笤帚把或者水瓢，它便箭一般夺门而逃，嘴里发出一阵哀鸣声。

结婚后，时光在一年年流逝，瑞普·凡·温克的日子越发艰难了。尖刻的脾性绝不会随年龄的增长而趋于温和，刻薄的舌头犹如利刃，越用越锋利。长时间以来，当他被迫走出家门时，他会去村子里的一个由智者、哲人及其他闲人组成的永久性俱乐部，在那儿寻求安慰。俱乐部的成员们坐在一家小客栈门前的长凳上聚会——小客栈用乔治三世陛下的肖像画当招牌（画中人红光满面）。夏天，他们躲在树荫下，懒洋洋地消磨一个个的长日，东一搭西一搭地议论议论村里的小道消息，要不就没完没了地讲故事——那些故事无聊乏味，令人昏昏欲睡。不过，有时旅人路过此地，偶尔会丢下一份旧报纸，可能会引发深刻的讨论，其见地恐怕也值得政治家花钱听一听的。小学校长德里克·凡·布麦尔衣冠楚楚，是个满腹经纶的小个子，即便是字典里最长的词也难不倒他。他为大家读报，语气郑重，而听者表情严肃，之后针对几个月前发生过的公众事件发表各自的真知灼见。

这个团体的议论导向完全由尼古拉斯·维德尔一手操纵。此人既是村子的一位元老，又是客栈的老板。他从早到晚一直坐在客栈门口，只在要躲避太阳光的时候才把座位稍微移动一下，以保证自己始终处于大树的阴凉之中。邻居们根据他的移动便可知时辰，准确得就跟观察日晷一样。其实，他很少讲话，只是一个劲地抽他的烟斗。不过，他的追随者们（伟人身后必有追随者）对他的一举一动都心领神会，可以揣摩出他的看法。当报上的事件或人们的议论叫他不高兴时，他会用劲地吸烟斗，一口接着一口气急败坏地把烟喷出来；而高兴时，他则慢悠悠、平心静气地将烟雾吸进嘴里，然后再轻轻地、平稳地吐出来，有时则是把烟斗从嘴边拿开，让香喷喷的烟气在鼻子边缭绕，一面庄严地点一点头，表示完全认可。

即使躲在这个堡垒里，倒霉的瑞普最后还是会被他凶悍的老婆赶出来。她会突然闯进来，搅乱这儿静谧的气氛，把与会者骂得狗血喷头；甚至连尼古拉斯·维德尔这等威严的人物也逃不脱这个可怕泼妇的污言秽语，她直截了当地指控他助长她丈夫游手好闲的恶习。

可怜的瑞普终于被逼到了几乎绝望的地步；要逃避田里的劳作和老婆的吵闹，也就只剩下拿起猎枪溜到树林里去这唯一的选择了。进了树林，他有时会在一棵树下坐下来，和“狼”一道分享袋子里的干粮。他同情“狼”，觉得它也是天涯沦落人，和他遭受着同样的迫害。“可怜的‘狼’啊，”他会说，“你的女主人叫你遭受折磨；不过别担心，我的孩子，只要我活着，就会有朋友帮你渡过难关！”“狼”听了直摇尾巴，深情地望着主人的脸。如果狗能够感受到这份同情心，那它一定会知恩图报的。

在一个秋高气爽的日子，瑞普又一次来林中漫游，不知不觉地爬上了卡茨基尔群山一处最高的峰顶。他来山里，是要用枪打松鼠的——这是他最喜欢的一项活动。砰砰砰，一声又一声的枪响回荡在山间。将近黄昏时分，他气喘吁吁，精疲力竭，便在悬崖上的一个长满野草的绿色小土墩上躺了下来。从树丛的空隙处，可以俯瞰低处连绵数英里的原野，那儿森林茂密，郁郁葱葱的。极目远眺，看得见在山下遥远的地方壮观的哈德逊河在流淌，静寂无声、气势磅礴地踏上了它的旅程，明镜似的河面上有的地方倒映着一片紫色的云彩，有的地方又点缀着一叶缓缓移动的孤帆，最后，河流隐没于蓝色的群山之间。

向另一侧望去，看得见下面一条幽深的山谷，荒凉、沉寂、杂草丛生，谷底堆满了从悬崖绝壁上坠落下来的乱石，落日的余晖几乎照不到那儿去。瑞普见景生情，沉思良久。暮色渐浓，群山投下长长的蓝色身影，遮在沟壑上。他明白，不等他回到村子里，天就会黑透的。一想到回家去面对叫人不寒而栗的凡·温克太太，他不禁沉重地叹了一口气。

他正欲下山，忽听远处有人在喊：“瑞普·凡·温克！瑞普·凡·温克！”他举目四看，周围并无一人，只看得见一只乌鸦孤零零地飞过山峰。他觉得一定是幻觉在欺骗自己，复又转身欲离去，谁料在苍茫、寂静的暮色里又听见了那叫喊声：“瑞普·凡·温克！瑞普·凡·温克！”“狼”听了，身上的毛都竖了起来，发出一声低沉的吠叫，躲闪到主人身边，惊恐地朝下面的山谷里张望。瑞普感到有点害怕，一阵战栗传遍了全身。他心怀恐惧，顺着狗的目光望去，见一个陌生人正吃力地一步一步慢慢爬上山来，背负重物，腰身都被压弯了。在这人迹罕至的荒山野岭竟然能看到人，叫他颇感诧异。他觉得来人八成是附近的人，需要他的帮助，于是急忙迎了过去。

走近时，见陌生人相貌古怪，他越发感到诧异了。对方是个老者，五短身材，胖墩墩的，头发浓密蓬松，胡须花白。此人身着古代荷兰装——上穿紧身背心，腰间扎一条皮带，下穿几条马裤，最外面的一条宽宽松松，两侧从上到下装饰着两排纽扣，膝盖处鼓起了两个大包。他肩上扛着一只大木桶，里面好像装满了酒。他招手让瑞普过去帮他一把。瑞普虽说有点犹豫，对这位新相识心存疑虑，但还是像往常一样，欣然出手相助。二人轮换着扛桶，沿着一条狭窄的溪谷往山上爬去——那溪谷显然是一条山涧干涸后留下的河道。路上，瑞普不时听到一阵阵滚动的隆隆声，像是远处在打雷。那声音似乎来自一条深谷，或者说是来自两座石山间的一个裂口，而他们脚下这条崎岖的小路正是通向那里的。他停下来听了听，猜想那是山区下雷阵雨夹带的雷声，于是就又朝前走了。

他们穿过深谷，来到一块凹地跟前——那凹地的形状像一个圆形小剧场，周围是悬崖峭壁，峭壁边缘上长着一些大树，伸展着枝丫，抬头看，只能从枝叶的缝隙间瞧见一线蓝天以及傍晚时分那亮亮的云彩。瑞普和他的同伴始终一声不吭地扛着桶前行。瑞普心里像个闷葫芦，不明白老者为何要扛着一桶酒到这荒山野岭里来，但对方怪模怪样，身上有一种叫人捉摸不透的东西，令他望而生畏，不敢与之交谈。走进剧场，眼前又出现了一幕奇怪的景象。但见剧场中央的一块平地上有几个模样古怪的人在玩九柱戏(4)。这些人的装束稀奇古怪，有的穿紧身短上衣，有的穿紧身背心，一个个腰带上挂着长刀，大多穿的裤子都肥肥大大，跟扛酒桶的老者所穿的是一个式样。论外表也都怪怪的——其中的一个大头宽脸，眼睛小得和猪眼一般；还有一个鼻子特别大，好像把脸都占满了，头戴一顶圆锥形白帽，白帽上插一根细细的红公鸡尾羽。这些人都留着大胡子，胡子颜色不同，形状各异。有个人似乎是他们的首领。此人是个年老的绅士，身体结实，有一张饱经沧桑的脸，身穿镶着花边的紧身短上衣，腰扎宽皮带，佩一柄短剑，头戴高帽，帽插羽翎，脚上穿着红袜子和系着玫瑰结的高跟鞋。这些人使瑞普想起了村里牧师多米尼·凡·夏克家客厅里挂的一幅佛兰德斯(5)油画，那幅画是荷兰人定居此地时从荷兰带来的。

尤其让瑞普感到奇怪的是：这些人明明是在娱乐，表情却极为凝重，神秘兮兮地一声不吭，这可是他所见过的最为沉闷的游戏了。四周静悄悄的，除了球滚动的声音之外，再无其他声音了。那些球滚动起来，山间便会响起隆隆的回声，似一阵阵的响雷。

瑞普和同路人走近时，他们突然停下球戏，凝神望着他，似一尊尊雕像，表情古怪、粗鲁而呆滞，叫他心里发毛、双腿发软。同路人将桶里的酒倒进几个大酒壶里，招手叫他过去给打球者上酒。瑞普吓得浑身发抖，依命而行。打球人一声不响，把酒一饮而尽，又继续玩他们的游戏了。

瑞普的畏惧不安渐渐消退了。趁着无人注意，他壮起胆来把那酒尝了一口，觉得味道很像上等的荷兰杜松子酒。他生性嗜酒，没一会儿又忍不住尝了一口。一口接着一口地喝，他频频举起酒壶，最后喝得神志模糊、头昏眼花，脑袋逐渐耷拉下来，昏沉沉酣然大睡。

一觉醒来，他发现自己仍躺在那个长满野草的绿色小土墩上（他起初就是从此处看到山谷里的那位老者的）。他揉揉眼睛——面前是一个阳光明媚的早晨，树丛中鸟儿在歌唱、跳跃，一只老鹰驾着山间清新的微风盘旋在高空。瑞普心里嘀咕道：“我肯定不是一整夜都待在这儿睡大觉的。”随后，他想起了入睡前的一幕幕情景——那个扛着一桶酒的陌生人……那山谷……荒山野岭里的那个隐秘去处……那几个玩九柱戏的哭丧着脸的人……那个酒壶……“对啦！就是那壶酒作的怪！那壶可恶的酒误了大事！”瑞普心里翻江倒海。“我怎么向凡·温克太太交代才好呢？”他环顾四周找他的枪，却发现原来那杆油光铮亮的鸟枪不见了，身边只有一杆破破烂烂的旧枪，枪筒上锈迹斑斑，枪栓脱落，枪托上满是虫蛀的小孔。他怀疑是山间那几个阴沉着脸玩游戏的家伙捉弄了他，用酒把他灌醉，偷走了他的枪。“狼”也不见了，可能是跑去追松鼠或者山鹑了。他吹口哨唤它，高声叫它的名字，但无济于事。他的口哨声和叫喊声四处回荡，然而狗却踪影全无。

他决计回到昨天傍晚的游戏现场去，遇到那帮子人，就让他们归还他的狗和枪。站起身走路时，却发现关节僵硬，没有平时那么灵活了。“这一定是在这大山的地上睡觉睡的，”他心想，“要是这么胡折腾，万一得了风湿病起不了床，凡·温克太太可就会给我好脸色看了。”他颇为费力地走下山谷，找到昨天傍晚他和那位老者曾经走过的那条干涸的溪沟。而眼前的景象却叫他吃了一惊——但见一条山涧正水沫飞溅地在溪谷里流淌，削岩击石，哗哗的流水声响彻了山谷。他急忙另外择道爬上山腰，艰难地穿过由桦树、檫树和金缕梅构成的杂树丛。野葡萄的藤蔓在树丛里左缠右绕，织成网阻住去路，时而将他绊倒，时而缠住他的脚。

最后，他顺着溪谷走到了悬崖跟前，那儿原先有裂口可以通向那个圆形剧场，而现在裂口不见了，一点痕迹都没有留下。石崖形成了一道高不可攀的墙壁，一股激流飞下石崖，泛着泡沫，似一张倒挂的水帘，滔滔的流水跌入一个宽宽的深水潭，周围的树木投下的阴影将那儿遮掩得光线暗淡。走到这里，可怜的瑞普只好收住了脚步。他再一次吹口哨，大声叫喊，呼唤他的狗。然而，作答的只有呱呱呱几声乌鸦的鸣叫——但见阳光普照的悬崖顶上有一株枯树，枯树上有一群乌鸦在飞来飞去地悠闲嬉戏。乌鸦们高高在上、无忧无虑，似乎在居高临下地望着这个身处困境的可怜人，对他嗤之以鼻。这下子该如何是好？早晨的时光在悄然流逝，瑞普饥肠辘辘，迫切地想吃早餐。他心情沉重，对他的狗和枪已不再抱有指望。他害怕见到妻子，但是饿死在山里总归不是办法。末了，他摇摇头，扛着那杆锈迹斑斑的旧枪，怀着满腹的心事和忧虑，踏上了返家的路程。

走近村子，沿路遇见了一些人，他却一个都不认识，这就叫他感到奇怪了，因为周围一带他自以为没有他不认识的人。那些人所穿的衣服，在样式上跟他熟悉的大不一样。他们痴呆呆望着他，脸上也同样露出惊讶的表情，而且每当把目光落在他身上，总要摸摸自己的下巴。见他们一再做出这个动作，瑞普不知不觉也跟着做了一下，这一摸可把他吓了一跳——他发现自己的胡子长得足足有一英尺长了！

到了村头，一群不认识的小孩跟在他屁股后边跑，冲他大喊大叫，对着他的花白胡子指指点点。村里的狗也没有一条是他认识的，他走过时冲着他狂吠乱叫。就连村子也变了样，变得比以前更大了，人也更多了。那一排排的房屋他见都没有见过，而他常去的那些熟悉的人家不见了踪影。如今，那些房屋的门首写的净是陌生的名字，窗口露出的净是陌生的面孔——所有的一切都是那么陌生。他心里感到很不安，开始怀疑他自己以及周围这个世界都中了魔法。此处明明是他土生土长的村子，才离开了一天就变了样。卡茨基尔群山仍巍然耸立在那儿……银色的哈德逊河仍在远处流淌……丘陵、沟壑仍和从前一模一样……瑞普一头雾水，心里感到迷茫……“昨天晚上的那壶酒有问题，”他心想，“喝了那酒，我的脑子才变糊涂的！”

他费了一番气力才找到了回自家的路，走近家门时蹑手蹑脚的，心里怕得要命，生怕会听见凡·温克太太那刺耳的尖叫声。他发现自己家的房屋已破败不堪——屋顶塌陷，窗户破碎，房门和铰链两分离。一条饿得半死的狗，样子很像“狼”，在房屋周围转来转去。他唤它的名字，而那畜生竟然冲他咆哮，龇着牙齿，后来理也没理他便跑开了。简直是一个忘恩负义的家伙！“这可是我自己的狗呀，就连它都把我给忘了！”可怜的瑞普叹了口气说。

他举步走进了屋子。说实话，凡·温克太太总是把这里收拾得井井有条的，而现在此处空空荡荡、冷冷清清，没有了人气。凄凉的场景压倒了他对老婆的畏惧，于是他大声喊老婆和孩子的名字。他的声音在冷清的房间里回荡，片刻之后周围又恢复了沉寂。他慌了神，抽身走开，匆匆忙忙赶往他常去的休闲地——村子里的那家客栈。客栈不见了，取而代之的是一幢快要散架的木头大房子，几扇硕大的窗户敞开着，有的玻璃碎了，用旧帽子和旧裙子堵住缺口。大房子的门首有几个大字：“乔纳森·杜利特尔联合旅馆”。昔日的那个宁静的荷兰小客栈门前有棵大树遮阴，而今大树也不见了踪影，被一根光秃秃的高柱子取代，柱顶上有个好像是红色睡帽的东西，那儿挂着一面随风飘扬的旗子，旗子上有些星星和条纹奇怪地组合在一起——所有的一切都是那么离奇古怪、匪夷所思。不过，他从招牌上总算还认出了国王乔治的那张红润的脸——他曾经多次在招牌下方安安静静地吸烟斗。然而，就连这幅画像也发生了奇异的变化——红色上衣换成了一件蓝黄色相间的上衣，手里的权杖换成了一把宝剑，头戴一顶三角帽，画像下面用大号字体写着：“华盛顿将军”。

门口跟往常一样聚集着一群人，不过没有一个是瑞普能记得起来的熟人。这些人就连性情好像都变了，不像从前那样悠闲、安静、不冷不热的，而是急躁、吵吵闹闹的，喜欢打口水仗。他想找那位宽脸膛、双下巴、不喜欢闲谈，而总是衔着根漂亮的长烟斗吞云吐雾的智者尼古拉斯·维德尔，还想找那位慢吞吞给大家读旧报纸的乡村教师凡·布麦尔，却都没有找到。他倒是看到了一个瘦瘦的、看上去脾气很坏的家伙，口袋里塞满了传单，正在高谈阔论什么公民权啦，选举啦，国会议员啦，自由啦，邦克山战役(6)啦，1776年的英雄(7)啦，还有其他的一些论调，全都是生僻难懂的词，让凡 ·温克越听越糊涂。

瑞普的出现，还有他那花白的长胡子、锈迹斑斑的鸟枪、怪异的衣着，后面还跟着一大群女人和孩子，立刻引起了旅馆前那些政客的注意。他们将他围在中间，充满好奇地上下打量着他。那位演说家挤上前来，把他拉到一边，问他投哪一方的选票。瑞普不知所云，茫然地望着对方。另有一个爱管闲事的小个子拽住他的胳膊，踮起脚尖，凑到他耳边问：“你是联邦党(8)还是民主党？”瑞普对这个问题同样大惑不解。这时候，一个头戴尖顶三角帽、自作聪明又自命不凡的老绅士，用胳膊肘把大家向左右推开，从人群中挤了过来，在凡·温克面前站定，一只手叉腰，另一只手拄着手杖，目光之锐利和帽顶之尖，似乎能刺穿瑞普的灵魂。他厉声喝问道：“正值选举之际，他扛着枪，身后跟着一群人，意在何为？是不是想在村子里制造骚乱？”

“天哪！先生们，”瑞普有点慌了神，大声叫屈，“我可是个本分的可怜人，是这儿土生土长的人，是国王的忠实臣民。愿上帝保佑国王！”

一听这话，看热闹的人群爆发出一片叫喊声：“亲英分子！亲英分子！奸细！逃亡者！把他轰出去！叫他滚蛋！”

那个头戴三角帽、自命不凡的人费了好大的力气才恢复了秩序，然后皱起眉头做出比原来严厉十倍的样子，再次盘问这个来路不明的犯罪嫌疑人，喝问他到此有何目的，想找什么人。可怜的瑞普低声下气地保证自己没有恶意，只不过是到这儿来找几个常来客栈聊天的邻居。

“是吗？他们是谁？你说说他们的名字？”

瑞普稍微想了想，然后问道：“尼古拉斯·维德尔在哪儿？”

现场一片沉寂。过了一会儿才有一位老者用尖细的声音回答道：“尼古拉斯·维德尔吗？嗨，他早死了，死了有十八年了！教堂的墓地里原来有块木头墓碑，刻着他的生卒年月什么的，后来烂掉了，不见了。”

“布鲁姆·达契尔在哪儿呢？”

“哦，战争一开始他就参军去了。有人说他在斯东尼角的战役中阵亡了……还有人说他在安东尼悬崖的脚下遇到风暴淹死了。具体情况我不清楚……反正他一去再没有回来。”

“教师凡·布麦尔在哪儿呢？”

“他也打仗去了，成了民军的大将军，眼下在国会里当议员呢。”

听见家乡和朋友们发生了如此可悲的变化，发现自己成了孤零零一个人被遗弃在这个世界上，瑞普的一颗心都碎了。这些人的回答涉及的时间跨度极大，包含的内容令他无法理解，每一句都叫他摸不着头脑。什么战争啦，国会啦，斯东尼角啦，叫他不知所云。他没有勇气再问其他朋友的下落，于绝望之中高喊了一声：“难道这儿就没有一个人认识瑞普·凡·温克吗？”

“嗨，你说瑞普·凡·温克吗？”有两三个人叫了起来，“当然认识喽！那边那个靠着树的就是瑞普·凡·温克！”

瑞普朝那边望去，看见了一个和自己上山那时候长得一模一样的人——样子也是那么懒懒散散，穿得也是那么破破烂烂。这下子，他彻底糊涂了。他甚至对自己产生了怀疑，弄不清自己是什么人了。正当他心里一片迷乱的时候，那个戴三角帽的家伙再次发难，喝问他是什么人，叫什么名字。

“苍天在上！”他不知所措地喊了一声，“我已经不是我自己了……我成了另外一个人了……那边那个人才是我……不……那是另一个人，变成了我的模样。昨天晚上我还是我自己来着，在山上睡了一觉，他们偷换了我的枪，所有的一切都变了样，连我也变成了另外一个人，说不出自己的名字，说不出自己是什么人！”

旁观的人群你看看我，我看看你，有的点头，有的意味深长地眨巴眼睛，有的则用手指轻敲自己的脑门。也有人压低声音建议夺下这个老家伙的枪，免得他开枪伤人。一听这话，那个头戴三角帽、自命不凡的人急忙开溜，生怕伤了自己。

就在这紧急关头，一个年轻漂亮的女子分开人群挤了过来，想仔细瞧瞧这个白胡子老头。她怀里抱着一个胖乎乎的孩子，那孩子一见瑞普的模样就吓着了，哇哇大哭起来。“别哭，瑞普，”女子叫道，“别哭，你这小傻瓜；这个老头不会伤害你的。”

孩子的名字、母亲的神态以及她说话的腔调，这一切在瑞普的心里唤醒了一连串的回忆。

“你叫什么名字，我的好太太？”他问道。

“朱迪丝·加迪尼耶。”

“你父亲叫什么名字？”

“唉，我可怜的父亲叫瑞普·凡·温克。二十年前他扛着枪离开家门，从那以后再也没有了音讯……他的狗自己跑了回来。谁也说不清他到底是开枪自杀了，还是被印第安人抓走了。事发时，我还是个小孩呢。”

现在只剩下一件事需要问了，而瑞普在问的时候连声音都发抖了：“你母亲在哪儿呢？”

“哦，她不久前也死了，是跟一个新英格兰小贩发脾气，血管破裂死的。”

这个消息最起码叫老实巴交的瑞普稍放宽了一些心。他再也无法控制自己，一把将女儿和那孩子拥在了怀里。“我是你爸爸！”他叫道，“离开你时，我是年轻的瑞普·凡·温克，现在成了老瑞普·凡·温克了！难道就没有一个人认识可怜的瑞普·凡·温克吗？”

大家站在那里惊呆了，后来有一个老太婆从人群中颤颤巍巍地走出来，用手遮在额头上，凝神打量一阵他的脸，随即叫喊起来：“没错！真是瑞普·凡·温克……真是他！欢迎你回家，老邻居。这二十年来，你跑到哪儿去了？”

瑞普三言两语就把自己的经历讲完了，因为二十年的时间对他来说只是短短的一个夜晚。邻人们听得目瞪口呆，有的则挤眉弄眼，有的吐舌头扮鬼脸。刚才的那场虚惊过后，那个头戴三角帽、自命不凡的人又回到了现场，此时噘噘嘴、摇摇头，而人群中其他的人也跟着摇起头来。

此时，只见彼得·凡德敦克老人从大路上慢慢腾腾走了过来，大家决定听听他的看法。他是一位跟他同名同姓的历史学家的后裔。那位历史学家编写过这个省最早的历史书。彼得是村子里最老的住户，对本地区的奇闻异事以及风土人情了如指掌。他立刻回想起了瑞普，以极其坚定的态度确认瑞普的讲述真实可信。他向大家保证确有其事，声称他的那个历史学家的祖先曾经留下过记载，说卡茨基尔山经常有奇怪的人出没。他还肯定地说：最初是伟大的亨德利克·哈德逊发现了这条大河以及这片地区，以后每隔二十年便率领着他那条“半月号”轮船上的水手来此地巡游一圈，以这种方式重访他建立功业的地方，观察观察以他的名字命名的河流和伟大城市。他说自己的父亲就曾亲眼看见他们身穿古代的荷兰服装在一个山坳里玩九柱戏，而他本人在一个夏日的下午也听到过他们打球的声音，那隆隆的声音像远方一阵阵的响雷。

长话短说。末了，人群散去，又回去忙更重要的选举事务了。瑞普的女儿携父归家，和她住在一起。她有一幢环境舒适、设施齐全的房屋，还有一个体格健壮、生性乐观的农夫丈夫。瑞普回想了一下，认出这个女婿就是当初经常爬到他背上玩的顽童当中的一个。至于瑞普的儿子（即他的继承人），也就是那个跟他长得一模一样、依树而站的人，靠给别人在田里当雇工过活；儿子显然继承了他的秉性，热衷于帮别人干活，对自家的事务却不闻不问。

如今，瑞普又恢复了过去的习惯，经常四处游逛。没多久，他就找到了许多以前的老友，但老友们由于时光的磨蚀，状态大不如从前。他倒喜欢跟年轻的一代交朋友，不久便在年轻的一代中深得人心了。

他在家无所事事，反正已到了享清福的年龄，就是什么也不干，也不会受到责难的。于是，他又重新坐到了旅馆门口的长凳子上，被村里人尊为元老、“战前”旧时代的一部活字典。过了一段时间，他才跟上了趟，听得懂大家唠嗑时说的话了，或者说明白了自打他昏睡过去之后国内发生的那些离奇古怪的事件——这期间发生了一场革命战争……这个国家已经摆脱了英国的奴役……他已经不是乔治三世陛下的臣民，而是美利坚合众国的一个自由公民了。其实，他并不关心政治，帝国变成合众国对他来说没有多大的影响；让他长期受尽压迫的只有一种专制——老婆的专横跋扈。幸好这种现象已不复存在。他苦尽甘来，终于摆脱了婚姻的枷锁，如今不管什么时候愿意回家就回家，愿意出门就出门，不用再害怕凡·温克太太的暴政了。不过，一提起老婆的名字，他依然会耸耸肩、摇摇头、两眼看天。这种神态可以被解读为对命运的屈服，也可以被视为获得解放后的喜悦。

遇见外乡人来杜利特尔联合旅馆住宿，他就把自己的经历讲给人家听。起初，人们注意到他每次讲的内容在一些细节上都不相同，无疑是因为刚刚醒来的缘故。后来，他的讲述才最终统一成一个版本，跟我此处记载的完全一样了。邻里间的男女老少对他的故事均能倒背如流。

有些人假装怀疑故事的真实性，硬说那是瑞普臆想出来的，而瑞普对此不置可否。不过，老一代荷兰裔居民对他的讲述几乎全都深信不疑。甚至时至今日，夏季的某个下午听见卡茨基尔山那儿传来雷声，他们总会说那是亨德利克·哈德逊和他的水手们在玩九柱戏。附近一带，“妻管严”丈夫们一旦觉得生活过于沉重，便寄希望于瑞普·凡·温克的酒壶，盼望从他的酒壶里喝上一口“排忧解愁酒”。

注释

有人可能会怀疑尼克博克先生以上的故事一定是受到了德国的一段迷信故事的影响——该迷信故事讲的是腓特烈·德·罗特巴特皇帝和吉普豪瑟山之间的传说。可是，故事后附加的注释会表明此讲述非杜撰，而是事实，以他一贯的忠实风格秉笔直书……

“也许很多人会觉得瑞普·凡·温克的故事是天方夜谭，然而我却笃信无疑，因为我了解古老的荷兰定居点那一带的情况，知道那儿很可能会发生离奇古怪的非凡事件。实际上，在哈德逊河沿岸的村庄里，我听到的许多故事比这还离奇，全都有鼻子有眼，不容你怀疑。我甚至还和瑞普·凡·温克本人交谈过，发现他是一个非常令人尊敬的老人，说话极有条理，表达观点前后连贯，凡是有头脑的人恐怕绝不会怀疑他的话有疑点。不仅如此，我还在一家地区法院里看到过关于此事的证词，上面有法官的亲笔交叉签名。

——迪德里克·尼克博克”

附笔

以下旅行笔记摘自于尼克博克先生的备忘录：

卡茨博格山（或称卡茨基尔山）历来都是传奇故事的摇篮。印第安人将其视为精灵的家园——那些精灵呼风唤雨，洒阳光、驱云团，决定着狩猎的淡季和旺季。精灵们领命于一个年老的母精灵，据说这个老精灵是他们的母亲。母精灵居住在卡茨基尔山最高的山峰上，经管日与夜的门户，在合适的时间开和闭。她将新月挂上天空，把旧月砍碎，形成诸多星辰。在干旱少雨的季节，她如果心情好，就会用蜘蛛网和晨露编织轻盈的雨云，站在高山之巅将雨云撒下去，那雨云一片片纷飞，在空中飘荡，似棉絮一般。后来，温暖的阳光把雨云融化，化为细雨落下，使草木旺盛、水果挂枝头，使得庄稼节节长高。不过，她要是心情不好，就会编织出墨一般黑的雨云，自己坐在当间，犹如一个大肚子蜘蛛隐身于蛛网里。一旦乌黑的雨云破开，下边的山川沟壑就会遭受水患！

根据印第安人的传说，很久以前有一种山神（或称山精）出没于卡茨基尔山的荒林野岭。他们喜欢恶作剧，想出各种馊点子，给印第安人带来无尽的烦恼。他们有时候会化作熊、豹或鹿，以迷惑猎手，引着猎手深入密林，攀上险山，使得他们疲于奔命，最后突然纵身一跳，消失不见，让猎手止步于万丈悬崖边缘或滔滔山涧跟前，吓出一身冷汗。

山神的居住地至今仍看得见——其实是一块岩石（或者说是一处崖壁），位于人迹罕至的大山深处，周围荒藤缠绕，野花遍地开放，名叫“花园岩”。 靠近它的脚下是一个小湖，那儿是孤单的鸬鹚栖息之地，湖面上漂着睡莲，水蛇躺在莲叶上晒太阳。对于这个地方，印第安人素有敬畏之心，就连胆子最大的猎手也不敢在附近追逐猎物。从前，有个猎手因迷路来到了“花园岩”，看见树杈上挂着几个葫芦，便顺手拿走了一个，后来慌不择路，葫芦掉在了石头上，里面涌出滔滔洪水，将他冲下悬崖，摔了个粉身碎骨。而那股水滚滚流向哈德逊河，至今仍流淌不息，即世人所熟知的“卡特斯夺命河”。

————————————————————

(1) 华盛顿·欧文写《纽约外史》时曾用过的笔名。

(2) 卡特赖特（1743—1823），英国发明家。

(3) 彼得·斯泰弗森特（1612—1672），新荷兰殖民地最后一任总督， 1664年将政权移交给了英国人，自此，新荷兰更名为纽约。

(4) 九柱戏类似现今的保龄球。

(5) 15世纪早期至17世纪的佛兰德斯地区包括今比利时西部、法国北部、荷兰沿海部分地区。

(6) 美国独立战争期间在波士顿邦克山发生的战役，共造成1000多名英国士兵和约400名美国爱国者伤亡。战役结果表明经验相对不足的美军在战场上能直面英军。

(7) 指的是在邦克山战役中为国捐躯者。

(8) 联邦党是在1792—1816年间存在的一个美国政党，是后来辉格党和共和党的前身之一。

鬼新郎

——一个旅行家的故事(1)

昨晚为他设宴，今夜他却尸体冰凉！
昨天领他进卧房，今夜钢刀做他的床！

——艾格尔爵士、格雷厄姆爵士、格雷·斯蒂尔爵士

在德国南部有一片高地叫奥登瓦德，距美因河与莱茵河交汇处不远，虽然是荒蛮之乡，却充满了浪漫气息。许多许多年之前，在其中的一座高丘上矗立着冯·兰德肖特男爵的城堡。如今，城堡已变成了残垣断壁，几乎完全隐没于山毛榉和黑黝黝的冷杉树那茫茫的林海里了。不过，那座古老的瞭望塔仍屹立不倒，跟我刚刚提到的城堡以前的主人一样，挣扎着把头抬得高高的，俯瞰着周围的景色。

这位男爵属于卡特赞尼兰博根大家族的一个日渐凋零的分支。(2)他继承了祖上的遗产，也继承了他们傲岸的性格。尽管先人们生性好战，大大损耗了家族产业，但男爵却气势依旧，竭力维持着家族昔日的排场。那时天下太平，德国贵族一般都抛弃了他们那像鹰巢一样高踞于群山中的生活不便的古堡，而在山谷里建造起比较方便的住宅。然而这位男爵却仍然高傲地固守着他小小的堡垒，以祖上遗传给他的顽固天性牢记着前辈高祖父一代结下的冤仇，所以和近旁的邻居们关系紧张。

男爵只有一个孩子，是个女儿。大凡独苗，老天多有恩赐，总会赐予奇异的禀赋作为补偿，男爵的这个掌上明珠亦是如此。所有的保姆、妇人、乡下的亲戚，无不在男爵面前夸她，说她的美貌在全德国无人可比。的确，这些人的夸赞所言不虚。另外，她自小就受到两位姑妈的精心监护，而这两位姑妈终生未嫁，早年曾在德国一个小宫廷里生活过几年，精通教育大家闺秀所必需的各门知识。在两位姑妈的谆谆教诲下，她成了一个多才多艺的奇才。她十八岁时，刺绣技艺令人叹为观止，曾在绣帘上绣出了全套的圣徒事迹，绣品上的人物表情逼真，一个个看上去活似炼狱里受难的鬼魂。在阅读方面，她也没有费多大气力，靠着自己拼读看完了好几种教会传说以及《启示录》里几乎所有骑士的传奇经历。她甚至写字也写得相当熟练，签名时能够做到一个字母也不遗漏，而且清晰可辨，让两个姑妈不戴眼镜也能看得清楚。她心灵手巧，善于制作各种各样雅致的小摆设，虽没有实际用途，却也可愉悦心性。除此之外，她还能歌善舞，精通当时流行的最为深奥的舞蹈，可以用竖琴和吉他弹奏出许多曲子，对于《歌谣集》里的那些柔情小调亦能够做到吟唱自如。

两个姑妈年轻时在风月场上善于打情骂俏，而今担负监护侄女的重任，摇身一变成了敏锐的保护人和严格的监督者，履行职责一丝不苟——若论当少女的监护人，恐怕没有谁比人老色衰的卖俏女更为严格谨慎、刻薄无情了。她们极少让侄女走出她们的视野，侄女一旦走出城堡的范围，必有人陪伴，或者说必有人严密监视。她们孜孜不倦地向她施教，要求她严守礼节和绝对服从。至于对那些臭男人——呸！她们要求侄女跟男人要保持很远的距离，绝对不要相信他们，除非获得允许，否则就是遇见天下最英俊的骑士，也不能看他一眼——即便他死在她的脚下，也不许看他。

这种教育模式收效很好，有目共睹。这位千金小姐成了性格温顺、举止端庄的典范。别的女孩子在这个浮华的世界里空空耗费灿烂的年华，如野花被人采摘又随手扔掉，而她却在两个追求完美的老处女的呵护之下，羞答答地长成了一个娇艳可爱的花季少女，就像一朵玫瑰花蕾在保护它的那些棘刺丛中含苞欲放。姑妈们看着她，眼里充满了自豪和喜悦，夸口说即便全世界的女孩子都走上邪路，谢天谢地，这种事情也绝不会发生在卡特赞尼兰博根家族这个女继承人身上。

不过，不管冯·兰德肖特男爵是多么缺儿少女，他的这个家族的人数却不少，老天倒是赐给了他一大群穷亲戚。他们一个个全都具有贫微的亲戚那种重感情的通病，如胶似漆地爱着男爵，一有机会就蜂拥而至，给城堡带来一片生气。每逢家族庆典日，这些好心人都要来欢聚一堂，一切开销均由男爵承担。酒足饭饱后，他们会宣称，天下没有比家族盛典举家欢乐更叫人高兴的事了。

男爵虽身材矮小，心地却很宽广，一想到自己是这块小天地里最显赫的人物，一颗心便满足得膨胀起来。古堡的墙上挂着一些武士的画像，威严地俯视着下方，而男爵特别喜欢讲他们的故事，那些故事冗长冗长的。他发现听他讲故事，谁都不如前来混吃喝的穷亲戚有耐心。他对传奇故事情有独钟，对那些流传于德国每一座山、每一条谷的奇闻异事笃信不疑。来古堡的食客们甚至比他更相信那些传说，听他讲述时，每次都会瞪大眼睛、张大嘴巴，即使听一百遍，也总是会露出惊讶的神情。冯·兰德肖特男爵就是这样过日子的——他是古堡饭桌旁的圣贤、自家小王朝里至高无上的君主，而叫他最有幸福感的是，他自认为是当代最有智慧的人。

在本故事开始的时候，城堡里聚集了一大群族人，因为有一件极其重大的事情就要发生——迎接将要娶男爵女儿为妻的新郎。双方的家长（男方的家长是巴伐利亚的一位旧贵族）经过协商，要通过儿女的婚事将两个尊贵的家族联合起来。前期的准备工作已经按部就班进行完毕。两位年轻人彼此并未见面，却已定下了婚约，举行婚礼的日期业已敲定。为了这桩婚事，年轻的冯·阿尔滕伯格伯爵被从军队里叫了回来，实际上他现在已在迎亲途中，前来男爵府迎娶新娘。他从乌兹堡写来一封信，说他的行程因事有所耽搁，信中写明了他预期抵达男爵府的日子和时辰。

古堡里一片忙乱，准备热烈迎接新郎官。美丽的新娘被精心打扮了起来。她的梳妆打扮都是在姑妈们的监督之下完成的，两个姑妈对她的衣着每一个细节都各持己见，争吵了整整一个上午。年轻的男爵小姐利用她们争执不休的机会，按照自己的品位打扮，产生了很好的效果。她看上去妩媚可爱，一定能叫年轻的新郎官一见钟情，由于怀着期待的心情，她面色更加娇艳。

她的脸和脖子罩上了一片红晕，胸脯轻轻地一起一伏，眼里不时闪烁着梦想的光芒，这一切都暴露出她的心里在发生着温柔的波动。姑妈们围着她打转——大凡终身未嫁的姑妈对这类事情往往都兴趣盎然。至于该有怎样的言谈举止，该以什么样的方式接待意中人，她们给她提了一大堆老成的忠告。

男爵也一样忙得不亦乐乎。实际上，并没有什么具体的事情需要他做，但这个小个子男人是个急性子，干事雷厉风行，当周围的人都在忙碌不停的时候，他不可能袖手旁观。他带着万分焦急的神情在城堡里跑上跑下，四处生乱，时不时会教训几句正在干活的仆人，让他们不要偷懒。他的嚷嚷声回荡在各个大厅和房间里，嗡嗡嗡的，像炎热夏日的一只绿头苍蝇，焦躁不安、喋喋不休。

与此同时，养肥了的小牛犊已宰杀完毕；森林里人声鼎沸，猎人们狩猎的吆喝声此起彼伏；厨房里堆满了各种美味佳肴；大量的莱茵酒和费雷酒从地窖里搬了出来，甚至动用了海德堡大酒桶(3)。万事俱备，只等着隆重迎接尊贵的客人，展示德国人热情好客的精神面貌了，可是客人却迟迟不见露面。一个小时又一个小时悄然流逝。原本倾洒在奥登瓦德森林上的阳光渐渐隐去，最后仅在群山之巅闪烁着光芒。男爵爬上最高的一座瞭望塔，望眼欲穿地向远方眺望，希望能看见伯爵和他的随从的身影。有一次，他觉得自己好像看见了他们，仿佛听见号角声从山谷里飘来，在山间激起一串串回音。果真有几个骑马人从远处沿着大道慢慢地走了过来，可是就在他们眼看要抵达山脚时，却突然转了方向。最后的一抹夕阳消失了，蝙蝠开始在暮色里飞来飞去，大道变得越来越模糊，那儿什么动静也看不见，只时不时见几个农夫慢慢吞吞地从田间归来。

兰德肖特家的古堡里一片茫然，人们不知所措。而就在这时，奥登瓦德的另一个地方却出现了一幅非常有趣的场景。冯·阿尔滕伯格伯爵正安安静静地行走在路上，坐骑迈着碎步，不慌不忙。这位新郎官安然若素，去迎娶新娘——反正所有的麻烦事以及扑朔迷离的求婚过程均由别人代劳，新娘和婚宴就在前方等着他，这些都是板上钉钉的事。走到乌兹堡时，他遇见了一个年轻的战友。二人曾在边疆一起服过兵役。这个战友名叫赫尔曼·冯·斯塔肯浮士德，是一个作战极为勇敢、心灵极为高尚的德国骑士，此时正从军中返回家里。他家的城堡距离兰德肖特家的古堡并不远，不过由于家族世仇，两家人一直相互敌视、形同路人。

两位年轻的朋友见面分外亲热，各叙衷曲，把各自经历的事情和命运讲给对方听。伯爵说他要去跟一个姑娘完婚——那姑娘他从没见过，但听人说有沉鱼落雁的容貌，这叫他喜不自禁。

鉴于两位朋友走的是同一方向，他们决定余下的路程结伴而行，打算早一点从乌兹堡动身，路上可以舒服一些。伯爵吩咐他的侍从随后赶来。

途中，他们回忆着军旅生活和冒险经历作为消遣，以解除旅途的烦闷。另外，伯爵老是不厌其烦地提到自己的新娘，说她美貌传播四方，幸福正在等待着他。

说着话，他们走进了奥登瓦德的荒山野岭，这儿的荒径行人绝迹，林深树密。德国的森林里土匪出没，城堡中闹鬼，这已成了广为人知的现象。而此时此地，散兵游勇成群结队，干起打家劫舍的勾当，数量多如牛毛。所以，两位朋友在密林中遇到一群散兵的袭击，也就不足为怪了。他们奋勇抵抗，但寡不敌众，眼看招架不住，幸好伯爵的侍从及时赶来助战。土匪们见了一哄而散。而此时伯爵已负致命重伤。大家轻手轻脚、小心翼翼地把他送回了乌兹堡，并从附近的修道院里请来一位修士，此人因善于医治精神和肉体的疾病而小有名气。可是面对致命重伤，他回天乏术，伯爵生命垂危，所剩的时间屈指可数。

伯爵临咽气之前，恳求他的朋友立刻赶往兰德肖特家的古堡，就说他身受致命之伤，无法如约和新娘完婚了。他虽然算不上一个感情极为炽热的恋人，却是一个极为讲究礼节的君子，似乎焦虑万分，只希望能把消息迅速送到，做到有礼有节。“除非能了结此事，否则我将死不瞑目。”他以非常凝重的口吻留下了这句遗言。值此生命存亡时刻提出的请求容不得犹豫，斯塔肯浮士德好言劝他静养，言辞诚恳地许诺一定完成他的心愿，并伸出手来庄严地对他发誓。气息奄奄的伯爵紧握他的手表示感谢，接着神志很快陷入了昏迷之中，口里说着胡话，念叨着他的新娘、婚约和誓言，还吩咐给他备马，说他要到兰德肖特家的古堡去，而就在他幻想着自己飞身上马的过程中咽了气。

斯塔肯浮士德面对战友突遭的厄运长长叹了口气，洒下了几滴英雄泪，随即便考虑起怎样去完成自己所承担的难堪的使命。他心情沉重，脑子里一片混乱，因为他要到仇人家去做不速之客，还要给对方带去噩耗，毁掉他们的希望，给他们的喜事泼上一盆冷水。不过，他的内心悄然产生了一丝好奇，想去看看那个在严密监护下与世隔绝，却又远近闻名的卡特赞尼兰博根家的美女。他对漂亮女性历来有强烈的倾慕之心，又生性不拘一格、勇于探索，使得他喜欢一切奇异的冒险行动。

临行之前，他和修道院的修士们一起做出了妥当的安排，要为他的朋友举行隆重的葬礼；他的战友将被安葬于乌兹堡大教堂，跟他的几位显赫亲戚的墓地相距不远，伯爵的那些悲恸欲绝的侍从负责运送主人的遗体。

话说到这里，又该讲讲古老的卡特赞尼兰博根家族那儿的情况了。他们焦急地期待着客人的到来，而盼望酒宴的心情更为急切。刚才说到可敬的小个子男爵在瞭望塔翘首以待，现在应该再讲讲他的状况。

夜色四合，而客人踪影全无。男爵于绝望之中走下了瞭望塔。酒宴一推再推，几个小时已经过去了，不能再耽搁了。肉已经烤过了头，弄得厨师忧心忡忡，全家上下就像一支因为饥饿而丧失了战斗力的守护城堡的驻军。无奈之下，男爵只好下令开饭，不再等客人了。大家在餐桌旁落座，正准备开吃，却听见大门外传来了号角声，报告有客人登门。接着又是一声长长的号角，久久回荡在古堡的庭院里，而城墙上的卫兵鸣号回应。男爵忙不迭跑去迎接未来的女婿。

吊桥放下，客人已走到大门前。来者是个威武的骑士，高高的个头，骑一匹黑色骏马。他面色苍白，眼睛却炯炯有神、风流多情，神态庄重而忧郁。男爵见他单人单骑，未带侍从，心里难免有些不快。这是一个重要的场合，来者将与一个显赫的家族联姻，然而他却缺乏起码的尊重，这叫男爵的自尊心一时受到了挫伤。不过他又让自己冷静下来，觉得一定是年轻人太性急，把侍从甩在后边，自己先一步到达了。

“对不起，”来客说道，“冒昧前来，多有打扰……”

没等他说完，男爵就打断了他的话，说出了一大堆恭维和寒暄的话语（说实在的，他对自己的礼节和口才颇感自豪）。来客尝试了一两次，想打断那滔滔不绝的话语，然而仅是徒劳，只好鞠了一躬，听任男爵讲下去。待男爵停住话头时，他们已到了城堡的内院。来客正准备说话，却又一次被打断了——只见几个女眷领着羞羞答答、满脸通红的新娘走了过来。他望着新娘，一时都看呆了，似乎整个灵魂都焕发出精神，痴痴望着那个可爱的人儿。一个老处女姑妈附在新娘的耳旁低语几声，新娘便怯生生抬起她那水汪汪的蓝眼睛，害羞地望一眼来客算作问候，随即又低下了头，眼睛看着地面。她没有说话，但唇边闪出一丝甜蜜的微笑，脸颊上露出柔情的酒窝，表明方才那一眼是满意的表示。一个十八岁的大姑娘，花一样的年龄，渴望着爱情和婚姻，不可能不喜欢一个如此英武的骑士。

客人姗姗来迟，此时已没有时间多谈。男爵素来独断专行，吩咐有话明天再说，随即便引着客人向尚未品尝的酒宴走去。

酒宴安排在城堡的大厅里。这儿四周的墙上悬挂着卡特赞尼兰博根家族那些英雄先辈面貌严厉的肖像，还有他们从战场和猎场上斩获的战利品。被砍破的盔甲、折断了的比武用的长矛以及破碎的旗帜，这些东西和森林猎场上获取的猎物混杂在一起；野狼的颌骨和野猪的獠牙夹在弓弩和战斧当中，令人毛骨悚然地狞笑着；一对巨大的鹿角叉开来，悬挂在年轻来客的头顶正上方。

这位骑士很少留意同桌的人或者主人的款待，好酒好菜几乎尝也未尝，似乎只顾欣赏新娘了。他说话声音极低，旁人无法听得见——情话历来都是低声低语的。不过，女恋人的耳朵有哪个是迟钝的，哪能听不清情郎的窃窃私语！他含情脉脉，同时神情庄重，似乎对姑娘产生了强烈的影响。她侧耳静听，脸上时不时会泛起红晕，间或羞答答地回答上一两句话。当对方的目光移开时，她会偷偷地瞥一眼他那风流倜傥的面容，充满柔情和幸福地轻轻舒一口气。明摆着，这一对年轻人已彼此倾心。两位深谙心灵秘密的姑妈断言他们一见钟情，已坠入了爱河。

宴会欢快地进行着，或者至少可以说很热闹——来宾们由于平时缺少油水，又因为山里的空气好而胃口大开，个个都狼吞虎咽。男爵又讲起了故事，那故事非常棒、非常长，精彩程度超过以往，产生了震撼效应。说到奇闻异事，听众们会惊奇得目瞪口呆，而说到滑稽的事情，他们则会恰到好处地捧腹大笑。说实话，男爵就像大多数大人物那样，鉴于身份高贵，轻易不讲笑话，要讲也很乏味。不过，餐桌上斟一杯上等的霍克海默酒，再加上叫人心情愉悦的陈酒，即使是乏味的笑话，也会使人禁不住笑出声来的。有几个贫穷但伶俐的人倒是讲了许多有趣的故事，但除非换个类似的场合，此处是不便复述的；有人附在女眷的耳朵根悄声讲俏皮话，乐得女眷想笑不敢笑，憋得浑身颤抖；男爵有个堂兄，家境贫寒但生性快活，直着嗓子高唱了一两首歌，听得两个老处女姑妈急忙用扇子遮挡。

在一片狂欢的气氛中，那位陌生客人却始终表情严肃、不苟言笑，与周围的环境格格不入。夜色渐浓，他脸上的神情也越来越沮丧。说来也怪，甚至连男爵的笑话似乎也只能加深他的忧郁。有时候他心事重重、沉思默想，有时则焦虑不安、目光茫然，显得心情极不平静。他和新娘的交谈愈来愈热切，也愈来愈神秘。新娘那漂亮、宁静的脸上不知不觉罩上了一层愁云，一阵阵战栗传遍她那婀娜的身躯。

这情景没有逃过众人的眼睛。新郎官莫名其妙的郁郁寡欢给大家欢快的心情浇了一盆冷水。大家的情绪受到了感染。他们窃窃私语、交换眼色，同时耸耸肩膀，困惑地摇摇头。歌声和笑声越来越稀少，谈话中断，气氛尴尬。后来，男爵开始讲荒诞故事和离奇的传说，一个比一个凄惨。讲到一个幽灵骑士将美丽的利奥诺拉掳走这个故事时，几个女眷被吓得大呼小叫——这个惊悚故事被写进了诗篇，全世界的人都读过，也都信以为真。

新郎听男爵讲故事，听得十分专心， 眼睛一动不动地紧盯着男爵。故事接近尾声时，只见新郎慢慢地从座位上站起来，变得越来越高，男爵目光迷离，觉得他简直成了一个高塔一样的巨人。待故事一讲完，他深深地叹了口气，语气庄重地跟在座的人们告别。所有的人都惊呆了，男爵更是如遭雷劈。

“什么！半夜三更你要离开城堡？为了迎接你，一切都安排好了。你想休息，是有地方住宿的。”

新郎摇了摇头，表情哀痛、神秘，说道：“今天夜里我必须到另外一个地方去睡觉。”

他话中有话，语气叫男爵颇感不安，但男爵还是鼓起勇气，又把自己好意的恳求重复了一遍。

这位陌生的客人默默地又摇了摇头，不管怎么挽留都铁下心要走，末了挥手告别众人，迈着缓慢的步子走出了大厅。老处女姑妈一时呆若木雕石塑；新娘低下头，眼中悄然掉下了泪珠。

男爵跟随着这位陌生的客人走到城堡的大院里，那匹黑马正站在那儿用蹄子刨地，不耐烦地打着响鼻。二人走到桥门，那儿长长的拱廊里有一盏油灯在发着幽暗的光。陌生的客人留住脚步跟男爵说话，声音空洞，在拱廊里听上去像是来自阴曹地府。

“现在没别人在跟前，”他说道，“我不妨把离开的原因告诉你吧。我有一个庄严的、不能不履行的约会……”

“为什么就不能派个人代你赴约呢？”男爵说。

“此事不能叫人代替，我必须亲自去才行。我必须赶到乌兹堡大教堂去……”

“唉，”男爵打起精神说，“还是等明天再去吧……明天你带新娘一起去。”

“行不通！行不通！”陌生的客人，语气比刚才凝重了十倍，“我不能跟新娘结合，而要去见蛆虫！蛆虫在坟墓里等着我呢！我是一个死人……途中被土匪所杀……尸体放在乌兹堡……今夜下葬……坟墓在等着我……我不能爽约！”

说完，他翻身上马，冲过吊桥，嘚嘚的马蹄声渐渐消失在夜间呼啸的狂风里。

男爵几乎吓掉了魂，回到大厅里把刚才的情况讲了讲。两个女眷当场吓昏了过去。其他的人想到自己竟和一个鬼魂同桌吃饭，不禁感到恶心。有的人认为来者可能是德国传说中的大名鼎鼎的鬼魂猎手。有的则觉得是山妖、树精或者别的什么鬼怪精灵——从很久很久以前开始，善良的德国人就一直被这些魑魅魍魉搅得不得安宁。有个穷亲戚斗胆提出了一种猜测，说这也许是那位年轻骑士搞的金蝉脱壳之计，骑士那高深莫测、郁郁寡欢的样子以及他那阴沉的性格很能说明问题。但这一猜测立刻引发了众怒，尤其叫男爵怒不可遏，大家觉得这简直就是异教徒的异端邪说，吓得他慌不迭放弃了自己的邪说，又回到了虔诚的基督徒的正道上。

不过，不管人们心里有什么样的疑问，第二天都得了澄清。次日有正式的信函送来，证实了年轻的伯爵遇害的消息，说他的葬礼在乌兹堡大教堂举行。

城堡里的人惊愕不已，当时的情景可想而知。男爵一头钻进自己的寝室，闭门不出。客人们本来是要跟他同喜同庆的，此刻见他痛苦万分，不忍心丢下他离去。人们徘徊于院落里，或者三三五五聚集在大厅内，摇头、耸肩，为如此好的一个人遭遇不幸而惋惜。他们在餐桌旁坐的时间比先前更长，吃更多的肉，喝更多的酒，为的是不让自己的精神崩溃。说起来，最叫人同情的是新娘，还未跟丈夫拥抱，就成了丧夫之女。那是怎样的一个丈夫啊！即便化成了鬼魂仍那么气宇轩昂、雍容高贵，活着的时候又该是多么出众啊！她的哀哭号泣响彻了屋宇。

守寡的第二天晚上，她回寝室休息，身旁有一位姑妈陪伴——后者硬要陪她一起睡觉。这位姑妈算是德国最能讲鬼怪故事的人了，此时所讲的是一个极长的鬼怪故事，没讲完她自己就睡着了。寝室所处的位置比较偏，俯瞰着一个小花园。侄女心事重重地躺在床上，呆呆望着冉冉升起的月亮把颤抖的月光投在窗前一株白杨树的枝叶上。城堡里刚敲过午夜的钟声，突然从花园里飘来一阵袅袅的乐声。她急忙从床上爬起来，轻手轻脚走到窗前。但见婆娑的树影里有一个高大的身影。当那人仰起头的时候，一道月光正好照在他的脸上。天呀！她发现那人竟是鬼新郎！就在这时，她的耳边响起了一声尖利的惊叫，原来她的姑妈也被乐声唤醒，悄悄跟在她后面走到了窗口，这当儿昏倒在了侄女的怀里。新娘再向窗外看时，鬼新郎已不见了踪影。

在这两个女人当中，最需要安慰的是那位姑妈——她已被吓得灵魂出窍。至于年轻的新娘，觉得对方虽是鬼魂，似乎也有着可亲可爱的地方。鬼魂固然难以满足一个害相思病的姑娘的感情，却也同样具有男子汉的英武，真人不可得，鬼魂亦可作为心灵的慰藉。姑妈宣称，再也不能叫她歇宿于这个寝室了，侄女这次却异常倔强，以同样强硬的语气说自己非此处不睡。结果，她将独眠于此。在她的恳求下，姑妈答应她不把闹鬼的事情讲出去，免得她连这一丁点人世间的悲情欢乐也享受不到——对她而言，住在一个由恋人的鬼魂在夜间站岗守卫的寝室，就是一种欢乐。

好心的老小姐究竟能把自己的诺言遵守多久，那就很难说了，因为她太喜欢讲奇闻异事了，能成为讲述这个可怕故事的第一人，那将是一件很能叫人感到得意的事情。不过，她倒是把秘密在肚子里闷了整整一个星期，至今这一带的人还把此事当作女人能严守秘密的佐证广为流传。一个星期后的一天早晨，一个消息传来，突然间解除了对她的所有约束。早饭时，人们发现男爵小姐不见了。她的房间空无一人……床上无人睡过……窗户洞开，那个笼中小鸟已经飞走！

一个伟大的人物突遭不幸，会在朋友间引起震动。只有亲眼见过这种场面的人才能想象得来男爵小姐失踪的消息会在城堡里造成多么大的惊惶和骚动。甚至就连那些穷亲戚也暂时中止了永不知疲倦的大吃大喝。那位姑妈一开始被吓得说不出话，惊得把手搓来搓去，后来才尖叫出了声：“是那个鬼！是那个鬼！那个鬼把小姐掳走了！”

她三言两语讲述了自己在花园里看到的那叫人毛骨悚然的一幕，一口咬定说那个鬼拐走了新娘。两个仆人证实了她的结论，说他们听见有马蹄声向山下去了，毫无疑问是那个鬼骑着黑色骏马把新娘带向了坟墓。这是一种不祥的征兆，让在场的人无不震惊，因为这类事情在德国极为寻常，有许多详实的历史书籍都有记载。

可怜的男爵处境悲惨，令人惋惜！一个爱女心重的父亲，一个伟大的卡特赞尼兰博根家族的成员，竟遭此不幸，实在令人心痛！他唯一的掌上明珠被带进了坟墓，或者说他将有一个妖怪女婿，恐怕还会有一大堆妖怪外孙。他六神无主，茫然不知所措。整个城堡人声鼎沸，乱作一团。他吩咐手下备马，一定要把奥登瓦德的大路小径、沟沟壑壑全都搜查个遍。只见他穿上长筒靴，腰挂宝剑，准备上马去搜寻（也许是徒劳的搜寻）。而就在这当儿，前方出现了一幕奇异的情景，使他愣住了——一个女子骑一匹小马朝着城堡跑了过来，旁边有一位骑士相伴。女子飞驰到城门前，飞身下马，跪倒在男爵的脚下，抱定他的双膝。女子不是别人，正是他那失踪的女儿，而陪伴她的骑士却是那个鬼新郎！男爵这一惊非同小可。他看看爱女，再看看那个鬼，简直都不敢相信自己的眼睛了。鬼新郎上次去了冥界，此时归来，看上去已大为改观。他衣帽光鲜，雄赳赳一身阳刚气，俨然一副贵族相，脸色不再惨白，表情不再阴郁，英俊的脸上朝气蓬勃，洋溢着青春的气息，一双黑色的大眼睛闪烁着欢乐的光芒。

这次神秘的事件很快就得到了澄清。这位骑士报了自己的名姓，说他是赫尔曼·冯·斯塔肯浮士德爵士（其实，诸位自始至终就知道他非鬼非怪）。他讲述了自己和那位年轻的伯爵所遇到的危险，说他快马加鞭到城堡来报告噩耗，而男爵滔滔不绝说话没个完，他每次想把事情讲清都插不进口。见到新娘后，他的一颗心都被俘虏了去。为了能在新娘身边多待上几个小时，他默然不语，让误会持续了下去。他心里既慌又乱，真不知怎样才能体面地抽身而退，后来男爵讲鬼怪故事激发了他的灵感，想出了这么一个离奇古怪的退路。由于害怕男爵不忘家族世仇，只好夜间偷偷来访……出没于花园，来到男爵小姐的窗下……向小姐表达爱意……赢得了小姐的芳心……成功地携小姐逃离家门……总而言之，他娶了这位绝代佳人。

要是换上别的事情，男爵是绝不会让步的，因为他一向顽固地坚持父亲的权威，并且对家族仇恨没齿难忘。不过他爱自己的女儿，曾经为爱女的失踪悲恸欲绝，此刻见她安然无恙，不由欣喜若狂。女婿固然是仇家儿郎，但谢天谢地，毕竟不是个鬼怪。有一点必须承认：这位骑士装神弄鬼，曾经欺骗过他，与他做人应该诚实的观念背道而驰。但在场的有几位打过仗的老朋友，他们说恋人们玩些花样是情有可原的——这位骑士不久前还在骑兵队里服役，当然享有这种特权。

因此，所有的事情都圆满解决了。男爵当场就宽恕了这一对新婚夫妇。城堡里恢复了欢庆的场面。穷亲戚们对家族的这位新成员交口称赞，说他风流倜傥、慷慨大方……还说他家有万贯之财。说句实话，两个姑妈多少有点愤慨，想不到她们严格地让男爵小姐与世隔绝，教导她服从管教，最后竟然有一个如此糟糕的结局。她们觉得都怪自己疏忽大意，没有给窗户装铁栅栏。一位姑妈讲述过自己看见鬼的情景，此时竟出现了这样的情况，不由倍感沮丧——她此生所见过的唯一的一个鬼到头来却是个假货。不过，她们的侄女发现那个鬼是个有血有肉的大活人，似乎高兴到了极点。本故事以圆满的结局告终。

————————————————————

(1) 原注：博学的读者，精通于没有实际用处的知识的人士会发现，这个故事一定是这位瑞士老人听来的法国趣闻，据说此事发生在巴黎。

(2) 原注：即卡茨艾尔博家族——那个地区的一个望族，昔日曾强大一时。据说，家族得此名是为了纪念家族里曾出现过的一位绝代佳人，该女因有美丽的粉臂（艾尔博“elbow”有臂膀的意思）而闻名遐迩。

(3) 海德堡大酒桶产于德国的海德堡，因巨大而闻名，一个桶能盛221726升酒，只用于盛大庆典，或者供游客参观。

睡谷的传说

——迪德里希·尼克博克的遗作

昏昏欲睡，看得见赏心悦目的情景，
眼睛半睁半闭，面前一场梦境；
华丽宫殿耸立在云层，
千古不变闪耀于夏日的天空。

——《懒散的城堡》(1)

哈德逊河东岸有一些河湾，呈锯齿形排列，其中有一处，水面极其辽阔，荷兰古代航行家称之为塔潘湾。穿过这片水域，他们总会谨慎地收帆，祈求圣尼古拉斯(2)的保佑。此处有个小集镇（或称商埠），有些人把它叫作格林斯柏格，但它还有一个更出名、更合适的名字叫作逗留镇。据说，这个名字是附近的一些村妇给起的，原因是她们的丈夫养成了一种癖性，每逢赶集日就逗留在镇上的酒馆里，流连忘返。随他们怎么说吧，反正我也无法举证，仅仅提一提罢了，说明我讲述的事情是有凭有据的。离这个小镇不远，大约在两英里开外，高山之间有一个小山谷，或者不如说是一块凹地，那儿恐怕是天下最安静的地方了。一条小溪穿谷而过，汩汩的水声如催眠曲使人昏昏欲睡，唯有偶尔一声鹌鹑的轻啼，或者啄木鸟啄木的声音，才会打破弥漫四野的寂静。

记得我少年时，第一次去打松鼠，就是在这个山谷一侧山腰上高大的胡桃树林子里。进林子时，正值中午，四周安静得出奇。我开了一枪，连我自己都被吓了一跳。那枪声打破了遍及四方的沉寂，久久不息，轰隆隆在山谷里回响。假如有一天我想隐居，躲开这纷纷扰扰的尘世，躲开麻烦不断的人生，悠悠然在梦境中度过余生，真不知还有什么地方比这个小山谷更为理想的了。

由于此地安静得令人昏昏欲睡，由于这儿的居民（最初来此处定居的荷兰人的后裔）性情落落寡合，这条与世隔绝的山谷长久以来被称为“睡谷”，此处的村童则被附近一带的人一致称作 “睡谷之子”。仿佛有一种昏沉沉、催梦的力量笼罩着整个山谷，甚至渗透入了那儿的空气中。有人说，殖民初期曾有一个神通广大的德国医生给这个地方施了魔法；还有人说，远在亨德利克·哈德逊船长发现这一带之前，就有一位印第安酋长，一个印第安族的先知或巫师之类的人物，曾给这条山谷施加过巫术。看来果真如此——至今，此地仍在某种魔力的影响之下，使得老百姓大脑受到控制，连走路也晕晕乎乎如在梦中。对于形形色色的奇谈怪论，他们都笃信不疑，整日恍恍惚惚，胡思乱想，经常以为自己看到了异象，以为自己听见空中传来天籁之音和天人的说话声。这儿到处闹鬼，到处盛传鬼怪故事，充斥着神秘的迷信色彩；山谷的上空出现流星雨以及彗星闪过的频率比其他任何一个地方都要多；梦魔和她的九个小鬼(3)似乎把这里当作了最喜爱的游乐场。

这是个神鬼出没的地方，而佼佼者则是一个骑在马背上的无头鬼，他似乎是所有天神天鬼的领袖。据有些人说，他是一个黑森州的(4)骑兵的鬼魂，在革命战争(5)中的一次无名战役里，脑袋给一颗炮弹打飞了。乡民们时常看见他在茫茫的夜色里疾驰而过，快如驾风飞过。他不仅出没于山谷中，有时也会出没于附近的大路小径，特别是离山谷不太远的教堂一带。实际上，本地区的一些可靠的历史学家已经把关于这个无头鬼的传说细心地收集起来，并且核对过了。他们声称，这个骑兵的尸身埋在教堂的墓地里，其阴魂夜夜都要骑马去昔日的战场寻找他的头颅。有时，他飞驰过山谷，速度快得就像一阵风，那是因为他耽搁得太久，急着要在天亮前赶回教堂墓地里去呢。

这个迷信传说的大致内容就是如此，它给这个神鬼出没的地区许多荒诞不经的故事提供了素材。该地区的住户在火炉边讲故事时，将此鬼称为“睡谷的无头骑兵”。

值得一提的是：我刚才说的这种见神见鬼的癖性，并不为山谷里土生土长的居民独有，但凡在此处住过一段时间的人，无不于不知不觉之中受之感染。在步入这个睡意蒙眬的地区之前，不管他们的头脑是多么清醒，只要待很短一段时间，吸几口具有魔力的空气，一定会受到影响，开始胡思乱想，做各种各样的梦，看到各种各样的鬼。

说起这块平静的小天地，我多有的是赞誉之词。在偌大的纽约州，这种带有荷兰风情的僻静的小山谷处处可见。在这个浮躁的国家里，他处移民潮和社会进步的潮流汹涌澎湃，催生了各种各样的变化，而此处的人口、风俗和习惯却始终不变。时代的潮流从旁边悄悄地流过。这些山谷就像隐身于湍流旁的一个个宁静的小水洼，看得见麦秆和泡沫静静地浮在水面，或者慢悠悠徘徊于这个微型港湾里，全然不受旁边匆匆流过的湍流的影响。想当年我曾在睡谷里那令人昏昏欲睡的树荫下散步，而今多年的时光已经逝去。但我相信，那些树木和人家仍在睡谷那隐秘的怀抱里繁衍生息。

在大自然的这个僻静的角落里，美国历史中很久以前的一个时间段里，也就是说在大约三十年前吧，出现过一位可敬的人物，名叫伊卡博德·克莱恩。此人移居于睡谷，或者按他的话说“逗留”于睡谷，为的是教育这一带的孩子们。他的老家是康涅狄格州，彼州为合众国提供了许多开发思想和开发森林的先驱，年年都会派出大批人才去边疆伐木，以及到乡村施教。克莱恩(6)这个姓对于他还是有点贴切的——他身材瘦长瘦长、窄肩膀、长胳膊长腿，两只手荡来荡去，离袖口简直有一英里远，两只脚完全可以当铲子使用，整个躯干松松垮垮，小脑袋，脑袋顶部是平的，两只耳朵大得像扇子，眼睛像两个大大的绿色玻璃球，鼻子长得似鹬嘴。这样的一颗脑袋，安在他那细长的脖子上，看上去像一只可以随时报告风向的风信鸡。刮风天里要是看见他从山腰大步流星走来，衣服鼓起，随风飘荡，你准会以为他是个饿鬼来到了人间，或者会把他错当成稻草人，从田间偷跑了出来。

他的学校是一座只有一个大房间的矮屋，用原木草草搭成，窗户有的镶嵌着玻璃，有的糊着旧习字簿的纸页。学校里无人的时候，自有巧妙的安全措施——用一根柳条缠在门柄上，再用几根木桩顶住窗板；这样，小偷进来容易出去难；此种防范措施，极可能是建筑师尤思特·冯·胡腾想出来的，而这位建筑师的灵感大概来源于捕鳗用的细颈篮那种神秘的结构。学校地点偏僻，但风景还算不错，位于一座林木茂盛的小山脚下，旁边有一条潺潺流淌的小溪，校舍的一端长着一株粗大的桦树。在令人昏昏欲睡的夏日，这里可以听见小学生们喃喃的读书声，声音很低，嗡嗡嗡的，像蜂巢里的蜜蜂在叫。这种声音时不时会被老师严厉的呵斥声打断，口吻有时是威胁，有时则是命令。也可能，打断读书声的是桦树枝条抽打学生的那种噼啪噼啪的骇人声音——这位老师用这种方式督促混日子的差生沿着繁花似锦的求知道路前行。实话实说，这位老师是个认真负责的人，心里时刻铭记着那条黄金格言：“小孩不打不成器。”伊卡博德·克莱恩的学生的确没少挨打。

不过，我可不想让读者以为他是学校里的一个心狠手辣的专制君主，以抽打学生为乐事。事实恰恰相反，他在执法的时候，总是区别对待，而非一味严厉。他常常轻饶弱者，严惩强者。遇到一见教鞭便吓得缩成一团的弱小孩子犯规，他会起宽容之心，放他们一马，而对于那些桀骜不驯、顽固不化、身穿宽松衣的荷兰小顽童，为了维护公理，他就加倍地惩罚。小顽童们绷着脸，硬不低头，越打越顽固，越打越倔强。他将这种惩罚称为“代他们的父母尽职”。每次惩罚完之后，他都要对顽童说几句安慰的话，说这都是为他们好，“他们会永远记住这教训，在以后的人生中，他们会因此而感谢他的”。

放学以后，他甚至成了大一些孩子的伙伴，跟他们一起玩耍。每逢节假日的下午，对于一些年纪较小的孩子，他都会护送其回家——小孩子家中往往有漂亮的姐姐或好客的妈妈，后者会以好酒好菜加以款待。实际上，他很有必要跟学生们搞好关系。教学方面，他收入微薄，恐怕连一日三餐的用项都不够——他虽然瘦，食量却很大，消化力堪比蟒蛇。不过，还是有补救办法的——根据该地区乡下的习惯，他可以到学生家中，吃住于农夫之家。于是，他在每个学生家里住一个星期，一家一家轮流住。每次入住，他都会随身携带一个小包袱，里面包着他的全部财产。

为了避免让农夫东家们花费过大，使得农夫们觉得上学划不来，负担太重，而教书先生都是些混吃混喝的人，于是他便用各种方法效力，表示自己是有用的，是讨人喜欢的。于是，他时常下田帮着干些轻活，帮着晾晒干草、修补篱笆、牵马饮水、赶牛回栏，以及劈柴冬天烧火用。他会放下在学校那个小王国里称王称霸的架子，撇开那种唯我独尊、盛气凌人的神态，变得十分温柔、异常随和。他会哄着孩子玩，尤其是哄那些幼婴，以赢得母亲们的好感，就像一只猛狮宽宏大量地抚育小羊羔(7)，坐在那儿，把孩子抱在膝上，用脚晃动着摇篮，一晃就是数个小时。

除了干这些杂事之外，他还教本地区的居民唱歌，教年轻人们唱赞美诗，因而获得了许多亮晃晃的先令。星期天，他会率领一班精挑细选出来的歌手到教堂去，站在教众面前亮相。此时，他沾沾自喜、不可一世，觉得出尽了风头，地位高出牧师一筹。此言不虚，因为他的歌声嘹亮，声音盖过了在场所有的人，奇怪的是至今教堂里仍余音袅袅。在寂静的星期天的上午，他的歌声半英里开外都可以听得见，声音直达磨坊水塘的对岸。据说，伊卡博德·克莱恩的歌声的确具有这样的力量。这位可敬的学究便是如此度日，处心积虑地（即普通人所说的“绞尽脑汁、不择手段”）寻找一些零碎差事勉强过活。有些人不了解脑力劳动之艰辛，还以为他过的是神仙一般的逍遥日子呢。

在乡下的女人圈里，老师可算是显赫的人物。女人们觉得当老师的是悠闲安逸、绅士一类的人，品位和才艺都远高于粗鲁的乡下小伙子，实际上，论学问只比牧师低一丁点。于是乎，伊卡博德·克莱恩只要出现在农家屋里，势必会在茶桌旁引起一阵忙乱——女人们会额外添上一盘糕饼或者蜜饯，偶尔还会摆上一把银质茶壶撑撑门面。我们的这位知识分子见年轻的农家女们笑脸相迎，不由心里乐开了花。星期天做礼拜中间休息，他陪着娇娘们走到教堂的院落里，见周围的树木上野藤缠绕，便从野藤上采摘葡萄献给她们，或背诵墓碑上的铭文供她们消遣，或在众多娇娘的簇拥下漫步于附近的磨坊水塘边。那些土包子乡下小伙子见他风度翩翩、谈吐高雅，难免嫉妒，急忙含羞躲避一旁。

他过的是一种半游牧式的生活，俨然就是个“流动信息站”，走家串户，把当地的小道消息带往各户人家，所到之处无不受到热情欢迎。此外，女人们敬重他，认为他是个学识渊博的人，因为他通读过许多书，可以说是科顿·马瑟(8)的《新英格兰巫术史》一书的绝对权威（顺便提一句，他本人坚定不移地相信巫术）。

实际上，他是个很复杂的人物，既有一些小智慧，又有点信神信鬼。他对稀奇古怪事物的爱好，以及对这类现象的领悟能力，都是非同寻常的，再加上生活在一个受魔力控制的地区，这种爱好和能力更是加强了不少。无论多么庸俗的故事，无论多么荒唐的传说，他都饶有兴趣地一概接受。他常常喜欢在下午放学之后，走到学校旁边那条潺潺流淌的小溪边，躺在茂盛的苜蓿丛上面，在那儿细细地阅读马瑟写的那些令人毛骨悚然的故事，直至暮色越来越浓，书上的字在眼前变得模糊不清。这时，他便放下书，沿着沼泽、小溪和可怕的森林，一路走到他所寄宿的那户农家。这是一个鬼怪出没的时刻，大自然里每一种响动都会令他心跳，激发他的种种想象。山坡上北美夜鹰(9)的一声啼叫、预告暴风雨来临的树蟾的叫声、猫头鹰凄厉的哀鸣、树丛中鸟儿受惊后逃窜发出的窸窣声，都会使他浮想联翩。萤火虫在最黑的地方发的光最亮——途中，时而会有一只特别亮的萤火虫从他面前飞过，吓他一大跳。如果碰巧有一只笨头笨脑的甲虫瞎飞瞎撞地朝他扑过来，这个可怜的人儿一定会吓得灵魂出窍，会以为是巫婆在施巫术。这种时候，为了驱除恐惧的心理，或者说为了赶走恶鬼，他唯一的办法就是唱赞美诗。他的歌声带着鼻音，拖得长长的，十分悦耳，从远处的山坡上飘来，或者回荡在暮色苍茫的小道上，睡谷的居民们于黄昏时分坐在自家门前听了，敬畏之心常常油然而生。

他还有一种乐趣也挺可怕的。在漫长的冬季的夜晚，他会和那些在火炉旁纺线的荷兰大妈们一道消磨时光——大妈们一边纺线，一边把苹果串在一起放在火上烤，烤得苹果发出刺啦刺啦的响声，一边还讲些神神鬼鬼的奇怪故事，什么鬼田、鬼溪、鬼桥和鬼屋啦，尤其爱讲那个无头的骑兵（她们有时称其为“睡谷的黑森骑兵”）。他也给大妈们讲巫婆的故事，讲早先流传于康涅狄格州的有关于各种凶兆的传说，有关于出现在空中的各种恐怖景象和声音的传说，同样令大妈们听得津津有味；他还会讲关于彗星和流星的种种猜想，告诉她们一个惊人的事实——地球是一直在转动的，地球人一半时间都是头朝下脚朝上生活着，吓得大妈们心惊肉跳。

他舒舒服服地坐在壁炉旁边，壁炉里木柴烧得哔哔剥剥地响，火光映得满室通红，根本不用害怕野鬼光顾。如果说这是一种享受的话，那么，这种享受是要付出高昂代价的，因为回家的路上他会感到非常害怕。在大雪纷飞的夜晚，白光幽幽，阴森可怕，仿佛有孤魂野鬼出现在他的面前！他多么渴望远处人家的窗口能闪出一线灯光，让那颤巍巍的灯光洒在这茫茫的荒野上啊！不知有多少次，路上看见披着白雪的灌木丛，像是裹着尸衣的鬼魂，吓得他屁滚尿流！不知有多少次，踩在冰雪覆盖的地面上，脚下咯吱作响，他被自己弄出的声响吓得魂飞天外，看也不敢朝后看一眼，生怕会瞧到什么狰狞的鬼怪紧随在他身后！不知有多少次，狂风吹过树林，林涛怒吼，吓得他大气不敢出，还以为是那个黑森骑兵疾驰而过，趁着夜色去寻找自己的头颅！

不过，这只是夜间的一些惊悚现象，是摸黑走路心里幻想出来的情景。他一生虽见鬼无数，独自出行时，非止一次遇见撒旦变成各种模样出现在面前，但天一亮，一切妖魔鬼怪都遁去了形影。尽管有妖魔作乱，尽管杂事缠身，他也并不在乎，要不是在人生道路上碰上一个生灵，他会高高兴兴度过一生的。此生灵给他造成的烦恼，比所有的妖魔鬼怪和巫师巫婆加在一起都要多。这生灵是一个女人。

每星期中有一个晚上，一些习乐弟子开班上课，跟他学唱赞美诗，其中有一女弟子名叫卡特丽娜·冯·塔塞尔。她是一个家境殷实的荷兰裔农夫的独生女，年方十八岁，面若桃花、美压群芳，丰满得像只小鹌鹑，那张熟透了的娇滴滴的红脸蛋赛过其父所种的鲜桃。她闻名于十里八乡，不仅因为她貌似天仙，还由于其有望继承大笔家产。同时，她还有点爱卖弄风情，这从她的服饰上可见端倪。她的服饰既有古装的典雅又有现代服装的时尚，极大限度地显现出了她的妖娆。她戴的首饰都是纯金的，黄澄澄的，是她的高祖母从萨阿丹带过来的。她上身穿一件诱人眼目的古色古香的胸衣，下穿一条惹人动心的短裙，露出她那双在本地区最漂亮的脚和脚踝。

伊卡博德·克莱恩对女性素怀柔情和痴心，难怪没多久便盯上了这块令人垂涎三尺的天鹅肉，尤其是到她父母的那幢大宅院里看望过她之后就更加如此了。巴尔图斯·冯·塔塞尔老人是个典型的家业兴旺的农夫，乐天知命、心胸开阔。除了他自己的农庄，对外边的情况他既不看也不想，这固然不错，却将农庄里的万般事务料理得舒舒服服、妥妥当当。他对自己的富有感到满足，却并不因此而盛气凌人。他因有偌大的家业而自豪，却并不追求生活的排场。他的宅院位于哈德逊河沿岸的一个僻静的小天地里，这儿绿茵铺地、土壤肥沃——荷兰裔的农夫一般都喜欢在这种地方安静度日。一株大榆树枝繁叶茂，遮护住他的房屋，树脚下有一个小泉眼，呈桶状，里面汩汩涌出清洌甘甜的泉水，静悄悄流过草地，一路泛着亮光，汇入附近的一条小溪中，溪岸上长满了赤杨和矮柳。农舍跟前有一座极大的谷仓，大得简直可以当教堂用。谷仓里装满了粮食，似乎把每个窗孔和每个缝隙都填实了。这儿，从早到晚都可听到用连枷打谷的声音，一刻也不停。小燕子和雨燕呢喃作声，在屋檐下飞来飞去；一群一群的鸽子在屋顶上晒太阳，有的翻起一只眼像是在看天气，有的将头藏在翅膀下或埋在胸前，有的昂首挺胸，有的咕咕叫着把头一点一点地求偶。一些皮毛光滑、笨乎乎的肥猪哼哼叫着，在猪圈里过着养尊处优的日子；不时会有几只正吃奶的的小猪跑出来，好像是想呼吸呼吸外边的空气。旁边的池塘里有些羽毛雪白的鹅，排成庄严的队列，与成群结队的鸭子一道游水。一群群的火鸡咯咯地叫着在院子里乱跑；院子里还有一些珍珠鸡，它们一个个怒气冲冲，气哼哼、不满地叫着，活像是脾气暴躁的家庭主妇。谷仓门前有只威风凛凛的公鸡，高视阔步，俨然就是个好丈夫、好武士、好绅士，它拍打着羽毛鲜亮的翅膀，发出豪迈和高兴的叫声，有时会用爪子刨土觅食，找到食物后就慷慨地唤来它那总是饥肠辘辘的妻子儿女，让它们大快朵颐。

这位学究看见这许多食物可供冬日饱餐，不禁口水直流。他心里像有只馋虫，不由想入非非，想象着那些跑来跑去的乳猪上了烤架，肚子里塞着布丁，嘴里含着苹果；想象着那些鸽子舒舒服服安眠于一个大馅饼里，身上盖了一层面皮当被子；白鹅们在汤盆里游泳；鸭子成双成对，身上抹了厚厚一层洋葱酱，安详地卧于菜碟上，就像是一对对新婚伉俪。看到猪，他就联想到了香喷喷的培根和鲜嫩可口的火腿；看见火鸡，他则联想到它们被绑起来，脑袋塞在翅膀下面，偶尔脖子上还挂着一串美味的腊肠当项链；甚至连那只雄赳赳的公鸡也直挺挺躺在了加餐盘上，爪子朝天，仿佛在讨饶——活着的时候，就凭它那威武的武士风度，是绝不会如此低三下四的。

伊卡博德·克莱恩发挥着自己的想象，想得都入了迷。他那绿色的大眼睛滴溜溜转，望着冯·塔塞尔家四周那丰茂的草地，望着那种植着小麦、黑麦、荞麦和玉米的肥田，望着那果实累累的果园，心里思慕着将要继承这一切财产的姑娘，想象力进一步膨胀，想到他将会把这些财产转手变为现金，投资购买下无边无际的野地，在那儿盖起一幢幢的房屋。他心里翻江倒海，幻想着自己的愿望已经实现，已经将如花似玉的卡特丽娜娶到了手，并且生儿育女。卡特丽娜带着儿女坐上马车，车上装着家里的杂物，车下挂着水壶和煎锅，而那些水壶和煎锅随车一摇一晃的，他则骑一匹母马护卫，后面跟着一匹小马，全家取道前往肯塔基或田纳西——或者是只有老天才知道的地方！

走进冯·塔塞尔家的家门，他的心就完全被征服了。这是一幢宽敞的农舍，屋脊高，屋顶呈斜坡状，垂得很低，这是第一代荷兰移民传下来的建筑风格——那低垂的屋檐在房前遮出一道走廊，走廊有门，雨雪天可以关闭。屋檐下挂着连枷、马具、各种耕作用具以及到附近河里捕鱼用的渔网。走廊两侧有几条长凳，供夏天纳凉时坐，而两端各放着一架大纺车和一台搅乳器，由此可见这条走廊十分重要，有着各种各样的用途。沿着这条走廊，心里遐想不已的伊卡博德步入了大厅，此处是整幢宅子的中心，是家里人经常聚会的地方。大厅里有一个长长的食具柜，上面摆着几排亮晃晃的锡镴制器皿，照得他眼花。一个角落里放着一只大口袋，里面装着待纺的羊毛；另一个角落堆着一匹匹刚从织机上取下来的棉毛制品；墙上挂着一串串的玉米和用绳子穿缀起来的干苹果、干桃子，犹如花饰一般，其中还夹杂着许多色彩艳丽的红辣椒；一扇门半开半掩，通向那间最讲究的起居室，他探首望去，只见那儿有爪足椅和深色红木桌子，件件亮得如明镜一样；铁制柴架和火铲、火钳都闪闪发着亮光，而柴架上挂着一些芦笋尖；几个工艺品橘子和海螺壳摆在壁炉架上作为装饰；壁炉架的上方挂着一串串各种颜色的鸟蛋；房间的正中央挂着一枚巨型鸵鸟蛋；墙拐角有一个碗橱，故意开着，露出许多珍贵的古代银器以及精心修补的古瓷器。

自打看见了这些令人赏心悦目的景象那一刻起，伊卡博德的心就再也平静不下来了。他现在唯一的念头，就是设法去赢得冯·塔塞尔的那个美艳女儿的爱情。然而，此举困难重重，其艰难程度远超过那些追求爱情的游侠骑士的命运。那些骑士要对付的只是些巨人、巫士、喷火的龙，以及诸如此类容易战胜的对手。他们只要打开一条路， 穿过铁门或铜门，翻越坚固的城墙，闯入囚禁着意中人的城堡就行了，容易得就跟切圣诞节的蛋糕一样，一下就可以切到中心。进了城堡，便能够获得美人心了。伊卡博德则不然，他得一路闯关去获得一个乡村女子的心，这颗心任性，反复无常，叫人难以捉摸，总是给你制造困难和障碍。同时，他还得对付一大批有血有肉的可怕的对手——无数爱慕她的乡下少年。那些少年把守着通到她心里去的每一扇门，彼此争风吃醋，相互怒目而视、虎视眈眈，可是一见新敌手出现，便会组成联合阵线，合力迎敌。少年中，有一个身材魁梧、吼声如雷、性如烈火的家伙最可怕。此人名叫亚伯拉罕，荷兰语的称呼叫布鲁姆·冯·布隆特。他是本地区的勇士，素以膂力过人和好勇斗狠著称。他膀大腰圆、肌肉强健，一头鬈发又黑又短，一张脸带着野性，但并不惹人讨厌，挂着愉快的表情，气势凌人。这么一个彪形大汉，再加上其力大无穷，因此获得“布鲁姆勇士”这一绰号，成了个闻名遐迩的人物。在骑马方面，他既精通理论又精通技巧，在马背上灵巧自如，和鞑靼人无异。若论赛马和斗鸡，他每次都能夺魁。在乡下，有力气就有威信。于是，邻里之间出现争端，就由他裁断。这时，他会歪戴着帽子，做出决断，语气坚定，不容置辩。他总是喜欢跟人打架或者恶作剧，这倒不是说他生就一副邪恶肚肠，而是因为性格顽皮。尽管看上去顽劣不堪，他其实却有着侠义风骨。他身边有三四个哥们，把他视为学习的榜样。他领着这几个哥们闯荡江湖，方圆几英里内有人打架或者出现热闹的场景，他们必到现场。冷天，他总是戴一顶皮帽子，帽子上缀一根夺人眼球的狐狸尾巴，叫人一看就知道是他。乡下凡有集会，就凭着这个标记，人们老远就能认出他来，随即闪至一旁，看着这几位勇猛的骑手呼啸而过。有时候，半夜三更也能听见他们一小队人马咋咋呼呼地从农舍旁飞驰而过，就像一队冲锋陷阵的顿河流域的哥萨克骑兵。熟睡的老妪从梦中惊醒，竖起耳朵听一听，直至那嗒嗒嗒的急促的马蹄声渐行渐远，这才长叹一声说：“唉，又是‘布鲁姆勇士’他们那一帮子人！”乡亲们看待他，心情十分复杂，既有畏惧，又有佩服和无奈。只要该地有人搞恶作剧，或者出现打架斗殴的事情，乡亲们总会摇摇头，断定又是“布鲁姆勇士”在兴风作浪了。

这个粗野撒泼的英雄不知何时相中了如花似玉的卡特丽娜，以粗野的方式对她大献殷勤，虽然他的爱情和表达爱情的手段有点像一只熊的温存和爱抚，但有人暗地里说，她没有完全叫他失望。有一点是肯定的：他的进攻就等于是一种信号，使得情敌们知难而退，因为谁都不愿意招惹一头正在发情的雄狮。于是乎，星期日晚上，只要一见他的马拴在冯·塔塞尔家门外的拴马桩上，便可以断定马的主人在里面求爱，或者用术语说正在“迸发火花”，其他的追求者便会绝望地走开，将战火燃烧到别的战场上去。

伊卡博德·克莱恩就是要跟这么一个令人生畏的情敌一决雌雄。综合考虑各种因素，比他更强壮的人恐怕也会退出竞争的，比他更聪慧的人也会以绝望告终。不过，他的性格却有着刚柔并济的特点，其肉体和精神就像一根藤手杖，易弯曲，但坚韧，有时会弯下腰身，却绝不会折断——哪怕受到一丁点压力他也会低头，然而压力一消退，他又会挺起胸膛，把头昂得跟以前一样高。

要说公开对抗“布鲁姆勇士”这样的情敌，那纯粹是发疯。这位情敌正在发情，绝不会认输的，其爱情的热度不次于那个疯狂恋人阿喀琉斯(10)。因而，伊卡博德的进攻采取的是静悄悄的迂回战术。他以音乐教师的身份作为掩护，经常到她家里去访问；不过，他这样做，并不是怕受到她父母的干涉（对恋人们而言，父母经常是爱情路上的拦路虎）。巴尔图斯·冯·塔塞尔平易近人，有着深厚的舐犊之情，爱自己的女儿甚至胜过爱他的烟斗。像所有通情达理、心胸开阔的慈父一样，他由着女儿按自己的性子做事。至于他的贤妻，手头的事都忙不过来呢，既要料理家务，又要看管鸡鸭。这位贤妻自有高见，认为家禽缺乏头脑，需要人照料，而女孩子是能够照顾好自己的。于是便出现了这样的情况：这位贤妻忙得在屋里跑来跑去，或者坐在走廊的一端纺纱，而老实巴交的巴尔图斯则坐在走廊的另一端，于暮色中吸着烟斗望着谷仓顶上那个木刻的小武士手持双剑跟屋顶上的风英勇作战。与此同时，伊卡博德却在大榆树下的泉水旁向这家的千金调情求爱，或者陪着这位千金踏着暮色散步。在暮色里，恋人说出的话最为动听。

我得声明：我本人对如何打动和赢得一个女人的心一窍不通。我觉得情场上的事如谜团一般扑朔迷离，让人佩服。有些女人似乎只有一个弱点，或者说只有一扇门可通达她们的心，有的则有千百条途径，可用千百种方法一举将她们的芳心俘获。要想俘获前一种女人，必须技艺高超，而俘获后一种女人就得有更大的本事，必须像将军一样懂得运筹帷幄，因为进攻者必须从各扇门、各扇窗户同时进攻才能攻克堡垒。赢得成千个普通女人的心固然值得称道，但只有能够把风骚女的心牢牢控制住的男人，才能称得上是真正的英雄。那个恶煞星一样的“布鲁姆勇士”当然不属于后一类情况；自从伊卡博德开始进攻，他的热情很明显在走下坡路了。星期天的晚上，再也看不见他的马拴在冯·塔塞尔家门外的拴马桩上了。渐渐地，他和睡谷的这位教师之间便产生了不共戴天的敌意。

若按布鲁姆好斗逞勇的天性，乐得光明正大地打一场，一了百了地解决这件争风吃醋的事情，方法简单合理，即按照古代游侠的风格以决斗见胜负。而伊卡博德深知这位情敌膂力超人，哪敢单一对决。他听说这位“布鲁姆勇士”放过狠话，说是要把 “这个教书先生对折起来，放在他自己学校里的书架上”。他好汉不吃眼前亏，决不能叫布鲁姆的狠话落到实处。他坚持以和平的方式解决争端，气得布鲁姆无计可施，不由将顽劣的天性暴露了出来，搞出一些野蛮的恶作剧作弄自己的情敌。“布鲁姆勇士”率领着他的那班顽徒千方百计地捉弄起伊卡博德来。他们不断侵扰他那平静的小王国，堵死唱歌学校的烟囱，把师生们熏出教室；尽管学校夜间关门闭户，窗户上装着铁栅栏，防范措施严密，他们照样会攻入校门，把里面翻个底朝天，搅得伊卡博德慌了神，以为是全地区的巫婆都跑了来施展巫术。但更叫人气恼的是，布鲁姆一有机会就当着卡特丽娜的面取笑他，让他出乖露丑。布鲁姆养了一条恶狗，教会它用一种荒唐可笑的声音发出哀嚎，声称它的声音能和伊卡博德的声音媲美，可以教卡特丽娜唱赞美诗。

这种状况持续了一段时间，敌对双方的情况没有发生实质性的变化。在一个风和日丽的秋日的下午，伊卡博德怀着满腹的心事，正襟危坐于教室里的高凳上，像往常一样看管着他的这个知识小王国里的一切事务。他晃动着手中的戒尺（戒尺乃象征着他专制权力的权杖），而执法用的桦树条安居在他宝座后边的三颗钉子上，这些对喜欢捣乱的学生起着威慑作用。他面前的书桌上，可以看到各种偷偷带进学校的小玩意儿以及严厉禁止的武器，这些都是从不学无术的顽童身上搜出来的，其中有吃了一半的苹果、气枪、陀螺、苍蝇笼子，还有许多纸折的气势汹汹的小斗鸡。显而易见，教室里刚刚出现过严厉的执法事件，因为学生们都在认真看书，但也有的人用一只眼盯着老师，拿书本挡住脸在悄悄说话，一片寂静中可以听见嗡嗡嗡的声音。突然，这种气氛被一个黑人的出现打破了。黑人穿一身粗麻布衣服和长裤，戴着一种圆顶的破帽子（帽子的形状与墨丘利(11)的帽子一样），骑一匹脏兮兮、野性未驯的小马，用一根麻绳当作马缰。他啪嗒啪嗒来到学校门前，送来了一份请柬，邀请伊卡博德当晚去冯·塔塞尔家参加联欢会——或称联谊会。他显示出很有身份的样子，说话文质彬彬、咬文嚼字——黑人办这类小事，总喜欢讲讲排场。完成了这项使命之后，他转身离去，纵马越过小溪，在山谷里飞奔，表现出有重任在身、刻不容缓的派头。

刚才还安安静静的教室这下子乱成了一锅粥。学生们被催得读课文的速度加快，即便念错了也一带而过；那些滑头的学生甚至将课文跳过去一半不读也不受罚；那些读得慢的，则响亮地挨上一教鞭，以此让他们加速，或者说是帮助他们跳过某个难读的字。之后，课本被随便扔在一边，懒得放到书架上去；墨水瓶被打翻；凳子被推倒；全校比平时提前一个小时放了学。学生们冲到外边的草地上，大声喊叫和笑闹，因这么早便获得解放而欢欣鼓舞，就像一群小精灵。

接下来，情意缠绵的伊卡博德开始梳妆打扮，在这上面比平时起码多花了半个小时的时间。他拿出自己最好的衣服（其实只是件褪了色的黑外套），又是刷又是擦的。然后，他对着校舍里挂着的一块破镜子把头发拨拉来拨拉去的。为了能够像一个真正的骑士那样出现在恋人面前，他还从自己借宿的那户农家借了一匹马（这户农家的主人是个脾气暴躁的荷兰裔老头，名叫汉斯·冯·里普尔），随即英武地跨上马，前去赴约，那派头活像是一个前去冒险的骑士。我觉得，讲浪漫故事就应该讲讲故事中真正的精彩之处，所以有必要形容一下这位英雄骑士的仪表、穿戴和坐骑。他骑的这匹马是拉犁的老马，精气神已消失殆尽，顽劣的性子却没有随之消失。这畜生骨瘦如柴、皮毛零乱，脖子细得像羊脖子，脑袋的形状似榔头，肮脏的马鬃和马尾乱糟糟的，沾满了麦秸；它的一只眼没有瞳仁，恶狠狠地冒着凶光，另一只眼则幽光闪闪，仿佛里面藏着恶鬼。想当年它一定性子暴烈如火，你光从它的名字“火药”就能看得出来。其实，这畜生曾经是主人心爱的坐骑——汉斯·冯·里普尔脾气暴躁，是个烈性子骑手，很可能把自己的脾性传导给了这畜生。如今它已入晚景，风光不再，但脾气比本地区任何一匹年轻的马都暴烈。

伊卡博德和这匹马很是搭配，相得益彰。他用的是一副短镫，骑到马上，膝盖高抬，几乎能抵到前鞍，瘦削的肘部像蚱蜢腿似的伸出去；他将马鞭笔直地执在手里，像执着权杖。马儿蹒跚行进，他的两只胳膊一晃一晃，就好像鸟儿在拍打翅膀。一顶羊毛小帽扣在他的鼻梁上端（他的前额太窄了，权且称为鼻梁上端吧），那件黑上衣的下摆飘荡起来，几乎碰到了马尾。伊卡博德骑着马走出汉斯·冯·里普尔家的院门时，就是这么一种模样，简直像是光天化日之下难得一遇的幽灵。

这一天正如我方才所说，是个风和日丽的秋日，天空清澈而静谧，大自然披着富丽的金黄色盛装，使人很容易联想到丰收的景象。层林尽染秋色，呈现出素雅的棕黄两色，而一些小树蒙上秋霜，显得色彩斑斓——橘黄、暗紫同猩红混杂一处。高高的天空中飞来一行一行的野鸭；山毛榉和山胡桃树丛里传来松鼠唧唧的叫声；周围一带刚割完麦子，麦茬地里不时响起一两声鹌鹑的啼鸣，声声惹人哀思。

小鸟们正在享受这最后的盛宴。它们欢情一片，扑闪着翅膀，叽叽喳喳地叫喊，忽东忽西嬉戏于灌木丛中和大树的枝头间，在这丰富多彩的天地里游玩。这里边有老实的雄知更鸟，它们是童子猎人最喜欢的猎物，叫声高亢，似吵架一般；有黑鹂，它们叫声一片，飞起来如乌云遮空；有金翅啄木鸟，它们顶着红冠，宽宽的黑肩膀，披一身华丽的羽毛；有黄连雀，它们长着红边的翅膀和黄尾巴梢，头上有一顶小羽冠；还有蓝松鸦，它们是些吵吵闹闹的花花公子，穿着鲜艳的淡蓝色外衣和白衬衫，叫不停、唱不停，又是点头致意，又是弓腰示好，那副神气就好像跟林中的鸟儿个个都处得相当融洽。

伊卡博德骑着马缓缓而行，沿途观望各种可以化为美食的果实和鸟禽，满心喜悦地欣赏着欢快、丰实的秋色。四面八方尽可见满世界的苹果，或挂在树上，压弯了枝头，或装入篮里、桶中，准备运到市场上出售，或堆积如山，准备榨汁用。放眼望去，远处可见大片的玉米田，金黄色的穗子从绿叶下探出头来，叫他联想到了玉米大饼和玉米布丁。黄澄澄的南瓜躺在玉米的穗下，朝着太阳挺起它们那漂亮的圆肚子——这样的丰收情景预示着将会有许多香喷喷的馅饼。再往前走一会儿，便到了香气扑鼻的荞麦田，这儿有一股蜂房的气味。他不由浮想联翩，想到了美味的荞麦薄煎饼，想到卡特丽娜·冯·塔塞尔用她那小小的、肉肉的纤手把黄油涂在煎饼上，再涂一层蜂蜜或糖浆，此情此景叫他心里顿生柔情蜜意。

就这样，他心里美好的念头和“甜蜜的假设”层出不穷，在连绵起伏的群山中沿着山坡前行，远远望去，可以将雄伟壮观的哈德逊河的几处旖旎的风光尽收眼底。太阳如滚动着的巨轮，渐渐向西方下沉。在辽阔的塔潘湾里，水面平稳如镜，但这儿或那儿偶尔会泛起几片微波，轻轻地摇晃，把碧蓝的远山倒影拉得长长的。几朵琥珀色云彩浮在天空，由于无风而纹丝不动。地平线抹上了一片绚丽的黄金色彩，那色彩渐渐变成了纯净的苹果绿，后来又换成了天空中部的那种蔚蓝色。夕阳的一道余晖倾斜着洒在河岸边巍巍矗立的悬崖那树木葱茏的顶端，徘徊不去，让深灰、泛紫的崖壁显得愈加幽暗。一只小帆船漂浮在远处的水面，随波逐流，船帆毫无用处地吊在桅杆上；天空的倒影映在平静的水中，使得那只船看上去像悬在半空。

伊卡博德抵达冯·塔塞尔家的宅院时，天色已近黄昏。他发现那儿济济一堂，都是当地的体面人物和花季少女。宾客中也有年纪大的农夫，瘦削的脸上皱巴巴的，穿着自家缝制的外套、长裤、蓝袜子、大皮鞋，外套上配着闪闪发亮的锡扣。他们的老伴一个个皱脸枯皮，但手脚利落，头戴缝着细密褶子的帽子，身穿长腰身的短上衣和自制的衬裙，随身带着剪刀、针线包和鲜艳的印花布口袋。健美的少女们，穿着方面差不多和她们的母亲一样老派，只是多了一顶草帽和一根漂亮的丝带，也许还多了件白罩裙什么的，于是就有了几分城里人的时髦风度。小伙子们则穿着短上衣，衣服的下摆方方正正的，上缀几排巨大的铜扣，一般都梳着当时流行的发型——能够搞到鳗鱼皮发膏者尤为青睐这种发型。当地人推崇鳗鱼皮发膏，认为它能够滋润头发，对头发有定型作用。

若论此时此刻的风云人物，便非“布鲁姆勇士”莫属了。他来参加聚会，骑的是他那匹心爱的马“冒失鬼”。 这个畜牲和它的主人一样，也是野里野气、调皮捣蛋，除了主人，别人谁都驾驭不了它。其实，“布鲁姆勇士”就喜欢骑心术不正的马，喜欢那些爱使坏心眼，巴不得叫骑手摔死的马，因为在他看来，容易驾驭的驯良的马不配给勇敢无畏的小伙子当坐骑。

说到此，我想再讲讲本故事男主角的情况——他一走进冯·塔塞尔家那辉煌壮丽的大厅，看见眼前种种诱人的景象，不由高兴得睁大了眼睛。真正吸引他眼球的并非那些丰满漂亮的少女和她们红红白白的服饰，而是在这果实累累的秋天里，那地道的、令人垂涎欲滴的荷兰乡村茶桌。只见那儿摆着一盘一盘各种各样的糕饼，有些种类简直叫不出名来，恐怕只有经验丰富的荷兰主妇才知道！其中有可口的炸面卷，有又软又糯的猪油煎饼，有又松又脆的炸糖糕，还有甜饼、松饼、姜饼、蜜饼和形形色色说不清的饼。另外还有苹果馅饼、桃肉馅饼和南瓜馅饼；有火腿片和熏牛肉；有一大盘一大盘的李子干、桃脯、梨脯和温柏果干；当然也有烤鲥鱼、烧仔鸡以及大碗大碗的牛奶和奶油，盘碗交织，摆了一大桌，情况大致如我所列。桌子的中央有一把古香古色的茶壶，壶嘴里冒出氤氲的热气……那气派的场面真是叫人叹为观止！真该多费些口舌把这些美食细细描述描述，可惜我已说得气喘吁吁，再加上时间有限，只好急匆匆讲下文了。幸亏伊卡博德·克莱恩没有像我这个记录者这般赶时间，而是不慌不忙地品尝每一种美食。

他这个人心地好、知道感恩，吃了别人家的东西，心里便高兴，脸上便欢笑——爱喝酒的人几杯酒落肚也是这种情形。他一边吃，一边禁不住溜溜转动着大眼睛观察四周，望着那奢华、辉煌得简直让人无法想象的场面，想到有朝一日自己有可能成为这儿的主人，便哑然失笑。他心想，用不了多久，他便会永远地离开那座破旧的校舍；他会冲着汉斯·冯·里普尔以及其他所有吝啬的东家轻蔑地打个响指，叫那些巡回借宿的胆敢称他为同行的教师统统滚蛋！

巴尔图斯·冯·塔塞尔在客人中间走来走去，面带满足和欢快的神情，一张圆脸、喜气洋洋，宛若中秋的满月。他表达热情的方式很简单，但效果很好——对待客人们，他仅仅是握握手、拍拍肩膀、哈哈大声笑笑，说一声“别客气，请随便哟”。

这时候，从休息室（或称会客大厅）里传来奏乐声，召唤宾客们前去跳舞。乐手是个头发灰白的老黑人，此人在该地区沿街卖艺已有半个多世纪。他的乐器和他本人一样衰老、破旧，大部分时间仅靠两三根琴弦奏乐。只见他拉一下弓点一下头；每当有新舞伴进入舞池，他便鞠一躬，几乎一躬到地，而且还跺一下脚。

伊卡博德对于自己的舞姿和歌喉颇感自豪。跳舞时，他手舞足蹈，浑身上下每一块肌肉都在舞动。看见他那松松垮垮的身子骨左摆右晃，踢踢踏踏满屋子跑，你准会以为那是受上天祝福的舞蹈家圣·维塔斯(12)转世现身了。他简直成了全体黑人崇拜的偶像；黑人们老老少少、高高矮矮，从农场和各户人家赶来看热闹，挤在门前，拥在窗口，一张张黑亮黑亮的脸聚在一起形成了金字塔状，目光中充满了喜悦，白白的眼球骨碌碌乱转，龇出一口白牙咧嘴大笑。我们的这位喜欢用教鞭抽打顽童的教师见状愈加起劲，愈加欢快。他的舞伴不是别人，正是他的心上人——这位舞伴见他脉脉含情、频抛媚眼，便淡雅地嫣然一笑。“布鲁姆勇士”看在眼里，恨在心头，嫉妒得不得了，坐在墙角独自生闷气。

跳舞结束之后，伊卡博德被一群比较有智慧的人吸引了过去——那些人和冯·塔塞尔老头坐在走廊的一端谈天说地，又是回忆往事，又是大讲特讲战争的故事。在我所说的那个时代，这个地区可以说是块灵地，满是历史典故，是个英才辈出的地方。战争期间，英军和美军曾在附近对垒；因而，此处匪患滋生，难民、牛仔以及各种边境的游骑将这儿搅得鸡犬不宁。时光流逝，每一个讲述历史故事的人都会凭着想象添油加醋，在记得不大清楚的时候，索性把自己说成是种种功业中的英雄。

这里可以听到道夫·马特林讲的故事。此人是个荷兰佬，身材高大，胡须发蓝，据说曾在战壕里开炮，用一门铁炮发射九磅重的炮弹，差点炸沉一艘英国战舰，只可惜他的那门炮开到第六炮时就报销了。还有位老先生也讲了段故事，此处就不提他的姓名了，他是个非常有钱的老爷，不能随便加以议论。他说他参加过白色平原战役，在那次防御战中作战出色，用一把短剑挡飞了一颗毛瑟枪的子弹；当时，他觉得子弹嗖的一声贴着剑锋飞过，击在剑柄上弹了出去。为了证明自己所言不虚，他随时都愿意出示那把剑，让大家看看被子弹打得有点歪的剑柄。另外还有几个人也说自己曾在战场上出生入死，建立了赫赫战功，几乎全都认为自己发挥过相当大的作用，才使得战争最终能圆满地结束。

不过，比起接下来讲的鬼怪传奇和幽灵故事，这类战争故事就是小巫见大巫了。该地区广为流传神鬼故事，这成为当地的一种瑰宝。此处比较封闭，历史悠久，成为各种传说和封建迷信的肥沃土壤。然而，流动人口在乡下的大多数地方无处不在，他们对这类传说不屑一顾。讲神鬼故事，在大多数村子里是没有市场的。不等坟墓里的鬼魂睡上一觉、伸个懒腰，活着的人早已走掉，到别的地方去了。于是乎，待鬼魂夜间出来走动时，想找个熟悉的人都找不到了。我们之所以只能在历史悠久的荷兰裔居住区听到神鬼故事，而在他处少有所闻，这恐怕便是其中的原因了。

不过，这一带流行神鬼故事，最直接的原因，无疑还是由于与睡谷紧邻。睡谷是个闹鬼的地方，那儿吹来的风都带有传染性，把梦境和幻想的气息带往四面八方。当时在冯·塔塞尔家里，正好有几位睡谷里的人也在场，他们照例又传播了一通千奇百怪的故事。有些故事耸人听闻，讲的是附近的一棵参天大树，而倒霉的安德烈少校(13)就是在那棵树下被抓住的，据说有人夜里看见了鬼出殡，听见了鬼哭丧。有的故事讲的是一身素白的女鬼，她经常出没于乌鸦山的幽暗山谷里，冬夜暴风雪来临之前常听见她那凄厉的叫喊——据说，她就是死在那儿的雪地里。这类故事的压轴戏仍是人们所喜欢的睡谷幽灵——无头骑兵，有人最近听见他经常在这一带巡逻，据说每天夜里都把马拴在教堂墓地里的坟茔之间。

这座教堂地处荒郊野外，似乎怨鬼最喜欢在这样的地方作祟。它矗立在一个小山岗之上，周围郁郁葱葱全是刺槐和高耸的榆树，它那洁白的粉墙在幽暗的林荫里羞答答地闪着微光，仿佛是纯洁的基督徒少女在含羞微笑。山坡的坡度比较缓和，一直通向一片由参天大树环绕的银光闪闪的水面，透过大树间的缝隙可以窥见哈德逊河岸上的巍巍青山。望一眼那长满青草的墓地，看见那儿阳光静谧，你会油然想到亡魂至少在那个地方可以得到安静的休息。在教堂的一侧，有一条宽宽的林木葱茏的山谷，谷中有一道奔腾咆哮的山涧，涧水中满都是乱石和倒下来的树干。距离教堂不远的这一段水流又深又黑，从前上面架着一座木桥。一条路通到桥跟前，而路和桥都被浓荫遮盖，掩没在林木之中，即便在大白天也阴森森的，夜间更是漆黑一团、狰狞可怕了。无头骑兵最喜欢这种地方，于是这儿就成了他常来常往之地。布鲁威尔老头是不信邪，不信鬼的；据他讲述，有一次路遇无头骑兵从睡谷里跑出来，他便跟在后边穷追不舍，飞马越过荆棘和矮树，爬过山坡，穿过沼泽，最后来到了木桥跟前。此时，无头骑兵摇身一变成了一具骷髅，抓住布鲁威尔老头，一把将他抛进山涧，随后轰隆一声响，腾空而起，消失在了树林的上空。

这个故事立刻就被“布鲁姆勇士”的故事超越了，后者讲述了一段自己的亲身经历，比这个故事要惊险三倍。他把那个黑森骑兵根本不放在眼里，觉得对方只不过是个徒有虚名的骑手罢了。他口气坚定地说：一天夜里，他从邻近的辛辛村回家，这个黑森骑兵从后面赶了上来。他提出要跟对方赛马，赌一碗酒喝。他本来是可以赢的，因为“冒失鬼”可以轻而易举击败那匹幽灵马。可是，刚到教堂旁的木桥跟前，黑森骑兵便打了退堂鼓，化作一道火光不见了。

这些故事是在黑暗中讲述的，讲述人声音含糊、低沉，时不时会有人抽上一口烟袋，而烟袋的火光会将听者的脸照亮。这些故事深深地印在了伊卡博德的心上。他投桃报李，引用了自己珍视的作家科顿·马瑟书里的几大段故事讲给大家听，中间还添加了许多他的故乡康涅狄格州的灵异事件，以及他在睡谷里走夜路时看到的各种恐怖现象。

这时，前来聚会寻欢的人群渐渐散了。老农夫们呼儿唤女，让全家人坐上马车踏上归程，辘辘的马车声久久回荡在空旷的路上和远处的山间。姑娘们骑到马上，坐在意中人身后的马鞍上，开心地笑着，她们的莺声燕语和嗒嗒嗒的马蹄声混杂在一起，荡漾于宁静的山林里，渐行渐弱，乃至最后彻底消失。大厅里刚才还人声鼎沸，一片热闹的景象，一下子就人去屋空，变得静悄悄的了。伊卡博德逗留未去，因为根据本地乡村的风俗习惯，情郎临别时得和女方说几句贴心的话。此时的他已胸有成竹，觉得自己已经登上了成功的大道。至于二人之间谈得怎么样，我就不便乱说了——其实我对当时的情况一无所知。不过，从某种迹象看来情况不妙。事实上，他没过多大一会儿就跑了出来，灰溜溜的，神情沮丧。唉，女人呀，女人！女人真是叫人难以捉摸！莫非那个小女子又玩什么鬼花样啦？难道她挑逗这个可怜的学究仅仅是个激将法，实则是为了套牢他的那个情敌？这只有天知地知，我却不知！我只能说：伊卡博德垂头丧气地溜了出来，全然不像一个前来俘虏美人心的勇士，倒像是个偷鸡贼。平时他来美人家，对她家的财富垂涎欲滴，总是左看右看的，此时已没有了这份心情，而是径直走到马厩，拳打脚踢地狠狠给了他那匹马几下子，毫不体贴地把它惊醒过来，哪管它在舒适的马厩里睡得正香，哪管它正在做美梦，梦见玉米和燕麦堆成了山，山谷里遍地都是猫尾草和苜蓿。

此时已是深夜，是鬼魂出没的时间。伊卡博德心情沉重、垂头丧气地打道回府，沿着逗留镇旁高山的山腰一路走去。下午时分，他曾沿着同一条路兴冲冲而来，现在却败兴而归。茫茫的夜色和他的心情一样，也是那般凄凉。塔潘湾在山下很远的地方，水面昏暗而朦胧，一片荒凉的景象；在岸边的几处地方停泊着小船，可以看见它们那高高的桅杆。在这死沉沉的深夜里，甚至连哈德逊河对岸的狗吠声他也能听得见。不过，那声音极其模糊、微弱，让他觉得自己跟那位人类的忠实伙伴相隔甚远。偶尔会有一只公鸡从睡梦中醒来，拖长声音喔喔喔乱叫一通——那声音非常遥远，像是来自大山里的某户农家，可在他听来像是来自梦乡。偶尔还可以听见蟋蟀的一两声悲鸣，或者听见附近沼泽地那儿传来带着喉音的呱呱的蛙鸣——那青蛙像是在辗转反侧，睡得不踏实。

下午听到的那些关于妖魔鬼怪的故事，此时一下子涌进了他的脑海。夜色愈来愈黑暗，天上的星星似乎愈加遥远，偶尔飞来几朵乌云会将星星遮盖得完全看不见。他从来没有感到过如此孤单，如此凄惨。此外，他正在走近一个传说中经常闹鬼的地方。路中央有一棵巨无霸郁金香树，像一个巨灵，鹤立鸡群般站在一片树木当间，仿佛一座分界碑。这棵树的树枝扭曲多瘤、奇形怪状，每根树枝都又粗又大，相当于普通树的树干，有的弯下来几乎触着地面，有的高高伸到空中去。此树跟倒霉的安德烈那悲惨的遭遇有诸多联系，因此，乡亲们一致称它为“安德烈少校之树”。老百姓见到它，有着复杂的心绪，既敬畏又迷信，一方面同情那个与大树同名的人不幸的命运，另一方面则是受到了相关的鬼怪故事的影响——那些故事讲的是些灵异现象，凄凄惨惨，叫人伤感。

伊卡博德走近这棵可怕的大树时，便吹口哨壮胆。他觉得有人也在吹口哨作为回应——其实，那只不过是一阵风扫过干枝枯叶发出的声响。又走近一些，他觉得好像看见一样白乎乎的东西倒挂在树干那儿，吓得他不禁勒住马缰，停止了吹口哨。但定睛仔细一看，才发现那是树身遭了雷击，树皮被剥掉，露出了树皮下白白的木头。突然，他听到了一声悲叹，吓得他上下牙直打架，膝盖抖得直磕碰马鞍。其实，那只不过是在微风中，两根巨大的树枝相互摩擦产生的声音罢了。最后，他总算有惊无险地从大树旁走了过去。但是，前边还会有更多的险情出现。

离这棵树大约两百码的地方，有一条小溪横过路面，流进一个被称为“威利沼泽谷”的幽谷里，那儿是一片湿地，树木茂密。溪水上架了几根粗大的原木，作为渡水之桥。道路的另一边，在小溪流到树林里去的地方，有一丛橡树和栗树，树身上布满了密密匝匝的野葡萄藤，把那儿遮得像一个深洞，阴森森的。走过这座桥，那可是极为严峻的考验。倒霉的安德烈就是在那个地方被抓住的。想当年，那些身强力壮的义勇骑兵，就是埋伏在这些栗树和藤葛的掩蔽之下，出其不意地擒获了他。自此，这儿就被人们认作是鬼怪作祟之地，学童孤身一人走夜路经过此处，无不胆战心惊。

伊卡博德朝着溪水靠近时，一颗心像打鼓般通通乱跳。不过，他还是鼓足了全部勇气，一连对他那匹马的肋骨踢了十几下，打算飞快地冲过这座桥。可是，这个畜生耍起了犟脾气，没有听命朝前冲，而是来了一个横向动作，斜刺里冲向了树篱。这一耽搁，叫伊卡博德心里更害怕了。他将另一侧的缰绳猛地一勒，用另一只脚狠踢马肚。他再怎么样都无济于事。那匹马固然改了方向，然而却是蹿到路的另一侧，冲进一片树莓和赤杨木混为一处的杂树丛。这位教书先生又是用鞭子抽，又是用脚后跟猛磕“火药”那瘦骨嶙峋的肚皮，使得它喘着粗气、打着响鼻冲向前去，然而到了桥头却来了个猛刹车，让背上的骑手差点没一头倒栽下去。而就在此时此刻，伊卡博德灵敏的耳朵听见桥旁边的烂泥地传来踢踏踢踏的脚步声。他发现在那儿的溪水旁边，在黑魆魆的树影里有样庞然大物，奇形怪状的，赫然矗立在那边。它一动也不动，就像一个巨大的怪物，似乎在暗影里积聚力量，准备一下子扑过来袭击这个路人。

这位学究吓得魂飞魄散、毛发倒立。这该如何是好？掉头跑吧，已为时过晚。再说，要真是妖怪，它可会腾云驾雾，难道能逃出它的手心吗？于是乎，这位学究壮起胆子、鼓足勇气，结巴着问了一声：“你是何人？”对方没有回答。他又问了一声，这次的声音更为忐忑。对方仍没有回答。他见状，又一次猛踢顽固的“火药”的肚皮，一面闭上眼睛，带着一种并非自愿的热情，高唱起赞美诗。这时，那个骇人的影影绰绰的东西倏然采取了行动，一跳便跳到了路当间。虽然夜色茫茫，周围一片漆黑，那个不知来历的东西的形状基本还是可以辨得清的。那东西好像是个骑兵，身躯庞大，骑在一匹身子骨强健的黑马上。这位骑兵既没有表示恶意也没有表示善意，只是淡然地沿着道路的一侧前行，慢悠悠走在“火药”瞎眼的那一面——此时，“火药”受了惊后胡来的那股劲儿已经过去。

伊卡博德对这位半夜三更突然出现的陌生旅伴并无好感，心里想到“布鲁姆勇士”和黑森骑兵赛马的那段经历，于是便催动坐骑，打算把这位旅伴甩在后面。然而，这个陌生人也催马前行，和他保持同样的步调。伊卡博德勒一勒缰绳，让马慢下来，想让陌生人头前走，而对方也依样照搬。伊卡博德的心沉到了谷底，鼓一鼓劲，想再次高唱赞美诗，可这次嘴发干，舌头像粘在了上颚上，一句歌词也唱不出来。这个旅伴纠缠不去，阴森、固执、沉默不语，显得神秘而可怕。过了没多大一会儿，叫人毛骨悚然的谜底就揭开了。在登上一块隆起的高地时，在天空的映衬下，那个旅伴的身形趋于明朗——只见他又高又大，身披斗篷。伊卡博德发现对方竟然没有头颅，这一吓差点没被吓死！接下来的发现更叫他惊魂难定——对方那颗本应该安在肩膀上的头颅，却被他放在了身前的马鞍上！他恐惧到了极点，对“火药”脚踢和鞭抽并举，一下下雨点般落在它身上，希望一举将这位旅伴甩在身后。可是，那个妖怪也全身发力，风驰电掣地紧随其后。双方一前一后一路狂奔，哪管山高林密，所到之处只见马蹄下碎石乱飞、火星四溅。伊卡博德没命地逃窜，瘦长的身子俯下去，贴在马头上，又轻又薄的衣服迎风飞舞。

转眼，双骑已来到了转向睡谷的那条路。可是，“火药”却像中了邪，没有走这条路，却冲向相反的方向，顺山势而下，一路向左。此路穿过一条遍地黄沙的空谷，大约有四分之一英里的路处于大树的浓荫遮盖之下，在那儿要过一架小桥（此桥因出现在鬼怪故事里而闻名于世）。过了桥，是一片起伏不平的绿油油的山坡，坡顶上就是那座墙壁粉白的教堂了。

在这场追逐之中，“火药”受惊狂奔，反而叫它那骑术不佳的骑手受益匪浅。不过，在空谷里跑到半路，马鞍的肚带突然断了，伊卡博德觉得马鞍在身下慢慢溜走。他一把抓住鞍头，想将马鞍固定住，却徒劳无益。幸亏他眼明手快，抱住了“火药”的脖子，才保住了一条小命，而马鞍落地，只听咔嚓一声，被追兵踩在了马蹄下。就在这一瞬间，他的脑海里闪过了汉斯·冯·里普尔雷霆大怒的镜头——那可是汉斯星期天去做礼拜时用的马鞍呀！不过，眼下可不是为这点小事担心的时候——那个妖怪跟在后面，追得正紧呢！再说，他骑术欠佳，不知费了多少气力才没有摔下马去，时而滑向一侧，时而又滑向另一侧，有时在马背的骨峰上猛烈地颠上颠下，他真怕会把自己颠得散了架。

这时候，林中出现了一片空地，让他高兴起来，他希望教堂的那座桥就在眼前不远的地方。但见溪水里闪烁着银星的映影，微微晃动着，由此判断他没有猜错。他看到教堂的粉墙在前方的树丛里朦朦胧胧地忽隐忽现。他想起“布鲁姆勇士”跟这个妖怪赛马，就是到了这个地方，妖怪突然销声匿迹了，于是心想：“只要能跑到桥头那儿，就平安无事了。”就在这时，他听见那匹黑马赶到了身后，气喘吁吁，鼻中喷着热气——他甚至觉得那热气都喷到了自己身上。他对着“火药”的肚皮又是一阵乱踢，踢得“火药”冲到桥上，踏得桥板咚咚响，再一跃便抵达了对岸。这时候，他回过头来查看情况——按说，那个追兵会化为一团鬼火消失不见的。谁料，他却看见那个妖怪踏着马镫立起身子，提起他的头颅要朝他扔过来。

伊卡博德急忙躲闪，要躲开那可怕的抛物，但已经来不及了。那玩意儿砰的一声巨响砸在了他的脑壳上，砸得他一个倒栽葱落在了尘埃里。“火药”、黑马以及那个妖怪骑兵旋风似的从他旁边一扫而过。

次日早晨，人们发现那匹老马没有了马鞍，缰绳拖在蹄子下，在主人家的大门外悠闲地啃青草。早饭时，伊卡博德没有露面，午饭时仍不见其人。学生们来到学校里没人管，便跑到溪水旁，悠闲自在地玩耍起来，而那位教书先生迟迟不见来。汉斯·冯·里普尔这下子有点慌了神，开始为可怜的伊卡博德感到担心，也在担心他的那副马鞍。大家伙儿出发去寻找他的下落，经过艰辛的努力，终于发现了他的踪迹。在通往教堂的一段路上，他们找到了那副马鞍，发现它被踩在了烂泥里。有几行马蹄印通向桥头，在路面上陷得很深，显然是疯狂的奔跑所留下的蹄印。过了桥，有一段溪水水面较宽，此处的水又深又黑，人们在岸上找到了不幸的伊卡博德的帽子，近旁还有一个摔得稀巴烂的南瓜。

大家开始在溪水里打捞，但那位教书先生却死不见尸。汉斯·冯·里普尔以他的遗产处理人的身份，检查了他的那个包袱，里面包着他的所有财物——两件半衬衫、两条围巾、一两双羊毛袜子、一条旧的灯芯绒裤子、一把锈剃刀、一本卷边折角的赞美诗集和一只旧音笛。至于学校里的书籍和家具，那些全都是公家的，只有科顿·马瑟的那本《巫术史》、一本《新英格兰年鉴》和一本圆梦算命的书是属于伊卡博德的。列在最后的那本书里夹着一张大大的纸，纸上有几句诗，原打算是献给冯·塔塞尔家的那个女继承人的，不知抄自何处，字迹歪斜、墨迹斑斑。这些巫术书和歪诗被汉斯·冯·里普尔一把火给烧掉了。他铁下心，从今往后再也不送自己的孩子去上学了，觉得学读这样的书、写这样的诗，真不知会有什么好结果。至于说那位教书先生的钱囊，他前一两天才拿到了季薪，不管有多少，反正他失踪的时候，那些钱就在他身上。

到了星期天，人们来教堂做礼拜，对这桩神秘的事件进行了种种猜测，有的聚集于墓地里，有的到小桥边，有的则围在发现帽子和南瓜的地方，睁大眼睛细看，你一言我一语地议论纷纷。大伙儿想起布鲁威尔的遭遇，想起“布鲁姆勇士”的经历，想起种种诸如此类的事件，绞尽脑汁地进行了通盘考虑，又把它们跟这桩案子的各种迹象做了比较，最后无奈地摇摇头，断定伊卡博德是被那个黑森骑兵掳走了。鉴于伊卡博德是个单身汉，又不欠谁的钱，他的事也就没人再操心了。学校迁到了睡谷的另一个地方，另一位学究取代了他的位置。

几年之后，一个年老的农夫去纽约参观（以上所讲的鬼怪故事就是出自此人之口），返家后，带来了一个消息，说伊卡博德·克莱恩仍活着，还说伊卡博德·克莱恩当初之所以要离开这一带，一是因为他害怕那个妖怪和汉斯·冯·里普尔，二是由于突遭那位女继承人的拒绝，让他无地自容；而今，他住在一个遥远的地方，一边教学，一边学习法律，步入了律师界，从事政治，参加竞选，为报社撰稿，最终当上了十英镑法庭(14)的法官。在自己的情敌销声匿迹之后不久，“布鲁姆勇士”便得意扬扬地跟如花似玉的卡特丽娜步入了婚姻的殿堂。每当有人讲起伊卡博德的神秘失踪，他的样子就像个知情人似的，一提到那个南瓜，他便笑得肚子疼。于是，一些人便怀疑他了解内情，而他硬是不肯说出来。

然而，对于这种事情，年老的村妇们是最有发言权的，她们坚称伊卡博德是被鬼掳走了。冬天的傍晚，当地人围火而坐，这件事成了大家津津乐道的谈资。那座桥也更加引人注意，使得迷信妖怪的人敬而远之，这恐怕就是近几年让那条路改道的原因了——现在去教堂可走磨坊水塘边。那座学校没有了人气，很快就破败了，据说那个不幸的学究已化为鬼魂，经常在那儿出没。宁静的夏日傍晚时分，农夫从田中归来，常常会产生幻觉，仿佛听见远处传来他的声音，听见他用凄凉的调子在唱赞美诗，其声其调回荡在沉寂而静谧的睡谷里。

附笔

在尼克博克先生的遗稿里发现的材料

以上的故事是我到曼哈托斯古城参加一个社团会议，在会场上听人讲述的，几乎一字不差。当时与会的有许多德高望重、地位显赫的市民。讲述者是一个生性快活、样子寒酸但具有绅士风度的老头，他穿一身椒盐色衣服，脸上有一种悲凉的幽默神情（我猜度他一定是个穷人）——他讲得绘声绘色，以博众人一笑。故事讲完后，大家哈哈大笑，颇为欣赏，其中最喜欢这个故事的是两三个副市议员（这几个人开会时一直在睡觉）。不过，有个高个子老人却声色不动。此人紧锁剑眉，自始至终表情严肃，不苟言笑，时而双臂交叉，时而歪着脑袋凝视，时而低头沉思，似乎在心里思考着一个个疑点。他属于有心计的那种人，从不随便发笑捧场，除非对方有响当当的理由让他笑——该理由必须合情理、合逻辑。待全场的人笑声消退，人们都静下来的时候，只见他把一个胳膊肘架在椅子扶手上，另一只手叉腰，脑袋很有分寸地微微一斜，发出了疑问：这个故事有何意义？想说明什么问题？

讲述者刚把酒杯举到嘴边，想喝口酒润润焦渴的喉咙，一听问话便停了下来，用充满敬意的目光看了一眼提问者，然后将酒杯又慢慢地放回到了桌子上，解释说本故事是想以严密的逻辑性证明——

“人生并非处处有笑声，处处有欢乐——我们只需讲个笑话，就会有笑声，就会有欢乐；

“因此，故事的主人公跟鬼骑兵赛马，那就叫他遭遇许多波折和磨难。

“于是，乡村教师被荷兰裔女继承人拒绝，象征了向国家的高度发展迈出了一步。”

那位不苟言笑的老先生听得一头雾水，被这种三段论的推理法搞得完全糊涂了，于是便将眉头皱得更紧了。身穿椒盐色衣服的讲述者用眼睛盯着他，露出几分得意的神情。末了，老先生说故事倒是挺好的，只是他觉得有点夸张，而且他心里仍有一两处疑点。

“实不相瞒，先生，”讲述者说道，“对于这个故事的真实性，我自己也是不太相信的。”

——迪德里克·尼克博克

————————————————————

(1) 十八世纪英国诗人汤姆逊的诗篇。

(2) 天主教圣人，航海家的保护神。

(3) 典出莎剧《李尔王》。

(4) 德国的一个地名。当地居民经常充当英国的雇佣兵。

(5) 指美国独立战争。

(6) 克莱恩（Crane）在英语中有“鹤”的意思。

(7) 典出《失乐园》第四章。

(8) 科顿·马瑟（1663—1728），美国作家，公理会传教士。

(9) 原注：北美夜鹰是一种鸟，只在夜间啼鸣。它得名于它的叫声（whip-poor-will），人们认为它的叫声跟这几个词的发音相似。

(10) 荷马史诗中的人物，是希腊神话中半神的英雄，在特洛伊战争中杀死了特洛伊第一勇士赫克托尔而扭转了战局。在特洛伊战争中，他爱上了特洛伊公主波吕克塞娜，声称可为其令双方停战。

(11) 古罗马神话中诸神的使者。

(12) 欧洲大陆传说中的舞蹈狂人，跳舞时如疯子一般。

(13) 英军军官，1780年被美军俘虏，以间谍罪被处于绞刑。

(14) 底层民事法庭，案件所涉及财产不超过十英镑。

魔鬼和汤姆·沃克

在马萨诸塞州，距离波士顿几英里的地方，有一个深水湾，从查尔斯湾开始延伸，弯弯曲曲插入内陆长达数英里，断头处是一个密密麻麻长满了树的沼泽（或称泥地）。水湾的一侧有一片美丽的林子，林子里光线暗淡；在对面的一侧，临水矗立着一座陡峭的山岗，山岗上稀稀拉拉长着几棵高龄橡树，一棵棵像巨无霸似的。根据古老的传说，海盗基德把他的财宝埋在了其中一棵树下。该水湾便于航行，夜间用小船便可神不知鬼不觉地将钱财运抵山脚下。山岗地势高，可以从那儿观察周围的动静，而橡树高大，是很好的地标，回头寻找财宝时极为便当。此外，这个古老的传说中还提到：埋财宝事宜由魔鬼主持，之后亦由它负责看管。众所周知，埋藏财物的事情向来都是由魔鬼经管的，尤其不义之财更是如此。不过不管怎么样，基德却一直没有回来取他的宝藏，因为他在波士顿被抓住，不久之后便被送到英国，以海盗罪绞死了。

大约是在一七二七年，新英格兰地震频仍，吓得许多不可一世的罪孽深重之人都跪了下来祈求宽恕。这儿附近住着一个窝窝囊囊的小气鬼，名叫汤姆·沃克。他妻子跟他一样也吝啬成性，因为两口子都是守财奴，甚至彼此反目，相互欺骗。这女人见什么都会拿走藏起来；母鸡下蛋，鸡蛋还没下出来，她就虎视眈眈地守在那儿准备抢走。她丈夫则总是东找西寻，想把她藏的东西找出来。对于哪些东西是公共财产，两口子没少吵架，一吵就吵得脸红脖子粗。他们住的房子气氛凄凉，孤零零的，像是饿鬼的住所。门外长着几棵萎靡不振的柏树，成了寒酸的标志。烟囱里不见冒炊烟，不见过路人留步于门前。他们家的地里到处是乱石，坑洼不平，地面上结了些青苔，薄得连石头都盖不住；一匹可怜兮兮的马儿在地里乱转，吃几口青苔，反而更加饥饿难耐；有时候，它会把头探出栅栏，可怜巴巴地望着从跟前经过的人，似乎在央求他们把它从这块闹饥荒的地里救出去。

这栋房子与这户人家都臭名在外。汤姆之妻是个泼妇，人高马大、性情暴躁、粗喉咙大嗓门，胳膊力大无穷。她跟丈夫吵起嘴来，常常只听得到她的声音。有时候，丈夫的脸上会出现伤痕，证明他们之间的冲突已经不仅仅是语言的交锋了。然而，竟无人敢出面劝架。谁要是独自一人从这儿走过，见了这恶言恶语、拳脚相加的场面，一定会心生畏惧，一边斜着眼看着这个缺乏和谐的人家，一边加快步子匆匆而过；如果是个单身汉，那他会庆幸自己幸亏没有老婆。

一天，汤姆·沃克到该地区一个比较远的地方去，返回时走的是沼泽地——他认为走那儿是条捷径。跟大多数捷径一样，凡是快捷之路，必不好走。沼泽地里密密匝匝到处是树，有松树也有铁杉树，那些树又高又大，阴森森的，有的足有九十英尺高，林中即便在正午时分也黑黢黢的，是附近一带猫头鹰的栖息之地。此处遍布水坑和泥潭，有些区域则杂草丛生、青苔铺地。绿色的地面常常会骗住行路人的眼睛，使得他会一脚踏入黑泥潭里窒息而亡。这儿还有许多黑乎乎的、污浊的池塘，成为蝌蚪、牛蛙以及水蛇的家园。松树和铁杉的树干半泡在水里，一半已腐烂，看上去就像睡在泥坑里的鳄鱼一样。

穿过这座险恶的林子，汤姆小心翼翼地择路而行，走啊走，走了许久。深深的泥沼里有着一丛丛的灯芯草和树根可以充当落脚点，但这样的落脚点极其危险，他踏上去时总是提心吊胆。有时，他又会像猫似的，沿着倒下来的树干谨慎前行；时不时会有一只鸬鹚突然尖叫一声，或者一只野鸭呱呱一声长鸣，从荒凉的池塘里飞起，弄得他吃惊不小。最终，他总算踏上了一块结实的土地，此处像个半岛，深入沼泽的腹地。想当年，印第安人同第一批殖民者交战，这儿曾是他们的一个据点。在此，他们建起了一种堡垒，自以为几乎牢不可破，于是便将这儿作为他们妻儿老小的避难所。如今，印第安人的那座堡垒只剩下了几段残垣断壁，而这些残垣和断壁也在逐渐消失，变得跟周围的土地一样平，几处已长满了橡树和其他的树木——这些树木的枝叶跟沼泽里的那些阴森的松树及铁杉树形成了鲜明的对比。

汤姆·沃克走到这座古老的堡垒时，已是暮色苍茫。他留住脚步，想休息休息。除了他，换上谁也不会愿意在这荒凉凄惨的地方歇脚的。跟印第安人打仗时流传下来一些故事，于是一般人都将此处视为不祥之地。据说，那些野蛮人曾经在这儿行法念咒，曾用活人祭祀恶鬼。然而，汤姆·沃克却不信邪，根本不害怕这样的故事。他坐在一棵倒下来的铁杉树树干上休息了一会儿，一边听着蟾蜍那不祥的叫声，一边用手杖向脚边的一堆黑土里捅了捅。他下意识地用手杖将土翻起，谁知手杖碰到了一样硬硬的东西。随即，他把那东西从那堆腐殖土里挖了出来。老天爷，面前的那玩意儿竟然是个裂开的人的头骨，头骨里深深嵌着一把印第安战斧！战斧锈迹斑斑，看得出这致命的一击发生在很久以前。这是一件悲惨的纪念品，纪念这印第安武士的最后据点曾发生过的那场惨烈的战斗。

“哼！” 汤姆·沃克鼻子哼了一声，照着头骨踢了一脚，想把上面的泥土踢掉。

“别碰那头骨！”一个瓮声瓮气的声音说。

汤姆抬起头来，看见一个黑铁塔般的汉子坐在他正对面的树桩上。他惊讶万分，因为他压根就没有看见有人走过来，也没听见过脚步声呀。而更叫他困惑的是：在越来越浓的暮色里，他发现这个陌生人既不是黑人也不是印第安人。此人身穿半印第安式的粗布衣服，腰间系一条红皮带（或布带），一张脸既不是纯黑色的，亦不是古铜色，他的那种黑像是用烟熏过、炭涂过，仿佛长年劳作于打铁炉和熔炉旁造成的。他的头发又黑又粗，乱蓬蓬的，全都竖起来，肩上扛着一把斧头。只见他皱起眉头，瞪圆那双发红的大眼睛，将汤姆打量了一番，然后用瓮声瓮气的粗哑的声音喝问：“你来我的地面有何贵干？”

“你的地面？”汤姆冷笑了一声说，“这地方不属于你，也不属于我，而是属于教堂执事皮博迪。”

“就让教堂执事皮博迪下地狱去吧。”陌生人说，“如果他不多想想自己的罪孽，不对周围的人宽容一些，我敢肯定他终究会有那么一天的。你瞧瞧那边，就知道他会有什么样的结局了。”

汤姆顺着陌生人手指的方向望去，看见了一棵大树——那大树外表枝繁叶茂，漂漂亮亮，但树心已经腐烂，几乎被拦腰砍断，来一阵狂风很可能就会将其刮倒。树皮上刻着教堂执事皮博迪的名字。该执事地位显赫，跟印第安人做买卖很刻薄，发了大财。汤姆环顾四周，发现那些高树上大多都刻着殖民时期某个伟人的名字，多多少少都被斧头砍过，均带有斧痕。他屁股底下坐的这棵树显然刚被砍倒不久，上面刻着克劳宁希尔德的名字。他想起这是一个富翁的名字，此人富得流油，经常俗不可耐地炫耀他的财富，而人们却背地里说他的钱是当海盗抢来的。

“他就要被当柴烧了！”黑汉一面说，一面得意地哼了一声，“你看得到，这儿柴源丰盛，够冬天烧的了。”

“这是教堂执事皮博迪的树木，你有什么权利砍倒己用？”汤姆问。

“我有的是优先权，”对方说，“你们白种人未来之前，这片林子是属于我的。”

“恕我斗胆问一声，你究竟是何人？”汤姆说道。

“我嘛，名字多着呢。有的地方叫我‘野猎人’，有的地方叫我‘黑矿工’，而这一带叫我‘黑樵夫’。 红种人把这块地方献给了我，为了对我表示尊敬，过去每隔一段时间就会把一个白人烤熟，作为香喷喷的祭品让我吃。自从红种人被你们这些白种野蛮人赶尽杀绝之后，我无以消遣，便主导对教友会和再浸礼会教徒的迫害，从中取乐；此外，我是奴隶贩子大赞助商和促进者，也是塞勒姆女巫的大主管(1)。”

“说来说去，如果我没猜错的话，你恐怕就是人们所传的恶魔喽。”汤姆不卑不亢地说。

“一点不错，愿意听你吩咐！”黑汉一面回答，一面彬彬有礼地微微点了点头。

按照古老的传说，他们的会见就是这样开始的，只是太亲热了些，令人难以相信。有人会觉得，在这么一个荒凉偏僻的地方，冷不丁碰上个怪人，无论谁都会被吓得魂不附体。岂不知汤姆却是个胆壮的硬汉，和母老虎妻子在一个房檐下生活多年，甚至见了魔鬼也不害怕了。

据说，在这么一番开场白之后，黑汉一边送他回家，一边和他长谈，很是热情。黑汉告诉他海盗基德曾在离沼泽不远的那高高的山岗上埋了许多财宝，就埋在那些橡树底下。那些财宝全归他支配和保护，他看不上眼的人，谁都别想找得到。由于对汤姆特别有好感，他愿意让汤姆得到这些财宝，但必须叫汤姆答应几个条件。究竟是什么条件，汤姆虽然从来也没有公开透露过，却不难猜得出。反正条件一定是很苛刻的，因为汤姆要求考虑一段时间再作答复。按说，在有钱可赚的时候，他对小事是不会斤斤计较的。他们俩走到沼泽的边上，陌生人收住了脚步。

“用什么来证明你说的是实情呢？”汤姆问。

“我在这儿按个手印为证吧。”黑汉说着，用手指在汤姆的额头上点了一下，然后转身回到了沼泽的树丛当中。据汤姆回忆说，眼见得他一点一点朝地里沉去，后来只能看得见头和肩膀，最终便消失得无影无踪了。

汤姆回到家里，发自己前额上有个黑指头印子，好像是烙上去的，无论用什么东西都擦不掉。

妻子一见他就告诉他一条消息，说那个富得流油的海盗阿布萨龙·克劳宁希尔德突然死了。报纸上已有讣告，用的仍是那种冠冕堂皇的词：“在上帝的子民中，一个伟大的人物倒下去了。”

这让汤姆想起了黑汉刚刚砍倒的那棵树，说是要当柴禾烧掉的。于是他便对妻子说：“就让那海盗化为灰烬吧，管他呢！”现在，他已经完全相信自己所听到的话以及所看到的情况并非幻想出来的。

按说，他是不愿意向妻子敞开心扉、说出心里话的，但这个秘密搅得他不得安宁，于是也就乐得跟她分享了。妻子一听说有藏宝，立刻就泛起了满肚子的贪欲，劝说丈夫答应黑汉的条件，把那些可以叫他们阔气一辈子的东西弄到手。汤姆也许愿意把自己出卖给魔鬼，但不愿意顺从妻子的意愿，于是便反其道而行之，断然拒绝那样做。二人为此争吵不休，每次吵得都不可开交。但妻子越吵，汤姆的意志越坚定，觉得决不能叫她得逞。

最后，妻子决定亲自出马促成这笔交易，如果成功，所有的财宝都归她一人独享。她和丈夫一样，也是个天不怕地不怕的主儿，于是在一个夏日的黄昏便动身到那座古老的印第安堡垒去了。这一去就去了好几个小时。待她回到家中，少言寡语，回话时一副闷闷不乐的样子。她说自己在暮色里遇见一个黑汉，那黑汉正在用斧头砍一棵大树的树根。对方满脸的不高兴，不愿意跟她谈条件；她还得再去一趟，这次去要带些见面礼，但具体是什么见面礼她却不肯说。

次日黄昏，她又到沼泽地里去了，围裙里包了一些沉甸甸的东西。汤姆等了又等，总是不见她回来，到了半夜，仍不见她的影子。第二天，早晨、中午和夜晚过去了，她仍没有归来。汤姆渐渐为她的安全感到有点担心，等他发现她用围裙把银茶壶、银匙子和一切细软值钱的东西都包了去的时候，心里便更加不安了。又过了一夜，又到了早晨，仍不见妻子返家。总而言之，她如泥牛入海，一去便没有了音讯。

至于她遭遇到了什么样的命运，虽然许多人声称自己了解内情，其实无人知道。历史学家们各抒己见、众说纷纭，把这件事搅成了一团乱麻。有的说她走进迷宫一样的沼泽地里，顿时迷失了方向，最后陷进水坑或泥潭里丧了命；有的则更加无情，说她带着家里的细软远走高飞，到别的省份享清福去了；有的说魔鬼迷了她的心窍，骗得她陷进了泥沼，人们在泥沼上发现了她的帽子可以作为证据。事实胜于雄辩——据说，在那天的黄昏时分，有人看见一个黑铁塔般的汉子肩扛利斧从沼泽地里走了出来，手中提着个包成包袱的格子花布围裙，得意扬扬的，一脸的邪气。

不过，最流行的也最可信的说法是：汤姆·沃克当时既为妻子感到担心，又为那些细软牵肠挂肚，最后只好出发前去印第安堡垒看个究竟。夏日的下午比较长，他就在那个阴森森的地方四处寻找，但一无所获。他喊着妻子的名字，一声又一声，然而听不见妻子的回应声。回答他的只有飞过的鸬鹚那凄厉的的叫声，或者牛蛙从附近池塘里传来的悲哀的呱呱声。据说，到了最后，在一片苍茫的暮色里，猫头鹰开始怪叫，蝙蝠飞来飞去，他的注意力突然被一群专吃腐肉的乌鸦吸引了去，只见那群乌鸦哇哇叫着在一棵柏树的上空盘旋。他定睛一瞧，看见一个格子花布包袱吊在树枝上面，近旁有一只巨大无比的秃鹫，似乎在看管那个包袱。他认出那是妻子的围裙，断定家里的细软就包在里面，于是高兴得跳了起来。

“先把东西拿到手再说，”他欣慰地自言自语道，“没有那女人照样能过日子。”

他噌噌地爬上树，而那只秃鹫展开巨大的翅膀，尖叫一声飞向了阴影幢幢的密林深处。他一把抓住那个格子花布包袱，打开一看却惊呆了——里面什么也没有，只有一颗心和一个肝脏！

根据最可信的说法，汤姆的妻子不见了，只剩下了这些。她很可能做过尝试，想用通常对付丈夫的那一套对付黑汉。一般人都认为一个恶女人敌得过魔鬼，然而在这次争锋中，此女似乎大祸临头了。她一定是经过殊死搏斗才不幸遇难的——据说，汤姆在大树跟前发现了许多深深的脚印和一把一把又粗又黑的头发，看样子那头发是从黑樵夫头上抓下来的。通过实践，汤姆深知妻子的神力。见了这又抓又掐短兵相接的惨烈搏斗留下的痕迹，他不禁耸了耸肩膀，叹一声：“哎哟哟，魔鬼准是吃了不少苦头！”

汤姆虽然痛失家中细软，但妻子的死却给了他一些安慰。他毕竟是个豁达的人，甚至对那个黑樵夫还有几分感激呢，觉得黑樵夫为他做了件好事。于是，他想把自己跟黑樵夫的交情深化深化，可他千找万找都找不到对方。那个黑鬼倒是非常谨慎的，不管别人怎么想，反正他可不是想见就能见的主儿。他善于把握时机，知道怎么出牌。

据说，最后由于迟迟找不到黑樵夫，汤姆焦躁到了极点，决定不管什么条件都会答应，只要能把那笔财宝拿到手即可。就在这时，在一天黄昏时分，他和黑樵夫不期而遇了——对方仍是樵夫打扮，肩扛利斧，在沼泽边转悠，嘴里哼着小调。他见了汤姆，对汤姆表现出的热情反应冷淡，爱答不理地回着话，一边继续哼着小调。

不过，汤姆渐渐引得他谈起了正事，二人针对协助汤姆弄到海盗财宝的条件进行了讨价还价。其中有一个条件是无须说的，因为大家都知道，凡是遇到魔鬼施恩于人，都会有这么一条。然而还有其他的一些条件，虽不那么重要，黑汉却坚决不肯让步。他认为：他帮助汤姆弄到钱财，那么，这笔钱财就得为他服务。因而，他提出让汤姆把钱用于贩奴，具体说，就是用这笔钱备办一条运黑奴的轮船。而汤姆却予以斩钉截铁的拒绝。他固然是个十恶不赦的坏蛋，但就连魔鬼也别指望诱使他染指于贩奴。

鹰鬼见汤姆在这一点上寸步不让，也就不再坚持了，接着便提出了一个代替的方案——让汤姆成为一个放高利贷的人。魔鬼急于招募放高利贷的人，将其视为自己特殊的人才。

对于这项提议，汤姆没有反对，因为这正中他的下怀。

“你下个月就在波土顿开一家交易店铺。”黑汉说。

“如果你愿意，我明天就开。”汤姆·沃克说。

“放贷出去，月息二分利。”

“哎呀，我要收四分利！”汤姆·沃克说。

“你要把那些商人的债券拿到手里，取消他们赎回抵押品的权利，逼得他们倾家荡产……”

“我要逼得他们下地狱！” 汤姆·沃克迫不及待地叫嚷道。

“为我放贷，你可真是个理想人才！”黑汉充满喜悦地说，“什么时候把那笔钱财交给你？”

“就在今晚。”

“一言为定！”魔鬼说。

“一言为定！”汤姆·沃克说。

接下来，二人握手，这笔生意就算成交了。

几天后，汤姆·沃克在波士顿开了家钱庄，自己当了掌柜。他手中有现钱，谁肯付高利息，他就借给谁，于是名声鹊起，而这消息不胫而走。贝尔彻总督(2)执政时期现金奇缺，至今人们对当时的情况仍记忆犹新。那时候，各种票据满天飞，政府发行的债券泛滥成灾。闻名于天下的“土地银行”就是在那时成立的。当时，投机的浪潮一浪高过一浪；人们发了疯似的开拓新移民区，在荒野里建城镇；地皮经纪人手拿绘制着租地、城镇及“黄金国”(3)的地图，四处兜揽生意——谁都不知道地图上的那些地方究竟在何处，但人人都愿意花钱购买。简而言之，投机的热潮此起彼伏，每隔一段时间就爆发一次，其热度达到了叫人瞠目的地步——人人都想白手起家，人人都想一夜致富。照例，一旦高烧消退，美梦破灭，幻想中的钱财化为泡影，发高烧的病人便会陷入悲惨的境地，四面八方都有人在哀叹：“世道难呀！”

就在这群情沮丧的大吉大利之时，汤姆·沃克在波士顿做起了高利贷的生意。很快，顾客便纷至沓来。其中有急需用钱、不惜冒险的人，有孤注一掷的投机商，有怀揣梦想的地皮经纪人，有不知节省的小商贩，有贷款无门的生意人——一句话，凡是走投无路、不惜任何代价都需要借钱的人，纷纷找上门来向汤姆·沃克借贷。

于是，汤姆就成了落难人公认的朋友，行为举止上也是一副“患难之交”的样子。话又说回来，他历来要求对方付出高额的利息和可观的保证金。申请人的灾难愈是深重，他的条件也就愈加苛刻。他敛聚了许多债券和许多抵押品，一点点把顾客的油全部榨干，干得就像被挤干了水的海绵，最后将他们一脚踢开。马车行驶时，由于不给车轴上油，车轮会咯吱咯吱呻吟个不停，你听了准会以为那是受他压榨的可怜的负债人的灵魂在哀号。

可是，等到汤姆老了以后，心事也逐渐重了。在现世，金银财宝都有了，他开始为来世发愁。想起自己跟黑汉朋友定下的交易条件，他便后悔不已，处心积虑想哄一哄黑汉，不去履行那些条件。于是乎，他突然间变成了一个热心上教堂做礼拜的人。祷告时，他大嗓门、高音量，仿佛要靠肺部的力量才能进天堂似的。实际上，你只要听他在哪个星期天祈祷时声音最高，就可以由此判断他这一星期造的孽最深。那些不声不响、一直在谦逊而坚定地走向天国的基督徒，看到自己竟然在这条路上，被这位新近皈依的教徒领了先，不由倍加自责。汤姆对待宗教，像对待钱财一样一丝不苟。他严厉地监督着邻居，动辄便严加斥责，似乎给邻人的账本上记一项罪名，就可以转化为他自己功劳簿上的一桩功德似的。他甚至主张恢复对教友会和再浸礼会教徒的迫害。总之，他对宗教的热忱变得和他的财富一样出了名。

不过，尽管汤姆异常注重宗教形式，内心却担惊受怕，唯恐魔鬼到底还是会找上门算账的。据说，为了避免魔鬼趁他冷不防将他抓走，他就在外套口袋里常备一本小开本《圣经》，还在钱庄的柜台上放一本巨大的对开本的《圣经》——上门的顾客常见他诵经不止。见有人来，他会摘下绿颜色的眼镜放在书上，作为读到那里的标记，然后转过身来洽谈高利贷生意。

有些人说，汤姆暮年时有点精神错乱，幻想着自己的末日即将来临，叫人给他的马换了新马掌，备了马鞍，拴了缰绳，然后把它四蹄朝天活埋掉，因为他认为到了末日，这个世界会颠倒过来。这样，他就会发现他那匹马直端端站立在那儿，让他随时都可以骑走。他打定主意，要在最糟糕的情况出现时一跑了之，远离他的那位老朋友。不过，这很可能只不过是老太太们的闲聊罢了。他要是真的采取了这样的预防措施，那完全是多此一举。最起码，那个可信的古老传说所讲的情况并非如此，而是以如下方式结束他的人生经历的：

那是一个热得要死的季节，在一个热烘烘的下午，黑云压顶，狂风暴雨眼看就要来临。汤姆头戴白纱帽，身穿印度丝绸晨衣，端坐于钱庄。当时， 他正要取消一个倒霉的土地投机商人赎回抵押品的权利。他口口声声说自己跟这位投机商交情很厚，而此时的目的却是要叫对方彻底破产。那个地皮经纪人苦苦哀求，让他宽限几个月，这一下惹恼了汤姆，使得他气不打一处来，声称连一天也不宽限。

“这会叫我倾家荡产，到济贫院靠施舍过日子的。”地皮经纪人说。

“慈悲要从自家开始，”汤姆回答道，“世道艰难，我得先照料好自己呀。”

“你从我身上已经赚了不少钱了。”那位投机商说。

汤姆耐不住性子，连平时装出的虔诚教徒的面子也不顾了，说道：“我要是赚过你一分钱，那就让魔鬼把我抓走好啦！”

他话音刚落，就听见临街的大门有人叩了三下，声音很大。他走出去看是什么人，只见那个黑汉站在门外，手里牵着一匹黑马，那黑马嘶鸣不已，焦躁得四蹄乱跳。

“汤姆，我今天来是来找你的！”黑汉粗声粗气地说。

汤姆急缩身想溜走，但为时已晚。小本《圣经》被他忘在外套口袋里了，而那个大本的《圣经》丢在了柜台上，就放在他正要勾销的抵押凭证的下面。没有哪个罪人比他更狼狈了，在完全没有防备的情况下被魔鬼抓了个正着。只见那黑汉像老鹰抓小鸡一样把他拎起来放在马鞍上，狠狠抽了马一鞭子，于是那马便驮着汤姆，冒着雷雨疾驰而去。钱庄的雇员们耳朵后夹着铅笔，一个个目瞪口呆地从窗户那儿望着他的背影。汤姆·沃克走了，骑着马在大街上飞奔，白帽子上下一颠一颠的，晨衣迎风飘荡，坐下骑风驰电掣，每跳跃一下，路面就会溅起一些火星。待雇员们再去看黑汉，他早已不见了踪影。

汤姆·沃克再也没有回来勾销那张抵押凭证。有个住在沼泽旁边的乡下人后来谈起这事，说那天雷雨下得正猛的时候，他听见大路那边传来震天动地的马蹄声和人的哀号声。他跑到窗前，看到一个人骑在马上发疯似的在野外狂奔，一如我刚才描述的那样，翻过山丘，一头钻进黑黢黢的长满了铁杉树的沼泽地，朝着那个古老的印第安堡垒冲去。随即，那个方向亮起一道闪电，似乎让整个林子都燃起了熊熊大火。

波士顿的老百姓听了只是摇摇头、耸耸肩，并没有像普通人所想象的那样恐慌，因为自从殖民时期第一批移民来到此处起，便有各种关于巫婆、妖怪以及千变万化的魔鬼的传说，人们早已见怪不怪了。他们立刻委托了几个人料理汤姆的财产。可是，他所有的财产都化为了乌有，不需要人料理了。他们检查他的保险箱，发现里面所有的债券和抵押凭证都成了灰烬；铁箱子里装的金条银锭变成了碎木片和刨花；马厩里两匹饿得半死的马成了两具骷髅。就在第二天，他家偌大的府邸陷于一片火海之中，被烧成了废墟。

*　*　*

汤姆·沃克和他的不义之财最后落得了这个下场。希望贪财者将这个故事记在心里，以此为训。此故事的真实性不容怀疑。汤姆·沃克从橡树底下掘出基德的财宝，所留下的那个坑至今仍可以看得见。在狂风暴雨的夜晚，经常有一道骑在马背上的鬼影出没于临近的沼泽以及那个古老的印第安堡垒，那鬼影身穿晨衣、头戴白帽——毫无疑问，这是那个高利贷商人的灵魂得不到安宁，跑出来作祟。实际上，这个故事已经变成一句俗语，即“魔鬼和汤姆·沃克”，广泛流传于新英格兰。

————————————————————

(1) 塞勒姆小镇位于波士顿以北25公里处，被人称为“女巫城”。早在1692年有一场声名狼藉的女巫审判，当时小镇上1500人口当中，有150人被误认为女巫而被吊死。

(2) 美国独立战争发生之前马萨诸塞和新泽西的总督。

(3) 1535年，曾经远征过印加帝国的西班牙人塞瓦斯蒂安·德·贝拉卡萨曾遇到一个印第安人，那个印第安人对他说，在远方有个地方黄金遍地，那儿的各种东西都是用黄金做的。后来，人们把那个神秘的地方称为黄金国。

阿拉伯占星家的传说

古时候，在好几百年以前，有一位名叫阿本·哈布兹的摩尔王统治着格拉纳达(1)王国。他是个有退隐之心的征服者——这就是说，他年轻时攻城略地、掳掠抢夺，如今年老体衰、意志薄弱，“渴望过安宁的日子”，别无所求，只求与别的国家和平共处，保持住自己的荣誉，安安稳稳地享受从邻国掠夺来的财物。

但事不凑巧，就这么一个极端通情达理、爱好和平的老国王，却偏偏要对付一些年轻气盛的敌手——那些年轻的王侯跟他从前一样好名、好战，一心要找他算账，了结他和他们父辈之间的恩怨。他精力旺盛的时候，曾用高压手段对付国内的一些边远地区，现在他渴望过安宁的日子，那些地区却起来造反，声称要将他围困在都城，使他成为瓮中之鳖。此时的他四面受敌。格拉纳达的周围净是险峻的荒山野岭，易于掩蔽敌军的动向，于是这位不幸的阿本·哈布兹国王时时都提心吊胆，真不知敌人会从哪儿突然冒出来。

他在各山头都建有瞭望塔，各隘口都派兵把守，命令一旦敌军出现就报警——夜间燃火，白日放烟，但这些终归是徒劳。他的敌人诡计多端，让他所有的防范措施一一落空，往往会从他意想不到的山谷里钻出来，就在他的眼皮底下蹂躏他的国土，然后带着俘虏和财物返回群山里。这个渴望安宁、意欲退隐的征服者处境极为艰难，如坐针毡。

正当阿本·哈布兹不胜其扰，被敌军的进犯搅得焦头烂额的时候，一位年老的阿拉伯术士飘然而至，来到了他的王宫里。他的白胡子一直垂至腰间，处处看得出他已是古稀高龄，而他却是一路从埃及走来，几乎未乘任何车马，仅靠一根刻着象形文字的手杖助他行路。他人未至，大名早已传到。此人名叫伊伯拉西姆·伊本·阿布·阿尤伯；据说当穆罕默德(2)在世的时候，就有他了；身为阿布·阿尤伯之子，他是先知最后的一个侍从。童年时，他曾随着阿姆鲁(3)的讨伐军进驻埃及，在埃及居住多年，跟着埃及祭司学习巫术，尤其是研习魔法。

另外，据说他还发现了长寿的秘诀，一直活到现在，已有两百多岁的高龄。不过，长寿的秘决是他在暮年时才发现的，于是，灰白头发和皱纹便保留了下来。

国王给了这位年老的奇人很高的礼遇，这位国王跟大多数衰老的帝王一样，十分宠信术士，想让他住在王宫里。然而，这位占星家却宁愿住在格拉纳达城近旁山坡上的一个岩洞里，也就是后来建了阿尔罕布拉宫(4)的山上。他叫人扩建岩洞，使之成为一个宽宽敞敞、气势宏伟的大厅，顶部开一个圆孔，像井口一般，可以从那儿观察天象，甚至在正午也能够望得见星辰。大厅的墙上刻满了埃及的象形文字、神秘的符号和星座图。他亲自指导格拉纳达的能工巧匠制作了许多仪器放置在大厅里，而这些仪器的神秘功能只有他一人知晓。

过了没多久，智者伊伯拉西姆就成了国王的心腹顾问，每逢有什么紧急情况，国王便向他请教。一次，阿本·哈布兹痛斥他的邻邦，说他们公理难容，哀叹自己被搅得日夜难安，必须时刻保持警惕，以防受到入侵。等他说完之后，占星家半天没言语，过了一会儿才回话说：“启奏陛下，我在埃及的时候，曾见过一种奇异的神器，是古代的一个女祭司发明的。波尔沙城附近有座山，从山顶可以俯瞰尼罗河大峡谷，山顶上有一只公羊，公羊的背上站着只公鸡，羊和鸡都是铜铸的，安在一根轴上，可以转动。一旦国家受到威胁，有敌来犯，公羊便会转过头，朝着敌军出现的方向，而公鸡则会啼叫。由此，城里的居民就会知道有险情出现，而且知道险情来自哪个方向，这样就能及时采取防范措施。”

“真主在上！”一心想过安静日子的阿本·哈布兹不由高声说道，“如果有一只这样的公羊为我观察周围群山里的动静，再有一只这样的公鸡遇到险情就啼叫，那可真是无价之宝呀！真主至大！有这样的哨兵在山顶站岗放哨，我在王宫里便可以高枕无忧了！”

占星家等到国王的狂热劲儿过去之后，才又继续说道：

“在战无不胜的阿姆鲁（愿他的英灵安息！）征服了埃及之后，我就留了下来，跟着他们的祭司熟悉他们的偶像崇拜，研习其中的规则和仪式，为的是能够掌握他们那举世闻名的神秘知识。一天，我坐在尼罗河边和一位年老的祭司聊天，他指着附近沙漠上那些似巍巍高山一般耸立的宏伟的金字塔，说道：‘许多知识都埋藏在那些金字塔里，与之相比，我们所能传授给你的知识便是小巫见大巫了。当中的那座金字塔里有一间墓室，而当初协助建造这座雄伟金字塔的那位祭司的木乃伊就安息在那里；和他葬在一起的还有一本神奇的书，书里包罗万象，涵盖了所有魔法和巫术的秘密。此书是天书，是亚当被贬到人间时带来的，后来代代相传，传到了智慧王所罗门的手里，所罗门按照此书的指点建起了耶路撒冷神庙。至于它怎么会落到造金字塔的那个人手里，那就只有无所不知的上天知道了。’

“听了那个埃及祭司的一席话，当时我心里升腾起一团火，一心想把那本书搞到手。征伐军里的许多士兵和许多埃及的本地人，我是可以指挥得动的。于是我说干就干，指挥他们凿穿金字塔上的坚硬石块，费尽千辛万苦，进入金字塔的内部，在那儿发现了一条秘密甬道。沿着甬道一路向前，穿过一个可怕的迷宫，我终于深入到了金字塔的中心，而且找到了那个墓室——那个大祭司的木乃伊在那儿安息了不知有多少个年头了。我破开棺椁，解开木乃伊身上那一层层的包布和绷带，终于从他怀里找到了那本宝书。我用颤抖的手一把抓起书，一路摸索着到了金字塔外面，把那个木乃伊丢在黑暗的墓室里，让他在那儿等着末日的复活和最后审判。”

“阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，”阿本·哈布兹嚷嚷道，“你是个伟大的旅行家，见到过不少奇异的现象。可是，无论是金字塔的秘密，还是智慧所罗门王的那本天书，对我又有什么用呢？”

“对你是有用的，国王陛下！正是研究了那本书，我掌握了魔法，能够遣神使鬼，让他们为我所用。我还了解了波尔沙城那个神器的秘诀，不仅能造出同样的神器，而且能造出威力更大的。”

“大智大慧的阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，”阿本·哈布兹高声叫道，“有这样的神器，远胜于山顶上的瞭望塔以及边境上的哨兵。快快为我建起这样的安全保障吧，国库里的财富供你随便使用。”

占星家立刻动手造神器，以满足这位君主的愿望。他先叫人在阿尔贝辛山的山脊上的那座王宫的顶上建起一座巨大的瞭望塔。该塔用的是埃及运来的石料，据说是从一个金字塔上拆下来的。瞭望塔的上部是一个圆形大厅，四周按照罗盘所指的每个方位，开了许多窗户，每个窗口前都有一张桌子，桌上摆着一队木头雕的人马和主管这个方向的一位指挥官的木头塑像，像棋盘上那样排兵布阵。每张桌子上放着一支小矛，只有锥子那么大，上面刻着某种文字。这座大厅有一扇铜门，还有一把很大的钢锁，经常是锁起来的，钥匙由国王本人掌握。

塔顶上有一个摩尔骑士的铜像，安在一个转轴上，一只胳膊上架着个盾牌，手中的长矛呈垂直状。骑士面朝城里，似乎在保卫着这座城市。不过，一旦有敌人来犯，他便会转过身面向敌方，将长矛端平，呈冲锋状。

这件神器建成之后，阿本·哈布兹迫不及待地想试试它的威力。以前，敌人来犯，渴望安宁的他会唉声叹气，而现在他却急切盼望敌人的进犯。没多久，他的愿望就成真了。一天清晨，奉命看守瞭望塔的哨兵前来报告，说铜骑士的脸转向了埃尔维拉山，他的长矛笔直指向洛浦隘口。

“快去传令擂鼓和吹号，准备打仗，让格拉纳达全城的居民都保持警惕。”阿本·哈布兹说。

“启禀国王陛下，”占星家说，“不必惊动城里的人，也不必命令你的武士们准备战斗，咱们不必动武就可以退敌。叫侍从们都下去吧，咱们俩独自到瞭望塔的秘密大厅里去就可以了。”

年迈的阿本·哈布兹在比他年纪更大的伊伯拉西姆·伊本·阿布·阿尤伯的搀扶下，一步一步登上瞭望塔的阶梯，用钥匙打开那扇铜门，走了进去。只见面对洛浦隘口的那扇窗户敞开着。占星家说：“那儿就是险情出现的方向。请你到跟前去，国王陛下，看一看那张桌子上的秘密吧。”

阿本·哈布兹国王走到那张摆着许多小木偶的棋盘一样的桌子跟前，不由惊呆了——他发现那些小木偶全都在动。那些小木马欢腾跳跃，武士们则挥枪舞剑，隐隐约约听得到鼓号声、叮叮当当的刀剑声以及战马的嘶鸣。不过，那一片喧嚣之声，就跟一个人夏日的中午躺在阴凉地里纳凉，昏昏欲睡时耳朵里听到的蜜蜂或苍蝇的嗡嗡声差不多，微弱而模糊。

“启禀陛下，”占星家说，“这证明敌军已进入了战场。他们一定是穿过洛浦隘口，翻越群山过来的。如果你愿意在他们之间制造一些恐慌和混乱，让他们退兵，但又不造成他们的伤亡，那你就用这根魔矛的手柄敲一敲木偶；如果你想让那儿出现血流成河的大屠杀场面，那就用矛尖刺它们。”

阿本·哈布兹的脸色变得铁青，只见他浑身发抖，一把抓住了那根魔矛，踉踉跄跄地走向桌子，兴奋得连他那白胡子都一颤一颤的。“阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，”他嘿嘿一笑，高声说道，“我看还是叫他们流点血吧！”

说着，他就用魔矛向一些小木偶一阵乱刺，接着又用魔矛的把手猛敲另外的一些木偶，被刺的木偶倒地阵亡，而其余的则彼此厮杀，混战作一团。

占星家费了好大的气力才阻拦住这位追求宁静的君主，让他住了手，以免使敌人被消灭得一个不剩。末了，他好言劝说国王离开了瞭望塔，然后派侦察兵进山到洛浦隘口那儿了解情况。

侦察兵回来后，报告说有一支基督教军队曾经攻进了大山深处，眼看就要兵临格拉纳达城下，而就在此时，他们之间发生了内讧，彼此之间挥戈相向，死伤惨重，最终全部退出了边境。

抗敌神器的威力得到了验证，这叫阿本·哈布兹喜不自胜。只听他说道：“我终于能过上太平日子了，而且能叫所有的敌人都在我的掌控之中。大智大慧的阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，你给我带来了这样的好日子，我怎么报答你才好呢？”

“启禀陛下，身为一个上了年纪的人，一个哲学家，生活简单，所需不多。我别无所求，只求你给我一些东西装饰我的岩洞，以适合于我隐居，那我就心满意足了。”

“凡大智大慧者都生活节俭，真是难能可贵！”阿本·哈布兹口中赞叹不已，心里却为自己付出如此廉价的补偿而暗暗高兴。他召来司库，说伊伯拉西姆要装饰隐居处所，所需经费，要司库悉数供给。

于是，占星家吩咐工匠凿开坚硬的岩石，辟出许多房间来，形成几排和他的占星大厅相连的套房。他又叫人在各个房间里安置了许多奢华的靠背大椅子和长沙发，墙上挂起极为贵重的大马士革缎子作为饰品。他解释说：“我年纪大了，不能再让这把老骨头睡石榻了；这些石头墙太潮湿，有东西遮盖遮盖才好。”

他还吩咐人造了浴室，浴室里有各种各样的香水和芳香精油。他解释说：“要让老年人的四肢不至于僵硬，要让因为搞研究而衰弱了的躯体恢复活力和柔韧，洗洗澡是很有必要的。”

接下来，他叫人在各个房间里挂上无数的银灯和水晶灯，亲自按照从埃及墓穴中得来的方子配了一种香油盛在灯里。这种油点亮后长明不熄，发出的光很柔和，类似强弱适度的白昼之光。他解释说：“太阳光对于老年人来说太刺眼、太强烈了。再说，这种灯光对哲学家搞研究是比较适宜的。”

阿本·哈布兹国王的司库见装饰占星家的隐居处所每日所需数目巨大，不由暗暗叫苦，于是便跑去向国王诉说。不过，阿本·哈布兹觉得君子一言驷马难追，只好耸了耸肩说：“必须有耐心。这老头是想根据金字塔的内部结构以及埃及宏伟的古迹打造一个哲人的隐居所。不过，无论什么事都有个结束，他的岩洞终究会装修完的。”

果不其然，占星家的隐居处最后终于竣工了。这儿简直成了一个奢华的地下宫殿。占星家对此表示十分满意，之后三天闭门不出，埋头于自己的研究工作。过完这段时间，他又跑去见司库，说道：“还有一样东西是不可少的，它能在我脑力劳动之余给我带来一点安慰。”

“大智大慧的伊伯拉西姆，我奉命提供你过隐居生活所需要的一切东西。这次你需要的是什么东西呢？”

“我想要几个舞女。”

“什么，要舞女！”司库惊讶得叫出了声。

“对，是要舞女，”这位圣人语气庄重地回答说，“要年轻漂亮的。看到青春和美色能叫人精神焕发。只要几个就够了，因为我是一个生活简朴的哲学家，很容易满足。”

当哲学家伊伯拉西姆·伊本·阿布·阿尤伯以圣人的方式在隐居所里安然度日时，追求平静的阿本·哈布兹则在瞭望塔里操纵着木偶激战不已。这简直太奇妙了——一个像他这样过惯了安逸日子的老人，竟然能把战争变成儿戏，坐在房间里自娱自乐，举手便可叫一支大军灰飞烟灭，简单得就跟杀灭苍蝇一样。

有一段时间，他沉浸在战争游戏中，变得恣意妄为起来，甚至嘲弄和羞辱自己的邻邦，挑逗他们来犯。邻邦们屡犯屡败，逐渐学乖了，最后无人敢来侵犯他的领土了。一连好几个月，铜骑士一直保持着和平状态——矛头指向天空；这位尊贵的老国王无从玩自己玩惯了的游戏，不禁感到不耐烦了，生活无风无浪、单调乏味，让他觉得厌倦。

后来有一天，神器铜骑士突然转了方向，将手中的长矛放低，矛尖一动不动地指向瓜狄克斯山。阿本·哈布兹急忙爬上瞭望塔，可是朝着那个方向的魔桌却一点动静也没有，桌上的武士纹丝不动。这种情况叫他大惑不解，于是他便派了一支骑兵去山里侦察。骑兵去了三天之后，回来说：

“我们检查了每一条山道，没有见铠甲也没有见刀枪舞动，一路百般搜索，只发现了一个基督教的绝色少女。当时是中午时分，该女子正在泉水旁睡觉，我们把她抓住带了来。”

“抓到一个绝色美女！”阿本·哈布兹激动得两眼闪射出异彩，不由叫出了声，“快带她来见我！”

那个有倾城倾国之色的少女被带了来。她戴着许多奢华的装饰品——在阿拉伯人征服西班牙期间，这样的装饰在西班牙哥特人中间是很流行的。只见她一头乌云一般的披肩长发，秀发上点缀着无数雪白耀目的珍珠，前额上有几枚宝石在闪闪发光，和她的一双美眸发出的光彩不相上下。她的脖子上挂着一条金链，金链上吊一把银质的小竖琴，而那小竖琴垂至腰间。

她那水汪汪的乌黑的眼睛闪闪发光，犹如将火花溅到了阿本·哈布兹那虽然衰老但仍多情的心上；她轻举莲步，妖妖娆娆，使得他神魂颠倒。“绝代的佳人呀，”他心醉神迷地叫了起来，“你究竟是何人，是干什么的？”

“我是一个哥特王储的女儿。不久前，家父还统治一方。可是，他的军队像中了魔法一样，在这群山之中被消灭了个干净。如今，家父流亡他乡，而他的女儿成了俘虏。”

“当心，陛下！”伊伯拉西姆·伊本·阿布·阿尤伯悄声说，“她恐怕就是常听人们说起的北方女巫，善作媚态以迷惑不明就里的人。我觉得她的眼里有一股妖气，一举一动都暗藏邪术。毫无疑问，她就是铜骑士所指的敌人。”

“阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，”国王回应道，“你是个大智大慧的人，这我可以肯定，也许还是个魔术师，可是你在了解女人方面却是个外行。在这方面，我的能力不输于任何人，甚至不输于智慧的所罗门本人，别看他有那么多王后妃嫔。若说这个少女，我看她并无害人之心。她天姿国色，深得我的宠爱。”

“请听臣下一言，陛下！”占星家说，“靠着我的神器，陛下屡战屡胜，而我却从未分享过任何战利品。这次，就把这个流离失所的俘虏赐给臣下吧，让她用银质的小竖琴给孤独寂寞的我以抚慰。如果她真的是个女巫，我也有驱巫之策，能够施法消除她的妖力。”

“怎么！还要女人！”阿本·哈布兹嚷嚷了起来，“不是已经给你舞女了，还不够抚慰你吗？”

“固然有舞女了，此话不虚，然而却没有歌女。辛勤研究之后身心疲惫，我很想有个小歌女能叫我精神焕发。”

“你可不要贪得无厌，隐士！”国王耐不住性子，这样说道，“这个少女我要留给我自己。她给我带来了极大的安慰，甚至不亚于美女亚比煞(5)给智慧的所罗门之父大卫王所带来的欢乐。”

不管占星家再怎么苦苦哀求和劝说，国王只是不答应，回绝的口气愈加坚定，最后二人不欢而散。圣人把自己关在他的隐居所里，左想右想，感到特别失望。不过，他在离开国王那儿时，又对国王提出了警示，要他当心那个危险的俘虏。可是，一个坠入情网的老人怎么能听得进去别人的劝告呢？阿本·哈布兹为情所累，早已被迷得颠三倒四，全部的心思都放在了那个哥特美人身上，千方百计想赢得对方的芳心。他固然已青春不再，但是他有金银财宝。一个老人要是有了心上人，一般都出手大方。他派人到格拉纳达的市场上去，将那儿最贵重的东方珍品都搜刮了来。绸缎、珠宝、珍贵的宝石、精制的香水——凡是亚非两大陆所出产的奇珍异宝，他都毫不吝惜地赠给这位落难的公主。城里举办各种表演和庆祝活动，供美人观看；轻歌曼舞，竞技斗牛——格拉纳达一时盛会不断、热闹非凡。对于这般盛大的场面，哥特公主处之泰然，似乎早已习惯了奢华的生活。她把一切都视为对她身份的尊重，或者更确切地说，是对她美丽容貌的崇拜——对女人而言，美丽的容貌甚至胜过高贵的身份，更应该得到崇拜。不但如此，她似乎暗中以此为乐，故意刺激国王挥霍无度，消耗他的国库；对于国王的骄奢淫逸，她好像觉得很自然。尽管这位位高权重的恋人殷勤慷慨，却好像并没有赢得美人的芳心。美人固然没有横眉冷对，却也没有笑脸相迎。每当他向美人倾诉衷肠时，对方都会弹起她那银制的小竖琴。琴声里有一种魔力，让国王立刻就打起瞌睡，睡意袭遍全身，随后便昏昏睡去。醒来后，他感到神清气爽，然而情欲却悄然消退。他的求爱虽然受挫，但昏睡中总有美梦陪伴，使这位梦中恋人心醉神迷。于是他一个梦接一个梦，沉迷其中，而格拉纳达全城都在嘲笑他的痴情；看到他为一曲轻歌一掷千金，民怨为之沸腾。

最后，危险终于降临在了阿本·哈布兹的头上，而他那神器没有发出任何警告。他的都城里突然发生了暴乱，手持刀枪的暴民们把他的王宫围得水泄不通，扬言要他的命，并处死他的基督徒情人。这位君主旧有的好战精神在他的心中死灰复燃，于是他率领一队卫兵冲上前去，杀得暴民们作鸟兽散，将一场暴乱摧毁于萌芽之中。

暴乱平息之后，他前去见占星家，而后者仍在隐居所里闭门不出，心里对他恨恨不已。

阿本·哈布兹步上前，以和解的语气说道：“大智大慧的阿布·阿尤伯之子呀，你曾经预言说这个俘虏来的美女会给我带来危险，而今这一预言得到了应验。既然你料事如神，请你告诉我怎样才能防患于未然呢？”

“那个异教徒少女是祸根。应该离开她。”

“那我宁肯放弃我的江山。”阿本·哈布兹高声说道。

“那你会面临危险，江山和美人都保不住。”占星家答道。

“知识最为渊博的哲学家呀，请别如此严厉，不要发火生气。我既是国王，又是个坠入爱河的人，请考虑一下我的双重苦恼，想出一个万全之策保护我，让我远离灾难。其实我并不在乎荣华富贵，也不在乎权力，只渴望平安度日，避开纷扰的尘世，到一处世外桃源，忘掉一切烦恼、浮华和灾难，由爱情相伴，安安静静度过余生残年。”

占星家抬起两道浓眉，把他上下打量了几眼。

“如果我让你住进这样的一个世外桃源，你给我什么作为回报呢？”

“你要什么回报，请尽管说。只要在我的权力范围之内，不管你要什么都可以。只要我在世一天，那东西就是属于你的。”

“陛下大概听说过伊莱姆花园，那是阿拉伯的一个世外桃源。”

“这个花园我倒是听说过，《古兰经》里有记载，就在《破晓》那一章里。而且，我还听去麦加朝觐的香客提到过那儿，说那里有诸多奇异的景观，可我觉得这些不过是粗鄙的传说，就像到遥远的国度旅游的游客讲的海外奇谈。”

“游客的话不可不信，陛下，”占星家语气郑重地说，“因为他们从遥远的国度带回来的是珍贵的见闻。至于人们通常所说的伊莱姆的宫殿和花园， 并非子虚乌有，我可是亲眼所见。你不妨听我讲一讲那段经历，因为它跟你的诉求有关。

“话说年轻时，我只不过是游走于沙漠上的一个阿拉伯小青年，替家父照管骆驼群。一次，在穿过阿登沙漠的途中，一匹骆驼离群走失了。我一连找了好几天也没有找到。一天中午，我累得头昏眼花，就躺倒在一棵棕榈树下，傍着一眼枯井睡着了。醒来后，我发现自己来到了一座城市的城门前。走进城门，我看到许多华丽的街道、广场和市集，然而悄无声息，不见一个人影。我信步向前走去，走到一座美轮美奂的宫殿前，那儿有座园子，里面有喷水池、鱼塘、树丛、花圃和果实累累的果园，却仍不见一个人影出现。那儿静悄悄的，静得叫我心里发毛，于是我急挪步离开。急慌慌走到城门外，再回头看时，那地方已消失不见，眼前只有静悄悄、一望无际的沙漠，其他什么也看不见。

“在那一带，我遇见了一个年老的伊斯兰教士，此人对当地的风土人情和各种神秘的现象了如指掌。我把自己见到的情况告诉了他，他回答说：‘那是沙漠里的一个奇迹——闻名遐迩的伊莱姆花园。它只是偶然对你这样漂泊迷路的人现一现，让迷路人看到塔楼、宫殿和长满了果树的园子，由此觉得心情愉悦，随后它就会彻底消失，叫你除了荒寂的沙漠，什么也看不到。关于这个花园，还有一段故事呢。在很久以前，亚狄人居住于此。他们的国王希达德，他是艾德之子，诺亚之曾孙，在这片土地上建了一座辉煌壮观的城市。城市建成之后，他看见眼前是一片富丽堂皇的景象，顿生傲慢自大之心，决定再造一座王宫，王宫旁边是花园，而花园足以跟《古兰经》中描述的天堂花园相媲美。然而，由于他目空一切、不可一世，上天让诅咒降到了他身上。他以及他的臣民被从大地上抹掉，而他那辉煌壮观的城市、宫殿和花园则处于永久的魔力控制之下，让世人再也看不见，只是偶尔出现一下，以此使人们永远记住他的罪孽。’

“陛下，这个故事以及我所看见的奇观从那以后便在我心里扎下了根。数年后，我在埃及得到了智慧王所罗门的那本天书，决定故地重游，再去寻找一下伊莱姆花园。我去了，睁开法眼，看到了那花园，于是住进希达德的王宫，在他那仿造天堂里过了几天逍遥日子。我施展法力，叫看管伊莱姆花园的魔仆俯首听命。魔仆将控制花园的符咒告诉了我——该符咒可以让花园现形，也可以让它隐形。陛下呀，就在这个地方，我可以为你建造同样的宫殿和花园，地址选在城市旁边的山上，因为我了解那神秘的符咒，而且掌握着智慧王所罗门的天书。”

“大智大慧的阿布·阿尤伯之子呀！”阿本·哈布兹高声叫道，一边浑身发着抖，一副迫不及待的样子，“你不愧是个旅行家，看见过许多神奇的景象，掌握了许多知识！那就为我建造一所这样的乐园吧。你要什么回报都可以，甚至可以把我的半壁江山赐给你。”

“岂敢，岂敢！”对方回答道，“你知道我是个老年人，一个哲学家，是很容易满足的。我别无所求，只求得到走进宫殿魔法大门的第一匹牲口和它所驮的东西。”

国王没想到对方的要求如此简单，二话没说，欣然表示同意。于是，占星家便破土开始动工了。他叫人在山顶上，就在他那座地下隐居所的上面，建起了一座巨大的拱门，或称望楼，直通一座坚固的塔楼的中心。

拱门外有一条连廊，或称门廊，连廊上有一个高高的拱顶，而廊里有一个入口，入口处装着两扇结实的大门。在入口的拱心石上，占星家亲手刻下了一把巨大的钥匙的图形，又在连廊拱顶的拱心石上刻了一只巨大的手，位置高于入口处的图形。这些东西用作符咒，他冲着它们用无人可懂的语言念了几句咒语。

拱门竣工后，他把自己关在占星大厅里，一连两天闭门不出，暗中作法念咒。到了第三天，他爬上山，在山顶上过了一整天。夜里很晚他才下了山，来见阿本·哈布兹。

“启禀陛下，”他说道，“我的工程终于完工了。山顶上的那座宫殿是人类所能设计出的最精美的宫殿，也是人们最渴望居住的宫殿。那儿有辉煌壮丽的大厅和回廊，有美丽的花园、清洌的泉水和芬芳的浴池。一句话，那一整座山被改造成了一个极乐世界。跟伊莱姆花园一样，它受到强大的法力保护，被隐藏起来，除了掌握符咒秘密的人，凡人是看不见、找不到的。”

“好样的！”阿本·哈布兹喜不自禁地高声叫道，“明天早晨天一亮，咱们就上山入住。”

这天夜里，国王兴奋得辗转反侧，难以成寐。次日，几乎还没等阳光照到白雪皑皑的内华达山的峰顶，他就骑上马，只带着几个亲信随从，沿着陡峭狭窄的小径上了山。他旁边走着一匹小白马，那位哥特公主骑在上面，只见她身上珠宝闪闪发光，颈上挂着她的那把银制的小竖琴。占星家步行，走在他的另一侧，拄着他的那根刻有象形文字的手杖——他从不骑任何坐骑。

阿本·哈布兹急于看见宫殿那光彩夺目的塔楼出现在山头上，看见花园的凉亭花台横亘于山脊之上，然而却迟迟瞧不见它们的身影。“那是个神秘的地方，是受魔法保护的，”占星家解释说，“不穿过那道受符咒控制的拱门，拥有了那个地方，你是什么也看不见的。”

接近那道拱门时，占星家停下来，把雕刻在拱顶上那只神秘的手和钥匙指给国王看，说道：“那是卫护这座乐园入口的镇符。除非那只手伸下来抓住那把钥匙，否则，无论是人力还是魔力，都奈何不了这座山的主人。”

就在阿本·哈布兹瞪圆双眼、张大嘴巴，默默无语、惊讶万分地观望之时，那匹小白马已驮着公主向前，从入口进去，到了望楼的中心。

“瞧呀！”占星家叫了起来，“这就是你答应过的给我的报酬——走进魔法大门的第一匹牲口和它所驮的东西。”

阿本·哈布兹笑了笑，觉得这老头在开玩笑，可是却发现对方是认真的，不由气得直哆嗦，连他那灰白胡子也在跟着发抖。

“阿布·阿尤伯之子，”他板着脸说道，“这模棱两可的话到底是什么意思？我答应过你把第一匹走进这个入口的牲口和它驮的东西赐给你，你明明知道其中真正的含义是什么。你可以到我的牲口棚里去，挑上一匹最强壮的骡子，驮走我库存的价值连城的珍宝，那些全归你。可是，你怎么胆敢起非分之心，夺走我心头的欢乐！”

“珍宝于我有何用？”占星家用一种轻蔑的语气高声说，“我有智慧王所罗门的天书，能掌握人世间所有的秘密宝藏。这个公主归我所有。陛下有言在先，不能反悔，我需要的是她。”

公主从马上居高临下，高傲地望着他们，看见这两个白胡子老头为了霸占青春和美色而起争端，她那玫瑰色的芳唇上不由泛起一丝藐视的微笑。国王勃然大怒，不顾一切地叫嚷道：“你这个沙漠里的贱种，就算你懂得不少邪法，也应当知道我是你的主人，不允许你对你的国王耍花招。”

“我的主人！我的国王！”占星家说道，“你恐怕只是鼹鼠国的国王，竟然想凌驾于掌握着所罗门法力的人之上！永别了，阿本·哈布兹，你就在这个弹丸之地称王称霸吧，就在这个傻瓜乐园里醉生梦死吧。至于我，我要在我那哲人隐居所里嘲笑你。”

他说着，一把抓住小马的缰绳，用手杖磕了磕地面，便带着那位哥特公主在望楼的中心位置沉入地心。地面在他们头上又合拢了，他们所进入的地洞口消失了，一点痕迹也没有留下。

阿本·哈布兹惊愕万分，一时连话也说不出来了。待醒过神之后，他叫来一千名工匠，在占星家遁去的那个地方用鹤嘴锄和铁锨朝地心挖。他们挖啊挖，但毫无进展，山体坚如磐石，让他们手中的工具无用武之地。即便能挖进去一点，然而刚将土铲出，地面就又合拢了。阿本·哈布兹到山脚下，再想找通向占星家的地下宫殿的洞口，却无处可寻了。原来明明是洞口，现在却成了原始岩石坚硬的地表。随着伊伯拉西姆·伊本·阿布·阿尤伯的遁形，他的神器也不灵验了。那个铜骑士死死地固定在原地，面向大山，矛尖指向占星家遁入地心的地方，仿佛那儿潜伏着阿本·哈布兹最凶狠的死敌。

时不时可以隐约听见大山的心里传来琴乐之声和一个女子的莺声燕语。一天，有个农夫向国王禀报，说头天夜里他发现岩石上出现了一个裂口，于是就爬了进去，向下一看，看见了一个地下大厅，占星家坐在大厅里的一个华美的长沙发上，听着那位公主弹奏银质小竖琴，头一点一点地昏昏欲睡，似乎竖琴的魔力控制了他的神智。

阿本·哈布兹找到了岩石上的那个裂口，可是它又合严了。他重鼓干劲，想把情敌从地下挖出来，但一切努力都化为泡影。刻在拱心石上的那只手和那把钥匙具有极大的魔力，非人力可以制胜。至于山头上占星家许诺建造宫殿和花园的地方，仍是光秃秃的，一片荒芜。也许，他所鼓吹的极乐世界受到魔法的控制，世人难见，要不然，这些都纯粹是他编造出的故事。世人都好心地认为一切都属于后一种情况。有人将这块地方称为“国王犯傻地”，也有人叫它“傻瓜乐园”。

令阿本·哈布兹更为苦恼的是：从前他掌握着那个骑士神器时，对邻邦又是辱骂又是嘲弄，杀戮他们以作消遣，如今他失去了魔法的保护，敌人就从四面八方攻占他的国土，使得这位渴望过平静日子的国王在风烛残年始终处于动乱的烦恼之中。

后来，阿本·哈布兹死了，被埋在了墓地里。光阴似箭，不知又过了多少年，那座多事的山头上建起了阿尔罕布拉宫，总算在某种程度上将传说中的乐土伊莱姆花园变成了现实。那座受魔力控制的拱门完整地保留至今，毫无疑问是受到了那只神秘的手和钥匙的保护，不过现在叫作“正义之门”，即阿尔罕布拉宫的正门。据说在这座拱门下面，年老的占星家至今仍住在他的地下大厅里，坐在长沙发上一边听公主弹奏银质小竖琴，一边打着盹。

夏夜，守卫拱门的几位年老多病的哨兵常常会听到琴声，感受到催眠之力，便在岗哨上酣然入睡。不仅如此，这种使人昏昏欲睡的力量简直弥漫了这片地方，连白天站岗的哨兵也往往被人瞧见坐在望楼的石凳上打盹，或者躺在附近的树下睡觉。实际上，在所有的基督教国家里，这儿恐怕是最容易叫人入睡的岗哨了。根据古老的传说，情况世世代代均是如此。公主始终是占星家的俘虏，而占星家也始终为公主的魔琴所迷惑，昏昏欲睡的。这种状况要延续到世界的末日，除非那只神秘的手能抓住那把神奇的钥匙，将这座被施了咒语的大山里的妖气一扫而空。

注释

阿尔·马卡里在《西班牙的伊斯兰王朝史》一书中引用了另一个阿拉伯作家的话讲述符咒神器，类似于本故事里提到的神器。

他说：在卡迪斯，从前有一座方形塔，高达一百肘尺，用一块块巨石筑成，用铜箍固定。塔顶有一尊人的塑像，右手持一物，面向大西洋，用左手的食指指着直布罗陀海峡。据说该塔是古代安达卢斯的哥特国王所建，用作航标，为海上的人导航。北非的巴巴利和安达卢斯的穆斯林将其视为符咒，认为它能对大海施展魔力。在它的指引下，大批海盗蜂拥而至，这些海盗属于一个叫玛居斯的国家，他们乘坐大船来到岸边，船头和船尾各有一张方形风帆。他们每隔六七年来一次，掳走海上所有的船只，然后在塔顶人像的指引下经海峡进入地中海，在安达卢斯的海岸登陆，烧杀掠夺，有时将锋芒指向对岸，甚至波及叙利亚。

后来国内爆发内战，一位穆斯林将领攻占了卡迪斯，听说塔顶上的人像是纯金的，便命令将其弄下来砸碎，结果发现那人像是黄铜铸成，外边镀了一层金。人像破碎了，它对大海的魔力也消失了。自此，再也未见海盗的踪影——人们只是在岸边两处地方发现了海盗沉船的残骸：一处在玛居斯的港口，另一处靠近阿尔·阿汗海角。

阿尔·马卡里上面提到的海上入侵者八成是北欧人。

————————————————————

(1) 格拉纳达位于西班牙内华达山脉北麓，此处曾被摩尔人占领。

(2) 穆罕默德（570—632），伊斯兰教创始人。

(3) 阿姆鲁（594—664），阿拉伯军队的统帅。

(4) 中古西班牙摩尔人诸王的豪华宫殿。

(5) 根据《旧约全书》，亚比煞是侍从献给大卫王的一个少女。

摩尔人遗产的传说

在阿尔罕布拉宫的城堡之内，王宫的正前方有一片宽展的空地，人称“蓄水池之地”，或称“蓄水池广场”（西班牙语叫la Plaza de los Algibes）。之所以得此名称，是因为此处地下有一些蓄水池，自打摩尔王朝时代就已经存在，从地表是看不见的。广场的一角有一眼摩尔式水井，是在岩石上凿出来的，很深很深，井水冷如寒冰，清澈似水晶。摩尔人打的井素有大名，世人皆知他们打井往往不辞劳苦，只为了求得最纯净、最甘甜的清泉。咱们现在说的这眼井在格拉纳达享有盛名，前来取水者络绎不绝，有的用大水罐盛水扛在肩上，有的赶着毛驴驮着装水的瓦罐，沿着阿尔罕布拉宫那浓荫遮蔽的道路上山下山，从清晨到深夜往来不息。

早在《圣经》中记载的那些年代，一到暑天，清泉以及水井旁就成了人们聚会闲谈的地方。此处所说的那眼井边，简直就是个长期俱乐部，从早到晚都聚集着一些人，有残疾人，有老太太，还有城堡里的一些好奇心十足的游手好闲者。他们坐在的石凳上，水井上方有如盖的浓荫为这些小道消息采集者遮阳。大家东一搭西一搭地讲些城堡里的琐事，一见取水人就打听城里的新闻，无论听到或看到什么，总要滔滔不绝发表一通议论。一天之中，无论什么时候，都可以看到一些闲散的主妇和懒惰的女佣或头顶或手提水罐跑来，听这些可敬的人物无休无止地高谈阔论，久久不愿离开。

在前来取水的人当中有一身材敦实、结实有力的罗圈腿小个子，名叫佩德罗·吉尔，而人们图简便，称他佩雷吉尔。此人是个水贩子，自然也就是加里西亚人了，即加里西亚自治区(1)的土著居民。老天制造出了各种不同种族的人，就像造出各种鸟兽一样，让他们从事各种劳动。在法国，擦皮鞋者必是萨瓦人，旅馆的门童必是瑞士人；在英国，盛行裙圈和发粉的那些日子，若论抬轿，谁也不如善走的爱尔兰人抬得稳当。在西班牙，水贩子和搬运工必是身材敦实的小个子加里西亚人。请人搬运东西，没谁会说“给我找个搬运工来”，而是说“给我请个加里西亚人来”。

以下言归正传。话说加里西亚人佩雷吉尔初涉此行时，只有一只大瓦罐，扛在肩上用以贩水。后来逐渐发迹，他便买了一头适合于干这一行的牲口当助手——即一只毛茸茸、结实有劲的毛驴。这个长耳朵助手的腰两侧各挂了一只大水罐，就像两个驮筐一样，上面盖着无花果树叶遮阳。在格拉纳达所有的水贩子里，谁也没有他那般勤劳，也都不如他快活。只见他跟在毛驴的身后沿街叫卖：“谁要水呀？谁要比雪还要冰的水呀？谁要阿尔罕布拉宫的井水，冷如寒冰，清澈似水晶？”他那欢快的叫声响彻了街头巷尾。在夏天，西班牙的城镇到处都可以听得见这样的叫卖声。每当他用亮晶晶的玻璃杯斟一杯井水给顾客喝的时候，都会说一句入耳的话，令对方高兴得露出微笑。如果顾客是位漂亮的夫人或脸带酒窝的少女，他则机灵地抛个媚眼，夸对方长得漂亮，让对方喜不自禁。于是乎，加里西亚人佩雷吉尔在格拉纳达就成了一个家喻户晓的人物，都说他是个最懂礼貌、最讨人欢喜、最快活的人。

孰不知，叫卖的声音高，喜欢开玩笑，并不一定说明心情轻松。别看老实巴交的佩雷吉尔表面轻松愉快，心里却有着许多忧虑和苦恼。他有一大家子人要养活——衣衫褴褛的孩子们饿得像一窝嗷嗷待哺的雏燕，叽里哇啦乱叫，傍晚见他回家，就围着他要吃的。他倒也是有“内助”的，但此女却对他没有一点帮助。她婚前是村里的大美女，出了名地爱跳波列罗舞和敲响板。如今，她仍旧保持着早年的嗜好，把老实巴交的佩雷吉尔辛辛苦苦挣来的钱胡糟蹋在俗艳的服饰上，每逢星期天、圣徒节日以及那许多数不清的假日（西班牙的节假日比工作日还要多），便常常骑着家里仅有的毛驴到乡间游山玩水。除此之外，她还邋里邋遢的，喜欢睡懒觉，是个头等喜欢嚼舌根的人，不管家，不管孩子，什么都抛下不管，趿拉着鞋四处串门交流是非。

而佩雷吉尔则逆来顺受，把婚姻的枷锁套在自己驯顺的脖子上。他将妻子儿女带来的沉重负担驮在自己身上，就像毛驴驮水罐那样恭顺。有时，他私下里也会摇头叹息，然而却从不敢质问他的那个懒婆娘的持家之道。

他对自己的孩子有着舐犊之情，甚至可以说像猫头鹰爱它的雏鸟一样。他看到自己的形象在儿女的身上得到了复制和保留——小家伙们个个都是身材敦实、结实有力的罗圈腿。老实巴交的佩雷吉尔最大的欢乐莫过于能挤出一天空闲时间，从牙缝里省出一点小钱，带着一群小家伙到平原上的那些果园里嬉戏玩耍——孩子们有的被他抱在怀里，有的扯着他的衣服下摆，有的屁颠屁颠跟在他身后。而这种时候，他的妻子却在和朋友们欢度假日，在达罗谷里翩翩起舞呢。

一个夏日的晚上，夜已深，差不多所有的水贩子都已休息，结束了一天的辛勤劳作。白天酷暑难当，夜里却月色皎洁，诱使南国的人们走出家门，流连于户外，呼吸几口柔和而清新的空气，以消除白天的暑热，同时活动一下筋骨，直至后半夜才回家。因而，街头仍有买水的顾客。佩雷吉尔身为慈父，总为儿女着想，为儿女不辞劳苦，此时想到自己的孩子在挨饿，于是便对自己说：“应该再到井边跑一趟，这样，星期天能给孩子们添碗肉汤喝。”说着，他又沿着阿尔罕布拉宫那陡峭的道路顽强地向山上爬去，一边走路一边唱歌，时不时还会用棍子在毛驴的腰眼上重重抽打一下，有时抽打是为了跟自己的歌合拍，有时则是为了叫毛驴打起精神——在西班牙，无论对任何负重的牲口，一般都是用狠狠抽打来代替草料的。

到了井边，他发现那儿空荡荡的，月光下只看得见一个穿着摩尔服装的外乡人，孤零零坐在石凳上。他不由收住了脚步，惊讶地望着对方，心里甚至有点害怕。而那个摩尔人有气无力地朝他招招手叫他过去，然后对他说道：“我浑身虚弱，怕是病了。请你帮帮忙把我送进城去。你送水挣多少钱，我会加倍给你的。”

小个子水贩子心软，听了外乡人的请求，顿生怜悯之情，说道：“救危扶贫是人之常情，我怎能要你的回报！神不允许的！”说完，他把摩尔人扶上驴背，慢慢地走向格拉纳达。可怜的摩尔人已经虚弱到了极点，一路上得扶着他，他才不至于从驴背上摔下来。

进了城，水贩子问摩尔人该把他送往何处。摩尔人声音微弱地说：“唉！我是个外乡人，举目无亲，无处栖身。求你让我今天晚上在你家里过一夜吧，我定有重谢。”

老实巴交的佩雷吉尔没料到自己竟会被这么一个异族的客人缠住，可他生就一副好心肠，见对方处境悲惨，不忍心拒绝对方要到他家过夜的的请求。于是，他把摩尔人领到了自己家中。孩子们像往日一样，听见毛驴踢踏踢踏地走来，一声喊迎了上去，可是看见包着头巾的外乡人，又吓得跑了回来，躲到他们母亲身后。做母亲的则勇敢地冲上前去，就像是一只老母鸡看见野狗跑过来，便竖起羽毛冲上去保护小鸡一样。

“天这么晚了，你竟然把一个异教徒带到家里来！”她嚷嚷道，“这不明明是引火烧身，想上宗教法庭么！”

“别发火，老婆！”佩雷吉尔说道，“这个可怜的外乡人有病在身，在这里举目无亲，难道你忍心把他赶走，让他死在街上吗？”

做妻子的本来还要争执，因为虽说她住的是穷屋陋室，但在维护家庭声誉方面则针锋相对，寸步不让。不过，这一次，矮小的水贩子脖子硬了起来，坚决不肯屈服。他扶着那个可怜的伊斯兰教徒下了毛驴，把他扶到家里最凉快的地方，铺了一张席子和一张羊皮让他躺下——在这户贫寒人家，只能以此当床了。

过了没多大一会儿，摩尔人突然浑身痉挛，颤抖得厉害。纯朴的水贩子急忙趋前救护，却无济于事。可怜的病人眼里流露出对他的感激。在抽搐的间歇，摩尔人把他叫到身旁，小声对他说：“我怕是不行了。如果我死了，我把这个匣子留给你，报答你的恩情。”摩尔人说着，解开了斗篷，露出捆在身上的一只檀香木匣子。“我的朋友，”可敬的小个子加里西亚人说道，“上帝一定会赐给你长寿，让你能活许多年，享受你的财宝。”摩尔人摇摇头，把手放在匣子上，本来还想交代几句关于匣子的情况，却突然又痉挛了起来，抖得比刚才更厉害了，须臾便咽了气。

水贩子的妻子见状，一下子乱了心绪，开口说道：“都怪你愚蠢的好心惹来了祸事，有心帮别人，却总是麻烦缠身。叫别人在咱们家发现这具尸体，那该如何是好？咱们会被错认成杀人犯，锒铛入狱的。即便侥幸不死，也会毁于公证员及警察之手。”

可怜的佩雷吉尔也同样万分苦恼，甚至有点后悔，怪自己不该因行善而自找麻烦。后来，他灵机一动，想出了个主意，便说道：“趁着天还没有亮，我可以把尸体运出城去，把它埋在塞尼河岸边的沙地里。没人看见摩尔人进了咱们家，对于他的死是不会有人知道的。”

他说干就干。妻子帮着他，二人用不幸的伊斯兰教徒临终前睡的那张席子把他的尸体卷起来，横搭在驴背上面，然后由佩雷吉尔将其运到河岸上去。

歹运却往往与人作对。他家对面住着一个理发匠，名叫帕蒂罗·帕德鲁果，属于惹是生非的一类人，最喜欢的就是打听别人的隐私、说长道短、设奸计捉弄人。这个无赖生得獐头鼠目，两条腿细如麻秆，口蜜腹剑，专会套人的话，对于别人家的私事无所不知，若论这方面的知识，恐怕那位大名鼎鼎的塞维利亚的理发师(2)也会自叹弗如。对于自己掌握的情况，他像个筛子似的一句话也留不住。据说，这家伙睡觉时一只眼睛是睁着的，一只耳朵也是竖着的，对于周围发生的事情既能看得见也能听得到。当然，对于格拉纳达城里的那些喜欢听小道消息的人来说，他就是个丑闻逸事的传声筒，所以在同行里他的顾客是最多的。

话说这爱管闲事的理发匠听见佩雷吉尔半夜三更归家弄出的响动以及他的妻子儿女叫嚷的声音，急忙把脑袋探出小窗口以看个究竟——他总是以此窗口作为瞭望台，眼见得他的邻居将一个身着摩尔式服装的人搀扶进了家门。他觉得此事十分蹊跷，弄得他一夜都没有合眼。隔上五分钟，他就会跑到窗口，望一望邻居家门缝里透出来的闪烁的灯光。天亮之前，他发现佩雷吉尔赶着毛驴出了门，毛驴的背上驮着一样怪模怪样的东西。

这个喜欢探听消息的理发匠坐不住了，立时穿好衣服，悄无声息摸上前去，远远跟在水贩子的后边，一直跟到塞尼河的岸边，然后就见他在沙地里挖了个坑，将一个死尸样的东西埋了进去。

理发匠慌忙回到家里，如热锅上的蚂蚁般在他的理发店里转来转去，不知碰翻了多少东西。这样一直折腾到太阳升起，随后他将一只脸盆夹在腋下，匆匆忙忙去了市长家——他每天都去为市长理容。

市长刚刚起床。帕蒂罗·帕德鲁果让他坐在椅子上，把布巾围在他的脖子上，放一盆热水在他的面前，然后用手指将他的胡子搓软。

“真是咄咄怪事呀！”身兼理发匠和小道消息传播者两职的帕德鲁果启口说道，“真是咄咄怪事呀！谋财害命、埋尸灭迹全发生在一个晚上！”

“你说什么？这是说的哪门子的事呀？”市长高声问。

“我是说，”理发匠一面回着话，一面拿起一块肥皂在这位高官的鼻子上和嘴上擦来擦去，因为西班牙的理发匠不屑于用刷子涂抹剃须液，“我是说，那个叫佩雷吉尔的加里西亚人谋财害命，杀了一个摩尔族的伊斯兰教徒，而且就在当天晚上埋尸灭迹。这一夜可真是一个凶夜！”

“这些你是怎么知道的？”市长问。

“别急，市长先生，听我细细道来。”帕蒂罗一面回答，一面用手捏着市长的鼻子，拿起一把剃刀轻轻地在他的脸上刮着。接下来，他把自己看见的情况一五一十讲了一遍。他一边为市长刮胡子、洗下巴，并用一块脏毛巾将下巴擦干，一边叙述着水贩子谋财害命，杀死和掩埋那个伊斯兰教徒的经过。

说来也巧，这位市长是个横行霸道、作威作福、贪得无厌的官吏，全格拉纳达城数他最腐败。不过，无可否认，他对于正义的估价倒是很高的，因为他出卖正义也是按着案子的轻重索价的。他将这桩案子定性为谋财害命——毫无疑问，这样的案子有大利可图。可是，怎么样执法才妥当呢？把罪犯抓住绳之以法，那只不过是绞刑架上添了个人而已；但是，如果拿到赃款，就会使执法者受益——按照他的信条，这才是实现正义的伟大目标。有了这样的小算盘，他把自己最信得过的一个警官叫了来。该警官骨瘦如柴，是个有着饿死鬼面相的恶棍，平时穿便装，着一身古代西班牙服饰，戴一顶宽大的卷边黑色獭皮帽子，脖子上围着一个古怪的领圈，披一件小黑斗篷，脏得发黑的内衣裹着他那精瘦、结实的躯体，手中老提着一根细细的白棍子，这是象征着他职务的可怕的标志。就是这样的一条古代西班牙种的执法猎犬被放了出去，去寻找那个不幸的水贩子的踪迹。他的动作快捷准确，未等可怜的佩雷吉尔回到家中，便抓住了他，将他连人带驴一起带去见法律的执掌人。

市长面露凶相，一副穷凶极恶的样子。“你给我听着，罪犯！”他咆哮道，吓得小个子加里西亚人腿都软了，“你给我听着，罪犯！你不用抵赖，你的犯罪事实我全都知道。你所犯的罪行，送你上绞架才合适。不过，我心肠软，是个通情达理的人。在你家里被谋杀了的那家伙是个摩尔人，是异教徒，是基督教的敌人。毫无疑问，你一定怀有炽烈的宗教热情，冲动之下才杀了他。因此，我要从宽处理。你只要把从他身上抢来的财物交出来，此事就不再追究。”

可怜的水贩子把所有的圣徒的名字都喊遍了，想叫他们证明自己的无辜。可是，没有一个圣徒显灵。话又说回来，假如圣徒显了灵，这位市长不把圣徒历(3)扔掉才怪呢。水贩子把自己救助垂死的摩尔人的经过陈述了一遍，语言简单、事实清楚，但最终还是白费口舌。“你是不是坚持说，”这位法官厉声喝道，“这个伊斯兰教徒身上既没有金银，也没有珠宝？金银珠宝不正是你犯罪的起因吗？”

“苍天在上，市长大人，”水贩子回答说，“除了一个檀香木小匣子，他身上一无所有。他将小匣子遗赠给了我，作为对我的报偿。”

“一个檀香木小匣子！一个檀香木小匣子！”市长连声叫道，联想到匣子里可能有宝石，两眼熠熠闪射出光芒。“匣子在哪里？你把它藏在哪里了？”

“启禀市长大人，”水贩子回答说，“它就在我家毛驴背上的一个驮篓里。衷心听从大人的指派。”

没等他话音落地，那位机灵的警官就冲了出去，一眨眼的工夫便把那个神秘的檀香木匣子拿了来。市长把匣子打开，急切得手都发抖了。在场的人全都凑上去看，想着里面肯定有珠宝，然而却大失所望，匣子里除了一张写满了阿拉伯文的羊皮纸和半截蜡烛之外，别的什么也没有。

在给犯人加罪名却捞不到好处的情况下，甚至在西班牙，法律也会变得公正起来。市长从一阵失望中清醒了过来，意识到这桩案子里的确没有赃款，于是就平心静气地听水贩子的辩词，而这辩词与水贩子妻子后来的证词相吻合。因而，他认为水贩子无罪，并将他当场释放。非但如此，他还允许水贩子把摩尔人的遗产——那个檀香木匣子以及里面的东西——一起带走，作为他做好事应得的报酬，却扣下毛驴充当诉讼费。

这下子，倒霉的小个子加里西亚人又得自己去背水了，肩头扛着一只大瓦罐步履艰难地前往阿尔罕布拉宫的水井取水卖。

一个夏日的中午，他冒着酷暑行走在山路上，平常好性子的他突然怒气冲胸，不由叫出了声：“狗市长，居然对一个穷人下手，抢走他赖以生存的毛驴！那可是我在这个世界上最好的朋友呀！”想起自己在工作中的那个可爱的伙伴，他满腔温情，心都快碎了。“啊，我的宝贝毛驴呀！”他将水罐放在一块岩石上，抹去额头上的汗珠，高声叫道，“啊，我的宝贝毛驴呀！我敢说你一定在思念着你的主人！我敢说你一定念念不忘这些水罐！可怜的毛驴呀！”

更叫他痛苦的是，一回家，妻子就对着他哭天抹泪，有发不完的牢骚。显而易见，她觉得自己理直气壮，因为她早就警告过他万不可过于热情好客，后来他的善举果然招来了灾难。她是个得理不饶人的婆娘，一有机会就摆出架势揶揄他，拿话头呛他。如果孩子要东西吃，或者要件新衣服穿，她就带着轻蔑的语气回答：“找你爸爸去！他是阿尔罕布拉宫里奇科国王(4)的王位继承人，叫他用摩尔人的那个宝贝匣子替你想办法吧。”

有谁像这个可怜人一样因行善反遭厄运，受到如此严厉的惩罚呢？不幸的佩雷吉尔已经心力交瘁，却还要默默忍受妻子的责骂。一天傍晚，他顶着暑热辛苦了一天，回到家来，妻子对着他又是一阵冷嘲热讽，而这次他终于耐不住性子了。他不敢还嘴，只是用眼睛盯着架子上的那个檀香木匣子，而那匣子半开着盖，似乎在嘲笑烦恼不堪的他。他气得一把抓起匣子摔到了地上，大叫道：“那天看见你，就算倒了霉了。千不该万不该，就不该把你的主人领回家来！”

匣子落地，匣盖大开，里面的羊皮纸卷滚了出来。

佩雷吉尔坐在那里盯着羊皮纸，闷闷不乐，半天不作声。后来，他陷入了沉思，暗忖：“那个摩尔人如此精心地保留着这玩意儿，说不准上面的字很重要呢。”于是他捡起羊皮纸卷揣在怀里，次日早晨沿街卖水时，在一家摩尔人开的店铺门前停了下来，求店主解释一下纸卷上那些字的含义。店主是个丹吉尔(5)人，在市场上卖珠宝首饰和香水为生。

这位摩尔人仔细读了纸卷上的字，然后捋一捋胡子，笑着说：“这是一种符咒，用它可以找到受魔力控制的宝藏。据说它法力无边，哪怕最结实的门闩和铁栅栏，还有那坚硬的岩石，在它面前也会不堪一击！”

“没用！”小个子加里西亚人叫了起来，“这对我有什么用？我又不是巫师，根本不懂宝藏什么的。”说完，他将水罐扛到肩上，把纸卷留在摩尔人手里，又去忙他的营生了。

当天傍晚暮色降临时，他走到阿尔罕布拉宫的水井旁边歇脚，发现那儿聚了一群人在闲聊。在这个天色昏暗的时辰，大家闲扯的内容跟往常没什么不同，仍然是些老掉牙的故事以及神鬼传奇。这些人都是一贫如洗的穷光蛋，特别喜欢聊当时最流行的话题——阿尔罕布拉宫里到处都有摩尔人埋藏的财宝，而那些财宝都被施了魔法。最值得一提的是：大家都深信在七层塔的底下深埋着大量的宝藏。

这些说法在老实巴交的佩雷吉尔的脑海里留下了非常深的印象。晚上摸黑独自行走在回家的路上，那些传说叫他浮想联翩：“如果七层塔下真的有宝藏，如果我留在摩尔人那儿的羊皮纸卷能帮我找到它，那该有多好呀！”想到此处，他顿时喜不自禁，肩上的水罐差点没掉下来摔碎。

夜里，他辗转反侧，几乎没有合眼，心里翻江倒海地想个不停。次日天一亮，他就奔到摩尔人的店里，把自己心里的所思所想都告诉了摩尔人。“你会念阿拉伯文，”他说道，“咱俩不妨一起去七层塔那儿，试一试这符咒的威力。即便不灵，也无害处可言；而如果符咒灵验，找到的宝藏咱俩就将其平分掉。”

“等一等，”这位伊斯兰教徒回答道，“光凭这符咒是不够的。要解读它，必须是在夜间，还得点上一支用特殊材料配制的蜡烛才行，而我手头是没有这种材料的。没有这种蜡烛，光有羊皮纸卷是不顶用的。”

“不必多言！”小个子加里西亚人高声说道，“我有这种蜡烛，马上就给你拿过来。”说完，他急如星火地赶回家，在檀香木匣子里找到那半截黄黄的蜡烛，很快拿了来。

摩尔人摸了摸，又嗅了嗅，然后说道：“这根黄蜡烛里掺有珍稀贵重的香料，正是羊皮纸卷上所说的蜡烛。点亮时，不管再结实的墙、再神秘的洞穴，都会敞开的。这蜡烛一灭，谁要是还留在里面没出来，那可就遭殃了。他会受到魔法的控制，会和那些财宝一道被禁锢在里面。”

二人商定要在当夜去试验符咒的威力。于是，这天半夜三更，除了蝙蝠和猫头鹰，没有生物在野外活动的时候，他们登上阿尔罕布拉宫的那座树木茂密的山丘，向七层塔进发——此塔林木环绕，被许许多多的民间传说渲染得狰狞可怕。他们挑灯摸路前行，穿过灌木丛和乱石堆，一直走到塔楼低层的地下室门前。他们怕得要命，战战兢兢地沿着石梯而下，向石洞的纵深处走去。石梯通向一间空室，那儿潮湿又阴森。再走下一段石梯，就到了一个位置更深的石室。这样，他们走过了四段石梯，层层深入，经过了四间石室。到了第四间石室，再朝前走路就不通了。根据传说，下面还有三间石室，然而却无法再深入，因为它们受到强大魔法的控制，被幽闭在地下。这第四间石室空气潮湿、寒冷，还带着泥土味，灯笼几乎连光也没有了。他们停下来等待，紧张得大气不敢出，一直等到隐约听见望楼上敲响午夜的钟声。这时，他们点亮那半截蜡烛，蜡烛马上散发出一股气味，里面有没药香、乳香及苏合香。

摩尔人开始急促地念纸卷上的阿拉伯文，几乎没等他念完就听见轰隆一声响，像地底下响起了闷雷，山摇地动，地面似打哈欠般张开一个口，露出了一段石阶。他们战战兢兢拾阶而下，借助灯笼的光亮发现自己进入了一间石室，里面刻满了阿拉伯文。石室的中央放着一口大箱子，用七条铁箍封死，箱子的两端各坐一个全身盔甲的摩尔人，但在符咒魔力的控制之下，全都木雕石塑般一动也不动。箱子前面有几只罐子，里面装满了金银珠宝。他们将手伸进一个最大的罐子，伸得有齐肘深，一把一把捞出许多黄澄澄的摩尔人铸的大金币，或者金镯子金首饰之类的东西，偶尔指头上还会勾起一个东方的珍珠项圈。他们浑身发抖，喘着粗气，将那些宝贝朝衣袋里直塞，一边还不时担惊受怕地望一眼那两个受魔法控制的摩尔人，但见那两个人脸色狰狞、纹丝不动，目不转睛地瞪着他们。后来，他们觉得自己听见了什么声音，吓得屁滚尿流，急忙向石阶奔去，连滚带爬冲到了上面的石室里，慌乱中碰倒蜡烛，致使烛光熄灭。接着又听见一声闷雷响，地面又合拢了。

二人惊讶万分，脚下不敢停留，急急忙忙摸黑逃出了塔楼，这时看见星光透过树梢洒落在地面上。他们在青草上席地而坐，平分了得来的财宝，决定这一次暂且罢手，以后找个夜晚再来一次，将罐子里的东西全部拿走。虽有言在先，但为确保万无一失，他们将探宝神器分开保管——一个保管羊皮纸卷，另外一个保管蜡烛。做完这件事之后，两人就一起带着轻松的心情，衣袋里装满金银珠宝，返回格拉纳达去了。

下山的时候，精明的摩尔人附在天真的小个子水贩子耳边，悄悄地说了两句忠告。

“佩雷吉尔朋友，”他说道，“此事必须严格保密，等咱们把全部财宝弄到手，没有危险的时候再说。万一有一点风声传到市长的耳朵里，那咱们可就玩完了！”

“这是当然的，”加里西亚人回应道，“此话一点不假。”

“佩雷吉尔朋友，”摩尔人说，“你是个谨慎的人，我知道你一定能守口如瓶；然而，你还有个妻子呢。”

“此事我对她只字不提。”小个子水贩子语气坚定地说。

“那好，”摩尔人说，“我相信你能够守口如瓶，也相信你一诺千金。”

水贩子的话恐怕是天下最诚恳、最郑重的诺言了。可是，你想想，有哪个男人有秘密能瞒得过自己的妻子呢？水贩子佩雷吉尔这样的男人是绝对不行的——他是个极其宠爱妻子、对妻子百依百顺的丈夫。回到家时，他看见妻子正郁郁寡欢地待在一个角落里。见他走进家门，妻子便嚷嚷了起来：“好呀，你总算回来了。你东游西逛的，这么晚才回家！我倒奇怪，你为什么不再带个摩尔人回家给你做伴。”说完，她泪如雨下，又是把两只手绞来绞去，又是用手捶胸。“我真是倒了邪霉了！”她呼天抢地地喊道，“真不知以后会有什么下场！家里被律师和警察搜刮一空，丈夫是个窝囊废，不给家里人挣衣食，却白天黑夜瞎转悠，跟异教徒摩尔人在一起胡混！可怜可怜我的孩子吧！可怜可怜我的孩子吧！我们母子该怎么办呢？将来都得上街头要饭去！”

老实巴交的佩雷吉尔见自己的配偶如此伤心，也情不自禁地潸然泪下。他的心里被感情充得满满的，就像他的衣袋里充满了金银珠宝一样，再也憋不住了。于是他把手伸进衣袋，掏出三四枚大金币来，将金币塞进妻子的怀里。可怜的女人诧异得瞪大了两眼，简直不明白这许多金子是从哪儿弄来的。还没等她醒过神来，小个子加里西亚人又掏出一根金链子在她面前晃来晃去，喜滋滋地直跳脚，嘴巴咧得都快到了耳朵根。

“圣母保佑我们吧！”做妻子的高声叫道，“佩雷吉尔，这是怎么回事？这该不是你谋财害命得来的不义之财吧？”

可怜的女人刚一产生这种想法，便认定是铁的事实了。她望见远处有一座监狱和一座绞刑架，仿佛看见小个子罗圈腿加里西亚人就被吊在绞架上，而这一幻想出的恐怖场景吓坏了她，于是她歇斯底里地呼天喊地闹腾起来。

可怜的丈夫真不知如何是好了。他想安抚妻子，让妻子打消脑子里的那些奇怪念头，却觉得别无良策，唯有一吐为快，将他如何遭此好运的经过说了出来。不过，在讲述之前，他让妻子立下极为庄重的誓言，绝不向任何一个人透密。

听了他的讲述，妻子那高兴的劲儿简直用语言无法形容。她伸出两臂，一下子紧紧地搂住丈夫的脖子，差点没把他闷死。“怎么样，老婆？”小个子男人欢天喜地地高声说，“摩尔人留下的遗产，你还有什么可说的？从今往后，我帮助落难的人，你可千万别再骂我了。”

老实巴交的加里西亚人躺到羊皮褥子上睡了，香甜得就像睡在鸭绒上一样。他的妻子却是另外一种情形。只见她把他衣袋里的宝贝全倒在了席子上，坐在那儿又是清点阿拉伯金币，又是试着戴项链和耳环，想象着有朝一日她获准能够享受这些宝贝时，那该是多么的风光。

第二天早晨，老实巴交的加里西亚人拿起一枚大金币跑到市场上，去了一家珠宝店想把它卖掉，假称是从阿尔罕布拉宫的废墟中捡到的。店主见金币上铸着阿拉伯文，是十足的纯金，却只给了他三分之一的价钱，而这位水贩子则十分满足。佩雷吉尔立时给孩子们买了几件新衣和各式各样的玩具，又采购了大量的食品，足够家里人大快朵颐，然后便打道回府。孩子们高兴得围着他跳舞，而他在中间也又蹦又跳的，觉得自己是天下最幸福的父亲。

水贩子的妻子果然守口如瓶，其守诺的严格程度叫人颇觉意外。整整有一天半的时间，她一脸神秘的表情，心里被秘密憋得都快要爆炸了，可是即便身边净是喜欢打听小道消息的人，却一句也没有透露。当然，她免不了会做出一些样子来，为自己的衣衫褴褛而向人表示歉意，说她打算定做一条金线和琉璃珠子镶边的裙子，还要定做一件连披肩的镶边头纱。她还放出风声，说她丈夫的身体状况不适合贩水，准备放弃这一行了。实际上，她还说他们全家要到乡间消夏，让孩子们呼吸山间清新的空气，闷热的夏天待在城里简直叫人受不了。

邻居们你看看我我看看你，都觉得这个穷婆子一定是疯了。她的装腔作势、故作高雅成了大伙儿的笑柄，她一转过身去，人们就拿她开玩笑。

如果说她在外边还克制着自己，进了家门可就要好好做出弥补了。她先把一串贵重的东方珍珠挂在脖子上，又把摩尔式手镯套在腕上，再拣出一顶钻石帽饰戴在头上，穿着她的那身破旧衣服走来走去，时不时还站在一面破镜子前把自己欣赏一番。一次，由于天真的虚荣心驱使，她实在按耐不住冲动，就珠光宝气地走到窗口炫耀，想赢得路人的钦羡。

仿佛是命运之神做出的安排，那个好管闲事的理发匠帕蒂罗·帕德鲁果此时坐在街对面的理发店里，正闲得无聊，他那双警惕的眼睛一下子就看见了钻石射出的光芒。一眨眼的工夫，他就冲到了瞭望窗口，发现水贩子的那个邋遢婆娘一身珠宝，将自己打扮得像个东方的新娘。他把那婆娘身上的珠宝列了一份精确的清单，然后即刻迈开大步向市长家疾奔。没过多大一会儿，那个饿狼似的警官便寻踪追去，不等太阳落山就将不幸的佩雷吉尔抓来见市长了。

“还有什么可说的，无赖！”市长气急败坏地咆哮道，“你曾经对我说那个死在你家里的异教徒什么也没留下，只留下了一个空匣子。而现在我听人说你妻子身穿破烂衣服，却戴满了珠玉、钻石首饰。你这个恶棍！你从那个悲惨的人儿身上得来的不义之财，都给我交出来，然后就等着上绞架吧——绞架早已在那儿候着你呢。”

水贩子被吓得魂飞天外，扑通一声跪倒在地，一五一十将他获得财富的神奇经历交代了一遍。市长、警官以及那个喜欢打听消息的理发匠都贪婪地竖起耳朵，细听这个关于魔法控制宝藏的阿拉伯故事。接着，警官奉命去把那个协助念符咒的摩尔人带了来。那个伊斯兰教徒发现自己最终还是落到了贪得无厌的法律的化身手里，早已吓得半死。后来看到水贩子站在那里，垂眼低眉，一副难为情的神态，他心里就彻底明白是怎么回事了。“可怜虫，”他经过水贩子身边时骂了一句，“我早就警告过你，对你的妻子只字都不能提！”

摩尔人的供词与他同案犯的话完全吻合，市长却假装不信，放出狠话威胁，说要将他们关入大牢彻查此事。

“请息怒，尊敬的市长阁下，”伊斯兰教徒此时已恢复了平日的机智和镇静，于是侃侃说道，“不要坏了兴头。财富人人有份，不必争抢。此事只有在座的几位知道，外人一概不知。咱们大家必须严守这个秘密。地洞里有金银财宝无数，足可以让大家盆满钵满。如果你们答应将得来的东西平分，便可以把里面的财宝悉数运出，否则，地洞就永远也别想打开。”

市长和警官私下商议了一阵。后者是个精于此道的老狐狸，只听他说：“不管什么条件都可以答应。先把那些宝贝弄到手再计较。到时候你可以把东西全扣下。如果他和他的同伴胆敢说个不字，就吓唬他们，说要把他们当作邪教徒和巫师，用火刑烧死他们。”

市长觉得此计大妙，于是变得和颜悦色，走到摩尔人跟前说：“这件事实在太离奇，不过，也许是真的。我必须亲眼见见才能够相信。今天夜里，就请你当着我的面念一念那符咒。如果真有财宝，那咱们就和和气气地平分，此事以后再不提起。假如你骗我，那你就别怪我手下无情了。现在得委屈一下你们，暂时留在此处。”

摩尔人和水贩子欣然同意了他的条件，相信这些条件最终会落实到实处的。

近半夜时分，市长带着警官和好管闲事的理发匠悄悄出发上路了，人人都全副武装。他们把摩尔人和水贩子当作犯人押着一起去，还牵去了水贩子的那头结实有力的毛驴，准备驮走拿到手的财宝。一行人神不知鬼不觉地抵达七层塔，将毛驴拴在一棵无花果树上，然后深入塔下的地洞，进了那第四层石室。

羊皮纸卷取了出来，点亮了黄蜡烛，摩尔人念了符咒。大地像上次那样开始颤抖，接着轰隆一声巨响，地面裂开，露出一段狭窄的石阶。市长、警官和理发匠全吓呆了，谁都没有勇气下去。摩尔人和水贩子相伴到了下边的室内，发现那两个摩尔人仍和从前一样默默无语，一动不动地端坐在那里。他们把两个装满了金币和宝石的大罐子搬过来，由水贩子一个一个扛到外面去。小个子虽说健壮有力，已习惯了扛重物，还是被压得脚步踉跄。当两个罐子放到毛驴的两侧时，他发现毛驴也几乎不堪重负了。

“这一次就到此为止吧，”摩尔人说道，“这些财宝够咱们搬运的了，可别在路上被人看见。这些足够叫咱们成为富人，使咱们人人满意。”

“下边还有别的珠宝吗？”市长问。

“最为值钱的是一个大箱子，”摩尔人说，“里面装满了珍珠和宝石。”

“无论如何也得把那箱子弄上来！”贪得无厌的市长叫嚷道。

“我不想再下去了，”摩尔人执拗地说，“对一个有理智的人来说，这些足够了，再弄就多余了。”

“我也不愿再去扛了，免得把我可怜的毛驴脊背压断。”水贩子说。

市长见自己的命令、威胁和央求一概不顶用，就转过身来对他的两个随从说：“你们俩帮我把箱子抬上来，里面的东西咱们平分。”说完，他带头走下石阶，警官和理发匠战战兢兢、无可奈何地紧随其后。

摩尔人见他们进入地下室，立刻吹灭了黄蜡烛，只听地面又跟从前一样轰隆一声合拢了，将那三位可敬的人物埋在了地底下。

随后，他急匆匆奔上一节节的石阶，一直跑到外边才停了下来。小个子水贩子在他后边甩开两条短腿拼命跑，紧跟了上来。

“你这是怎么啦？”佩雷吉尔刚一喘过气就嚷嚷了起来，“市长和那两个人被关在地下室里了。”

“这是真主的意愿！”摩尔人虔诚地说。

“难道你不放他们出来啦？”加里西亚人问。

“真主禁止他们出来！”摩尔人一面回答，一面捋着自己的胡子。“天书上写着，他们将永远被魔法禁锢在地下，有破禁者出现，才能使他们重见天日。真主之愿不可违！”说完，他一扬手将蜡烛远远地扔进了山谷阴森森的树丛里。

这下子，就是想救那三个人也没门了。摩尔人和水贩子便赶着毛驴，驮着无数金银财宝向城里走去。老实巴交的佩雷吉尔情不自禁地搂住与自己同甘共苦的长耳朵朋友又亲又吻，庆幸它逃离了法律的魔爪。实际上，心地纯朴的小个子简直快乐到了极点，一是因为他获得了这许多珍宝，二是由于毛驴失而复得。

两个走运的伙伴和和气气、公公平平对这笔财富进行了分配。值得一提的是，摩尔人偏爱首饰，于是便将珍珠、宝石及珍玩之类的东西大多划分到了他那一堆财宝里，却以多出五倍的数量把亮晃晃的金银财宝分给水贩子，使得对方极为满意。二人不敢停留，生怕横生枝节，便远走高飞，到别的国家安然享用他们的财富了。摩尔人回到了非洲他的故乡丹吉尔城。加里西亚人带着妻子儿女以及他的毛驴，风风光光地去了葡萄牙。在葡萄牙，受到妻子的训诫和教导，他居然摇身一变成了个显赫人物。妻子叫这小个子在长长的身子上穿一件紧身衣，在短腿上套一双长袜，帽插羽翎，腰挂宝剑，又叫他抛弃旧名佩雷吉尔，改用比较尊贵的名字——堂·佩德罗·吉尔。他的孩子虽然都是矮个头、罗圈腿，但活泼快乐。至于吉尔夫人，那可是浑身上下镶金线、裹花边、挂流苏，每个指头都戴着金光闪闪的戒指，简直就是一个邋遢婆娘穷讲究的典范。

话说那位市长和他的随从，一直被禁锢在七层塔之下，至今仍受到魔法的控制。也许，有朝一日，西班牙需要启用卑鄙的理发匠、如狼似虎的警官和贪污腐败的市长，才会有人打听他们的下落。否则，他们就得耐心等待别人救他们，说不定他们会永受魔法的控制，直至世界末日呢。

————————————————————

(1) 位于西班牙西北部。

(2) 法国著名作家博马舍（1732—1799）的政治喜剧《塞维利亚的理发师》里的主人公。

(3) 基督教往往将圣徒的肖像印在日历上，以此为教徒们的学习榜样。

(4) 格拉纳达摩尔王朝的末代君主。

(5) 摩洛哥北部古城。

Legend of the Arabian Astrologer

In old times, many hundred years ago, there was a Moorish king named Aben Habuz, who reigned over the kingdom of Granada. He was a retired conqueror, that is to say, one who, having in his more youthful days led a life of constant foray and depredation, now that he was grown feeble and superannuated, “languished for repose,” and desired nothing more than to live at peace with all the world, to husband his laurels, and to enjoy in quiet the possessions he had wrested from his neighbors.

It so happened, however, that this most reasonable and pacific old monarch had young rivals to deal with; princes full of his early passion for fame and fighting, and who were disposed to call him to account for the scores he had run up with their fathers. Certain distant districts of his own territories, also, which during the days of his vigor he had treated with a high hand, were prone, now that he languished for repose, to rise in rebellion and threaten to invest him in his capital. Thus he had foes on every side; and as Granada is surrounded by wild and craggy mountains, which hide the approach of an enemy, the unfortunate Aben Habuz was kept in a constant state of vigilance and alarm, not knowing in what quarter hostilities might break out.

It was in vain that he built watchtowers on the mountains, and stationed guards at every pass with orders to make fires by night and smoke by day, on the approach of an enemy. His alert foes, baffling every precaution, would break out of some unthought-of defile, ravage his lands beneath his very nose, and then make off with prisoners and booty to the mountains. Was ever peaceable and retired conqueror in a more uncomfortable predicament?

While Aben Habuz was harassed by these perplexities and molestations, an ancient Arabian physician arrived at his court. His gray beard descended to his girdle, and he had every mark of extreme age, yet he had travelled almost the whole way from Egypt on foot, with no other aid than a staff, marked with hieroglyphics. His fame had preceded him. His name was Ibrahim Ebn Abu Ayub, he was said to have lived ever since the days of Mahomet, and to be son of Abu Ayub; the last of the companions of the Prophet. He had, when a child, followed the conquering army of Amru into Egypt, where he had remained many years studying the dark sciences, and particularly magic, among the Egyptian priests.

It was, moreover, said that he had found out the secret of prolonging life, by means of which he had arrived to the great age of upwards of two centuries, though, as he did not discover the secret until well stricken in years, he could only perpetuate his gray hairs and wrinkles.

This wonderful old man was honorably entertained by the king; who, like most superannuated monarchs, began to take physicians into great favor. He would have assigned him an apartment in his palace, but the astrologer preferred a cave in the side of the hill which rises above the city of Granada, being the same on which the Alhambra has since been built. He caused the cave to be enlarged so as to form a spacious and lofty hall, with a circular hole at the top, through which, as through a well, he could see the heavens and behold the stars even at mid-day. The walls of this hall were covered with Egyptian hieroglyphics with cabalistic symbols, and with the figures of the stars in their signs. This hall he furnished with many implements, fabricated under his directions by cunning artificers of Granada, but the occult properties of which were known only to himself.

In a little while the sage Ibrahim became the bosom counsellor of the king, who applied to him for advice in every emergency. Aben Habuz was once inveighing against the injustice of his neighbors, and bewailing the restless vigilance he had to observe to guard himself against their invasions; when he had finished, the astrologer remained silent for a moment, and then replied, “Know, O King, that when I was in Egypt I beheld a great marvel devised by a pagan priestess of old. On a mountain, above the city of Borsa, and overlooking the great valley of the Nile, was a figure of a ram, and above it a figure of a cock, both of molten brass, and turning upon a pivot. Whenever the country was threatened with invasion, the ram would turn in the direction of the enemy, and the cock would crow; upon this the inhabitants of the city knew of the danger, and of the quarter from which it was approaching, and could take timely means to guard against it.”

“God is great!” exclaimed the pacific Aben Habuz, “what a treasure would be such a ram to keep an eye upon these mountains around me; and then such a cock to crow in time of danger! Allah Akbar! how securely I might sleep in my palace with such sentinels on the top!”

The astrologer waited until the ecstasies of the king had subsided, and then proceeded.

“After the victorious Amru (may he rest in peace!) had finished his conquest of Egypt, I remained among the priests of the land, studying the rites and ceremonies of their idolatrous faith, and seeking to make myself master of the hidden knowledge for which they are renowned. I was one day seated on the banks of the Nile, conversing with an ancient priest, when he pointed to the mighty pyramids which rose like mountains out of the neighboring desert. ‘All that we can teach thee,’ said he, ‘is nothing to the knowledge locked up in those mighty piles. In the centre of the central pyramid is a sepulchral chamber, in which is inclosed the mummy of the high-priest, who aided in rearing that stupendous pile; and with him is buried a wondrous book of knowledge containing all the secrets of magic and art. This book was given to Adam after his fall, and was handed down from generation to generation to King Solomon the wise, and by its aid he built the temple of Jerusalem. How it came into the possession of the builder of the pyramids, is known to him alone who knows all things.’

“When I heard these words of the Egyptian priest, my heart burned to get possession of that book. I could command the services of many of the soldiers of our conquering army, and of a number of the native Egyptians: with these I set to work, and pierced the solid mass of the pyramid, until, after great toil, I came upon one of its interior and hidden passages. Following this up, and threading a fearful labyrinth, I penetrated into the very heart of the pyramid, even to the sepulchral chamber, where the mummy of the high-priest had lain for ages. I broke through the outer cases of the mummy, unfolded its many wrappers and bandages, and at length found the precious volume on its bosom. I seized it with a trembling hand, and groped my way out of the pyramid, leaving the mummy in its dark and silent sepulchre, there to await the final day of resurrection and judgment.”

“Son of Abu Ayub,” exclaimed Aben Habuz, “thou hast been a great traveller, and seen marvellous things; but of what avail to me is the secret of the pyramid, and the volume of knowledge of the wise Solomon?”

“This it is, O king! By the study of that book I am instructed in all magic arts, and can command the assistance of genii to accomplish my plans. The mystery of the Talisman of Borsa is therefore familiar to me, and such a talisman can I make; nay, one of greater virtues.”

“O wise son of Abu Ayub,” cried Aben Habuz, “better were such a talisman, than all the watch towers on the hills, and sentinels upon the borders. Give me such a safeguard, and the riches of my treasury are at thy command.”

The astrologer immediately set to work to gratify the wishes of the monarch. He caused a great tower to be erected upon the top of the royal palace, which stood on the brow of the hill of the Albaycin. The tower was built of stones brought from Egypt, and taken, it is said, from one of the pyramids. In the upper part of the tower was a circular hall, with windows looking towards every point of the compass, and before each window was a table, on which was arranged, as on a chess-board, a mimic army of horse and foot, with the effigy of the potentate that ruled in that direction, all carved of wood. To each of these tables there was a small lance, no bigger than a bodkin, on which were engraved certain Chaldaic characters. This hall was kept constantly closed, by a gate of brass, with a great lock of steel, the key of which was in possession of the king.

On the top of the tower was a bronze figure of a Moorish horseman, fixed on a pivot, with a shield on one arm, and his lance elevated perpendicularly. The face of this horseman was towards the city, as if keeping guard over it; but if any foe were at hand, the figure would turn in that direction, and would level the lance as if for action.

When this talisman was finished, Aben Habuz was all impatient to try its virtues; and longed as ardently for an invasion as he had ever sighed after repose. His desire was soon gratified. Tidings were brought, early one morning, by the sentinel appointed to watch the tower, that the face of the bronze horseman was turned towards the mountains of Elvira, and that his lance pointed directly against the Pass of Lope.

“Let the drums and trumpets sound to arms, and all Granada be put on the alert,” said Aben Habuz.

“O king,” said the astrologer, “let not your city be disquieted, nor your warriors called to arms; we need no aid of force to deliver you from your enemies. Dismiss your attendants, and let us proceed alone to the secret hall of the tower.”

The ancient Aben Habuz mounted the staircase of the tower, leaning on the arm of the still more ancient Ibrahim Ebn Abu Ayub. They unlocked the brazen door and entered. The window that looked towards the Pass of Lope was open. “In this direction,” said the astrologer, “lies the danger; approach, O king, and behold the mystery of the table.”

King Aben Habuz approached the seeming chess-board, on which were arranged the small wooden effigies, when, to his surprise, he perceived that they were all in motion. The horses pranced and curveted, the warriors brandished their weapons, and there was a faint sound of drums and trumpets, and the clang of arms, and neighing of steeds; but all no louder, nor more distinct, than the hum of the bee, or the summer-fly, in the drowsy ear of him who lies at noontide in the shade.

“Behold, O king,” said the astrologer, “a proof that thy enemies are even now in the field. They must be advancing through yonder mountains, by the Pass of Lope. Would you produce a panic and confusion amongst them, and cause them to retreat without loss of life, strike these effigies with the but-end of this magic lance; would you cause bloody feud and carnage, strike with the point.”

A livid streak passed across the countenance of Aben Habuz; he seized the lance with trembling eagerness; his gray beard wagged with exultation as he tottered toward the table: “Son of Abu Ayub,” exclaimed he, in chuckling tone, “I think we will have a little blood!”

So saying, he thrust the magic lance into some of the pigmy effigies, and belabored others with the but-end, upon which the former fell as dead upon the board, and the rest turning upon each other began, pell-mell, a chance-medley fight.

It was with difficulty the astrologer could stay the hand of the most pacific of monarchs, and prevent him from absolutely exterminating his foes; at length he prevailed upon him to leave the tower, and to send out scouts to the mountains by the Pass of Lope.

They returned with the intelligence, that a Christian army had advanced through the heart of the Sierra, almost within sight of Granada, where a dissension had broken out among them; they had turned their weapons against each other, and after much slaughter had retreated over the border.

Aben Hazuz was transported with joy on thus proving the efficacy of the talisman. “At length,” said he, “I shall lead a life of tranquillity, and have all my enemies in my power. O wise son of Abu Ayub, what can I bestow on thee in reward for such a blessing?”

“The wants of an old man and a philosopher, O king, are few and simple; grant me but the means of fitting up my cave as a suitable hermitage, and I am content.”

“How noble is the moderation of the truly wise!” exclaimed Aben Habuz, secretly pleased at the cheapness of the recompense. He summoned his treasurer, and bade him dispense whatever sums might be required by Ibrahim to complete and furnish his hermitage.

The astrologer now gave orders to have various chambers hewn out of the solid rock, so as to form ranges of apartments connected with his astrological hall; these he caused to be furnished with luxurious ottomans and divans, and the walls to be hung with the richest silks of Damascus. “I am an old man,” said he, “and can no longer rest my bones on stone couches, and these damp walls require covering.”

He had baths too constructed, and provided with all kinds of perfumes and aromatic oils:“For a bath,” said he, “is necessary to counteract the rigidity of age, and to restore freshness and suppleness to the frame withered by study.”

He caused the apartments to be hung with innumerable silver and crystal lamps, which he filled with a fragrant oil, prepared according to a receipt discovered by him in the tombs of Egypt. This oil was perpetual in its nature, and diffused a soft radiance like the tempered light of day. “The light of the sun,” said he, “is too garish and violent for the eyes of an old man, and the light of the lamp is more congenial to the studies of a philosopher.”

The treasurer of King Aben Habuz groaned at the sums daily demanded to fit up this hermitage, and he carried his complaints to the king. The royal word, however, had been given; Aben Habuz shrugged his shoulders: “We must have patience,” said he, “this old man has taken his idea of a philosophic retreat from the interior of the pyramids, and of the vast ruins of Egypt; but all things have an end, and so will the furnishing of his cavern.”

The king was in the right; the hermitage was at length complete, and formed a sumptuous subterranean palace. The astrologer expressed himself perfectly content, and, shutting himself up, remained for three whole days buried in study. At the end of that time he appeared again before the treasurer. “One thing more is necessary,” said he, “one trifling solace for the intervals of mental labor.”

“O wise Ibrahim, I am bound to furnish every thing necessary for thy solitude; what more dost thou require?”

“I would fain have a few dancing women.”

“Dancing women!” echoed the treasurer, with surprise.

“Dancing women,” replied the sage, gravely; “and let them be young and fair to look upon; for the sight of youth and beauty is refreshing. A few will suffice, for I am a philosopher of simple habits and easily satisfied.”

While the philosophic Ibrahim Ebn Abu Ayub passed his time thus sagely in his hermitage, the pacific Aben Habuz carried on furious campaigns in effigy in his tower. It was a glorious thing for an old man, like himself, of quiet habits, to have war made easy, and to be enabled to amuse himself in his chamber by brushing away whole armies like so many swarms of flies.

For a time he rioted in the indulgence of his humors, and even taunted and insulted his neighbors, to induce them to make incursions; but by degrees they grew wary from repeated disasters, until no one ventured to invade his territories. For many months the bronze horseman remained on the peace establishment, with his lance elevated in the air, and the worthy old monarch began to repine at the want of his accustomed sport, and to grow peevish at his monotonous tranquillity.

At length, one day, the talismanic horseman veered suddenly round, and lowering his lance, made a dead point towards the mountains of Guadix. Aben Habuz hastened to his tower, but the magic table in that direction remained quiet; not a single warrior was in motion. Perplexed at the circumstance, he sent forth a troop of horse to scour the mountains and reconnoitre. They returned after three days' absence.

“We have searched every mountain pass,” they said, “but not a helm nor spear was stirring. All that we have found in the course of our foray, was a Christian damsel of surpassing beauty, sleeping at noontide beside a fountain, whom we have brought away captive.”

“A damsel of surpassing beauty!” exclaimed Aben Habuz, his eyes gleaming with animation; “let her be conducted into my presence.”

The beautiful damsel was accordingly conducted into his presence. She was arrayed with all the luxury of ornament that had prevailed among the Gothic Spaniards at the time of the Arabian conquest. Pearls of dazzling whiteness were entwined with her raven tresses; and jewels sparkled on her forehead, rivalling the lustre of her eyes. Around her neck was a golden chain, to which was suspended a silver lyre, which hung by her side.

The flashes of her dark refulgent eye were like sparks of fire on the withered, yet combustible, heart of Aben Habuz; the swimming voluptuousness of her gait made his senses reel. “Fairest of women,” cried he, with rapture, “who and what art thou?”

“The daughter of one of the Gothic princes, who but lately ruled over this land. The armies of my father have been destroyed, as if by magic, among these mountains; he has been driven into exile, and his daughter is a captive.”

“Beware, O king!” whispered Ibrahim Ebn Abu Ayub, “this may be one of those northern sorceresses of whom we have heard, who assume the most seductive forms to beguile the unwary. Methinks I read witchcraft in her eye, and sorcery in every movement. Doubtless this is the enemy pointed out by the talisman.”

“Son of Abu Ayub,” replied the king, “thou art a wise man, I grant, a conjuror for aught I know; but thou art little versed in the ways of woman. In that knowledge will I yield to no man; no, not to the wise Solomon himself, notwithstanding the number of his wives and concubines. As to this damsel, I see no harm in her; she is fair to look upon, and finds favor in my eyes.”

“Hearken, O king!” replied the astrologer. “I have given thee many victories by means of my talisman, but have never shared any of the spoil. Give me then this stray captive, to solace me in my solitude with her silver lyre. If she be indeed a sorceress, I have counter spells that set her charms at defiance.”

“What! more women!” cried Aben Habuz. “Hast thou not already dancing women enough to solace thee?”

“Dancing women have I, it is true, but no singing women. I would fain have a little minstrelsy to refresh my mind when weary with the toils of study.”

“A truce with thy hermit cravings,” said the king, impatiently. “This damsel have I marked for my own. I see much comfort in her; even such comfort as David, the father of Solomon the wise, found in the society of Abishag the Shunamite.”

Further solicitations and remonstrances of the astrologer only provoked a more peremptory reply from the monarch, and they parted in high displeasure. The sage shut himself up in his hermitage to brood over his disappointment; ere he departed, however, he gave the king one more warning to beware of his dangerous captive. But where is the old man in love that will listen to council? Aben Habuz resigned himself to the full sway of his passion. His only study was how to render himself amiable in the eyes of the Gothic beauty. He had not youth to recommend him, it is true, but then he had riches; and when a lover is old, he is generally generous. The Zacatin of Granada was ransacked for the most precious merchandise of the East; silks, jewels, precious gems, exquisite perfumes, all that Asia and Africa yielded of rich and rare, were lavished upon the princess. All kinds of spectacles and festivities were devised for her entertainment; minstrelsy, dancing, tournaments, bull-fights;—Granada for a time was a scene of perpetual pageant. The Gothic princess regarded all this splendor with the air of one accustomed to magnificence. She received every thing as a homage due to her rank, or rather to her beauty; for beauty is more lofty in its exactions even than rank. Nay, she seemed to take a secret pleasure in exciting the monarch to expenses that made his treasury shrink; and then treating his extravagant generosity as a mere matter of course. With all his assiduity and munificence, also, the venerable lover could not flatter himself that he had made any impression on her heart. She never frowned on him, it is true, but then she never smiled. Whenever he began to plead his passion, she struck her silver lyre. There was a mystic charm in the sound. In an instant the monarch began to nod; a drowsiness stole over him, and he gradually sank into a sleep, from which he awoke wonderfully refreshed, but perfectly cooled for the time of his passion. This was very baffling to his suit; but then these slumbers were accompanied by agreeable dreams, which completely enthralled the senses of the drowsy lover; so he continued to dream on, while all Granada scoffed at his infatuation, and groaned at the treasures lavished for a song.

At length a danger burst on the head of Aben Habuz, against which his talisman yielded him no warning. An insurrection broke out in his very capital: his palace was surrounded by an armed rabble, who menaced his life and the life of his Christian paramour. A spark of his ancient warlike spirit was awakened in the breast of the monarch. At the head of a handful of his guards he sallied forth, put the rebels to flight, and crushed the insurrection in the bud.

When quiet was again restored, he sought the astrologer, who still remained shut up in his hermitage, chewing the bitter cud of resentment.

Aben Habuz approached him with a conciliatory tone. “O wise son of Abu Ayub,” said he, “well didst thou predict dangers to me from this captive beauty: tell me then, thou who art so quick at foreseeing peril, what I should do to avert it.”

“Put from thee the infidel damsel who is the cause.”

“Sooner would I part with my kingdom,” cried Aben Habuz.

“Thou art in danger of losing both,” replied the astrologer.

“Be not harsh and angry, O most profound of philosophers; consider the double distress of a monarch and a lover, and devise some means of protecting me from the evils by which I am menaced. I care not for grandeur, I care not for power, I languish only for repose; would that I had some quiet retreat where I might take refuge from the world, and all its cares, and pomps, and troubles, and devote the remainder of my days to tranquillity and love.”

The astrologer regarded him for a moment, from under his bushy eyebrows.

“And what wouldst thou give, if I could provide thee such a retreat?”

“Thou shouldst name thy own reward, and whatever it might be, if within the scope of my power, as my soul liveth, it should be thine.”

“Thou hast heard, O king, of the garden of Irem, one of the prodigies of Arabia the happy?”

“I have heard of that garden; it is recorded in the Koran, even in the chapter entitled ‘The Dawn of Day.’ I have, moreover, heard marvellous things related of it by pilgrims who had been to Mecca; but I considered them wild fables, such as travellers are wont to tell who have visited remote countries.”

“Discredit not, O king, the tales of travellers,” rejoined the astrologer, gravely, “for they contain precious rarities of knowledge brought from the ends of the earth. As to the palace and garden of Irem, what is generally told of them is true; I have seen them with mine own eyes—listen to my adventure; for it has a bearing upon the object of your request.

“In my younger days, when a mere Arab of the desert, I tended my father's camels. In traversing the desert of Aden, one of them strayed from the rest, and was lost. I searched after it for several days, but in vain, until, wearied and faint, I laid myself down at noontide, and slept under a palm-tree by the side of a scanty well. When I awoke, I found myself at the gate of a city. I entered, and beheld noble streets, and squares, and market-places; but all were silent and without an inhabitant. I wandered on until I came to a sumptuous palace with a garden adorned with fountains and fishponds, and groves and flowers, and orchards laden with delicious fruit; but still no one was to be seen. Upon which, appalled at this loneliness, I hastened to depart; and, after issuing forth at the gate of the city, I turned to look upon the place, but it was no longer to be seen; nothing but the silent desert extended before my eyes.

“In the neighborhood I met with an aged dervise, learned in the traditions and secrets of the land, and related to him what had befallen me. ‘This,’ said he, ‘is the far-famed garden of Irem, one of the wonders of the desert. It only appears at times to some wanderer like thyself, gladdening him with the sight of towers and palaces and garden walls overhung with richly-laden fruit-trees, and then vanishes, leaving nothing but a lonely desert. And this is the story of it. In old times, when this country was inhabited by the Addites, King Sheddad, the son of Ad, the great grandson of Noah, founded here a splendid city. When it was finished, and he saw its grandeur, his heart was puffed up with pride and arrogance, and he determined to build a royal palace, with gardens which should rival all related in the Koran of the celestial paradise. But the curse of heaven fell upon him for his presumption. He and his subjects were swept from the earth, and his splendid city, and palace, and gardens, were laid under a perpetual spell, which hides them from human sight, excepting that they are seen at intervals, by way of keeping his sin in perpetual remembrance.’

“This story, O king, and the wonders I had seen, ever dwelt in my mind; and in after years, when I had been in Egypt, and was possessed of the book of knowledge of Solomon the wise, I determined to return and revisit the garden of Irem. I did so, and found it revealed to my instructed sight. I took possession of the palace of Sheddad, and passed several days in his mock paradise. The genii who watch over the place, were obedient to my magic power, and revealed to me the spells by which the whole garden had been, as it were, conjured into existence, and by which it was rendered invisible. Such a palace and garden, O king, can I make for thee, even here, on the mountain above thy city. Do I not know all the secret spells? and am I not in possession of the book of knowledge of Solomon the wise?”

“O wise son of Abu Ayub!” exclaimed Aben Habuz, trembling with eagerness, “thou art a traveller indeed, and hast seen and learned marvellous things! Contrive me such a paradise, and ask any reward, even to the half of my kingdom.”

“Alas!” replied the other, “thou knowest I am an old man, and a philosopher, and easily satisfied; all the reward I ask is the first beast of burden, with its load, which shall enter the magic portal of the palace.”

The monarch gladly agreed to so moderate a stipulation, and the astrologer began his work. On the summit of the hill, immediately above his subterranean hermitage, he caused a great gateway or barbican to be erected, opening through the centre of a strong tower.

There was an outer vestibule or porch, with a lofty arch, and within it a portal secured by massive gates. On the keystone of the portal the astrologer, with his own hand, wrought the figure of a huge key; and on the key-stone of the outer arch of the vestibule, which was loftier than that of the portal, he carved a gigantic hand. These were potent talismans, over which he repeated many sentences in an unknown tongue.

When this gateway was finished he shut himself up for two days in his astrological hall, engaged in secret incantations; on the third he ascended the hill, and passed the whole day on its summit. At a late hour of the night he came down, and presented himself before Aben Habuz. “At length, O king,” said he, “my labor is accomplished. On the summit of the hill stands one of the most delectable palaces that ever the head of man devised, or the heart of man desired. It contains sumptuous halls and galleries, delicious gardens, cool fountains, and fragrant baths; in a word, the whole mountain is converted into a paradise. Like the garden of Irem, it is protected by a mighty charm, which hides it from the view and search of mortals, excepting such as possess the secret of its talismans.”

“Enough!” cried Aben Habuz, joyfully, “to-morrow morning with the first light we will ascend and take possession.” The happy monarch slept but little that night. Scarcely had the rays of the sun begun to play about the snowy summit of the Sierra Nevada, when he mounted his steed, and, accompanied only by a few chosen attendants, ascended a steep and narrow road leading up the hill. Beside him, on a white palfrey, rode the Gothic princess, her whole dress sparkling with jewels, while round her neck was suspended her silver lyre. The astrologer walked on the other side of the king, assisting his steps with his hieroglyphic staff, for he never mounted steed of any kind.

Aben Habuz looked to see the towers of the palace brightening above him, and the imbowered terraces of its gardens stretching along the heights; but as yet nothing of the kind was to be descried. “That is the mystery and safeguard of the place,” said the astrologer, “nothing can be discerned until you have passed the spell-bound gateway, and been put in possession of the place.”

As they approached the gateway, the astrologer paused, and pointed out to the king the mystic hand and key carved upon the portal and the arch. “These,” said he, “are the talismans which guard the entrance to this paradise. Until yonder hand shall reach down and seize that key, neither mortal power nor magic artifice can prevail against the lord of this mountain.”

While Aben Habuz was gazing, with open mouth and silent wonder, at these mystic talismans, the palfrey of the princess proceeded, and bore her in at the portal, to the very centre of the barbican.

“Behold,” cried the astrologer, “my promised reward; the first animal with its burden which should enter the magic gateway.”

Aben Habuz smiled at what he considered a pleasantry of the ancient man; but when he found him to be in earnest, his grey beard trembled with indignation.

“Son of Abu Ayub,” said he, sternly, “what equivocation is this? Thou knowest the meaning of my promise: the first beast of burden, with its load, that should enter this portal. Take the strongest mule in my stables, load it with the most precious things of my treasury, and it is thine; but dare not raise thy thoughts to her who is the delight of my heart.”

“What need I of wealth?” cried the astrologer, scornfully; “have I not the book of knowledge of Solomon the wise, and through it the command of the secret treasures of the earth? The princess is mine by right; thy royal word is pledged; I claim her as my own.”

The princess looked down haughtily from her palfrey, and a light smile of scorn curled her rosy lip at this dispute between two gray-beards, for the possession of youth and beauty. The wrath of the monarch got the better of his discretion. “Base son of the desert,” cried he, “thou may'st be master of many arts, but know me for thy master, and presume not to juggle with thy king.”

“My master! my king!” echoed the astrologer,—“the monarch of a mole-hill to claim sway over him who possesses the talismans of Solomon! Farewell, Aben Habuz; reign over thy petty kingdom, and revel in thy paradise of fools, for me, I will laugh at thee in my philosophic retirement.”

So saying he seized the bridle of the palfrey, smote the earth with his staff, and sank with the Gothic princess through the centre of the barbican. The earth closed over them, and no trace remained of the opening by which they had descended.

Aben Habuz was struck dumb for a time with astonishment. Recovering himself, he ordered a thousand workmen to dig, with pickaxe and spade, into the ground where the astrologer had disappeared. They digged and digged, but in vain; the flinty bosom of the hill resisted their implements; or if they did penetrate a little way, the earth filled in again as fast as they threw it out. Aben Habuz sought the mouth of the cavern at the foot of the hill, leading to the subterranean palace of the astrologer; but it was nowhere to be found. Where once had been an entrance, was now a solid surface of primeval rock. With the disappearance of Ibrahim Ebn Abu Ayub ceased the benefit of his talismans. The bronze horseman remained fixed, with his face turned toward the hill, and his spear pointed to the spot where the astrologer had descended, as if there still lurked the deadliest foe of Aben Habuz.

From time to time the sound of music, and the tones of a female voice, could be faintly heard from the bosom of the hill; and a peasant one day brought word to the king, that in the preceding night he had found a fissure in the rock, by which he had crept in, until he looked down into a subterranean hall, in which sat the astrologer, on a magnificent divan, slumbering and nodding to the silver lyre of the princess, which seemed to hold a magic sway over his senses.

Aben Habuz sought the fissure in the rock, but it was again closed. He renewed the attempt to unearth his rival, but all in vain. The spell of the hand and key was too potent to be counteracted by human power. As to the summit of the mountain, the site of the promised palace and garden, it remained a naked waste; either the boasted elysium was hidden from sight by enchantment, or was a mere fable of the astrologer. The world charitably supposed the latter, and some used to call the place “The King's Folly;” while others named it “The Fool's Paradise.”

To add to the chagrin of Aben Habuz, the neighbors whom he had defied and taunted, and cut up at his leisure while master of the talismanic horseman, finding him no longer protected by magic spell, made inroads into his territories from all sides, and the remainder of the life of the most pacific of monarchs was a tissue of turmoils.

At length Aben Habuz died, and was buried. Ages have since rolled away. The Alhambra has been built on the eventful mountain, and in some measure realizes the fabled delights of the garden of Irem. The spell-bound gateway still exists entire, protected no doubt by the mystic hand and key, and now forms the Gate of Justice, the grand entrance to the fortress. Under that gateway, it is said, the old astrologer remains in his subterranean hall, nodding on his divan, lulled by the silver lyre of the princess.

The old invalid sentinels who mount guard at the gate hear the strains occasionally in the summer nights; and, yielding to their soporific power, doze quietly at their posts. Nay, so drowsy an influence pervades the place, that even those who watch by day may generally be seen nodding on the stone benches of the barbican, or sleeping under the neighboring trees; so that in fact it is the drowsiest military post in all Christendom. All this, say the ancient legends, will endure from age to age. The princess will remain captive to the astrologer; and the astrologer, bound up in magic slumber by the princess, until the last day, unless the mystic hand shall grasp the fated key, and dispel the whole charm of this enchanted mountain.

Note to the Arabian Astrologer

Al Makkari, in his history of the Mahommedan Dynasties in Spain, cites from another Arabian writer an account of a talismanic effigy somewhat similar to the one in the foregoing legend.

In Cadiz, says he, there formerly stood a square tower upwards of one hundred cubits high, built of huge blocks of stone, fastened together with clamps of brass. On the top was the figure of a man, holding a staff in his right hand, his face turned to the Atlantic, and pointing with the forefinger of his left hand to the Straits of Gibraltar. It was said to have been set up in ancient times by the Gothic kings of Andalus, as a beacon or guide to navigators. The Moslems of Barbary and Andalus, considered it a talisman which exercised a spell over the seas. Under its guidance, swarms of piratical people of a nation called Majus, appeared on the coast in large vessels with a square sail in the bow, and another in the stern. They came every six or seven years; captured every thing they met with on the sea; guided by the statue, they passed through the Straits into the Mediterranean, landed on the coasts of Andalus, laid every thing waste with fire and sword; and sometimes carried their depredations on the opposite coasts even as far as Syria.

At length it came to pass in the time of the civil wars, a Moslem Admiral who had taken possession of Cadiz, hearing that the statue on top of the tower was of pure gold, had it lowered to the ground and broken to pieces: when it proved to be of gilded brass. With the destruction of the idol, the spell over the sea was at an end. From that time forward, nothing more was seen of the piratical people of the ocean, excepting that two of their barks were wrecked on the coast, one at Marsu-l-Majus (the port of the Majus), the other close to the promontory of Al-Aghan.

The maritime invaders above mentioned by Al Makkari must have been the Northmen.

Legend of the Moor's Legacy

Just within the fortress of the Alhambra, in front of the royal palace, is a broad open esplanade, called the Place or Square of the Cisterns, (la Plaza de los Algibes,) so called from being undermined by reservoirs of water, hidden from sight, and which have existed from the time of the Moors. At one corner of this esplanade is a Moorish well, cut through the living rock to a great depth, the water of which is cold as ice and clear as crystal. The wells made by the Moors are always in repute, for it is well known what pains they took to penetrate to the purest and sweetest springs and fountains. The one of which we now speak is famous throughout Granada, insomuch that water-carriers, some bearing great water-jars on their shoulders, others driving asses before them laden with earthen vessels, are ascending and descending the steep woody avenues of the Alhambra, from early dawn until a late hour of the night.

Fountains and wells, ever since the scriptural days, have been noted gossiping places in hot climates; and at the well in question there is a kind of perpetual club kept up during the livelong day, by the invalids, old women, and other curious do nothing folk of the fortress, who sit here on the stone benches, under an awning spread over the well to shelter the toll-gatherer from the sun, and dawdle over the gossip of the fortress, and question every water-carrier that arrives about the news of the city, and make long comments on every thing they hear and see. Not an hour of the day but loitering housewives and idle maid-servants may be seen, lingering, with pitcher on head or in hand, to hear the last of the endless tattle of these worthies.

Among the water-carriers who once resorted to this well, there was a sturdy, strong-backed, bandy-legged little fellow, named Pedro Gil, but called Peregil for shortness. Being a water-carrier, he was a Gallego, or native of Gallicia, of course. Nature seems to have formed races of men, as she has of animals, for different kinds of drudgery. In France the shoeblacks are all Savoyards, the porters of hotels all Swiss, and in the days of hoops and hair-powder in England, no man could give the regular swing to a sedan-chair but a bog-trotting Irishman. So in Spain, the carriers of water and bearers of burdens are all sturdy little natives of Gallicia. No man says, “Get me a porter,” but, “Call a Gallego.”

To return from this digression, Peregil the Gallego had begun business with merely a great earthen jar which he carried upon his shoulder; by degrees he rose in the world, and was enabled to purchase an assistant of a correspondent class of animals, being a stout shaggy-haired donkey. On each side of this his long-eared aide-de-camp, in a kind of pannier, were slung his water-jars, covered with fig-leaves to protect them from the sun. There was not a more industrious water-carrier in all Granada, nor one more merry withal. The streets rang with his cheerful voice as he trudged after his donkey, singing forth the usual summer note that resounds through the Spanish towns: “Quien quiere agua—agua mas fria que la nieve?”—“Who wants water—water colder than snow? Who wants water from the well of the Alhambra, cold as ice and clear as crystal?” When he served a customer with a sparkling glass, it was always with a pleasant word that caused a smile; and if, perchance, it was a comely dame or dimpling damsel, it was always with a sly leer and a compliment to her beauty that was irresistible. Thus Peregil the Gallego was noted throughout all Granada for being one of the civilest, pleasantest, and happiest of mortals. Yet it is not he who sings loudest and jokes most that has the lightest heart. Under all this air of merriment, honest Peregil had his cares and troubles. He had a large family of ragged children to support, who were hungry and clamorous as a nest of young swallows, and beset him with their outcries for food whenever he came home of an evening. He had a helpmate, too, who was any thing but a help to him. She had been a village beauty before marriage, noted for her skill at dancing the bolero and rattling the castanets; and she still retained her early propensities, spending the hard earnings of honest Peregil in frippery, and laying the very donkey under requisition for junketing parties into the country on Sundays, and saints' days, and those innumerable holidays which are rather more numerous in Spain than the days of the week. With all this she was a little of a slattern, something more of a lie-abed, and, above all, a gossip of the first water; neglecting house, household, and every thing else, to loiter slipshod in the houses of her gossip neighbors.

He, however, who tempers the wind to the shorn lamb, accommodates the yoke of matrimony to the submissive neck. Peregil bore all the heavy dispensations of wife and children with as meek a spirit as his donkey bore the water-jars; and, however he might shake his ears in private, never ventured to question the household virtues of his slattern spouse.

He loved his children too even as an owl loves its owlets, seeing in them his own image multiplied and perpetuated; for they were a sturdy, long-backed, bandy-legged little brood. The great pleasure of honest Peregil was, whenever he could afford himself a scanty holiday, and had a handful of marevedis to spare, to take the whole litter forth with him, some in his arms, some tugging at his skirts, and some trudging at his heels, and to treat them to a gambol among the orchards of the Vega, while his wife was dancing with her holiday friends in the Angosturas of the Darro.

It was a late hour one summer night, and most of the water-carriers had desisted from their toils. The day had been uncommonly sultry; the night was one of those delicious moonlights, which tempt the inhabitants of southern climes to indemnify themselves for the heat and inaction of the day, by lingering in the open air, and enjoying its tempered sweetness until after midnight. Customers for water were therefore still abroad. Peregil, like a considerate, painstaking father, thought of his hungry children. “One more journey to the well,” said he to himself, “to earn a Sunday's puchero for the little ones.” So saying, he trudged manfully up the steep avenue of the Alhambra, singing as he went, and now and then bestowing a hearty thwack with a cudgel on the flanks of his donkey, either by way of cadence to the song, or refreshment to the animal; for dry blows serve in lieu of provender in Spain for all beasts of burden.

When arrived at the well, he found it deserted by every one except a solitary stranger in Moorish garb, seated on a stone bench in the moonlight. Peregil paused at first and regarded him with surprise, not unmixed with awe, but the Moor feebly beckoned him to approach. “I am faint and ill,” said he, “aid me to return to the city, and I will pay thee double what thou couldst gain by thy jars of water.”

The honest heart of the little water-carrier was touched with compassion at the appeal of the stranger. “God forbid,” said he, “that I should ask fee or reward for doing a common act of humanity.” He accordingly helped the Moor on his donkey, and set off slowly for Granada, the poor Moslem being so weak that it was necessary to hold him on the animal to keep him from falling to the earth.

When they entered the city, the water-carrier demanded whither he should conduct him. “Alas!” said the Moor, faintly, “I have neither home nor habitation, I am a stranger in the land. Suffer me to lay my head this night beneath thy roof, and thou shalt be amply repaid.”

Honest Peregil thus saw himself unexpectedly saddled with an infidel guest, but he was too humane to refuse a night's shelter to a fellow being in so forlorn a plight, so he conducted the Moor to his dwelling. The children, who had sallied forth open-mouthed as usual on hearing the tramp of the donkey, ran back with affright, when they beheld the turbaned stranger, and hid themselves behind their mother. The latter stepped forth intrepidly, like a ruffling hen before her brood when a vagrant dog approaches.

“What infidel companion,” cried she, “is this you have brought home at this late hour, to draw upon us the eyes of the inquisition?”

“Be quiet, wife,” replied the Gallego, “here is a poor sick stranger, without friend or home; wouldst thou turn him forth to perish in the streets?”

The wife would still have remonstrated, for although she lived in a hovel she was a furious stickler for the credit of her house; the little water-carrier, however, for once was stiffnecked, and refused to bend beneath the yoke. He assisted the poor Moslem to alight, and spread a mat and a sheep-skin for him, on the ground, in the coolest part of the house; being the only kind of bed that his poverty afforded.

In a little while the Moor was seized with violent convulsions, which defied all the ministering skill of the simple water-carrier. The eye of the poor patient acknowledged his kindness. During an interval of his fits he called him to his side, and addressing him in a low voice, “My end,” said he, “I fear is at hand. If I die, I bequeath you this box as a reward for your charity:” so saying, he opened his albornoz, or cloak, and showed a small box of sandal-wood, strapped round his body. “God grant, my friend,” replied the worthy little Gallego, “that you may live many years to enjoy your treasure, whatever it may be.” The Moor shook his head; he laid his hand upon the box, and would have said something more concerning it, but his convulsions returned with increasing violence, and in a little while he expired.

The water-carrier's wife was now as one distracted. “This comes,” said she, “of your foolish good nature, always running into scapes to oblige others. What will become of us when this corpse is found in our house? We shall be sent to prison as murderers; and if we escape with our lives, shall be ruined by notaries and alguazils.”

Poor Peregil was in equal tribulation, and almost repented himself of having done a good deed. At length a thought struck him. “It is not yet day,” said he, “I can convey the dead body out of the city, and bury it in the sands on the banks of the Xenil. No one saw the Moor enter our dwelling, and no one will know any thing of his death.”

So said, so done. The wife aided him; they rolled the body of the unfortunate Moslem in the mat on which he had expired, laid it across the ass, and Peregil set out with it for the banks of the river.

As ill luck would have it, there lived opposite to the water-carrier a barber named Pedrillo Pedrugo, one of the most prying, tattling, and mischief-making of his gossip tribe. He was a weasel-faced, spider-legged varlet, supple and insinuating; the famous barber of Seville could not surpass him for his universal knowledge of the affairs of others, and he had no more power of retention than a sieve. It was said that he slept but with one eye at a time, and kept one ear uncovered, so that, even in his sleep he might see and hear all that was going on. Certain it is, he was a sort of scandalous chronicle for the quid-nuncs of Granada, and had more customers than all the rest of his fraternity.

This meddlesome barber heard Peregil arrive at an unusual hour at night, and the exclamations of his wife and children. His head was instantly popped out of a little window which served him as a look-out, and he saw his neighbor assist a man in Moorish garb into his dwelling. This was so strange an occurrence, that Pedrillo Pedrugo slept not a wink that night. Every five minutes he was at his loophole, watching the lights that gleamed through the chinks of his neighbor's door, and before daylight he beheld Peregil sally forth with his donkey unusually laden.

The inquisitive barber was in a fidget; he slipped on his clothes, and, stealing forth silently, followed the water-carrier at a distance, until he saw him dig a hole in the sandy bank of the Xenil, and bury something that had the appearance of a dead body.

The barber hied him home, and fidgeted about his shop, setting every thing upside down, until sunrise. He then took a basin under his arm, and sallied forth to the house of his daily customer the alcalde.

The alcalde was just risen. Pedrillo Pedrugo seated him in a chair, threw a napkin round his neck, put a basin of hot water under his chin, and began to mollify his beard with his fingers.

“Strange doings!” said Pedrugo, who played barber and newsmonger at the same time—“strange doings! Robbery, and murder, and burial all in one night!”

“Hey!—how!—what is that you say?” cried the alcalde.

“I say,” replied the barber, rubbing a piece of soap over the nose and mouth of the dignitary, for a Spanish barber disdains to employ a brush—“I say that Peregil the Gallego has robbed and murdered a Moorish Mussulman, and buried him, this blessed night. Maldita sea la noche;—accursed be the night for the same!”

“But how do you know all this?” demanded the alcalde.

“Be patient, Señor, and you shall hear all about it,” replied Pedrillo, taking him by the nose and sliding a razor over his cheek. He then recounted all that he had seen, going through both operations at the same time, shaving his beard, washing his chin, and wiping him dry with a dirty napkin, while he was robbing, murdering, and burying the Moslem.

Now it so happened that this alcalde was one of the most overbearing, and at the same time most griping and corrupt curmudgeons in all Granada. It could not be denied, however, that he set a high value upon justice, for he sold it at its weight in gold. He presumed the case in point to be one of murder and robbery; doubtless there must be a rich spoil; how was it to be secured into the legitimate hands of the law? for as to merely entrapping the delinquent—that would be feeding the gallows; but entrapping the booty—that would be enriching the judge, and such, according to his creed, was the great end of justice. So thinking, he summoned to his presence his trustiest alguazil—a gaunt, hungry-looking varlet, clad, according to the custom of his order, in the ancient Spanish garb, a broad black beaver turned up at its sides; a quaint ruff; a small black cloak dangling from his shoulders; rusty black under-clothes that set off his spare wiry frame, while in his hand he bore a slender white wand, the dreaded insignia of his office. Such was the legal bloodhound of the ancient Spanish breed, that he put upon the traces of the unlucky water-carrier, and such was his speed and certainty, that he was upon the haunches of poor Peregil before he had returned to his dwelling, and brought both him and his donkey before the dispenser of justice.

The alcalde bent upon him one of the most terrific frowns. “Hark ye, culprit!” roared he, in a voice that made the knees of the little Gallego smite together,—“hark ye, culprit! there is no need of denying thy guilt, every thing is known to me. A gallows is the proper reward for the crime thou hast committed, but I am merciful, and readily listen to reason. The man that has been murdered in thy house was a Moor, an infidel, the enemy of our faith. It was doubtless in a fit of religious zeal that thou hast slain him. I will be indulgent, therefore; render up the property of which thou hast robbed him, and we will hush the matter up.”

The poor water-carrier called upon all the saints to witness his innocence; alas! not one of them appeared; and if they had, the alcalde would have disbelieved the whole calendar. The water-carrier related the whole story of the dying Moor with the straightforward simplicity of truth, but it was all in vain. “Wilt thou persist in saying,” demanded the judge, “that this Moslem had neither gold nor jewels, which were the object of thy cupidity?”

“As I hope to be saved, your worship,” replied the water-carrier, “he had nothing but a small box of sandal-wood which he bequeathed to me in reward for my services.”

“A box of sandal-wood! a box of sandal-wood!” exclaimed the alcalde, his eyes sparkling at the idea of precious jewels. “And where is this box? where have you concealed it?”

“An' it please your grace,” replied the water-carrier, “it is in one of the panniers of my mule, and heartily at the service of your worship.”

He had hardly spoken the words, when the keen alguazil darted off, and reappeared in an instant with the mysterious box of sandal-wood. The alcalde opened it with an eager and trembling hand; all pressed forward to gaze upon the treasures it was expected to contain; when, to their disappointment, nothing appeared within, but a parchment scroll, covered with Arabic characters, and an end of a waxen taper.

When there is nothing to be gained by the conviction of a prisoner, justice, even in Spain, is apt to be impartial. The alcalde, having recovered from his disappointment, and found that there was really no booty in the case, now listened dispassionately to the explanation of the water-carrier, which was corroborated by the testimony of his wife. Being convinced, therefore, of his innocence, he discharged him from arrest; nay more, he permitted him to carry off the Moor's legacy, the box of sandal-wood and its contents, as the well-merited reward of his humanity; but he retained his donkey in payment of costs and charges.

Behold the unfortunate little Gallego reduced once more to the necessity of being his own water-carrier, and trudging up to the well of the Alhambra with a great earthen jar upon his shoulder.

As he toiled up the hill in the heat of a summer noon, his usual good humor forsook him. “Dog of an alcalde!” would he cry, “to rob a poor man of the means of his subsistence, of the best friend he had in the world!” And then at the remembrance of the beloved companion of his labors, all the kindness of his nature would break forth. “Ah, donkey of my heart!” would he exclaim, resting his burden on a stone, and wiping the sweat from his brow—“Ah, donkey of my heart! I warrant me thou thinkest of thy old master! I warrant me thou missest the water-jars—poor beast.”

To add to his afflictions, his wife received him, on his return home, with whimperings and repinings; she had clearly the vantage-ground of him, having warned him not to commit the egregious act of hospitality which had brought on him all these misfortunes; and, like a knowing woman, she took every occasion to throw her superior sagacity in his teeth. If her children lacked food, or needed a new garment, she could answer with a sneer—“Go to your father—he is heir to King Chico of the Alhambra: ask him to help you out of the Moor's strong box.”

Was ever poor mortal so soundly punished for having done a good action? The unlucky Peregil was grieved in flesh and spirit, but still he bore meekly with the railings of his spouse. At length, one evening, when, after a hot day's toil, she taunted him in the usual manner, he lost all patience. He did not venture to retort upon her, but his eye rested upon the box of sandal-wood which lay on a shelf with lid half open, as if laughing in mockery at his vexation. Seizing it up, he dashed it with indignation to the floor: “Unlucky was the day that I ever set eyes on thee,” he cried, “or sheltered thy master beneath my roof!”

As the box struck the floor, the lid flew wide open, and the parchment scroll rolled forth.

Peregil sat regarding the scroll for some time in moody silence. At length rallying his ideas: “Who knows,” thought he, “but this writing may be of some importance, as the Moor seems to have guarded it with such care?” Picking it up therefore, he put it in his bosom, and the next morning, as he was crying water through the streets, he stopped at the shop of a Moor, a native of Tangiers, who sold trinkets and perfumery in the Zacatin, and asked him to explain the contents.

The Moor read the scroll attentively, then stroked his beard and smiled. “This manuscript,” said he, “is a form of incantation for the recovery of hidden treasure, that is under the power of enchantment. It is said to have such virtue that the strongest bolts and bars, nay the adamantine rock itself, will yield before it!”

“Bah!” cried the little Gallego, “what is all that to me? I am no enchanter, and know nothing of buried treasure.” So saying, he shouldered his water-jar, left the scroll in the hands of the Moor, and trudged forward on his daily rounds.

That evening, however, as he rested himself about twilight at the well of the Alhambra, he found a number of gossips assembled at the place, and their conversation, as is not unusual at that shadowy hour, turned upon old tales and traditions of a supernatural nature. Being all poor as rats, they dwelt with peculiar fondness upon the popular theme of enchanted riches left by the Moors in various parts of the Alhambra. Above all, they concurred in the belief that there were great treasures buried deep in the earth under the tower of the seven floors.

These stories made an unusual impression on the mind of the honest Peregil, and they sank deeper and deeper into his thoughts as he returned alone down the darkling avenues. “If, after all, there should be treasure hid beneath that tower: and if the scroll I left with the Moor should enable me to get at it!” In the sudden ecstasy of the thought he had well nigh let fall his water-jar.

That night he tumbled and tossed, and could scarcely get a wink of sleep for the thoughts that were bewildering his brain. Bright and early, he repaired to the shop of the Moor, and told him all that was passing in his mind. “You can read Arabic,” said he, “suppose we go together to the tower, and try the effect of the charm; if it fails we are no worse off than before; but if it succeeds, we will share equally all the treasure we may discover.”

“Hold,” replied the Moslem; “this writing is not sufficient of itself; it must be read at midnight, by the light of a taper singularly compounded and prepared, the ingredients of which are not within my reach. Without such a taper the scroll is of no avail.”

“Say no more!” cried the little Gallego; “I have such a taper at hand, and will bring it here in a moment.” So saying, he hastened home, and soon returned with the end of yellow wax taper that he had found in the box of sandal-wood.

The Moor felt it and smelt to it. “Here are rare and costly perfumes,” said he, “combined with this yellow wax. This is the kind of taper specified in the scroll. While this burns, the strongest walls and most secret caverns will remain open. Woe to him, however, who lingers within until it be extinguished. He will remain enchanted with the treasure.”

It was now agreed between them to try the charm that very night. At a late hour, therefore, when nothing was stirring but bats and owls, they ascended the woody hill of the Alhambra, and approached that awful tower, shrouded by trees and rendered formidable by so many traditionary tales. By the light of a lantern they groped their way through bushes, and over fallen stones, to the door of a vault beneath the tower. With fear and trembling they descended a flight of steps cut into the rock. It led to an empty chamber damp and drear, from which another flight of steps led to a deeper vault. In this way they descended four several flights, leading into as many vaults one below the other, but the floor of the fourth was solid; and though, according to tradition, there remained three vaults still below, it was said to be impossible to penetrate further, the residue being shut up by strong enchantment. The air of this vault was damp and chilly, and had an earthy smell, and the light scarce cast forth any rays. They paused here for a time in breathless suspense, until they faintly heard the clock of the watch-tower strike midnight; upon this they lit the waxen taper, which diffused an odor of myrrh and frankincense and storax.

The Moor began to read in a hurried voice. He had scarce finished when there was a noise as of subterraneous thunder. The earth shook, and the floor, yawning open, disclosed a flight of steps. Trembling with awe they descended, and by the light of the lantern found themselves in another vault, covered with Arabic inscriptions. In the centre stood a great chest, secured with seven bands of steel, at each end of which sat an enchanted Moor in armor, but motionless as a statue, being controlled by the power of the incantation. Before the chest were several jars filled with gold and silver and precious stones. In the largest of these they thrust their arms up to the elbow, and at every dip hauled forth handfuls of broad yellow pieces of Moorish gold, or bracelets and ornaments of the same precious metal, while occasionally a necklace of oriental pearl would stick to their fingers. Still they trembled and breathed short while cramming their pockets with the spoils; and cast many a fearful glance at the two enchanted Moors, who sat grim and motionless, glaring upon them with unwinking eyes. At length, struck with a sudden panic at some fancied noise, they both rushed up the staircase, tumbled over one another into the upper apartment, overturned and extinguished the waxen taper, and the pavement again closed with a thundering sound.

Filled with dismay, they did not pause until they had groped their way out of the tower, and beheld the stars shining through the trees. Then seating themselves upon the grass, they divided the spoil, determining to content themselves for the present with this mere skimming of the jars, but to return on some future night and drain them to the bottom. To make sure of each other's good faith, also, they divided the talismans between them, one retaining the scroll and the other the taper; this done, they set off with light hearts and well-lined pockets for Granada.

As they wended their way down the hill, the shrewd Moor whispered a word of counsel in the ear of the simple little water-carrier.

“Friend Peregil,” said he, “all this affair must be kept a profound secret until we have secured the treasure, and conveyed it out of harm's way. If a whisper of it gets to the ear of the alcalde, we are undone!”

“Certainly,” replied the Gallego, “nothing can be more true.”

“Friend Peregil,” said the Moor, “you are a discreet man, and I make no doubt can keep a secret: but you have a wife.”

“She shall not know a word of it,” replied the little water-carrier, sturdily.

“Enough,” said the Moor, “I depend upon thy discretion and thy promise.”

Never was promise more positive and sincere; but, alas! what man can keep a secret from his wife? Certainly not such a one as Peregil the water-carrier, who was one of the most loving and tractable of husbands. On his return home, he found his wife moping in a corner. “Mighty well,” cried she as he entered, “you've come at last; after rambling about until this hour of the night. I wonder you have not brought home another Moor as a house-mate.” Then bursting into tears, she began to wring her hands and smite her breast: “Unhappy woman that I am!” exclaimed she, “what will become of me? My house stripped and plundered by lawyers and alguazils; my husband a do-no-good, that no longer brings home bread to his family, but goes rambling about day and night, with infidel Moors! O my children! my children! what will become of us? We shall all have to beg in the streets!”

Honest Peregil was so moved by the distress of his spouse, that he could not help whimpering also. His heart was as full as his pocket, and not to be restrained. Thrusting his hand into the latter he hauled forth three or four broad gold pieces, and slipped them into her bosom. The poor woman stared with astonishment, and could not understand the meaning of this golden shower. Before she could recover her surprise, the little Gallego drew forth a chain of gold and dangled it before her, capering with exultation, his mouth distended from ear to ear.

“Holy Virgin protect us!” exclaimed the wife. “What hat thou been doing, Peregil? surely thou hast not been committing murder and robbery!”

The idea scarce entered the brain of the poor woman, than it became a certainty with her. She saw a prison and a gallows in the distance, and a little bandy-legged Gallego hanging pendant from it; and, overcome by the horrors conjured up by her imagination, fell into violent hysterics.

What could the poor man do? He had no other means of pacifying his wife, and dispelling the phantoms of her fancy, than by relating the whole story of his good fortune. This, however, he did not do until he had exacted from her the most solemn promise to keep it a profound secret from every living being.

To describe her joy would be impossible. She flung her arms round the neck of her husband, and almost strangled him with her caresses. “Now, wife,” exclaimed the little man with honest exultation, “what say you now to the Moor's legacy? Henceforth never abuse me for helping a fellow-creature in distress.”

The honest Gallego retired to his sheep-skin mat, and slept as soundly as if on a bed of down. Not so his wife; she emptied the whole contents of his pockets upon the mat, and sat counting gold pieces of Arabic coin, trying on necklaces and earrings, and fancying the figure she should one day make when permitted to enjoy her riches.

On the following morning the honest Gallego took a broad golden coin, and repaired with it to a jeweller's shop in the Zacatin to offer it for sale, pretending to have found it among the ruins of the Alhambra. The jeweller saw that it had an Arabic inscription, and was of the purest gold; he offered, however, but a third of its value, with which the water-carrier was perfectly content. Peregil now bought new clothes for his little flock, and all kinds of toys, together with ample provisions for a hearty meal, and returning to his dwelling, sat all his children dancing around him, while he capered in the midst, the happiest of fathers.

The wife of the water-carrier kept her promise of secrecy with surprising strictness. For a whole day and a half she went about with a look of mystery and a heart swelling almost to bursting, yet she held her peace, though surrounded by her gossips. It is true, she could not help giving herself a few airs, apologized for her ragged dress, and talked of ordering a new basquina all trimmed with gold lace and bugles, and a new lace mantilla. She threw out hints of her husband's intention of leaving off his trade of water-carrying, as it did not altogether agree with his health. In fact she thought they should all retire to the country for the summer, that the children might have the benefit of the mountain air, for there was no living in the city in this sultry season.

The neighbors stared at each other, and thought the poor woman had lost her wits; and her airs and graces and elegant pretensions were the theme of universal scoffing and merriment among her friends, the moment her back was turned.

If she restrained herself abroad, however, she indemnified herself at home, and putting a string of rich Oriental pearls round her neck, Moorish bracelets on her arms, and an aigrette of diamonds on her head, sailed backwards and forwards in her slattern rags about the room, now and then stopping to admire herself in a broken mirror. Nay, in the impulse of her simple vanity, she could not resist, on one occasion, showing herself at the window to enjoy the effect of her finery on the passers by.

As the fates would have it, Pedrillo Pedrugo, the meddlesome barber, was at this moment sitting idly in his shop on the opposite side of the street, when his ever-watchful eye caught the sparkle of a diamond. In an instant he was at his loophole reconnoitering the slattern spouse of the water-carrier, decorated with the splendor of an eastern bride. No sooner had he taken an accurate inventory of her ornaments, than he posted off with all speed to the alcalde. In a little while the hungry alguazil was again on the scent, and before the day was over the unfortunate Peregil was once more dragged into the presence of the judge.

“How is this, villain!” cried the alcalde, in a furious voice. “You told me that the infidel who died in your house left nothing behind but an empty coffer, and now I hear of your wife flaunting in her rags decked out with pearls and diamonds. Wretch that thou art! prepare to render up the spoils of thy miserable victim, and to swing on the gallows that is already tired of waiting for thee.”

The terrified water-carrier fell on his knees, and made a full relation of the marvellous manner in which he had gained his wealth. The alcalde, the alguazil, and the inquisitive barber, listened with greedy ears to this Arabian tale of enchanted treasure. The alguazil was dispatched to bring the Moor who had assisted in the incantation. The Moslem entered half frightened out of his wits at finding himself in the hands of the harpies of the law. When he beheld the water-carrier standing with sheepish looks and downcast countenance, he comprehended the whole matter. “Miserable animal,” said he, as he passed near him, “did I not warn thee against babbling to thy wife?”

The story of the Moor coincided exactly with that of his colleague; but the alcalde affected to be slow of belief, and threw out menaces of imprisonment and rigorous investigation.

“Softly, good Señor Alcalde,” said the Mussulman, who by this time had recovered his usual shrewdness and self-possession. “Let us not mar fortune's favors in the scramble for them. Nobody knows any thing of this matter but ourselves; let us keep the secret. There is wealth enough in the cave to enrich us all. Promise a fair division, and all shall be produced; refuse, and the cave shall remain for ever closed.”

The alcalde consulted apart with the alguazil. The latter was an old fox in his profession. “Promise any thing,” said he, “until you get possession of the treasure. You may then seize upon the whole, and if he and his accomplice dare to murmur, threaten them with the fagot and the stake as infidels and sorcerers.”

The alcalde relished the advice. Smoothing his brow and turning to the Moor, “This is a strange story,” said he, “and may be true, but I must have ocular proof of it. This very night you must repeat the incantation in my presence. If there be really such treasure, we will share it amicably between us, and say nothing further of the matter; if ye have deceived me, expect no mercy at my hands. In the mean time you must remain in custody.”

The Moor and the water-carrier cheerfully agreed to these conditions, satisfied that the event would prove the truth of their words.

Towards midnight the alcalde sallied forth secretly, attended by the alguazil and the meddlesome barber, all strongly armed. They conducted the Moor and the water-carrier as prisoners, and were provided with the stout donkey of the latter to bear off the expected treasure. They arrived at the tower without being observed, and tying the donkey to a fig-tree, descended into the fourth vault of the tower.

The scroll was produced, the yellow waxen taper lighted, and the Moor read the form of incantation. The earth trembled as before, and the pavement opened with a thundering sound, disclosing the narrow flight of steps. The alcalde, the alguazil, and the barber were struck aghast, and could not summon courage to descend. The Moor and the water-carrier entered the lower vault, and found the two Moors seated as before, silent and motionless. They removed two of the great jars, filled with golden coin and precious stones. The water-carrier bore them up one by one upon his shoulders, but though a strong-backed little man, and accustomed to carry burdens, he staggered beneath their weight, and found, when slung on each side of his donkey, they were as much as the animal could bear.

“Let us be content for the present,” said the Moor; “here is as much treasure as we can carry off without being perceived, and enough to make us all wealthy to our heart's desire.”

“Is there more treasure remaining behind?” demanded the alcalde.

“The greatest prize of all,” said the Moor, “a huge coffer bound with bands of steel, and filled with pearls and precious stones.”

“Let us have up the coffer by all means,” cried the grasping alcalde.

“I will descend for no more,” said the Moor, doggedly; “enough is enough for a reasonable man—more is superfluous.”

“And I,” said the water-carrier, “will bring up no further burden to break the back of my poor donkey.”

Finding commands, threats, and entreaties equally vain, the alcalde turned to his two adherents. “Aid me,” said he, “to bring up the coffer, and its contents shall be divided between us.” So saying he descended the steps, followed with trembling reluctance by the alguazil and the barber.

No sooner did the Moor behold them fairly earthed than he extinguished the yellow taper; the pavement closed with its usual crash, and the three worthies remained buried in its womb.

He then hastened up the different flights of steps, nor stopped until in the open air. The little water-carrier followed him as fast as his short legs would permit.

“What hast thou done?” cried Peregil, as soon as he could recover breath. “The alcalde and the other two are shut up in the vault.”

“It is the will of Allah!” said the Moor devoutly.

“And will you not release them?” demanded the Gallego.

“Allah forbid!” replied the Moor, smoothing his beard. “It is written in the book of fate that they shall remain enchanted until some future adventurer arrive to break the charm. The will of God be done!” so saying, he hurled the end of the waxen taper far among the gloomy thickets of the glen.

There was now no remedy, so the Moor and the water-carrier proceeded with the richly laden donkey toward the city, nor could honest Peregil refrain from hugging and kissing his long-eared fellow-laborer, thus restored to him from the clutches of the law; and in fact, it is doubtful which gave the simple hearted little man most joy at the moment, the gaining of the treasure, or the recovery of the donkey.

The two partners in good luck divided their spoil amicably and fairly, except that the Moor, who had a little taste for trinketry, made out to get into his heap the most of the pearls and precious stones and other baubles, but then he always gave the water-carrier in lieu magnificent jewels of massy gold, of five times the size, with which the latter was heartily content. They took care not to linger within reach of accidents, but made off to enjoy their wealth undisturbed in other countries. The Moor returned to Africa, to his native city of Tangiers, and the Gallego, with his wife, his children, and his donkey, made the best of his way to Portugal. Here, under the admonition and tuition of his wife, he became a personage of some consequence, for she made the worthy little man array his long body and short legs in doublet and hose, with a feather in his hat and a sword by his side, and laying aside his familiar appellation of Peregil, assume the more sonorous title of Don Pedro Gil: his progeny grew up a thriving and merry-hearted, though short and bandy-legged generation, while Señora Gil, befringed, belaced, and betasselled from her head to her heels, with glittering rings on every finger, became a model of slattern fashion and finery.

As to the alcalde and his adjuncts, they remained shut up under the great tower of the seven floors, and there they remain spell-bound at the present day. Whenever there shall be a lack in Spain of pimping barbers, sharking alguazils, and corrupt alcaldes, they may be sought after; but if they have to wait until such time for their deliverance, there is danger of their enchantment enduring until doomsday.

第七章　彩虹鸽的故事

在前一章中，我很少提及彩虹鸽去过的地方和发生的事情。在寻找彩虹鸽的十天旅程中，第一天刚德就确定无疑地发现了彩虹鸽的踪迹，但为了能连续看清那些事情，让彩虹鸽亲自讲述自己的历险故事会更好。要是运用幻想的语法和想象的字典，我们就不难理解他了。

十月的一天中午，当我们在大吉岭坐上回城的火车的时候，彩虹鸽卧在笼子里，开始讲述他最近从丹坦逃向新格里拉又飞回来的故事。

“懂得多种语言的主人啊，懂得所有人语和兽语的巫师啊，听听我的故事吧。听听一只可怜的鸟儿结结巴巴、漫无目的的叙述吧。因为这条河的根在山里，所以我的故事就从山里讲起吧。

“我在鹰巢附近听到和看到鹰的魔爪把我的母亲撕成碎片的时候，难过极了，决定去死，但并不是被那些阴险鸟儿的魔爪杀死。要是我注定要成为一顿美餐，那就让我成为空中之王的美餐吧。于是，我飞到鹰巢旁边的壁架上，但他们不愿伤害我。他们的巢里充满悲痛。他们的父亲被捕杀了，他们的母亲外出猎捕野鸡和野兔去了。到目前为止，小鹰们只吃过母亲为他们捕杀的食物，所以他们不敢攻击我并干掉还活着的可怜巴巴的我。在过去的几天里，我看到好多鹰，但我不知道他们为什么都不伤害我。

“随后，你们就来了，要抓住我并把我放进笼子里。我没有心情陪伴人类了，所以就抓住机会飞走了，但我记得你的那些朋友和他们居住的地方，在向南飞往丹坦的路上，我跟他们待在一起。在那两天里——因为我只飞了两天——我受到了一只刚刚长出羽毛的隼的攻击，我把他打得一败涂地。事情是这样的：一天早上，我飞过锡金下面的树林时，听到头顶风声呼啸。我明白此刻这意味着什么，就恶作剧地突然停飞，那只正扑向我的隼一下扑空，一头栽了下去，翅膀擦过了树梢。我升高疾飞，但他追了上来。于是，我开始在空中盘旋。我高飞，噢，飞得很高，我的肺在那里都呼吸不到空气了，就不得不再次下降。

“可是，我刚一下降，那只隼就带着一种凶多吉少的呼啸声扑向了我。幸运的是，此时此地，一生中我第一次尝试像我见到父亲做的那样翻滚，我成功地连续翻滚了两次，然后像喷泉一样蹿起。那只隼又一次扑空，他冲上来想继续攻击，但我没有给他机会。我向他飞去。就在我飞过他身边的时候，他下沉又升起，企图抓住我，我又翻滚了一次，狠狠地撞他，他失去了平衡。我不知道发生了什么，但当时我感到有什么东西把我往下吸，吸到了地球的深处。我的翅膀没有力量。我像鹰一样坠落——沉甸甸的，难以避免——用我的全部重量打在隼的头上。我想这一下把他打木了，他也下坠，消失在下面的树林里，但我很高兴地发现自己落在了一棵冬青树的树枝上。

“我是被一股气流吸下去的。自那第一次经历以后，我又有过许多次类似的经历，但我根本不明白为什么在一些树和溪流上方，空气变得很冷，形成一股涡流，把撞上这股涡流的鸟儿吸进去。在那次被涡流旋上旋下之后，我不得不学会在那些涡流中上下旋转地飞行。可是，我不讨厌涡流，因为我第一次遭遇的气流救了我一命。

“坐在那棵冬青树上，我变得很饿，这驱使我飞回家。幸运的是，再也没有无情的隼阻止我箭一般的飞行。

“不过，我从那只刚长羽毛的凶手手下成功逃脱，这让我找回了勇气。你一回到家，我就对自己说：‘他作为我的朋友，看到我活着，就不会为我担心。我必须重新飞过充满猎鹰的天空，检验自己的勇气。’

“因此，我开始了真正的漫长的冒险历程。我向北飞向鹰巢，在喇嘛庙停下来，那里的一位圣人早些时候曾为我祝福。在那里，我又拜访了我的老朋友雨燕夫妇。我继续向北飞去，路过新格里拉，最后到达了鹰巢。那些鹰已经飞走了。于是，我在那里舒服地生活，但不太高兴，因为那些鹰把各种垃圾都留在巢里，我害怕巢里充满害虫。尽管我白天待在鹰巢里，但我还是决定在树上过夜，不受可怕的虫子叮咬。这样在鹰巢里进进出出两天后，我在其他鸟儿中间赢得了巨大威望。他们怕我，也许是因为他们把我当成了一种鹰，就连那些隼也对我敬而远之。这给了我需要的所有自信，因此一天清晨，看见一队白色楔形的鸟儿飞往南方，飞得很高，我也加入了他们的队伍。他们不介意我加入他们，他们是飞向锡兰[1]和更远地方寻找阳光充足的海洋的大雁。

“飞行两个小时后，天气越来越暖和，那些大雁降落到了一条湍急的山溪上。他们不像那些鹰，极少向下看，而是望着地平线。他们发现遥远的天边出现了一小道白蓝色，就飞成一条直线，慢慢地降落，仿佛地面升起要迎接他们似的。很快，所有的鸟儿都纵身飞进了银色的溪流，因为此时看上去溪水与其说是蓝色，不如说是银色。大雁漂浮在水面上，但我知道我不会游泳，于是就坐在树上看他们的滑稽动作。你知道，大雁的嘴是多么扁平丑陋，但现在我明白其中的原因了。他们把嘴当作钳子来夹生长在两岸的贝壳。大雁不时地用嘴夹起一棵植物或一只贝壳，然后把它扭得变形，就像屠夫扭鸭的脖子一样。之后，它常常会在喉咙里把它用力压碎，整个儿吞下去，但还没等通过长长的喉咙，那东西就逐渐缩小，化为乌有。我看到其中一个家伙做得比这个还糟糕。他在河岸的一个洞里发现了一条鱼——瘦得像一条水蛇似的；他开始拽。他越拽，那东西变得越瘦越长。慢慢地，经过了一场可怕的拉锯战，那个可怜的家伙被从洞里拽了出来。随后，大雁跳上了河岸，把猎物甩在地上，用嘴压碎他按住的那一部分，几乎压成了肉酱，因此无怪乎那个扭动的猎物已经一命呜呼。接着，不知从哪里又走来一只大雁。（顺便说一下，难道大雁不飞或不游的时候，不是最丑陋的鸟儿吗？尽管他们会像梦一般漂浮在水池里，但在陆地上他们却像拄着拐杖的瘸子一样一瘸一拐！）现在两只大雁开始争斗，他们互相啄起了对方的羽毛，用翅膀拍打着从地面上跳起来用脚踢对方。就在他们忙着争斗，忘记了他们争斗的焦点的时候，一只像猫一样的家伙——可能是一只水獭——从芦苇丛里猛扑过来，抓住那条死鳗鱼，转眼就不见了踪影。这时候，两只大雁宣布停战，但已经来不及了！噢，他们还没有，啊——鹅有理智！跟他们比较，我们鸽子似乎是聪明的典范。

“他们停止争斗后，领头雁嚷道——‘咯，呱，呱，呱！’那一刻，所有的大雁都用力划水，增加冲力。他们又拍打了几下翅膀，飞到了空中。现在看上去他们是多么优美啊！宽大的翅膀发出柔和的飒飒声，他们的脖子和身体犹如天空中的图画，形成了一个非常养眼的楔形。这一幕我永远难忘。

“不过，每一个鸟群都有掉队者。一只大雁被落下了，因为他还在跟一条鱼搏斗。他终于叼起了那条鱼，飞起来，寻找一棵树，以便可以隐藏在上面吃鱼。突然空荡荡的天空飞来了一只巨大的隼，向他发动袭击。大雁飞得更高，但那只隼不依不饶，没有松懈。他们盘旋上升，发出了尖叫声和嘎嘎声。突然，一阵微弱却又清晰的雁叫声传来。是领头雁在呼唤那个掉队者，这分散了他的注意力。他几乎还没搞清楚状况，就回应了一声。就在那个时刻，鱼从他的嘴里掉了下来。那条鱼开始像一片树叶似的落下。那只隼俯冲下来，就在隼准备用利爪刺穿鱼的时候，空中传来了波涛般的轰鸣声。转眼之间，一只鹰飞下来，活像岩石从高高的悬崖落下一般。那只隼拼命而逃。这一幕让我欢天喜地。

“鹰的两只翅膀犹如两面巨帆，利爪闪电般伸出来，一下子抓住了那条鱼——随后，空中之王身披金褐色的盔甲悠然飞去，风吹皱了他膝盖上面的羽毛。远处，那只隼还在拼命奔逃！

“我很高兴他远去，因为我不得不四处飞行，寻找马帮路，我在那里可以找到人们掉落的一些种粒。我很快就找到了一些，吃了一顿还算像样的饭之后，栖在一棵树上就睡着了。我醒来后已到了下午三点左右。我决定继续飞行，飞到那座神圣的喇嘛庙去，拜访我的雨燕朋友们。我的飞行没有遇到任何不幸，因为如今我已经学会了小心翼翼地飞行。我一般都飞得很高，能清晰地俯瞰地平线。尽管我的脖子没有大雁那样长，但每隔几分钟我就会转过头，用眼睛的余光扫视一下，以确保没有什么东西在后面攻击我。

“我及时到达了那座寺庙，这时喇嘛们正准备好站在小圣堂边缘，以便在日落时分向世界赐福。雨燕夫妇在巢穴附近飞来飞去，他们安顿三个小宝宝上床睡觉了。当然，他们很高兴接待我。晚祷仪式后，喇嘛们喂我吃食，那位亲切的老喇嘛说了一句祝福的话，就是有人所说的“大慈大悲”那样的祝福，赐福与我。随后，我从他的手里飞走的时候，感到无所畏惧。在那种身心状态中，我飞进了自己的窝。我的窝巢在喇嘛庙屋檐下，紧挨着雨燕。

“十月的夜晚是寒冷的。清晨，当喇嘛们敲钟的时候，小雨燕们飞来飞去，练习飞行。我和他们的父母亲不得不飞起来，以摆脱早晨的寒冷。那天，我待在那里，帮助他们为南飞做准备。我惊讶地得知，他们打算在他们要去的锡兰或非洲筑巢。他们对我解释说，筑一个雨燕巢绝不是一件容易的事儿。接着，为了满足我的求知欲，他们向我讲述了他们的筑巢技巧。”

[1]锡兰，斯里兰卡的旧称，印度洋岛国，因接近赤道终年如夏，素有“印度洋上的珍珠”之称。

第一章　彩虹鸽战前训练

我们回城之后，到处都流传着欧洲某地即将发生一场战争。冬天即将到来，我决定对彩虹鸽进行如此这般必要的训练，以便他应召，成为英国作战部的一名信鸽。因为彩虹鸽习惯了喜马拉雅山东北部的气候，所以他会成为欧洲任何一个国家的军队的一名无价信使。即使现在借助电报和无线电，任何军队也无法免除信鸽的帮助。当目前这个故事自行展开的时候，你对所有这一切就会明白。

在为战时特殊工作训练鸽子时，我遵循刚德认可的我自己的一项计划。顺便说一下，这位老朋友跟我们一路来到了城里。他在我的家里小住了两三天，然后决定离开，说：“城市让人难以忍受。我永远不喜欢任何城市，但这座城市让我害怕，又是有轨电车，又是汽车。我要是不尽快抖落脚上的城市尘土，就会完全成为一个胆小鬼。丛林里的老虎不会吓倒我，但我对汽车不敢这样说。现代城市的一个十字路口一分钟危及的生命，要比最危险的森林里的一天危及的还多。再见！我还是去树林吧，那里沉静，空气没有恶臭和灰尘，天空高远，呈蓝绿色，没有纵横交错的电线杆和电报线。我听到的不是工厂的汽笛声，而是鸟儿的鸣唱；我要面对的是无辜的老虎和黑豹，而不是小偷和枪手。再见！”

但是，在离开之前，刚德帮我买了大约四十多只信鸽和一些筋斗鸽。你可能会问我偏爱这两种鸽子的原因。尽管我不知道我为什么对筋斗鸽和信鸽情有独钟，但扇尾鸽、凸胸鸽和其他鸽子适合观赏，却不实用，这话没错。我们家有一些这种鸽子，但最终证明他们很难跟信鸽和旅鸽结伴，所以我最后完全欣赏起了这些纯粹的飞行员。

在印度，我们有一个我并不喜欢的奇异风俗。要是你卖一只信鸽，无论是以多么昂贵的价格卖出去的，这只鸽子从新主人那里飞回你那里，便又会成为你的财产，无论价值多少，你都不用退还卖鸽子的钱。我知道这在鸽迷当中已成公认的习俗，所以我首先必须得让这些新得到的宠物喜欢我。我花钱买了他们，就不希望他们飞回到他们从前的主人那里。我尽最大努力让他们忠心耿耿，珍爱他们的新家。但是，生活是现实的。我不得不从最必要的步骤开始。头几个星期，我不得不绑住他们的翅膀，以确保他们完全在我们家的房顶范围内。绑住鸽子的翅膀，以免他们飞走，这是一种微妙的技巧。你拿一根线，把线的一头穿过鸽子的一只翅膀，然后从另一只翅膀下面，非常接近翅膀根部的地方，穿过去，直到环绕整个翅膀。接下来，你用线的另一头按照同样的步骤穿过第一只翅膀下面，越过第二只翅膀，如此这般直至翅膀末端，两根线头在那里系在一起。这非常像织补东西。这是一种完全没有痛苦的囚禁方式，因为尽管这样会阻止鸽子飞行，但并不妨碍鸽子张合翅膀。他既能伸展翅膀，也能用嘴按摩翅膀。之后，我常常把新鸽子放在房顶的不同角落，以便他们能站着不动，用眼睛适应新环境的色彩和特性。这个过程至少需要十五天。

在这里，我必须记载彩虹鸽在被用上述方法绑住翅膀后做的一件巧妙的事情。十一月初，我卖了彩虹鸽，就是为了看看他被松开细线的捆绑后会不会飞回到我的身边。

好吧，买走彩虹鸽两天后，他的新主人就来找我说：“彩虹鸽已经逃跑了。”

“怎么逃跑的？”我问道。

“我不知道，但我在屋里找不到他了。”

“你绑住他的翅膀了吗？他能飞吗？”我又问道。

“他的两只翅膀都被绑住了。”他回答说。

这让我惊骇不已。我说：“噢，你这骆驼的兄弟、驴子的表亲，你不应该跑到这里，而应该到你自己家附近去找找他。你没有看出他想设法飞走，但既然他的翅膀被绑住，他是不是从房顶掉下去了呢？到如今，他已经被某只猫杀死吞吃了。噢，这是对鸽子的一种屠杀。你已经剥夺了人类信鸽的王冠！你已经谋杀了鸽子的荣耀！”我这样责备他。

我的话完全把那个人吓坏了，他恳求我跟他一起去寻找彩虹鸽。我的第一个想法就是要从猫那里救出这个可怜的家伙。我们寻找了整整一个下午，但白忙了一场。我在十二个小时内仔细查看了更多的肮脏小巷，盼望能赶在某只脏猫之前，找到陷入绝境的彩虹鸽，这比我下半辈子走过的小巷都要多。唉，我们还是没有找到他。那天夜里，我回家很晚，为此遭到一番严厉的责骂，极其伤心地上床睡觉了。

妈妈理解我的心情，不希望我带着受伤和激动的心情进入梦乡。她说：“你的鸽子是安全的，平心静气地去睡吧。”

“为什么，妈妈？”

她回答说：“要是你平静，你的平静思想就会帮助你。要是你平心静气，你的平静就会使他平静。要是他平静，他的思想就会良好运转。我的宝贝，你知道，彩虹鸽的思想是多么敏锐。要是他心神稳定开始行动，他就会克服所有的障碍，平安到家。现在让我们向大慈大悲的神祈祷吧，让我们自己平静下来。”于是，我们在寂静夜晚的团团包围下静静地坐了半个小时，说：“我是平静的。愿一切存在的东西都平静。平静，平静，愿平静降临万物！OmShanti[1]，shanti，shanti!”

当我准备睡觉的时候，妈妈说：“你现在绝不会再做噩梦了。因为神的平和与怜悯在你心中照亮，所以你夜里会得到充分的休息。平和！”

毫无疑问，我最终得到了充分的休息。因为第二天上午十一点左右，彩虹鸽就飞起，掠过了天空。他飞得很高。他是如何让翅膀得到解放，我不得不让他用自己的语言告诉你们。让我们再次使用幻想的语法和想象的词典吧。

“噢，精通多种语言的主人啊，”彩虹鸽在我们自己的房顶开口说道，“我在那个新主人的家里一天也受不了了！他给我被虫子污染过的谷粒吃，让我喝不新鲜的水。毕竟，我是一个生灵，我为什么要被当成石头或碎片对待？此外，他用臭烘烘的渔具绑住我的翅膀。我会跟这种人待在一起吗？绝不会！所以，他刚把我放在他的白色房顶下了楼，我就拍打着翅膀飞走了。唉！我的翅膀沉甸甸的，飞起来让我疼痛难忍。于是，我就落在了附近小巷的一家商店的遮阳篷上面。我坐在那里等待，盼望着救援。我看到几只雨燕飞过，我对他们呼喊，但他们不是我的朋友。我看到一只野鸽，我呼喊，但他也没有任何反应。正在这时，我看到一只黑猫向我走来。死亡向这里走来，越来越近，黄玉色的眼睛红光闪闪。黑猫蹲伏下来，准备纵身跃起。我也纵身跃起——飞过了他的头顶，飞到了遮阳篷上方大约五英尺的飞檐上，一只雨燕曾在那里筑巢。尽管极其艰难，但我还是紧紧地抓住了那个地方，直到那只黑猫销声匿迹。这时候，我又纵身飞起。我上方四五英尺就是房顶。我落到了那里。但是，我的一只翅膀受伤了。为了减轻痛苦，我按摩起了翅膀的根部。我用嘴一根一根地挤压和揉搓羽毛，然后什么东西就滑了下来。我已经成功地把一根小羽毛从渔具的束缚中挣脱了出来。渔具臭烘烘的，恶心死了。我接着揉搓和挤压下一根羽毛，瞧，第二根羽毛也自由了。噢，这是一种多么好的感觉啊！很快，整个翅膀都自由了。就在这时，那只黑猫再次出现在了房顶上，但现在我能飞出大约十英尺，于是就飞到了一座高层建筑的飞檐上面，在那里找到了一个便利的栖息地。我从那里望着那只致命的黑猫，只见他蹲伏下来，然后纵身扑向刚从我的翅膀上脱落的渔具。这向我阐明了一个新的体验：吸引那只猫的是这条臭烘烘的钓鱼线，而不是我。我立即开始啄捆绑我另一只翅膀的细线，才解脱一半翅膀，夜幕就降临了，当我终于摆脱翅膀上最后一个臭烘烘的绳索的羁绊的时候，我不得不等到天亮再飞回家，因为猫头鹰会在黎明时分飞行，隼来得晚些，我希望空中有一条安全通道。现在，我终于到家了——我又饿又渴。”

我对新来的鸽子做的第一件事，就是喂他们食物和新鲜的水。我从来不让他们喝他们洗过澡的水。因为彩虹鸽的翅膀上有一股鱼腥味，所以我把他和其他鸽子分开，给了他单独的住处。花费了三天之久，洗了三次痛快的澡之后，彩虹鸽才又适合文明社会。让我顺便说一下，我的父亲让我把钱退给那个买彩虹鸽的人，因为这种结果可悲可叹。实话告诉你，我当时不想那样做。但是，现在感到听从父亲的话是对的。两个星期后，在解开新买的那些鸽子的翅膀之前，我收买那些鸽子，让他们喜欢我。每天早晨，我都会把一些谷粒和花生泡在酥油（清牛油）里。谷粒和花生在酥油里泡一整天之后，我就给每只爱鸽各喂十几粒。他们非常喜欢那些美食，不到两天时间就已经形成了一个习惯，每天下午五点钟之前飞到我身边，讨要酥油美食。又过了三天，我细致入微地解开他们的翅膀，在四点四十五之前解开他们。他们一感觉到自由，就全都飞走了。但是，你瞧，在发现他们获得自由最初的欢欣过后，他们又飞落到了房顶上，要酥油花生和谷粒吃！尽管我们不得不通过喂饱鸽子来赢得他们的信任是一种遗憾，但可叹的是，我已经注意到有许多男男女女在这方面类似鸽子！

[1]Om是所有自然的一切声音，就像是神的名字一样。Shanti是“平和”的意思。

第七章　彩虹鸽讲述如何送情报

“那个重要日子前的整个夜晚，我没大合眼。尽管我藏在刚德的大衣下面，但他并不知道我醒着。你贴在一个时而像公鹿奔跑，时而像松鼠爬树，时而收留陌生狗做伴的人的心脏旁边，是不可能入睡的……刚德的心脏不时地咚咚直跳，你也许在几码开外都能听到。在如此近的距离内，他还做了一件让你睡不着的事情；整整一夜，他呼吸都不均匀。他时而长长地吸气，时而急促地呼吸，就像一只逃离猫的老鼠一般。我在这样一个人的大衣下面睡觉，还不如设法在暴风雨天里睡觉。

“然后，就是那条狗！我何尝忘记他呢？当刚德第一次遇到他的时候，我吓得要死，但他没有闻到我身上的气味，不知何故，从下面升起的空气告诉我，他完全就像幽灵一般，最终他却成了我们的朋友。他的脚步声我一辈子都难以忘记，他走起路来像猫一样轻柔。他一定是一条野狗，因为住在文明世界的狗都很吵闹，他们甚至不会悄声走路。人类的伙伴都在堕落，除了猫之外，每种动物在人类社会里都变得粗心吵闹。但是，这条狗完全是野生的，他走起路来悄无声息，他连呼吸都不出声。那么，我又是怎么知道他在那里的呢？是从地上升起的扑鼻而来的气味。

“经过了一个极不舒服的无眠之夜，刚德放飞了我，我几乎认不出他放飞我的那个地方。所以，我从一棵树飞到另一棵树，找到自己的方位，这只会让我大吃一惊。因为现在天已经亮了，树林里到处都是眼睛。一些陌生的蓝眼睛通过管子望着不同的方向。他们后面有一些人，一个人从树梢上望着，距离我栖息的地方大约一英尺。因为我们周围所有那些铁狗都在狂叫——噗啪啪啪啪，所以他没有听到我飞来。

“可是，当我飞起的时候，他看到了我。我觉得，要是我没有赶紧藏在其他树下，他就会打死我；他的确开了好多枪，但我躲在了像隐士的头发那样浓密的杂树丛后面。我决定先从一棵树跳到另一棵树上，直到前方没有危险。我花了不少时间这样跳了大约半英里。最后，我的双脚感觉疲惫不堪，于是我决定起飞，不管有没有危险。

“幸运的是，没有人看到我起飞。我在空中兜了几个大圈后，飞上高空。我从树木看上去小得像树苗一样的森林处，朝不同的方向张望。在东方露出曙光的天空中，一群飞机像金色战车一样从远处飞过来。这意味着，要是我等待过久，敌人就会向我扑来。于是，我开始向西飞去。这仿佛是树顶上千个狙击手要向我开火的信号。

“我想，当我盘旋而上飞到德国兵藏身的树顶上方的时候，他们拿不准我是不是他们的信鸽，但狙击手们一观察到我向西飞去，就确定我不是他们的信鸽，一起朝我开火，想把我打下来，查明我脚上带的是什么情报。

“不管怎样，在清冷的冬日天空中，我不可能不被冻僵永远向上飞，我不想让那些敌机超过我，我又一次向西猛冲。又一堵子弹墙像死亡之网一样在我面前展开。可是，我别无选择，要么闯过去，要么被逼近的敌机打死，这些飞机飞得很近，我都能看清里面的人。于是，我继续向西猛冲。幸运的是，大约一个月前受伤的尾巴到现在几乎已经恢复了正常大小。要是没有这个尾羽，完成任务就会难上加难。我继续向我们的阵地飞去，枪炮的齐射越来越猛。毫无疑问，所有狙击手和远处战壕里的人都在向我射击。我曲折前行，盘旋，翻滚，实际上我施展了自己知道的所有绝技，来躲避越来越密集的枪林弹雨，但这一切弯来绕去的动作浪费了我一些时间。我稍微动一下，其中一架飞机已经飞到了攻击距离内，开始从我后面和上方密集开火。我只有向前飞，所以就继续向前冲。噢！我飞得是多么起劲——像最激烈的暴风雨一样迅疾。随后——啪嗒啪嗒噗——我被打中了！我的腿断了，子弹正打在了大腿根附近，那条系着情报的腿像隼爪下面挂着的一只麻雀一样耷拉着。噢！尽管疼痛难忍，但我没有时间去想，因为飞机还在追我，我比先前更加努力地飞着。

“终于，我们自己的阵地进入了我的视野。我飞低了些，那架飞机也俯冲了下来。我设法翻滚，但都没有成功，我的那条腿使我尝试不了任何技巧。接着，啪——啪——啪嗒——啪嗒嗒——我的尾翼被打中了，羽毛纷纷飘落，一时间遮住了德军战壕里士兵的视线。所以，我倾斜着向我们的阵地飞去——一下子飞过了头，就又兜了个圈。随后，我看到了奇异的一幕——那架飞机被我们的士兵打中了。它摇摇晃晃、歪歪扭扭坠落下来。然而，在坠落起火之前，它做了一件最糟糕的事情——击中并打断了我的右翅。看到它在空中着火坠落，我感到满意，但我越来越疼痛，感觉好像有二十只秃鹰正在把我撕成碎片。不过，多亏了鸽神，我失去了痛苦或快乐的感觉，觉得仿佛有一座大山似的重量在把我向下拉……

“他们让我住了一个月的鸽子医院。尽管我的翅膀得到了修复，那条腿也被接好了，但它们再也无法支持我飞起来了。我每次跃向空中，不知怎么回事，耳朵里都充满了可怕的枪声，眼睛只看到燃烧的子弹。我非常害怕，会马上冲到地上。你可能会说，我听到的是想象的声音，看到的是想象的子弹墙，可能是，但它们产生的效果对我来说跟真的一样。我的翅膀瘫痪了，内脏因恐惧而冰封。

“除此以外，没有刚德，我不愿飞行。一个人的肤色不是棕色的，眼睛又是蓝色的，我为什么要从他的手上起飞呢？我以前从不了解这种人。我们鸽子不喜欢所有的局外人。最后，他们把我放进笼子，带到了刚德所在的那家医院，把我留在他的身边。我看到他的时候，简直认不出他了，因为他的眼睛——刚德的眼睛——带着一种真正恐惧的神色！是的，这一次他也被吓得不知所措。像所有的鸟类和野兽一样，我知道恐惧是什么样子，所以我为刚德感到难过。

“可是，他一看到我，那层恐惧的薄膜就离开了他的眼睛，他的眼里燃起了快乐的光芒。他在床上坐起来，双手抱住我，亲吻我的脚，这只脚上曾经绑过他要送的那份情报。随后，他轻轻地拍了拍我的右翅，说：‘即使非常痛苦，噢，你这神圣羽毛的星座，你把主人的情报带给了朋友们，为所有的鸽子和整个印度军队赢得了荣誉。’他又一次亲吻了我的脚。他的谦卑打动了我，他也让我谦卑起来。我记得，当那架飞机把我的翅膀部分打断之后，我落在印度军队战壕的时候，我不再感到骄傲，因为要是我当时落在德军的战壕，那么……他们就会抢走系在我腿上的那份情报，他们会团团包围刚德和那条野狗藏身的森林——想到他们会做的一切，我就瑟瑟发抖！唉！那条狗，我们真正的朋友和救星，他如今在哪里呢？”

To Suresh Chandra Banerji, Esq.

Dear Suresh:

Since Gay-Neck needs a protector, I thought of you for several reasons. First of all, being a poet, an observer of nature, and a traveller, you would be able to protect the book from being condemned. In fact, there is no one who can do it as well as yourself.

You know the country where Gay-Neck grew. You are versed in the lore of birds. For a pigeon, life is a repetition of two incidents: namely, quest of food and avoidance of attacks by its enemies. If the hero of the present book repeats his escape from attacks by hawks, it is because that is the sort of mishap that becomes chronic in the case of pigeons.

Now as to my sources, you well know that they are too numerous to be mentioned here. Many hunters, poets like yourself, and books in many languages have helped me to write Gay-Neck. And if you will permit it, I hope to discharge at least a part of my debt by dedicating this book to one of my sources—yourself.

I remain most faithfully yours,
Dhan Gopal

Chapter One Birth of Gay-Neck

The city of Calcutta, which boasts of a million people, must have at least two million pigeons. Every third Hindu boy has perhaps a dozen pet carriers, tumblers, fan-tails and pouters. The art of domesticating pigeons goes back thousands of years in India, and she has contributed two species of pigeons as a special product of her bird fanciers, the fan-tail and the pouter. Love and care have been showered on pigeons for centuries by emperors, princes and queens in their marble palaces, as well as by the poor, in their humble homes. The gardens, grottos and fountains of the Indian rich—the small field of flowers and fruits of the common folk, each has its ornament and music—many-coloured pigeons and cooing white doves with ruby eyes.

Even now, any winter morning, foreigners who visit our big cities may see on the flat-rooted houses innumerable boys waving white flags as signals to their pet pigeons flying up in the crisp cold air. Through the blue heavens flocks of the birds soar like vast clouds. They start in small flocks, and spend about twenty minutes circling over the roofs of their owners' homes. Then they slowly ascend, and all the separate groups from different houses of the town merge into one big flock, and float far out of sight. How they ever return to their own homes is a wonder, for all the house-tops look alike in shape in spite of their rose, yellow, violet and white colours.

But pigeons have an amazing sense of direction and love of their owners. I have yet to see creatures more loyal than pigeons and elephants. I have played with both, and the tusker on four feet in the country, or the bird on two wings in the city, no matter how far they wandered, were by their almost infallible instinct brought back to their friend and brother—Man.

My elephant friend was called Kari, of whom you have heard before, and the other pet that I knew well was a pigeon. His name was Chitra-griva; Chitra meaning "painted in gay colours," and Griva, "neck"—in one phrase, pigeon Gay-Neck. Sometimes he was called "Iridescence-throated."

Of course, Gay-Neck did not come out of his egg with an iridescent throat; he had to grow the feathers week by week; and until he was three months old, there was very little hope that he would acquire the brilliant collar; but at last, when he did achieve it, he was the most beautiful pigeon in my town in India, and the boys of my town owned forty thousand pigeons.

But I must begin this story at the very beginning. I mean with Gay-Neck's parents. His father was a tumbler who married the most beautiful pigeon of his day; she came from a noble old stock of carriers. That is why Gay-Neck proved himself later such a worthy carrier pigeon in war as well as in peace. From his mother he inherited wisdom, from his father bravery and alertness. He was so quick-witted that sometimes he escaped the clutches of a hawk by tumbling at the last moment right over the enemy's head. But of that later, in its proper time and place.

Now let me tell you what a narrow escape Gay-Neck had while still in the egg. I shall never forget the day when, through a mistake of mine, I broke one of the two eggs that his mother had laid. It was very stupid of me. I regret it even now. Who knows? Maybe with that broken egg perished the finest pigeon of the world. It happened in this way. Our house was four stories high—and on its roof was built our pigeon-house. A few days after the eggs were laid I decided to clean the pigeon-hole in which Gay-Neck's mother was sitting on them. I lifted her gently and put her on the roof beside me. Then I lifted each egg carefully and put it most softly in the next pigeon hole, which, however, had no cotton or flannel on its hard wooden floor. Then I busied myself with the task of removing the debris from the birth-nest. As soon as that was done, I brought one egg back and restored it to its proper place. Next I reached for the second one and laid a gentle but firm hand on it. Just then something fell upon my face like a roof blown by the storm. It was Gay-Neck's father furiously beating my face with his wings. Worse still, he had placed the claws of one of his feet on my nose. The pain and surprise of it was so great that ere I knew how, I had dropped the egg. I was engrossed in beating off the bird from my head and face, and at last he flew away. But too late: the little egg lay broken in a mess at my feet. I was furious with its clumsy father and also with myself. Why with myself? Because I should have been prepared for the father bird's attack. He took me for a stealer of his eggs, and in his ignorance was risking his life to prevent my robbing his nest. May I impress it upon you that you should anticipate all kinds of surprise attacks when cleaning a bird's home during nesting season.

But to go on with our story. The mother bird knew the day when she was to break open the egg-shell with her own beak, in order to usher Gay-Neck into the world. Though the male sits on the egg pretty nearly one-third of the time—for he does that each day from morning till late afternoon—yet he does not know when the hour of his child's birth is at hand. No one save the mother bird arrives at that divine certainty. We do not yet understand the nature of the unique wireless message by which she learns that within the shell the yolk and the white of her egg have turned into a baby-bird. She also knows how to tap the right spot so that the shell will break open without injuring her child in the slightest. To me that is as good as a miracle.

Gay-Neck's birth happened exactly as I have described. About the twentieth day after the laying of the egg, I noticed that the mother was not sitting on it any more. She pecked the father and drove him away every time he flew down from the roof of the house and volunteered to sit on the egg. Then he cooed, which meant, "Why do you send me away?"

She, the mother, just pecked him the more, meaning, "Please go. The business on hand is very serious."

At that, the father flew away. That worried me, for I was anxious for the egg to hatch, and was feeling suspicious about its doing it at all. With increased interest and anxiety I watched the pigeon-hole. An hour passed. Nothing happened. It was about the third quarter of the next hour that the mother turned her head one way and listened to something—probably a stirring inside that egg. Then she gave a slight start. I felt as if a tremor were running through her whole body. With it a great resolution came into her. Now she raised her head, and took aim. In two strokes she cracked the egg open, revealing a wee bird, all beak and a tiny shivering body! Now watch the mother. She is surprised. Was it this that she was expecting all these long days? Oh, how small, how helpless! The moment she realizes her child's helplessness, she covers him up with the soft blue feathers of her breast.

Chapter Two Education of Gay-Neck

There are two sweet sights in the bird world: one when the mother breaks open her egg in order to bring to light her child, and the other when she broods and feeds him. Gay-Neck was brooded most affectionately by both his parents. This brooding did for him what cuddling does for human children. It gives the helpless ones warmth and happiness. It is as necessary to them as food. This is the time when a pigeon-hole should not be stuffed with too much cotton or flannel, which should be put there more and more sparingly so that the temperature of the nest does not get too hot. Ignorant pigeon fanciers do not realize that as the baby grows larger he puts forth more and more heat from his own body. And I think it is wise not to clean the nest frequently during this time. Everything that the parents allow to remain in the nest contributes to making their baby comfortable and happy.

I remember distinctly how, from the second day of his birth, little Gay-Neck automatically opened his beak and expanded his carnation-coloured body like a bellows every time one of his parents flew back to their nest. The father or the mother put their beaks into his wide-open maw and poured into it the milk made in their own organs from millet seeds that they had eaten. I noticed this; the food that was poured into his mouth was very soft. No pigeon ever gives any seeds to its baby even when it is nearly a month old without first keeping them in its throat for some time, which softens the food before it enters the delicate stomach of the baby.

Our Gay-Neck was a tremendous eater. He kept one of his parents busy getting food while the other brooded or stayed with him. I think the father bird brooded and worked for him no less hard than the mother. No wonder his body grew very fat. His carnation colour changed into a yellowish-white—the first sign of feathers coming on. Then that gave way to prickly white feathers, round and somewhat stiff, like a porcupine needle. The yellow things that hung about his mouth and eyes fell away. Slowly the beak emerged, firm, sharp and long. What a powerful jaw! When he was about three weeks old, an ant was crawling past him into the pigeon hole at whose entrance he was sitting. Without any instruction from anybody he struck it with his beak. Where there had been a whole ant now lay its two halves. He brought his nose down to the dead ant and examined what he had done. There was no doubt that he had taken that black ant for a seed, and killed an innocent passer-by who was friendly to his race. Let us hope he was ashamed of it. Anyway, he never killed another ant the rest of his life.

By the time he was five weeks old he could hop out of his birth nest and take a drink from the pan of water left near the pigeon holes. Even now he had to be fed by his parents, though every day he tried to get food on his own account. He would sit on my wrist and dig up a seed at a time from the palm of my hand. He juggled it two or three times in his throat like a juggler throwing up balls in the air, and swallowed it. Every time Gay-neck did that, he turned his head and looked into my eyes as much as to say: "Am I not doing it well? You must tell my parents how clever I am when they come down from sunning themselves on the roof." All the same, he was the slowest of my pigeons in developing his powers.

Just at this time I made a discovery. I never knew before how pigeons could fly in a dust-storm without going blind. But as I watched the ever-growing Gay-Neck, I noticed one day that a film was drawn over his eyes. I thought he was losing his sight. In my consternation I put forth my hand to draw him nearer to my face in order to examine him closely. No sooner had I made the gesture than he opened his golden eyes and receded into the rear of the hole. But just the same I caught him and took him up on the roof, and in the burning sunlight of May I scrutinized his eyelids. Yes, there it was: he had, attached to his eyelid, another thin lid as delicate as tissue paper, and every time I put his face toward the sun he drew that film over the two orbits of gold. And so I learned that it was a protective film for the eye that enabled the bird to fly in a dust-storm or straight toward the sun.

In another fortnight Gay-Neck was taught how to fly. It was not at all easy, bird though he was by birth. A human child may love the water, yet he has to make mistakes and swallow water while learning the art of swimming. Similarly with my pigeon. He had a mild distrust of opening his wings, and for hours he sat on our roof, where the winds of the sky blew without quickening him to flight. In order to make the situation clear, let me describe our roof to you. It was railed with a solid concrete wall as high as a boy of fourteen. That prevented even a sleep-walker from slipping off the height of four stories on summer nights, when most of us slept on the roof.

Gay-Neck I put on that concrete wall every day. There he sat for hours at a time, facing the wind, but that was all. One day I put some peanuts on the roof and called him to hop down and get them. He looked at me with an inquiring eye for a few moments. Turning from me, he looked down again at the peanuts. He repeated this process several times. When at last he was convinced that I was not going to bring these delicious morsels up for him to eat, he began to walk up and down the railing, craning his neck occasionally towards the peanuts about three feet below. At last, after fifteen minutes of heart-breaking hesitancy, he hopped down. Just as his feet struck the floor, his wings, hitherto unopened, suddenly spread themselves out full sail as he balanced himself over the nuts. What a triumph!

About this time I noticed the change of colours on his feathers. Instead of a nondescript grey-blue, a glossy aquamarine glowed all over him. And suddenly one morning in the sunlight his throat glistened like iridescent beads.

Now came the supreme question of flight. I waited for his parents to teach him the first lessons, though I helped the only way I could. Every day for a few minutes I made him perch on my wrist; then I would swing my arm up and down many times, and in order to balance himself on such a difficult perch he had to shut and open his wings frequently. That was good for him, but there ended my part of the teaching. You may ask me the reason of my hurrying matters so. He was already behind in his flying lessons, and in June the rains begin to fall in India; and with the approach of the rainy season any long flight becomes impossible. I wished to train him in learning his directions as soon as I could.

However, one day long before the end of May, his father undertook the task. This particular day a brisk north wind, which had been sweeping about and cooling the atmosphere of the city, had just died down. The sky was as clear as a limpid sapphire. The spaces were so clear that you could see the house-tops of our town, then the fields and arbours of the country in the farthest distance. About three o'clock in the afternoon, Gay-Neck was sunning himself on the concrete wall of the roof. His father, who had been flying about in the air, came down and perched next to him. He looked at his son with a queer glance, as much as to say: "Here, lazy-bones, you are nearly three months old, yet you do not dare to fly. Are you a pigeon or an earthworm?" But Gay-Neck, the soul of dignity, made no answer. That exasperated his father, who began to coo and boom at him in pigeon-language. In order to get away from that volubility, Gay-Neck moved; but his father followed, cooing, booming and banging his wings. Gay-Neck went on removing himself farther and farther; and the old fellow, instead of relenting, redoubled his talk, and pursued. At last the father pushed him so close to the edge that Gay-Neck had only one alternative, that is, to slip off the roof. Suddenly his father thrust upon his young body all the weight of his old frame. Gay-Neck slipped. Hardly had he fallen half a foot when he opened his wings, and flew. Oh, what an exhilarating moment for all concerned! His mother, who was downstairs dipping herself in the water, and performing her afternoon toilet, came up through the staircase and flew to keep her son company. They circled above the roof for at least ten minutes before they came down to perch. When they reached the roof the mother folded her wings as a matter of course, and sat still. Not so the son: he was in a panic, like a boy walking into cold and deep water. His whole body shook, and his feet trod the roof gingerly as he alighted, skating over it furiously and flapping his wings in order to balance himself. At last he stopped, as his chest struck the side of the wall, and he folded his wings as swiftly as we shut a fan. Gay-Neck was panting with excitement, while his mother rubbed him and placed her chest against him as if he were a mere baby who badly needed brooding. Seeing that his task had been done successfully, Gay-Neck's father went down to take his bath.

Chapter Three Training in Direction

Now that, like a newly trained diver, he had overcome his fear of plunging into the air, Gay-Neck ventured on longer and higher flights. In a week's time he was able to fly steadily for half an hour, and when he came home to the roof, he swooped down as gracefully as his parents. There was no more of that panicky beating of wings in order to balance himself as his feet touched the roof.

His parents, who had accompanied Gay-Neck in his preliminary flights, now began to leave him behind, and to fly much higher above him. For a while I thought that they were trying to make him fly still higher; for the son always made an effort to reach the level of his parents. Perhaps his elders were setting the little fellow a superb example. But at last, one day early in June, that explanation of mine was shaken by the following fateful incident. Gay-Neck was flying high: he looked half his usual size. Above him flew his parents, almost as small as a man's fist. They were circling above him with the regularity of a merry-go-round. It looked monotonous and meaningless. I removed my gaze from them; after all, it is not comfortable to look steadily upwards for long. As I lowered my eyes towards the horizon, they were held by a black spot moving swiftly, and growing larger every second. I wondered what sort of bird he was, coming at such a speed in a straight line, for in India birds are named in the Sanskrit, Turyak, or "curve-tracers."

But this one was coming straight, like an arrow. In another two minutes my doubts were dispelled. It was a hawk making for little Gay-Neck. I looked up and beheld a miraculous sight. His father was tumbling steadily down in order to reach his level, while his mother, bent on the same purpose, was making swift downward curves. Ere the terrible hawk had come within ten yards of the innocent little fellow, both his flanks were covered. Now the three flew downwards at a right angle from the path of their enemy. Undeterred by such a move, the hawk charged. At once the three pigeons made a dip that frustrated him, but the force with which he had made the attack was so great that it carried him a long distance beyond them. The pigeons kept on circling in the air with an ever-increasing downward trend. In another minute they were half-way to our roof. Now the hawk changed his mind. He went higher and higher into the sky: in fact, he flew so high that the pigeons could not hear the wind whistling in the feathers of his wings; and as he was above them they could not see their foe. Feeling that they were safe, they relaxed. It was evident that they were not flying so fast as before. Just then I saw that above them, way up, the hawk was folding his wings: he was about to drop, and in an instant he fell upon them like a stone. In desperation I put my fingers in my mouth and made a shrill whistle, a cry of warning. The pigeons dived like a falling sword, yet the hawk followed. Inch by inch, moment by moment he was gaining on them. Faster and faster he fell: now there were scarcely twenty feet between him and his prey. There was no doubt that he was aiming at Gay-Neck. I could see his sinister claws. "Won't those stupid pigeons do anything to save themselves?" I thought in an agony. He was so near him now—if they would only keep their heads, and—Just then they made a vast upward circle. The hawk followed. Then they flew on an even but large elliptical path. If a bird flies in a circle, he either tends to swing to the centre of that circle or away from it. Now the hawk missed their intention, and tended towards the centre, making a small circle inside their big one. No sooner was his back turned to them than the three pigeons made another dive, almost to our roof, but the sinister one was not to be deterred. He followed like a tongue of black lightning. His prey made a curving dive onto the roof, where they were safe at last under my wide spread arms! That instant I heard the shriek of the wind in the air; about a foot above my head the hawk flew by, his eyes blazing with yellow fire and his claws quivering like the tongue of a viper. As he passed I could hear the wind still whistling in his feathers.

After that narrow escape of my pet birds, I began to train Gay- Neck to a sense of direction. One day I took all three birds in a cage towards the east of our town. Exactly at nine in the morning I set them free. They came home safely. The next day I took them and equal distance to the west. Inside a week they knew the way to our house from within a radius of at least fifteen miles in any direction.

Since nothing ends smoothly in this world, the training of Gay- Neck finally met with a check. I had taken him and his parents down the Ganges in a boat. When we started, it was about six in the morning. The sky was littered with stray clouds, and a moderate wind was blowing from the south. Our boat was piled high with rice as white as snow on whose top were heaped mangoes red and golden in colour, like a white peak afire with the sunset.

I should have foreseen that such auspicious weather might turn suddenly into a terrible storm, for after all, boy though I was, I knew something about the freaks of the monsoon in June.

Hardly had we gone twenty miles before the first rain-clouds of the season raced across the sky. The velocity of the wind was so great that it ripped off one of the sails of our boat. Seeing that there was no time to be lost, I opened the cage and released the three pigeons. As they struck the wind, they vaulted right over and flew very low, almost falling into the water. They flew thus close to the surface of the river for a quarter of an hour, making very little headway against the hard wind. But they persisted, and another ten minutes saw them safely tacking and flying landward. Just about the time they had reached the string of villages on our left, the sky grew pitch black, a torrential cloudburst blotted everything out, and we saw nothing but inky sheets of water through which the lightning zigzagged and danced the dance of death. I gave up all hope of finding my pigeons again. We were almost shipwrecked ourselves, but fortunately our boat was beached on the shore of a village. Next morning, when I came home by train, I found two wet pigeons instead of three. Gay-Neck's father had perished in the storm. No doubt it was all my fault; and for the few days that followed, our house was given up to mourning. The two pigeons and I used to go up on the roof, whenever the rain left off a bit, in order to scan the sky for a glimpse of the father. Alas, he never returned.

Chapter Four Gay-Neck in the Himalayas

Since the rain and the heat in the plains proved excessive, my family decided to take us to the Himalayas. If you take a map of India, you will find that in its northeast corner is a town called Darjeeling, standing almost face to face with Mount Everest, the highest peak in the world. After travelling, not too fast, by caravan, several days from Darjeeling, my family, myself and my two pigeons reached the little village of Dentam. There we were ten thousand feet above sea-level. At such a height an American mountain or the Alps would have at least some snow, but in India, which is in the tropics, and on the Himalayas, hardly thirty degrees north of the equator, the snowline does not commence under ten thousand feet, and the jungle of the foot-hills, abounding with animals, is so cold after September that all its denizens migrate southwards.

Let me give you just a slight picture of our setting. Our house of stone and mud overlooked small valleys where tea was grown. Beyond, between serried ridges that struck out in harsh but majestic curves, were valleys full of rice-fields, maize, and fruit orchards. Farther on rose the dark evergreen-clad precipices over which reared thousands of feet of pure white ranges, the Kangchenjunga, the peak Makalu, and the Everest ranges. In the first flush of dawn they looked white; but as the light grew in brightness and the sun rose higher, peak after peak defined itself, not far off on the horizon, but piercing the very middle of the sky whence poured a flood of crimson light like the very blood of benediction.

One usually sees the Himalayas best in the early morning, for they are covered with clouds during the rest of the day. Hindus, who are religious people, get up in good time to behold the sublime hills and to pray to God. Can there be a better setting to prayers than those mountains most of whose peaks yet remain unexplored and untrodden by man? Their inviolate sanctity is something precious that remains a perpetual symbol of divinity. Heights like that of the Everest are symbols of the highest reality—GOD. They are symbolic of God's mystery, too, for with the exception of the early morning they are, as I have said, shrouded with clouds all day. Foreigners who come to India imagine they would like to see them all the time; but let no one complain, for he who has beheld Everest in its morning grandeur and awe-inspiring glory will say: "It is too sublime to be gazed at all day long. None could bear it continually before his eyes."

In July those early-morning views of the Everest are not vouchsafed us every day, for it is the month of rain. All the ranges lie in the grip of the most devastating blizzards. Once in a while, above the battle of storms and driven snow, the peaks appear—a compact mass of hard ice and white fire. They glow intensely in the sunlight, while at their feet the snow-clouds whirl and fall like fanatical dervishes dancing frenziedly before their terrible god.

During the summer my friend Radja and our teacher in jungle lore, old Ghond, came to visit our home. Radja was about sixteen years old, already a Brahmin priest, and Ghond we always called old, for none knew his age. Both Radja and I were handed over to that most competent of hunters for the purpose of studying under his guidance the secrets of jungle and animal life. Since I have described them in my other books, I need not repeat myself here.

As soon as we had settled down in Dentam, I began to train my pigeons in the art of direction. Whenever we had a clear day we climbed all the forenoon toward the higher peaks amid ilexes and balsam forests, and released our birds from some monastery roof or from the house of a nobleman. And towards evening, when we returned home, we invariably found Gay-Neck and his mother there before us.

We had hardly half a dozen clear days during the whole month of July, but under the guidance of the almost omniscient Ghond, and with my friend Radja, we travelled very far in a short time. We visited and stayed with all classes of the mountain folk, who looked much like Chinese. Their manners were elegant and their hospitality was generous. Of course, we took the pigeons with us, sometimes in a cage but most of the time under our tunics. Though we were frequently soaked with rain, Gay-Neck and his mother were religiously guarded from the weather.

Towards the end of July we made a journey beyond every lamasery (monastery) and baron's castle of Sikkim that we three human beings and the two pigeons had seen and known. We passed Singalila, where there was a nice little lamasery, on towards Phalut and the Unknown. At last we reached the homeland of the eagles. Around us were bare granite cliffs surrounded by firtrees and stunted pines; before us to the north lay the Kangchenjunga and the Everest ranges. Here, on the edge of an abyss, we released our two birds. In that exhilarating air they flew like children running from school at the end of the day. Gay-Neck's mother flew far upwards in order to show her son the sublime heights.

After the two birds had flown away, we three men talked of what they might be seeing as they sped above the altitudes. Before them, no doubt, rose the twin peaks of the Kangchenjunga group, slightly lower than Mount Everest but just as impeccable and austere as that immaculate peak untrodden still by the feet of men. That fact roused profound emotions in us. We saw the mountain in the distance, just for a few minutes, like a mirror before the Face of God, and I said to myself: "O thou summit of sanctity, thou inviolate and eternal, may no man tarnish thee, nor may any mortal stain thy purity even by his slightest touch. May thou remain forever unvanquished, O thou backbone of the universe, and measurement of immortality."

But I have brought you so high not to tell you about mountains, but of an adventure that befell us there. Now that Gay-Neck and his mother had flown, we gave up watching them and went in quest of an eagle's nest that was on a neighbouring cliff. The Himalayan eagle is brown with a soft golden glow, and though very beautiful to look at—it is in perfect proportion of beauty with strength—yet it is a fierce beast of prey.

But at first on this particular afternoon we encountered nothing savage. On the contrary, we found two fluffy white eaglets in an eyrie. They looked as engaging as new-born babes. The southern wind was blowing right in their eyes, but they did not mind it. It is in the nature of the Himalayan eagle to build his nest facing the direction of the wind. Why? No one knows. Apparently the bird likes to face that which he floats up on.

The younglings were nearly three weeks old, for they were already shedding their birthday cotton-like appearance, and had begun to grow real plumage. Their talons were sharp enough for their age, and their beaks hard and keen.

An eagle's eyrie is open and large. Its entrance-ledge—that is to say, landing-place—is about six or seven feet wide, and quite clean. But within, where it is dark and narrow, there is a perfect litter of twigs, branches, and a little of the hair and feathers of victims, every other part of their prey being devoured by the eaglets. The parents devour most of the bones, hair and feathers with the meat.

Though the surrounding country was clad in stunted pine trees, yet it was full of bird noises. Also, strange insects buzzed in the firtrees. Jewelled flies fluttered on blue wings over mauve orchids, and enormous rhododendrons glowed in sizes sometimes as large as the moon. Now and then a wild cat called, apparently talking in his noonday sleep.

Suddenly Ghond told us to run a dozen yards and hide in a bush. Hardly had we done so when the noises about us began to subside. In another sixty seconds the insects stopped their buzzing, the birds ceased to call, and even the trees seemed to grow still with expectation. In the air slowly rose the thin whistle of something. In a few moments it fell into a lower key. Hard upon it came a weird noise almost sounding like a shriek, and a giant bird flew down to the eagle's eyrie. The wind was still whistling in its wings. By its size Ghond thought it was the mother of the two babies. She remained still in the air till the eaglets withdrew into the inner recesses of their home. From her talons hung something well skinned, like a large rabbit. She landed, dropping her prey on the ledge. One could see that her wings from tip to tip measured half a dozen feet. She folded them as a man folds a paper; then, seeing that her children were coming towards her, she drew in her talons lest they pierce their unarmoured tender flesh. Now she hobbled like a cripple. The two little fellows ran and disappeared under her half-open wings, but they did not want to be brooded, for they were hungry. So she led them outwards to the dead rabbit, tore away some of its flesh, excluded any bone that clung to it, and gave it to them to swallow. Again, from below and all about, the insects and birds resumed their noises. We rose from our hiding and started homeward after Radja and I had extracted a promise from Ghond that he would bring us back later to see the full-fledged eaglets.

And so in a little over a month we returned. We brought with us Gay-Neck and his mother, for I wished the little fellow to fly the second time so that he would know with absolute certainty every village, lamasery, lake and river as well as the beasts, and the other birds—cranes, parrots, Himalayan herons, wild geese, divers, sparrow-hawks and swifts. On this trip we went about a hundred yards beyond the eagle's nest. The finger of autumn had already touched the rhododendrons. Their flaming petals were falling out; their long stems, many feet high, rustled in the winds. Leaves of many trees had begun to turn, and the air was full of melancholy. At about eleven, we uncaged our pigeons, who flew away into the sapphire sky that hung like a sail from the white peaks.

They had flown for about half an hour when a hawk appeared above them. It drew nearer the two pigeons and then drove at them. But the prey proved too wary; they escaped scatheless. Just as Gay- Neck and his mother were coming down swiftly to where the trees were, the hawk's mate appeared and attacked. She flew at them as her husband had done, without gaining her objective. Seeing that their prey was escaping, the male hawk cried shrilly to his mate; at that, she stopped in the air, just marking time. The pigeons, feeling safe, quickened their wing motion and flew southwards, while the two hawks followed, converging upon them from the east and the west. Wing-beat upon wing-beat, they gained on the pigeons. Their wings, shaped like a butcher's hatchet tipped off at the end, cut through the air like a storm… one, two, three—they fell like spears! Gay-Neck's mother stopped, and just floated in the air. That upset the calculation of the hawks. What to do now? Which one to fall upon? Such questioning takes time, and Gay-Neck seized the chance to change his course. Swiftly he rose higher and higher. In a few moments his example was followed by his mother, but she had lost time, and the hawks rose almost vaulting up to her. Then apparently a sudden panic seized her; she was afraid that the hawks were after her son, and in order to protect him—which was utterly unnecessary—she flew towards the two pursuers. In another minute both of those birds of prey had pounced upon her. The air was filled with a shower of feathers! The sight frightened Gay-Neck, who fell upon the nearest cliff for protection and safety. It was his mother's error that deprived her of her own life and probably imperiled that of her son.

We three human beings began a search for the cliff where Gay- Neck had fallen. It was no easy task, for the Himalayas are very treacherous. Pythons, if not tigers, were to be feared. Yet my friend Radja insisted, and Ghond the hunter agreed with him, saying that it would augment our knowledge.

We descended from the cliff that we were on and entered a narrow gorge where the raw bones lying on the ground convinced us that some beast of prey had dined on its victim the previous night. But we were not frightened, for our leader was Ghond, the most well-equipped hunter of Bengal. Very soon we began a laborious climb through clefts and crevices full of purple orchids on green moss. The odour of fir and balsam filled our nostrils. Sometimes we saw a rhododendron still in bloom. The air was cold and the climb unending. After two in the afternoon, having lunched on a handful of chola (dried beans softened in water), we reached the cliff where Gay-Neck was hiding. To our surprise we discovered that it was the eagle's nest with two eaglets—the babies of our previous visit—now full-fledged. They were sitting on the front ledge of their eyrie, while to our utter amazement we saw Gay-Neck at the farthest corner of a neighbouring ledge, cowering and weak. At our approach the eaglets came forward to attack us with their beaks. Radja, whose hand was nearest, received an awful stroke that ripped open the skin of his thumb, whence blood flowed freely. The eagles were between us and Gay-Neck, and there was nothing to be done but to climb over a higher cliff to reach him. Hardly had we gone six yards away from the nest when Ghond signed to us to hide as we had done the first time we had come. We did so with celerity, under a pine, and soon, with a soft roar in the air, one of the parent eagles drew near. In a few seconds there fell a high-pitched sound as the eagle sailed into its nest. A shiver of exquisite pleasure ran up and down my spine as her tail-feather grazed our tree and I heard that whistling mute itself.

Let me re-emphasize the fact that people who have an idea that the eagle builds its nest on an isolated, inaccessible cliff are mistaken. A powerful bird or beast does not have to be so careful in choosing its home. It can afford to be negligent. The nest of such a gigantic bird must have as its first requirement space so that it can open and shut its wings in the outer court of its home, and a place so spacious cannot be too inaccessible. Next, the eagle has no knack at building nests. It chooses a ledge that juts out of a cliff-cavern where nature has already performed two-thirds of the task. The last third is done by the birds themselves, and it merely consists in getting branches, leaves, and blades of grass together as a rough bed where the eggs may be laid and hatched.

All those details we gathered as we crawled out of our hiding place and examined—for the second time—the eyrie from a distance. There was no doubt that they were our old friends—the two babies—grown big, and their mother. She, even now though they were grown up, drew in her talons as a matter of habit lest they hurt her children. But it was momentary; after she had made sure that they were racing to meet her, she opened them and stood firmly on the outer ledge. The eaglets, though they should not be called so now that they were full-fledged, rushed forward and took shelter under her wide-spread wings. But the little beasts did not stay there long; they did not want to be loved; they were very hungry; they wanted something to eat, and alas, she had brought nothing. At that, they turned from her and sat facing the wind, waiting.

At Ghond's signal we all three rose and began to climb. In the course of another hour we had crawled in lizard-like silence over the roof of the eagles' nest. Just as I passed over it, an abominable odour of bones and drying flesh greeted my nostrils. That proved that the eagle—king of birds though he is—is not so clean and tidy as a pigeon. I, for one, prefer a pigeon's nest to an eagle's eyrie.

Soon we reached Gay-Neck and tried to put him in his cage. He was glad to see us, but fought shy of the cage. Since it was getting late, I gave him some lentils to eat. Just about the middle of his meal, seeing him deeply absorbed in eating, I made an effort to grab him with my hand. That frightened the poor bird, and he flew away. The noise of his flight brought the mother eagle out of the inner recess of her nest. She looked out, her beak quivering and her wings almost opening for flight. At once all the jungle noises below were stilled, and she sailed away. We felt that all was over for Gay-Neck. Suddenly a shadow fell upon him. I thought it was the eagle pouncing; however, it rested on him only a moment and then receded, but he had had the fright of his life, and he flew away, driven by sheer terror, in a zigzag course, far beyond our sight.

I was convinced that we had lost Gay-Neck. But Ghond insisted that we would find the bird in a day or two, so we decided to wait and spend our time there.

Night came on apace, and we sought shelter under some pines. The next morning we were told by Ghond that the day had come for the young eagles to fly. He concluded: "Eagles never give their children lessons in flight. They know when their eaglets are ready for it. Then the parents leave for ever."

All that day the parent eagle did not re-visit her nest. When night came again her children gave up all hope of her return, and withdrew into the inner part of their home. It proved a memorable night for us. We were so far up that we were quite sure of no attack by a four-footed beast of prey. Tigers and leopards go downwards, not that they fear the heights, but because, like all animals, they follow their food. Antelopes, deer, water buffalo and wild boars graze where valleys and jungle-growth are plentiful, and since they go where grass, sapling, luscious twigs, in short, their dinner, grows on riverbanks, those who live by eating them search for them there. That is why, with the exception of birds and a few animals such as wild cats, pythons and snow leopards, the heights are free of beasts of prey. Even the yak, who takes the place of the cow, does not climb so high very frequently or in large numbers. One or two mountain goats one sees occasionally, but nothing larger, and so our night was free of any dramatic experience. But this was amply compensated for by the piercing cold that possessed and shook our bodies in the early dawn. Sleep was out of the question, so I sat up, and wrapping all the blankets of my bedding around me, watched and listened. The stillness was intense—like a drum whose skin had been so stretched that even breathing on it would make it groan. I felt hemmed in by the piercing soundlessness from every direction. Now and then, like an explosion, came the crackling of some dry autumn leaves as a soft-footed wild cat leaped on them from the branch of a tree not far away. That sound very soon sank like a stone in the ever-rising tide of stillness. Slowly, one by one, the stars set. The rising tide of mystery that was reigning everywhere deepened, when like the shaking of lances something shivered in the eagles' eyrie. There was no doubt now that the day was breaking. Again rose the same sound from the same place. The eagles were preening their wings as a man stretches himself before fully waking from sleep. Now I could hear a rustle near by that I thought must be the two eagles coming forward on the front ledge of their nest. Soon came other noises. Storks flew by overhead; strange birds like cranes shouldered the sky. And near by the bellow of a yak tore the stillness asunder as if he had put his horn through the skin of a drum. Far down, birds called one another. At last fell a white light on the Kangchenjunga Range. Then Makalu appeared with an immense halo of opal back of his head. The lower ranges, as high as Mont Blanc, put on their vesture of milk-white glory; shapes and colours of stone and tree leaped into sight. Orchids trembled with morning dew. Now the sun, like a lion, leaped on the shoulder of the sky, and the snow-bastioned horizons bled with scarlet fire.

Ghond and Radja, who were already awake, stood up; then the latter, a well-trained priest, chanted the Sanskrit Vedic prayer to Savitar—the Sun:

O thou blossom of eastern silence,
Take thy ancient way untrodden of men.
Go on thy dustless path of mystery,
Reach thou the golden throne of God,
And be our advocate
Before His Silence and His compassionate speechlessness.

The prayer frightened the eagles, unaccustomed to human voices. But ere they were excited to fury, our little ritual was over and we hid ourselves under the stunted pine. The eagles, left without any breakfast, looked out and scanned the sky for a sign of their parent. They gazed below where flocks of parrots and jays flew, as small as humming-birds. Wild geese came trailing across the snowy peaks where they had spent the night on their journey southwards. Soon they too grew as small as beetles, and melted into space. Hour after hour passed, yet no sight of the big eagle! The full-fledged eaglets felt hungrier and hungrier, and began to fret in their nest. We heard a quarrel going on in the interior of the eyrie that grew in intensity and noise till one of them left home in disgust and began to climb the cliff. He went higher and higher. Up and up he walked without using his wings. By now it was past midday; we had luncheon, yet still there was no sight of the parent birds. We judged that the eagle left in the nest was the sister, for she looked smaller than the other eaglet. She sat facing the wind, peering into the distance, but she too grew downhearted. Strange though it may sound, I have yet to see a Himalayan eagle that does not sit facing the wind from the time of its birth until it learns to fly, as a sailor boy might sit looking at the sea until he takes to navigating it. About two in the afternoon, that eagle grew tired of waiting in the nest. She set out in quest of her brother, who was now perching on the top of a cliff far above. He too was facing the wind. As his sister came up, his eyes brightened. He was glad not to be alone, and the sight of her saved him from the melancholy thought of flying for food. No eagle-child have I seen being taught to fly by its parents. That is why younglings will not open their wings until driven by hunger. The parent eagles know this very well, and that is why when their babies grow up, and the time has come, they leave them and go away.

The little sister, laboriously climbed till she reached her brother's side, but alas, there was no room for two. Instead of balancing themselves on their perch, the sister's weight knocked her brother almost over. Instantly he opened his wings wide. The wind bore him up. He stretched out his talons, but too late to reach the ground. He was at least two feet up in the air already, so he flapped his wings and rose a little higher. He dipped his tail—which acted like a rudder, and swung him sideways, east, south, east. He swung over us, and we could hear the wind crooning in his wings. Just at that moment a solemn silence fell on everything; the noises of insects stopped; rabbits, if there were rabbits, hid in their holes. Even the leaves seemed to listen in silence to the wing-beats of this new monarch of the air as he sailed higher and higher. And he had to go way up, for only by going very far could he find what he sought. Sometimes eighteen hundred to three thousand feet below him, an eagle sees a hare hopping about on the ground. Then he folds his wings and roars down the air like lightning. The terrible sound of his coming almost hypnotizes the poor creature, and holds him bound to the spot, listening to his enemy's thunderous approach, and then the eagle's talons pierce him.

Seeing her brother go off in this way, and being afraid of loneliness, the sister suddenly spread her wings too. The wind blowing from under threw her up. She also floated in the air and tacked her flight by her tail towards her comrade, and in a few minutes both were lost to sight. Now it was our turn to depart from those hills in search of our pigeon. He might have gone to Dentam. But it behooved us to search every lamasery and baronial castle that had served Gay-Neck as a landmark in his past flights.

Chapter Five On Gay-Neck's Track

As we descended into the bleak oblivion of the gorges below, we suddenly found ourselves in a world of deepening dark, though it was hardly three in the afternoon. It was due to the long shadows of the tall summits under which we moved. We hastened our pace, and the cold air goaded us on. As soon as we had descended about a thousand feet and more, it grew warmer by comparison, but as night came on apace the temperature dropped anew and drove us to seek shelter in a friendly lamasery. We reached that particular serai where the lamas, Buddhist monks, most generously offered us hospitality. They spoke to us only as they had occasion in serving us with supper and in escorting us to our rooms. They spend their evenings in meditation.

We had three small cells cut out of the side of a hill, in front of which was a patch of grassy lawn railed off at the outer edges. By the light of the lanthorns we carried, we found that we had only straw mattresses in our stone cells. However, the night passed quickly, for we were so tired that we slept like children in their mothers' arms. About four o'clock next morning I heard many footsteps that roused me completely from sleep. I got out of bed and went in their direction, and soon I discerned bright lights. By climbing down and then up a series of high steps, I reached the central chapel of the lamasery—a vast cave under an overhanging rock, and open on three sides. There before me stood eight lamas with lanthorns that they quietly put away as they then sat down to mediate, their legs crossed under them. The dim light fell on their tawny faces and blue robes, and revealed on their countenances only peace and love.

Presently their leader said to me in Hindustani: "It has been our practise for centuries to pray for all who sleep. At this hour of the night even the insomnia-stricken person finds oblivion; and since men when they sleep cannot possess their conscious thoughts, we pray that Eternal Compassion may purify them, so that when they awake in the morning they will begin their day with thoughts that are pure, kind and brave. Will you mediate with us?"

I agreed readily. We sat praying for compassion for all mankind. Even to this day, when I awake early I think of those Buddhist monks in the Himalayas praying for the cleansing of the thoughts of all men and women still asleep.

The day broke soon enough. I found that we were sitting in a cleft of a mountain, and at our feet lay a precipice sheer and stark. The tinkling of silver bells rose softly in the sunlit air; bells upon bells, silver and golden, chimed gently and filled the air with their sweet music: it was the monks' greeting to the harbinger of light. The sun rose as a clarion cry of triumph—of Light over Darkness, and of Life over Death.

Below, I met Radja and Ghond at breakfast. It was then that a monk who served us said, "Your pigeon came here for shelter yesterday." He gave a description of Gay-Neck, accurate even to the nature of his nose-wattle, its size and colour.

Ghond asked, "How do you know we seek a pigeon?"

The flat-faced lama, without even turning an eye-lash, said in a matter-of-fact tone, "I can read your thoughts."

Radja questioned with eagerness: "How can you read our thoughts?"

The monk answered: "If you pray to Eternal Compassion for four hours a day for the happiness of all that live, in the course of a dozen years, He gives you the power to read some people's thoughts, especially the thoughts of those who come here.… Your pigeon we fed and healed of his fear when he took shelter with us."

"Healed of fear, my Lord!" I exclaimed.

The lama affirmed most simply: "Yes, he was deeply frightened. So I took him in my hands and stroked his head and told him not to be afraid; then yestermorn I let him go. No harm will come to him."

"Can you give your reason for saying so, my Lord?" asked Ghond politely.

The man of God replied to him thus: "You must know, O Jewel amongst hunters, that no animal, nor any man, is attacked and killed by an enemy until the latter succeeds in frightening him. I have seen even rabbits escape hounds and foxes when they kept themselves free of fear. Fear clouds one's wits and paralyses one's nerve. He who allows himself to be frightened lets himself be killed."

"But how do you heal a bird of fear, my Lord?"

To that question of Radja's the holy one answered: "If you are without fear, and you keep not only your thoughts pure but also your sleep untainted of any fear-laden dreams for months, then whatever you touch will become utterly fearless. Your pigeon now is without fear, for I who held him in my hand have not been afraid in thought, deed and dream for nearly twenty years. At present your pet bird is safe: no harm will come to him."

By the calm conviction in his words, spoken without emphasis, I felt that in truth Gay-Neck was safe; and in order to lose no more time, I said farewell to the devotees of Buddha and started south. Let me say that I firmly believe that the lamas were right. If You pray for other people every morning, you can enable them to begin their day with thoughts of purity, courage and love.

Now we dropped rapidly towards Dentam. Our journey lay through places that grew hotter and more familiar. No more did we see the rhododendrons. The autumn that farther up had touched the leaves of trees with crimson, gold, cerise and copper was not so advanced here. The cherry trees still bore their fruits; the moss had grown on trees thickly, and the wind had blown on them the pollen of orchids, large as the palm of your hand, blossoming in purple and scarlet. Many white daturas perspired with dewdrops in the steaming heat of the sun. The trees began to appear taller and more terrible. Bamboos soared upwards like sky-piercing minarets. Creepers as thick as pythons beset our path. The buzzing of the cicada grew insistent and unbearable, and jays jabbered in the woods. Now and then a flock of green parrots flung their emerald glory in the face of the sun, then vanished. Insects multiplied. Mammoth butterflies, velvety black, swarmed from blossom to blossom, and innumerable small birds preyed on numberless buzzing flies. We were stung with the sharpest stings of worms, and now and then we had to wait to let pass a serpent that crossed our path. Were it not for the practised eyes of Ghond, who knew which way the animals came and went, we would have been killed ten times over by a snake or a buffalo. Sometimes Ghond would put his ear to the ground, and listen. After several minutes he would say: "Ahead of us, buffalos are coming. Let us wait till they pass." And soon enough we would hear their sharp hoofs moving through the undergrowth with a sinister noise as if a vast scythe were cutting, cutting, cutting the very ground from under our feet. Yet we pressed on, stopping for half an hour for lunch. At last we reached the borders of Sikkim, whose small valley glimmered with ripening red millet, green oranges and golden bananas, set against hillsides glittering with marigolds above which softly shone the violets.

Just then we came to a sight that I shall never forget. At our feet on the narrow caravan road the air burned in iridescence: the heat was so great that it vibrated with colours. Hardly had we gone a few yards when like a thunderclap rose a vast flock of Himalayan pheasants; then they flew into the jungle, their wings burning like peacocks' plumes in the warm air. We kept on moving. In another couple of minutes flew up another flock but these were mud coloured birds. In my perplexity I asked Ghond for an explanation.

He said: "Do you not see, O Beloved of Felicity, the caravan that passed here was loaded with millet? One of their sacks had a hole in it. A few handfuls of millet leaked out on the road before the sack was sewn up. Later on arrived these birds, and fed themselves here. We came upon them suddenly and frightened them to flight."

"But, O Diadem of Wisdom," I asked, "why do the males look so gorgeous and why are the females mud-coloured? Is nature always partial to the male?"

Ghond made the following explanation: "It is said that Mother Nature has given all birds the colours that hide them from their enemies. But do you not see that those pheasants are so full of splendour that they can be sighted and killed even by a blind man?"

Radja exclaimed, "Can they?"

Ghond answered: "O, wary beyond thy years, no! The real reason is that they live on trees, and do not come down before the earth is very hot. In this hot India of ours the air two inches above the ground is so burning that it quivers with a thousand colours; and the plumage of the pheasant is similar. When we look at them we do not see birds, but the many-coloured air that camouflages them completely. We almost walked on them a few moments ago, thinking them but a part of the road at our feet."

"That I comprehend," resumed Radja reverently. "But why did the female look mud-coloured and why did they not fly away with the male?"

Ghond answered without hesitation: "When the enemy approaches and takes them by surprise, the male flies up to face the enemy's bullets, though without thought of chivalry. The females' wings are not so good. Besides, she, being of the colour of the earth, opens her wings to shelter her babies under them, then lies flat on the ground, completely melting away her identity into that colour scheme. After the enemy goes away in quest of the corpses of their already slaughtered husbands, the females run away with their babies into the nearest thicket.… And if it is not too late in the year, and if their grown-up babies are not with them, the mother birds singly flop to the ground and lie there, making the gesture of protecting their young. Self-sacrifice becomes a habit with them, and habitually they put forth their wings whether they have any young ones with them or not. That is what they were doing when we came upon them; then suddenly they realized that they were without anyone to protect, and as we still kept on coming down upon them they took to flight, poor fliers though they are."

With the approach of dusk we took shelter in the house of a Sikkimese nobleman whose son was a friend of ours. There we found further traces of Gay-Neck, who had been to their house many times before, and so when he reached the familiar place on his latest visit he had eaten millet seeds, drunk water and taken his bath. Also, he had preened his wings and left two small azure feathers that my friend had preserved for the sake of their colouring. When I saw them my heart leaped in joy, and that night I slept in utter peace and contentment. There was another reason for sleeping well, for Ghond had told us to rest deeply, as after the following day's march we were to spend the night in the jungle.

The next night, when we sat on that tree-top in the deep jungle, often did I think of the home of my Sikkimese friend and its comforts.

Imagine yourself marching all day, then spending the night on a vast banyan tree in the very heart of a dangerous forest! It took us a little over half an hour to find that tree, for banyans do not often grow in high altitudes, and also the same reason that made us choose the banyan made us look for a very large one of its kind—it would be of no use to us if it were slender enough for an elephant to break down by walking backwards against it! That is how the pachyderm destroys some very stout trees. We looked for something tall, and so stout that no elephant could reach its upper branches with his trunk and not even two tuskers could break it by pushing against it with their double weight.

At last we found a tree to our liking. Radja stood on Ghond's shoulder, and I on Radja's, until we reached branches as thick as a man's torso. I climbed and sat on one of them and from it let down our rope ladder that we always carried in the jungle for emergencies such as the present one. Radja climbed up and sat near me; then Ghond ascended the branch and sat between us. Now we saw that below us where Ghond had stood it had not only grown dark as the heart of a coal-mine, but there glowed two green lights set very close to each other. We knew too well whose they were. Ghond exclaimed jovially, "Had I been delayed down there two extra minutes, the striped fellow would have killed me."

Seeing that his prey had escaped him, the tiger gave a thunderous yell, scourging the air like a curse. At once a tense silence fell, and smothered all the noise of insects and little beasts, and it descended further and deeper until it sank into the earth and seemed to grip the very roots of the trees.

We made ourselves secure on our perch, and Ghond passed the extremely flexible rope ladder around his waist, then Radja's, then mine, fastening the rest of it around the main trunk of the tree. We tested it by letting it bear the weight of one of us at a time. This precaution was taken for the purpose of preventing a sleep-stricken member of our group from slipping down to the floor of the jungle, for after all, in sleep the body relaxes so that it falls like a stone. Finally, Ghond arranged his arms for pillows for our heads when slumber came.

Now that we had taken all the necessary precautions, we concentrated our attention on what was happening below. The tiger had vanished from under our tree. The insects had resumed their song, which was again and again stilled for a few seconds as huge shapes fell from far-off trees with soft thuds. Those were leopards and panthers who had slept on the trees all day and were now leaping down to hunt at night.

When they had gone the frogs croaked, insects buzzed continually and owls hooted. Noise, like a diamond, opened its million facets. Sounds leaped at one's hearing like the dart of sunlight into unprotected eyes. A boar passed, cracking and breaking all before him. Soon the frogs stopped croaking, and way down on the floor of the jungle we heard the tall grass and other undergrowth rise like a haycock, then with a sigh fall back. That soft sinister sigh like the curling up of spindrift drew nearer and nearer, then … it slowly passed our tree. Oh, what a relief! It was a constrictor going to the water-hole. We stayed on our tree-top as still as its bark— Ghond was afraid that our breathing might betray our position to the terrible python.

A few minutes later we heard one or two snappings of small twigs almost as faint as a man cracking his fingers. It was a stag whose antlers had got caught in some vines, and he was snapping them to get himself freed. Hardly had he passed when the jungle grew very tense with expectation. Sounds began to die down. Out of the ten or a dozen different noises that we had heard all at once, there now remained only three: the insects' tick tack tock, the short wail of the stag—no doubt the constrictor was strangling him near the water-hole—and the wind overhead. Now the elephants were coming. Hatis (elephants), about fifty in a herd, came and played around the place below us. The squeal of the females, the grunt of the males, and the run run run of the babies filled the air.

I do not remember what happened next, for I had dozed off into a sort of waking sleep, and in that condition I heard myself talking pigeon-language to Gay-Neck. I was experiencing a deep confusion of sleep and dream. Someone shook and roused me. To my utter amazement Ghond whispered: "I cannot hold you any more. Wake up! Mischief is abroad. A mad elephant has been left behind. The straggler is bent on harm. We are not high enough to be altogether out of the reach of his trunk, and if he raises it far enough he will scent our presence. Wild elephants hate and fear man, and once he gets our odour he may stay about here all day in order to find out where we are. Rouse thy vigilance, lad. Draw the blade of alertness before the enemy strikes."

There was no mistake about that elephant. In the pale light of early dawn I could discern a sort of hillock darkly moving about under our tree. He was going from tree to tree and snapping off a few succulent twigs that autumn had not yet blighted. He seemed greedy and bent on gorging himself with those delicacies, rare for the time of the year. In about half an hour he performed a strange trick, putting his fore-feet on the bole of a thick tree, and swinging up his trunk. It gave him the appearance of a far-spreading mammoth; with that enormously long reach he almost touched the top of the tree, and twisted the most delectable branches off its boughs. After having denuded it of its good twigs, he came to a tree next to ours, and there did the same thing. Now he found a slender tree that he pulled down with his trunk, and placed his fore-feet on the poor bent thing and broke it with a crash under his own weight. He ate all that he could of that one. While he was breakfasting thus, his rampage frightened the birds and monkeys, who flew in the air or ran from tree to tree jabbering in terror. Then the elephant put his feet on the stump of the broken tree and reached up into ours until he touched the branch on which we sat. Hardly had he done so when he squealed, for the odour of man all beasts fear, and swiftly withdrew his trunk. After grunting and complaining to himself, he put up his trunk again very near Ghond's face. Just then Ghond sneezed almost into the elephant's nostrils. That struck panic into the latter's heart; he felt beleaguered by men. Trumpeting and squealing like a frightened fiend, he dashed through the jungle, breaking and smashing everything before him. Again the parrots, thick as green sails, flew in the sky. Monkeys screamed and raced from tree to tree. Boars and stags stampeded on the floors of the jungle. For a while the din and tumult reigned unchecked. We had to wait some time before we dared to descend from our perch in order to resume our homeward journey.

Late that day we reached home after being carried on horseback by a caravan that we were fortunate enough to meet. All three of us were dead tired, but we forgot our fatigue when we beheld Gay- Neck in his nest in our house at Dentam. Oh, what joy! That evening, before I went to sleep, I thought of the calm, quiet assurance of the lama who said, "Your bird is safe."

Chapter Six Gay-Neck's Truancy

But the day after our return Gay-Neck flew away again, in the morning, and failed to put in an appearance later. We waited for him most anxiously during four successive days, and then, unable to bear the suspense any longer, Ghond and I set out in search of him, determined to find him, dead or alive. This time we hired two ponies to take us as far as Sikkim. We had made sure of our path by asking people about Gay-Neck in each village that we had to pass through. Most of them had seen the bird, and some of them gave an accurate description of him: one hunter had seen him in a lamasery nesting next to a swift under the eaves of the house; another, a Buddhist monk, said that he had seen him near their monastery in Sikkim on a river-bank where wild ducks had their nest, and in the latest village that we passed through on the second afternoon we were told that he was seen in the company of a flock of swifts.

Led by such good accounts we reached the highest table-land of Sikkim and were forced to bivouac there the third night. Our ponies were sleepy, and so were we, but after what seemed like an hour's sleep, I was roused by a tenseness that had fallen upon everything. I found the two beasts of burden standing stiff; in the light of the fire and that of the risen half-moon I saw that their ears were raised tensely in the act of listening carefully. Even their tails did not move. I too listened intently. There was no doubt that the silence of the night was more than mere stillness; stillness is empty, but the silence that beset us was full of meaning, as if a God, shod with moonlight, was walking so close that if I were to put out my hand I could touch his garment.

Just then the horses moved their ears as if to catch the echo of a sound that had moved imperceptibly through the silence. The great deity had gone already; now a queer sensation of easing the tense atmosphere set in. One could feel even the faintest shiver of the grass, but that too was momentary; the ponies now listened for a new sound from the north. They were straining every nerve in the effort. At last even I could hear it. Something like a child yawning in his sleep became audible. Stillness again followed. Then a sighing sound, long drawn out, ran through the air, and sank lower and lower, like a thick green leaf slowly sinking through calm water. Then rose a murmur on the horizon as if someone were praying against the sky-line. About a minute later the horses relaxed their ears and switched their tails, and I, too, felt myself at ease. Lo! Thousands of geese were flying through the upper air. They were at least four thousand feet above us, but all the same the ponies had heard their coming long before I did.

The flight of the geese told us that dawn was at hand, and I sat up and watched. The stars set one by one. The ponies began to graze. I gave them more rope; now that the night had passed, they did not need to be tied so close to the fire.

In another ten minutes the intense stillness of the dawn held all things in its grip, and that had its effect on our two beasts. This time I could clearly see both of them lifting their heads and listening. What sounds were they trying to catch? I did not have long to wait. In a tree not far off a bird shook itself; then another did the same thing, on another bough. One of them sang. It was a song-sparrow, and its cry roused all nature. Other song-sparrows trilled; then other birds, and still others! By now shapes and colours were coming to light with blinding rapidity. Thus passed the short tropical twilight, and Ghond got up to say his prayers.

That day our wanderings brought us to the lamasery near Singalila of which I have spoken before. The lamas were glad to give us all the news of Gay-Neck. They informed me that the previous afternoon Gay-Neck and the flock of swifts who nested under the eaves of the monastery had flown southwards.

Again with the blessings of the lamas we said farewell to their hospitable serai, and set out on Gay-Neck's trail. The mountains burned like torches behind us as we bestowed on them our last look. Before us lay the autumn-tinted woods glimmering in gold, purple, green and cerise.

Chapter Seven Gay-Neck's Story

In the preceding chapter I made scanty references to the places and incidents through which Gay-Neck was recovered. Ghond found his track with certainty the first day of our ten days' search for him, but in order to see those things clearly and continuously, it would be better to let Gay-Neck tell his own Odyssey. It is not hard for us to understand him if we use the grammar of fancy and the dictionary of imagination.

The October noon when we boarded the train at Darjeeling for our return journey to town, Gay-Neck sat in his cage, and commenced the story of his recent truancy from Dentam to Singalila and back.

"O master of many tongues, O wizard of all languages human and animal, listen to my tale. Listen to the stammering, wandering narrative of a poor bird. Since the river has its roots in the hill, so springs my story from the mountains.

"When near the eagles' nest I heard and beheld the wicked hawk's talons tear my mother to pieces, I was so distressed that I decided to die, but not by the claws of those treacherous birds. If I was to be served up for a meal, let it be to the king of the air; so I went and sat on the ledge near the eagles' nest, but they would do me no harm. Their house was in mourning. Their father had been trapped and killed, and their mother was away hunting for pheasants and hares. Since up to now the younglings had eaten only what had been killed for them, they dared not attack and finish poor me who was alive. I do not know yet why no eagle has harmed me; during the past days I have seen many.

"Then you came to catch and cage me. As I was in no mood for human company, I flew away, taking my chances as I went, but I remembered places and persons who were your friends and I stayed with them on my way south to Dentam. During those two days—for I flew only two days—I was attacked by a newly fledged hawk, and I gave him the best defeat of his life. It was in this wise; one morning as I was flying over the woods below Sikkim, I heard the wind screech overhead. I knew what that meant now, so I played a trick. I stopped all of a sudden, and the hawk, who was falling upon me, missed me and fell way down, grazing his wing on a tree-top. I rose higher and flew fast, but he caught up, and then I began to make circles in the air. I rose high, oh, so high that my lungs could not breathe the air there, and I had to come down again.

"But no sooner had I descended than with an ominous screech and cry the hawk fell upon me. Fortunately, then and there, for the first time in my life I tried to tumble as I had seen my father do, and I succeeded in making a double tumble, then shooting up like a fountain. Again the hawk missed and rose to attack, but I gave him no chance. I flew at him. And just as I was passing him, he dipped down, then up, and clutched at me; again I tumbled, striking him so hard that he lost his balance. I do not know what happened, but that very moment I felt something sucking me down, down to the depth of the earth. My wings were powerless. I fell as an eagle falls—heavy and inevitable—striking the hawk on the head with my full weight. I think the blow stunned him. He too fell, and was lost in the woods below, but I was glad to find myself on the branch of an ilex tree.

"I had been sucked down by an air current. Since that first experience of mine, I have met many others like it, but I have never understood why it was that above certain trees and streams the air gets very cold and makes a current that draws into itself the bird that strikes it. I had to learn the lesson of flying in those currents after being whirled up and down by them. But I do not hate them, since the first air current I encountered saved my life.

"Sitting on that ilex tree, I became so hungry that it drove me to fly home. Luckily, no soulless hawk obstructed my arrow-like flight.

"But my successful escape from that newly fledged murderer gave me back my courage, and as soon as you came home I said to myself: 'Now that he, my friend, has seen me alive, he will not worry about me. I must fly anew through the falcon-infested air and test my courage.'

"Now began my real Odyssey. I went northwards to the eagles' nest, and stopped at the lamasery where a holy man had blessed me on an earlier occasion. There I re-visited Mr. and Mrs. Swift, my old friends. Moving farther north, I went past Singalia at last and reached the eyrie of the eagles who had flown away. So I made myself comfortable there, but not too happy, for the eagles leave all kinds of refuse in their nests, and I am afraid they swarm with vermin. Though I spent my day in the eagles' nest, I decided to spend the night in a tree, free from horrid insects. After a couple of days, my going in and out of the eyrie gave me great prestige among other birds. They feared me, perhaps because they took me for a sort of eagle. Even the hawks began to give me a wide berth. That gave me all the confidence that I needed, so early one morning, seeing a white wedge of birds coming south, flying very high, I joined them. They did not mind my joining them; they were wild geese going towards Ceylon and beyond, in the quest of a sunny ocean.

"Those geese, after two hours' flight, as the day became warmer, descended onto a rapid mountain stream. Unlike the eagles, they rarely looked downwards, but watched the horizon lines. They spied a little ribbon of whitish-blue far off against the sky, and flew in a slowly declining straight line till it seemed as if the earth were rising to meet us, and soon all plunged into the silver stream, for now the waters looked more silvery than blue. They floated on the water, but as I knew that I was not web-footed, I sat on a tree and watched their antics. You know how flat and ugly the bills of geese are, but now I saw the reason for it. They used them like pincers on things such as shells that grew on the side of the banks. Every now and then a goose would put his bill on a plant or a shell, then wring it out of position as a butcher would wring a duck's neck. After that it would devour its victim wholesale, crushing it in its powerful throat, but ere it passed very far down its size dwindled to nothing. I saw one fellow do worse than that. He found a fish—as lean as a water-snake—in a hole under the bank; he began to pull it. The more he pulled, the thinner and longer it got. Slowly, after a terrific tug of war, the poor fellow was dragged from his hole. Then the goose hopped up the shore and flung it on the ground. His bill had crushed the part it had held onto, nearly into pulp, so no wonder his wriggling victim was already dead. Then from nowhere walked up to him another goose. (By the way, are not geese the most ungainly birds when they are not flying or swimming? On the water they resemble dreams floating on pools of sleep, but on land they hobble like cripples on crutches!) By now the two geese were quarrelling. They pulled each other's feathers; they slapped with their wings; they kicked each other with their feet every time they hopped up above the ground. While they were thus engaged, oblivious of their bone of contention, a cat-like creature, probably an otter, pounced from among the reeds, grabbed the dead eel, and vanished. Now the geese declared a truce, but too late! Oh, they have no more sense than, well—geese! Compared with them, we pigeons seem paragons of cleverness.

"After they had stopped fighting, the chief goose cried—'Cluck, caw, caw, caw!' That instant all of them paddled hard to gather momentum. A few extra wing-beats and they were in the air. How beautiful they looked now! That soft soughing of vast wings, their necks and bodies like drawings against the sky, making a severe eye pleasing wedge. I shall never forget it.

"But every flock has its straggler. One fellow was left behind, because he was still struggling with a fish. At last he secured it, and flew up in quest of a tree where he could eat it under cover. Suddenly from the empty air an enormous hawk attacked him. The goose rose higher, but the indefatigable hawk did not relent. Up and up they circled, screaming and quacking. Suddenly a faint but clear echo of a honk was heard. The chief of the flock was calling the straggler; that distracted him. Hardly knowing what he was doing, he honked back an answer. That instant the fish fell from his mouth. It began to fall like a leaf. The hawk dipped, and just as he was going to pierce it with his talons, down the air came a surge and roar. In a trice an eagle fell as a rock falls down a high precipice. That hawk ran for his life, and that gave me a great deal of pleasure to behold.

"Under the eagle's two wings like vast sails, the talons forked out lightning fashion and grabbed the fish—then the monarch of the air in his shining armour of brown gold sailed away, the wind ruffling the feathers above his knees. Far away, the hawk was still running for his life!

"I am glad he went very far away, for I had to fly about in quest of a caravan road where I could get some seeds dropped by men. I soon found some, and after a tolerably decent meal I perched on a tree and went to sleep. When I woke it was mid-afternoon. I decided to fly way up, to reach the blessed lamasery, and visit my friends the swifts. My flight was unattended by any mishap, for I had learned to fly carefully by now. I generally went very far up and looked down, as well as at the horizon. Though I have not so long a neck as a wild goose, yet I turned and took side glances every few minutes in order to make sure that nothing was attacking my rear.

"I reached the monastery just in time, as the lamas were getting ready to stand on the edge of their chapel in order to pour benediction upon the world during sunset. Mr. and Mrs. Swift were flying near the nest where their three youngsters were put to bed. Of course, they were glad to receive me. After their vesper services, the monks fed me, and the sweet old lama said something about a blessing that someone called Infinite Compassion had put upon me. Then I flew from his hand feeling absolutely fearless. In that state of mind and body I entered my nest next to the swifts under the eaves of the lamasery.

"The nights in October are cold. In the morning, while the priests rang their bells, the little swifts flew about for exercise while their parents and I had to fly to shake off the chill of the morning. That day I spent there in order to help them make preparations for their journey south. I was surprised to learn that they intended to build a nest in Ceylon or Africa whither they were going. They explained to me that a swift's nest is not at all any easy thing to construct. Then in order to assuage my thirst for knowledge, they told me how they erect their homes."

Chapter Eight Gay-Neck's Odyssey (continued)

"In order to make clear to you the swift's skill at architecture, let me first of all draw attention to the swift's handicaps. He has a small beak fit for catching flying insects. His mouth is very wide to enable him to catch his prey while he is on the wing. Very few insects can escape his wide-open mouth as he comes down on them. As he is very small, Mr. Swift cannot lift much weight. No wonder his house is built out of slender materials such as straw and twigs of trees no thicker than a middle-sized needle.

"The first time I saw a swift he looked paralysed and deformed. All swifts know that they have wretched legs. The bird has hardly any legs to balance upon. His small feet like fish-hooks, made for sticking on to places, emerge right out of his body; his little hook like claws seem inflexible. He has not enough leg between his body and his feet, and this deprives him of the springiness that longer legs supply to other birds. No wonder he cannot hop or jump. But that defect is squared by his one advantage—he can cling to stone palisades, marble eaves, and alabaster friezes of houses as no other bird can. I have seen my friend Swift hang on to polished walls as if they were corrugated surfaces.

"Under these handicaps, all he can do is to choose holes in walls just under the eaves for his home. But there he cannot lay his eggs, for they would roll off. So he catches flying straws and small falling leaves, and glues them to the stone floor of his nest with his saliva. That is the secret of his skill at architecture. His saliva is wonderful; it dries and hardens like the best glue of the cabinet-makers. When the nest is made ready, the long white eggs are laid. Among the swifts, women are not so emancipated as among the pigeons. Our women enjoy equal rights with men, but the female swift has always the larger part of the work to do. For instance, Mr. Swift never sits on the eggs; he lets his wife do it. Occasionally he brings her food during the day, but otherwise he spends all his waking hours visiting male swifts whose wives are similarly occupied. I told my friend Swift he ought to copy the pigeons and give more freedom to his wife, but he seemed to think this a pet joke of mine.

"At last our preparations were made, and one fine autumn morning the five swifts and I set out in a southerly direction, piloted by Mr. Swift. We never went in a straight line, but zigzagged east or west, though we held to a general southern course. The swifts eat flies and gnats that float on rivers and lakes. They go about fifty miles an hour—a blinding speed for a small bird—and do not like woods because while their gaze is fixed downwards in search of insects, they may break their wings on a tree. They prefer open clear spaces above the waters, and with their scythelike long wings they cleave the air as swiftly as an eagle falls on its prey. Think of the precision of the swift's eye and mouth! While he is whirling over the water, he snaps up flying insects with such ease that the space he traverses is completely cleared of all the gnats and flies who a few moments before danced in the sunlight.

"Thus we went over streams, ponds and lagoons. By the way, Mr. Swift eats his food in a hurry and takes his drink the same way. He flies over the water, skimming up drops as he goes, and swallowing them at a very high rate of speed. No wonder that he hates to fly in a place crowded with boughs, larches and saplings.

"But so much flight in open air has its drawbacks. While a swift is eating insects with such speed, a sparrow-hawk may fall on him from above. Under these circumstances the swift cannot dip down, for that would mean death by drowning. I must tell you of one such attack on my friends. They were busy catching their dinner on a vast lake one afternoon, and while I was flying about, keeping an eye on the younger swifts, down came a sparrow-hawk. I who had undertaken to look after the children had to act quickly even at the risk of my own life. Without an instant's hesitation I plunged and tumbled, inserting my body between the enemy and the young ones. Well, the sparrow-hawk had never expected so much nerve from a member of the dove family, nor did he calculate my weight. I was at least five ounces heavier than he. He struck my tail with his talons, tore a few feathers, and thinking that he had got something he circled the air for a moment or two. Before he realized that he had only my feathers, all the swifts were safe, clinging to the bark of a tree out of anybody's reach. But the small sparrow-hawk was so infuriated that he fell on me with the fury of a large one. However, his body was very small and his talons smaller, and I knew they could not pierce my feathers and my skin very far. So I accepted his challenge and tumbled up. He followed. I shot downwards; he too dived after. Then I began to rise high. He pursued as before. But those little hawks fear the upper air, and his wings lagged now. To my two wing-beats he could make but one. Seeing him hopeless and tired, I planned to teach him the lesson of his life. No sooner had I conceived than I executed my plan. I shot downwards. He plunged after. Down, down, down! The water of the lake rose towards us, higher and higher every second till it looked no farther than the width of my wing. Then I flung forward a few inches and struck a warm air current that helped me upwards. As you know, air warmed in the hollow places and valleys of mountain country has a tendency to shoot up into cooler regions. We birds look for these currents to help us when we have need to make a sudden upward flight. Now I tumbled three times, and when I looked down I found that sparrow hawk drowning in the water. He had not been able to reach the air current. After a considerable ducking, he laboriously flew ashore, and there under thick leaves hid his disgrace. That instant the swifts came out of their hiding-place and flew southwards.

"The next day we met some wild ducks. They had coloured throats like mine, but otherwise they were as white as snow. They were stream ducks, whose habit is to float down a mountain brook after fish. When they have gone far, they rise out of the water and fly back to their starting-place. So they spend the day like shuttles going back and forth. Their bills were flatter than those of the geese, and they are dented inside, for once they close on a fish the bills never slip. They did not seem to care much for the shellfish, but that was probably because the fish in the lake were so plentiful. The swifts did not like the place because the ducks' wings beat the air continually and blew away the insects that normally fly over any water surface. Still, they were glad to see ducks that loved and lived on mountain torrents, never bothering about the calm water so dear to most ducks.

"It was these ducks who warned us against the owls and other murderers of the night that infested those regions. So we did our best to hide in places too small for owls to go into. It was easy to find holes in a tree small enough for the swifts, but I decided to stay in the open and take my chances. Night came on apace. Pretty soon my eyes could serve me no longer. Darkness within darkness, like layers of black cloth, lay upon them. I commended myself to the Gods of my race and tried to sleep. But who could sleep with those owls who-whoing about? Terror seized me for the night. Not an hour passed without some bird's shrieking in pain. The owls, too, hooted in triumph. Now a starling, then a bulbul (the Indian nightingale) would cry mortally, and die under the owl's grip. Though my eyes were shut, my ears knew the carnage that went on. A crow shrieked. Then another, then another. Almost a flock flew up in terror and smashed themselves against trees. But better that kind of death than to be killed by the searing and tearing beaks and claws of the owls. Soon to my utter confusion I smelt weasels in the air, and then I felt that death was at hand. That made me desperate; I opened my eyes to see. A pale white light was shining on all things. There before me, about six feet away, was a weasel. I flew up, though that increased the danger of my being killed by the owls. And sure enough, along came one, hooting and screaming. Two more owls followed. I heard their wing-beats, and by the nature of the sounds I knew that we were flying over the water, for it echoed back even the slightest shiver of our feathers. I could not fly in any direction very far, since I saw not more than six feet at a time, so I waited in the air, groping for a current that sucked the air of the river up above the boughs that hung over it. Alas, those owls were on me already, but I tumbled, then swung into a circle. The owls would not give up the chase. I rose farther up. Now the moonlight like water dripped from my wings. I could see a little more clearly, and that brought me back my courage. But my enemies did not relent. They too rose, and more light fell on their eyes, blinding them, though not completely. Suddenly two of them plunged towards me. Up I flew. The owls missed—lo! They had fallen on each other. Their claws locked together, their wings flapping helplessly in the air, they screamed like fiends and fell among the reeds of the river-bank.

"Now I looked about carefully and noticed to my surprise that I had flown towards the dawning of day and not at the moon. My terror-stricken eyes had not seen truly. But there were no more owls about; they had begun to seek for places of hiding from the growing sunlight. Although I felt safe, I kept away from the prodigious shadows of the tall trees, for even now an owl might lurk there. I stayed on a slender branch on a tree-top that caught the first flight of the sun's arrows, transfiguring it into an umbrella of dancing gold. Slowly the light spread farther down till the white torrent below trembled with colours like a weasel's eyes.

"Just then on the river-bank I saw an appalling sight. Two large crows, blacker than coal, were jabbing and prodding with their beaks a helpless blinking owl, caught in the reeds. Now that the sun shone, it could not open its eyes. Of course the night's slaughter done among the crows was large, and it was the crows' turn to avenge their wrongs, but I could not bear the sight of two of them killing that trapped owl. So I flew away from the murderers and went to seek my friends the swifts. I recounted some of my experiences, and the parents told me that they had heard terrible cries of distress that kept them from slumber. Mr. Swift asked if everything was safe outside, and I thought it was. When we came out, I found that poor owl lying dead, among the reeds!

"Strange to say, that morning we saw no ducks on the stream. Apparently they had flown very early in the morning in a southerly direction, and we decided to do the same. We planned not to seek the company of other birds going our way. For during the season of migration, wherever flocks of pigeons, grouse and other birds go, their enemies, such as owls, hawks and eagles, go after them. In order to avoid danger and such shocking sights as we had seen before, we flew to the east, and after going eastwards a whole day, we rested in the village of Sikkim. The next day we flew south for half a day, and again eastwards. That sort of roundabout journey took a long time, but it saved us no end of trouble. Once we were overtaken by a storm, and were blown into a lake country, and there I saw an amazing sight. I was on a tree-top, when below me I discerned a lot of domesticated ducks floating on the water, each one with a fish in its mouth. But none of them swallowed his morsel. I had never seen ducks resist the temptation to eat fish before, so I called the swifts to behold the sight. They clung to the barks of several trees and looked at the ducks, but they could hardly believe their eyes. What was the matter with them? Pretty soon a boat heaved in sight, poled by two men, flat-faced and yellow. On seeing them, the ducks paddled to the boat as fast as they could go. Reaching it, they hopped up, and then—can you believe it?—they dropped their capture into a large fish basket, and jumped down into the lake to fish for some more, and that went on for at least two hours. Apparently those Tibeto-Burman fishermen never cast nets. They tied a string tightly, almost to the choking point, around their ducks' necks, and then brought them to the lake to catch fish. Whatever the latter caught, they brought to their human masters. However, when their basket became full, they undid the strings that were around the ducks' necks, who then plunged into the lake, and gorged themselves on fish.

"Now we flew away far from the lakes for a while in quest of harvest-fields. There the swifts fell on the insects that flew about newly mown grain, and devoured them. I, too, ate to repletion of the grain, though not of the insects. While sitting on the fence of a rice-field, I heard someone hitting something. It sounded very much like a chaffinch cracking open a cherry-stone with his beak in order to get at its kernel. (Isn't it strange that a little bird's beak has the power of a nutcracker?) But, when I wandered nearer the place, under the fence, whence the noise was coming, I found another bird—a Himalayan thrush. He was engaged, not in cracking cherry stones, but in hitting a slowly moving snail with his beak. Tick, tack; tick, tack—tack! He hammered on and on until the snail was stunned into stillness. The thrush raised his head and looked around, poised himself on tiptoe, opened his wings, took a quick aim and struck three more blows—tack, tack, tack! The shell broke open, revealing a delicious snail. He lifted it up with his beak, which was bleeding slightly; apparently he had opened his mouth too wide and hurt its corners. After balancing the snail correctly in his grasp, he flew up and vanished into a tree where his mate was waiting for supper.

"The rest of our journey through the grain fields of Sikkim was uneventful. The only thing that is worth remembering was the trapping of peacocks by men in the forests. These birds come to the hot southern marshes in quest of food and warmth when the snakes and other creatures whom they eat go into winter quarters in the north.

"Peacocks and tigers admire one another. The former like to look at the tiger's skin, and he enjoys the beauty of their plumes. Sometimes at the water-hole a tiger will stand gazing at the plumes of a peacock on a bough, and the peacock will crane his neck to feast his eyes on the beauty of the striped skin. Now comes man, the eternal aggressor, on the scene. For instance, a man one day brought a piece of cloth painted exactly like a tiger's skin, so that no bird could tell by looking at it that it was not the striped one himself. Then he set a noose on a branch of a tree nearby, and slunk away. I could tell by the odour of the painted cloth that it was not a tiger, but peacocks have no sense of smell worth speaking of. They are victims of their own eyes. So in a few hours a pair of peacocks came and began to gaze at the make-believe tiger from a tree-top, coming lower and lower. They deceived themselves into the belief that the tiger was asleep. Emboldened by that illusion, they came very close and stood on the branch near the trap. It did not take them long to walk into it, but how they both stepped into a single trap I cannot make out. No sooner were they caught than they shrieked in despair. Then appeared the trapper, and played another trick on them. He threw up two large black canvas caps and lassoed them on each peacock's head, hiding the poor bird's eyes. Once the eyes are darkened, a bird never resists much. The man now tied their feet so that they could not walk; then he set one on each end of his bamboo pole. Slowly he lifted it by the middle, put it on his shoulder and walked off, the long tails of the peacocks streaming down like cataracts of rainbow before and behind him.

"There ends my Odyssey. The next day I said good-bye to the swifts. They went farther south, and I was glad to get home, a wiser and a sadder bird. Now," demanded Gay-Neck, "tell me this: Why is there so much killing and inflicting of pain by birds and beasts on one another? I don't think all of you men hurt each other. Do you? But birds and beasts do. All that makes me so sad."

Chapter One Gay-Neck's Training for War

After we returned to town, the air was filled with the rumours of a coming war somewhere in Europe. Now that winter was at hand, I decided to give Gay-Neck such training as would be necessary in case he was asked to be a carrier for the British War Department. Since he was used to the climate of the northeastern Himalayas, he would be an invaluable messenger for the army in any European country. Even now, with the aid of wireless telegraph and radio, no army can dispense with the help of carrier-pigeons. All that will become clear to you as the present story unfolds itself.

In training carriers for war work, I followed a plan of my own that Ghond approved. By the way, the old fellow came all the way to town with us. He stayed in our house two or three days, then decided to leave, saying: "The city is unbearable. I never loved any city, but this one frightens me with its electric tramway and how-aghari [wind chariot]—the automobile. If I do not shake the dust of this town off my feet very soon, I shall be nothing better than a coward. A tiger in the jungle does not frighten me, but I cannot say the same of an automobile. One crossing of a modern city street imperils more lives in a minute than a day in the most dangerous forests. Farewell! I go where the woods wear stillness for a dress, the air is free of odours and dust, and the sky, a hollowed turquoise, is not cross-cut and pierced with poles and telegraph wires. Instead of factory whistles I shall hear the song of birds; and in the place of thieves and gunmen I shall have innocent tigers and panthers face to face. Farewell!"

But before he left, he helped me to buy about forty more carriers, and some tumblers. You may ask me the reason of my preference for these two kinds. I do not know that I have any exclusive love for tumblers and carriers, but it is true that fan-tails, pouters and other pigeons are more ornamental than useful. In our house we had some of these varieties, but they proved so difficult to keep in company with the carriers and travellers that I finally bestowed all my appreciation on pure flyers.

In India we have a queer custom that I do not like. If you sell a carrier, no matter at what fabulous price, and it flies away from its new owner and comes back to you, it becomes your property again, and no matter what the value, you never refund the price. Knowing that to be the accepted custom among pigeon-fanciers, I had to train my newly acquired pets before anything else to love me. Since I had paid for them, I did not wish them to return to their former owners. I did my very best to make them cherish their new home loyally. But life is practical. I had to begin with the most necessary steps. The first few weeks I had to tie up their wings in order to keep them completely within the bounds of our roof. The art of tying a pigeon's feathers so that he is prevented from flying is delicate. You take a thread, and pass one end of it over one feather and under the next, very near its root, all the way until the entire wing is encompassed. Then you pass the other end of the thread by the same process under the first, over the second, and so on to the end of the wing, where the two ends of the thread are tied. It is very much like darning. It is an utterly painless form of captivity, for though it prevents a pigeon from flying, yet he is not kept from opening or flapping his wings. He can stretch them and can massage them with his beak. After this, I used to put my new pigeons at different corners of the roof so that they might sit still, and with their eyes take in the colour and quality of their new surroundings. At least fifteen days should be allowed for this process.

Here I must record a cunning thing that Gay-Neck did when his wings were tied in the above manner. I sold him early in November just to see if he would return to me when his wings were freed from their chain of threads.

Well, two days after purchasing Gay-Neck, his new owner came to me and said, "Gay-Neck has run away."

"How?" I asked.

"I don't know, but I cannot find him in my house."

"Did you tie his wings? Could he fly?" I asked.

"His wings were tied." he answered.

That struck terror to my soul. I said: "Oh, your brother of a camel and cousin of an ass, instead of running hither, you should have sought for him in your own neighbourhood. Do you not see that he tried to fly, but since his wings were tied, he fell off your roof? And by now he has been killed and devoured by some cat. Oh, this is a slaughter of a pigeon. You have robbed mankind of its diadem of carriers! You have murdered the glory of pigeonhood!" Thus I reproached him.

My words frightened the man so thoroughly that he begged me to come with him and hunt for Gay-Neck. My first thought was to rescue the poor fellow from cats. We spent a whole afternoon, but in vain. I examined more sordid alleyways in twelve hours, expecting to find him at bay before some mangy cat, than I have done in all the rest of my life. Alas, he was not to be found. That night I came home late, for which I got a good scolding, and went to bed a broken hearted boy.

My mother, who understood my state of mind, did not wish me to enter the world of sleep with hurt and excited feelings. She spoke: "Your pigeon is safe. Go to sleep in a calm mood."

"Why, Mother?"

She answered: "If you are calm, your tranquil thoughts can help you. If you are peaceful, your serenity will make him serene. And if he is serene, his mind will work well. And you know, my beloved, how keen Gay-Neck's mind is. If he sets to work with tranquillity he will overcome all obstacles and reach home and safety. Now let us make a prayer to Infinite Compassion, and calm ourselves." So we sat surrounded by the silence of night for half an hour, saying: "I am serene. All that exists is serene. Peace, peace, peace be unto all! Om Shanti, shanti, shanti!"

As I was going to sleep, my mother said: "You will now dream no bad dreams. Now that God's peace and compassion are kindled in you, you will have a night of fruitful rest. Peace!"

That it proved to be fruitful there is no doubt. For about eleven in the morning, Gay-Neck flew up across the sky. He rode high. How he freed his wings I shall have to tell you in his own language. Let us again use the grammar of fancy and the dictionary of imagination.

"O master of many tongues," began Gay-Neck on our own roof, "I could abide not more than a day in that man's house! He gave me insect-infected grain to eat, and made me drink water that was not fresh. After all, I am a soul; why should I be treated as a stone or shard? Moreover, he tied my wings with evil-smelling fishing tackle. Would I stay with such an one? Never! So hardly had he put me on the white roof of his house and gone downstairs, than I flapped my wings and flew. Alas! My wings were heavy, and it hurt me to fly. So I fell on the awning of a shop in the lane near by. There I sat waiting and watching for help. I saw some swifts go by; I called to them, but they were not my friends. I saw a wild pigeon; I called, but he too made no response. Just then I beheld a dark cat coming towards me. Here was death on four feet. As it drew nearer and nearer, its topaz eyes burned with red. It crouched and made ready to spring. I, too, sprang—clear over his head on to the cornice about five feet above the awning, where a swift had made his home. Though it was most difficult, I clung to that spot until the black one vanished. Now I leaped again. Four or five feet above me was the roof. There I perched. But my wing hurt. In order to ease my pain, I massaged the roots of my feathers. One by one my beak pressed and rubbed them, and then something slipped. One small feather I had succeeded in pressing out of the grip of the fishing tackle, which stank exceedingly. I kept on rubbing and pressing the next feather, and, behold, it too was free. Oh, what a glorious feeling! Soon the entire wing was free. Just then the black cat re-appeared on the roof, but now I was able to fly about ten feet and I reached the cornice of a high building, where I found a convenient perch. Thence I watched the deadly cat. He crouched, and sprang upon the fishing tackle just shed from my wing. That told me a new story: it was the stench of the fishing tackle that had attracted him, and not me. Forthwith I began to bite and press the cord that bound my other wing. By the time I had freed half the feathers, night came on; and when I had thrown my last evil-smelling chain away from my wing, I was forced to await the dawn to fly home, for owls fly in the early twilight, and hawks come later, and I wished to have a safe path through the air. Now I am at home—I am hungry and thirsty."

The first thing I did with my new pigeons was to give them food and fresh water. I never let them drink the water they bathed in. Since Gay-Neck's wing smelt of fish, I gave him separate quarters from the other pigeons. It took three days longer and three good baths before Gay-Neck was fit for decent society. In passing, let me remark that my father made me return the money to the man who had bought Gay-Neck with such deplorable results. To tell you the truth, I did not wish to then. But now I feel I did right in obeying my parent. After a fortnight, and before unbinding the wings of my newly acquired pigeons, I bribed them to love me. Every morning I would put some millet seed and peanuts in ghee (clarified butter). After they had been soaked in butter all day, I gave a dozen each to every one of my pets. They were so fond of those delicacies that in two days' time they had formed the habit of coming to me before five in the afternoon, begging for buttered seeds. In three more days I freed their wings, in a subtle way, undoing them about fifteen minutes before five. They all flew off the moment they felt their liberty. But lo, after the first exhilaration of finding their freedom had passed, they flew down to the roof again for their meal of buttered peanuts and millet seeds! It is a pity that we have to win our pigeons' confidence by feeding their stomachs, but alas! I have noticed that there are many men and women who resemble pigeons in this respect!

Chapter Two War Training (continued)

The new pigeons gradually learned to fly farther and farther away from the house as day followed day. At the end of a month they were taken a distance of fifty miles and more and uncaged, and with the exception of two who apparently fled home to their previous owner, all returned to me under Gay-Neck's leadership.

The question of an undisputed leadership was not an easy one to settle. In fact, a serious battle had to be fought out between Gay-Neck and two new males, Hira and Jahore. The last named was a pure-black tumbler. His feathers shone like panther's fur. He was gentle and not fierce, yet he refused to submit to Gay-Neck's leadership of the entire flock. You know how quarrelsome and full of display carriers generally are. On my roof all the carrier males used to strut, coo and talk as if each one of them was the monarch of all he surveyed. If Gay-Neck thought himself Napoleon, Hira (Diamond), the white carrier—as white "as the core of sunlight," to express it poetically—considered himself Alexander the Great, while Jahore (Black Diamond), though not a carrier, let it be known that he was Julius Caesar and Marshal Foch rolled into one. Besides those three, there were other conceited males, but they had already been beaten in battle by one or the other of the above three. Now it was necessary to fight out the question of absolute leadership of the entire flock.

One day Hira was seen preening his wings and talking nonsense in the presence of Mrs. Jahore, a beautiful jet-black creature with eyes as red as bloodstone. Matters had hardly gone any distance when from nowhere came Jahore, and fell upon Hira. The latter was so infuriated that he fought like a fiend. Beak against beak, feet against feet, and wings pitted against wings. All the other pigeons fled from the ring where the two males were engaged in trouncing each other. Gay-Neck stood over them, calm as an umpire over a tennis match. At last, after half a dozen set-tos, Hira won. Puffing himself to the uttermost limits of his conceit, he went over to Mrs.Jahore as much as to say: "Madame, your husband is a coward. Behold what a fine fellow I am. Buk, bukoom, kumkum." She gave him one crushing look of contempt, and flapping her wings withdrew to her husband in their home. Hira looked crestfallen and sulky in turn; then in a sudden paroxysm of anger he fell upon Gay-Neck tooth and nail. The latter, taken unaware, was very nearly knocked out at the first fury of the attack. Hira pecked and slapped him till he felt too dizzy to stand up, so Gay-Neck ran away pursued by the mad fellow. They ran in a circle, spinning like two tops. I could hardly see which was pursuer and which pursued. They went at such high speed that I could not see when they stopped and started to peck and slap each other. The explosive sound of wing hitting wing filled the air with an ominous clamour. Now feathers began to fly in every direction. Suddenly, beak to beak and claw in claw they wrestled and spun on the floor—two birds became a single incarnation of fury. Seeing that they could not reach any decision that way, Gay- Neck extricated himself from his rival's grip and flew up in the air. Hira followed, flapping his wings tremendously fast. About three feet above the ground Gay-Neck put his claws like talons around Hira's windpipe, and set to squeezing it more and more tightly, and at the same time kept up a terrific cannonade of wing-beats that, like flails of steel, threshed out a shower of snowy feathers from his opponent's body. Now, hid in that falling blizzard of feathers, the two rolled on the ground, pecking each other with the virulence of two maddened serpents. At last Hira let go and wilted like a torn white flower on the floor. One of his legs had been dislocated. As for Gay-Neck, his throat and neck had hardly any feathers left. But he was glad that the struggle had been settled one way or another. And he knew full well that had Hira not first expended half his strength fighting Jahore, he, Gay-Neck, might not have won the battle. However, all is well that ends well. I bandaged and did all that was necessary to Hira's leg. In another thirty minutes all the pigeons were eating their last meal of the day, utterly oblivious of what had happened so recently. No sulking and bearing of grudges in their blood—no doubt they all came from a fine set of ancestors! Good breeding prevailed even among the smallest of them, and needless to add, Hira took his defeat like a gentleman.

By now January had come, with cool weather and clear skies, and the competition for pigeon prizes began. Each man's flock was tested on three points: namely, team-work, long-distance flight and flight under danger. We won the first prize on the first point, but I am sorry to say that owing to a sad mishap, which you shall learn of in its proper place, my pigeons could not compete for the other two.

This is the nature of the team-work competition. The various flocks of pigeons fly way up from their respective homes. Once they are beyond the reach of whistling and other sounds that indicate their master's voice, the diverse flocks coalesce. Then spontaneously they agree to fly under the leadership of a pigeon whom they consider fit. All this happens up in the air where pigeon-wit and pigeon-instinct prevail, and the bird who flies forward and is allowed to lead does so without ever realizing the nature and the reason of the honour that has been bestowed on him.

The temperature dropped to forty-five. It was a fine cold morning for our part of India, in fact the coldest day of the year. The sky above, as usual in the winter, was cloudless and remote, a sapphire intangibility. The city houses—rose, blue, white and yellow—looked like an army of giants rising from the many coloured abyss of dawn. Far off, the horizons burned in a haze of dun and purple. Men and women in robes of amber and amethyst, after having said their morning prayers to God, were raising their arms from the house-tops in gestures of benediction to the rising sun. City noises and odours were unleashed from their kennels of the night. Kites and crows were filling the air with their cries. Over the din and clamour one could yet hear the song of the flute-players. At that moment the signal whistle blew that the contest had begun, and each pigeon-fancier waved from his roof a white flag. Instantly from nowhere innumerable flocks of pigeons rose into the sky. Flock upon flock, colour upon colour, their fluttering wings bore them above the city. Crows and kites—the latter of two species, red and brown—fled from the sky before the thundering onrush of tens of thousands of carriers and tumblers. Soon all the flocks—each flying in the shape of a fan—circled in the sky like so many clouds caught in large whirlpools of air. Though each moment they ascended higher, for a long time each owner of a flock knew his own from the others; and even when at last the separate flocks merged into a single unit and flew like a solid wall of wings, I could pick out, by the way they flew, Gay-Neck, Hira, Jahore and half a dozen others. Each bird had personal characteristics that marked him as he flew. When any owner wished to call the attention of any one of his pigeons, he blew a shrill whistle with certain stops as a signal. That attracted the bird's attention if he was within reach of the sound.

At last the whole flock reached such a height that not even the blast of a trumpet from any pigeon-fancier could reach it. Now they stopped circling in the air and began to move horizontally. The competition for leadership had begun. As they manoeuvred from one direction of the heavens to another, we, the owners below, had to look up intently in order to make sure of the characteristics of the one whom the pigeons had trusted to lead their flight. For a moment it looked as if my Jahore would lead. But hardly had he gone to the head of the flock when they all turned to the right. That brought about a confusion in the ranks, and, like horses on a race-course, all kinds of unknown pigeons pushed forward. But in time each one of them was pushed back by the rest of the flock. This happened so often that we began to lose interest in the contest. It looked as though some nondescript pigeon would win the coveted leadership prize.

Now suddenly rose the cry from many house-tops: "Gay-Neck, Gay-Neck, Gay-Neck!" Yes, many of that pigeon-fanciers were shouting that name. Now I could see—without the slightest shadow of error—my own bird at the head of the vast flock—a leader among leaders—directing their manoeuvres. Oh, what a glorious moment! He led them from horizon to horizon, each time rising a few feet higher, till by eight in the morning not a pigeon could be seen in any corner of the sky. Now we furled our flags and went downstairs to study our lessons. At midday, when again we went above, each man could see the entire wall of pigeons descending. Lo! Gay-Neck was still leading. Again rose the shout "Gay-Neck, Gay-Neck!" Yes, he had won the palm, for he had remained in leadership for more than four hours, and was coming down as he had gone up—a master!

Now came the most dangerous part of the flight. The Commander of the vast concourse gave the order to disband, and flock after flock split from the main body, each separate flock flying away to its home. But not too quickly. Some must guard the sky above them while the others flew homeward. Gay-Neck held my little flock in a kind of umbrella formation to protect the rear of the receding pigeons belonging to other contestants. Such is the price of leadership—the other name of self-sacrifice.

But now began a horrible climax. In India during the winter the buzzards called Baz come south. They do not eat carrion; like the eagle and the hawk the Baz generally eats what he kills with his own talons. They are mean and cunning—I think they are a class of low born eagles—but they resemble kites, although their wings are not frayed at the ends. They fly in pairs slightly above a flock of kites and are hidden by them from their prey, which, however, they can see in this way without ever being seen themselves.

On that particular day, just when Gay-Neck had won the leader's laurels, I perceived a pair of Baz flying with a flock of kites. Instantly I put my fingers in my mouth and blew a shrill whistle. Gay-Neck understood my signal. He redistributed his followers, he himself leading the centre, while Jahore and Hira he ordered to cover the two ends of the crescent, in which shape the flock was flying. The entire group held together as though it were one vast bird. They then began to dip down faster and faster. By now the task for which they tarried in the heavens was done. All the other flocks that they had played with in the morning had gone home.

Seeing them dip down so fast, a Baz fell in front of them like a stone dropping from a Himalayan cliff. Just when he had descended to the level of my birds, he opened his wings and faced them. This was no new tactic, for it has been used in the past by every Baz in order to strike terror into a flock of pigeons. That it succeeds in ten cases out of eleven is undeniable, for when it happens the terror struck pigeons lose their sense of solidarity and fly pell-mell in every direction. No doubt that was what the Baz hoped for now; but our wily Gay-Neck, beating his wings, flew without a tremor under the enemy about five feet, drawing the whole flock after him. He did it, knowing that the enemy never pounces upon a solidly unified group. But hardly had he gone a hundred yards forward when the second, probably Mrs. Baz, fell in front of the pigeons and opened her wings as her husband had done. But Gay-Neck paid no attention. He led the whole flock straight toward her. It was inconceivable. No pigeon had dared do that before, and she fled from their attack. Hardly had her back been turned when Gay-Neck and the rest of the pigeons dipped and swooped as fast as they could go. By now they were hardly six hundred feet from our roof, and then, as fate would have it, Mr. Baz, like a shell full of high explosives, fell again, this time right in the middle of the crescent, and opened his wings and beak like forks of fire, crying and shrieking with fury. That produced its effect. Instead of one solid wall of pigeons, the flock was cut in two, of which one half followed Gay-Neck, while the other, smitten with abject fear, flew none knew whither. Gay-Neck did what a true leader does in great crises. He followed that panic-stricken flock until his section overtook it, and in no time, lo, they had merged into a single group once more. Hardly had that taken place when Mrs. Baz in her turn descended like a thunderbolt between him and the other pigeons. She almost fell on his tail, and cut him off from the rest, who now, deprived of their mentor, sought safety in flight, paying no heed to anything. That isolated Gay-Neck completely, and exposed him to attacks from every side. Still undaunted, he tried to fly down to his retreating followers. Ere he had descended a dozen feet, down before him swooped Mr. Baz. Now that Gay-Neck saw the enemy so near, he grew more audacious, and tumbled. It was a fortunate action. Had he not done so, Mrs. Baz, who had shot out her talons from behind, would have captured him then and there.

In the meantime the rest of my pigeons were beating on, and had almost reached home. They were falling on the roof as ripe fruits fall from a tree. But one among them was not a coward. On the contrary, he was of the very essence of bravery. It was Jahore, the black diamond. As the whole crowd settled down on our roof, he tumbled and flew higher. There was no mistake about his intentions. He was going to stand by Gay-Neck. Seeing him tumble again, Mr. Baz changed his mind. He gave up pursuing Gay-Neck and swooped down after Jahore. Well, you know Gay-Neck—he dipped to the rescue of Jahore—circling and curving as swiftly as a coil of lightning, leading Mrs. Baz panting after him. She could not make as many curves as Gay-Neck, no, not nearly so many. But Mr. Baz, who was a veteran, had flown up and up to take aim; this put Jahore in danger. One more wrong turn, and Mr. Baz would have him. Alas! poor bird, he did the thing he should not have done. He flew in a straight line below Mr. Baz, who at once shut his wings and fell like a thunderclap of Silence. No noise could be heard, not even "the shadow of a sound." Down, down, down, he fell, the very image of death. Then the most terrible thing happened. Between him and Jahore slipped, none knew how, Gay-Neck, in order to save the latter and frustrate the enemy. Alas! Instead of giving up the attack, the Baz shot out his talons, catching a somewhat insecure hold of the intruder. A shower of feathers covered the air. One could almost see Gay-Neck's body writhing in the enemy's grip. As if a hot iron had gone through me, I shrieked with pain for my bird! But nothing availed. Round and round, higher and higher that Baz carried him, trying to get a more secure hold with his talons. I must admit something most humiliating here. I had been so intent on saving Gay-Neck that I did not notice when Mrs. Baz fell and captured Jahore. It must have happened very swiftly, right after Gay- Neck was caught. Now the air was filled with Jahore's feathers. The enemy held him fast in her talons, and he made no movement to free himself. But not so Gay-Neck; he was still writhing in the grip of Mr. Baz. As if to help her husband to grasp his prey more securely, Mrs. Baz flew very close to her lord. Just then Jahore struggled to get free. That swung her so near that her wing collided with her husband's. The fellow lost his balance. As he was almost over-turned in the air, with another shower of feathers Gay-Neck wrenched himself free from his grip. Now he dropped down, down, down.… In another thirty seconds a panting, bleeding bird lay on our roof. I lifted him up in order to examine his wound. His two sides were torn, but not grievously. At once I took him to the pigeon doctor, who dressed his wounds. It took about half an hour, and when I returned home and put Gay-Neck in his nest, I could not find Jahore anywhere. His nest, alas, was empty. And when I went up to the roof, there I found Jahore's wife sitting on the parapet, scanning every direction of the sky for a sign of her husband. Not only did she spend that day, but two or three more in the same manner. I wonder if she found any consolation in the fact that her husband sacrificed himself for the sake of a brave comrade.

Chapter Three Mating of Gay-Neck

Gay-Neck's wounds healed very slowly. Until about the middle of February he could not be made to fly more than ten yards above the roof. The duration of his flight, too, was very short. No matter how frequently I chased him off the roof, I could not keep him in the air more than a quarter of an hour. At first I thought that it was his lungs that were out of order. When, after investigation, they proved sound, I ascribed his disinclination to fly to his heart, which might have been injured by his latest mishap. That assumption also proved erroneous after a second investigation.

So, utterly exasperated by Gay-Neck's behaviour, I wrote a long letter to Ghond describing everything that had happened. It turned out that he had gone on a hunting-trip with some Englishmen. Receiving no help from that quarter, I decided to examine my pigeon most closely. Day after day I put him on our house-top, and watched, but no clue was vouchsafed me as to the nature of his trouble. So I gave up all hope of seeing Gay-Neck fly again.

About the end of February I received a cryptic note from Ghond from the deeps of the jungle. It read: "Your pigeon is frightened. Cure him of his fear. Make him fly." But he did not say how. Nor could I devise anything that would make Gay-Neck wing his way into the higher spaces. It was no use chasing him off the roof, for if I chased him off one corner, he flew across to another and perched there. And what was most disconcerting was that if the shadow of a cloud or a flock of birds flying in the sky fell on him on our roof, he would tremble with terror. Doubtless every shadow that fell filled his mind with the feeling that it was a Baz or a falcon swooping down on him. That gave me an idea of how badly shaken Gay-Neck was. How to cure him of his disease of fear proved most baffling. Had we been in the Himalayas, I would have taken him to the holy man who once healed him of a similar ailment, but here in the city there was no lama. I was forced to wait.

March had ushered in spring, and Gay-Neck, who had gone through an unusual moulting, looked like the very heart of a deep and large aquamarine. He was beautiful beyond description. One day, I know not how, I found him talking to Jahore's widow. She looked very bright with the advent of spring. In the sunlight her black-opal complexion glowed like a tropical night shot with stars. Of course I knew that marriage between her and Gay-Neck, though not the best thing for their offspring, might win him from his fear and her from the morose temper that had grown upon her ever since Jahore died.

In order to encourage their friendship, I took the two together in a cage to my friend Radja, who lived on the edge of the jungle about two hundred miles away. The name of his village was Ghatsila. It stood on the bank of a river across which lay high hills densely forested and full of all kinds of animals. Radja, being the priest of the village, which office his ancestors had held for ten centuries, and his parents were housed in a large building of concrete. The village temple, also of concrete, was adjacent to the house. In the courtyard of the temple, surrounded by high walls, Radja every night performed the duty of reading the Scriptures and explaining them to the peasantry that assembled there. While he would read aloud inside, outside would come from far off the yell of a tiger or the trumpeting of wild elephants across the narrow river. It was a beautiful and sinister place. Nothing dangerous happened in the village of Ghatsila, but you did not have to go very far to encounter any beast of prey that you cared to seek.

The train that brought me there reached Ghatsila at night. Radja and two servants of his house greeted me at the station. One of the servants took my bundle on his shoulder, and the other carried the cage with the two pigeons. Each of us had to carry a hurricane-proof lantern, an extra one having been brought for me. In single file, one servant leading and another in the rear, we walked for an hour. My suspicions were aroused, and I asked, "Why do we go round about?"

Radja said: "In the spring wild animals pass through here going north. We can't take short cuts through the woods."

"Nonsense!" I exclaimed. "I have done it many times before. When do we reach home?"

"In half an hour—"

Then, as if the very ground had opened at our feet and belched out a volcano with a terrific noise, arose the cry "Hoa—ho—ho— ho—hoa!"

The pigeons fluttered their wings in panic in their cage. I gripped Radja's shoulder with my disengaged hand, but instead of sharing my feelings he laughed out loud. And—like master like servant—the two servants laughed too.

After their mirth had subsided, Radja explained: "You have done this many times, have you? Then why did the cry of monkeys frightened by lanterns scare you?"

"Monkeys?" I questioned.

"Yes, lots of them," my friend reminded me, "go north this time of the year. We frightened a whole flock in the trees overhead. That's all. In the future don't take every monkey yell for the roar of a tiger."

Fortunately, we reached home shortly, without any other incident to upset my complacency.

The next morning Radja went to his duties at his ancestral temple, while I sought the roof and uncaged my birds. At first they were bewildered, but seeing me near them with my hands full of buttered seeds, they settled down to breakfast without any ado. Pretty nearly all of that day we spent on the roof. I dared not leave them by themselves very long lest the strangeness of their surroundings upset them.

In the course of the week that followed, the two birds made themselves at home in Ghatsila, and moreover became extremely intimate with each other. There was no doubt now that I had acted wisely in isolating them from the rest of the flock. About the eighth day of our stay, Radja and I were surprised to see Gay-Neck fly in pursuit of his mate. She flew on, but at a low altitude. He followed. Seeing him catch up to her, she rose and turned back. He too did the same, and followed after. Again she rose. But this time he balked, and began to circle the air beneath her. However, I felt that he was regaining his confidence. At last Gay- Neck, the paragon of pigeons, was healing himself of his fear and of his horror of the heavens; he was once more at home in the sky.

The next morning the birds flew higher and played with each other. Gay-Neck again refused to go all the way, and began to come down hastily instead of circling in the air below her. That puzzled me, but Radja, who was a keen person, explained. "A cloud, large as a fan, has come over the sun. Its shadow fell so suddenly that Gay- Neck thought it was his enemy. Wait until the cloud passes, and then—"

Radja was right. In a few more seconds the sun came out and its light dripped from Gay-Neck's wings once more. At once he stopped coming downwards and began to make circles in the air. His mate too, who had been coming down to keep him company, waited for him a hundred feet or so above. Now Gay-Neck rose, beating his wings like an eagle freed from his cage. The sunlight made pools of colour about him as he swerved and swung up and up. Soon, instead of following, he led his mate. Thus they ascended the sky—he healed of fear completely, and she ravished by his agility and power.

The next morning both of them made an early start. They flew far and very long. For a while they were lost beyond the mountains, as if they had slid over their peaks and down the other side. They were gone at least an hour.

At last they returned about eleven o'clock, each bearing in his beak a large straw. They were going to build a nest for the laying of eggs. I thought I would take them home, but Radja insisted that we should stay at least a week longer.

Every day during that week we spent some hours in the more dangerous jungle across the river, taking the two pigeons with us in order to release them in the dense forest hardly five miles from Radja's house. Gay-Neck forgot everything save testing his sense of direction and making higher flights. In other words, love for his mate and the change of place and climate healed him of fear, that most fell disease.

Here let it be inscribed in no equivocal language that almost all our troubles come from fear, worry and hate. If any man catches one of the three, the other two are added unto it. No beast of prey can kill his victim without frightening him first. In fact, no animal perishes until its destroyer strikes terror into its heart. To put it succinctly, an animal's fear kills it before its enemy gives it the final blow.

Chapter Four War Calls Gay-Neck

By the First Week of August, just after the children were born, Hira and Gay-Neck had gone from Calcutta to Bombay, setting sail with Ghond to serve in the World War. I sent that bachelor bird Hira with Gay-Neck because the army had need of both.

I was very glad that Gay-Neck had some knowledge of his little ones before he sailed for the battlefield of Flanders and France. The chief reason for this happiness was that I knew that a pigeon whose wife and new-born children are waiting at home rarely fails to return. That bond of love between Gay-Neck and his family assured me that he would do his work of carrying messages very well. No sound of gun-fire, nor bullets, as long as he lived, could keep him from returning home at the end.

But here one may raise the question that home was in Calcutta and the war was thousands of miles away. That is true. But all the same, because he had left his wife and children at home, he would do his utmost to fly back to his temporary nest with Ghond.

It is said that Gay-Neck carried several important messages between the front and General Headquarters where the Commander -in-Chief and Ghond waited for him. Of course, Gay-Neck was attached to Ghond first. But in the course of the following months he became very fond of the Chief.

Ghond and not I went to the front with the two pigeons, for I was under age and ineligible for any kind of service, so the old fellow had to take them. During the voyage out from India to Marseilles, Hira and Gay-Neck and the old hunter became fast friends. I have yet to see any strange animal resist Ghond's friendship long, and since my pigeons had known him before, it was easy for them to respond to him.

During the stay of the Indian Army in Flanders from September 1914 till the following spring, Ghond remained near General Headquarters with his cage, while Hira or Gay-Neck was taken by different units to the front. There from time to time messages were written on thin paper weighing no more than an ounce, and were tied to his feet; then he was released. Gay-Neck invariably flew to Ghond at the General Headquarters of the army. There the message was deciphered and answered by the Commander-in-Chief himself. It is rumoured that the latter personage loved Gay-Neck, and valued his services highly.

But it is better to listen to Gay-Neck's own story. As the experiences of a dream cannot be told except by the dreamer, so some of the adventures of Gay-Neck he should recount in person.

"After we crossed the black water—the Indian Ocean and the Mediterranean—we travelled by rail through a very strange country. Though it was September, yet that country—France—was as cold as southern India in the winter. I expected to see snow capped mountains and giant trees, for I thought I was nearing the Himalayas. But no hills higher than our tallest bamboo trees could I perceive on the horizon. I do not see why a land has to be cold when it is not high.

"At last we reached the battle-front. It turned out to be the rear end of it, but even there you could hear the boom, boom, boom of the fire-spitters. And, as a normal pigeon, I have all fire-spitters no matter of what size and shape. Those metal dogs barking and belching out death were not to my liking. After I had been there a couple of days, our trial flight began. There were only four pigeons of our own city besides Hira and myself. You know how rash Hira could be. No sooner had we flown up above the houses of a large village than Hira flew towards the direction of the boom, boom, boom. He wanted to investigate. Well, in an hour's time we were there. Oh, what a noise! Big balls of fire, spat out like thunderbolts by the metal dogs hidden under trees, hissed and exploded below us. I was frightened, so I rose higher and higher. But no peace there in the highest heavens could I find. From nowhere came vast eagles roaring and growling like trumpeting elephants. At such a terrific sight, we flew towards where Ghond was waiting for us. But the eagles, two of them, followed! We went faster and faster. Fortunately, they could not overtake us. Just as we had expected, those eagles came down where we lived. I felt death was at hand. Those eagles were going to devour us in our cages like weasels. But no! They stopped trumpeting soon and lay down on the field—dead. Two men each jumped out of the stomachs of those two birds and walked away. I wondered how eagles could devour human beings. And how could the fellows come out alive?

"Soon enough the men returned from their errand, climbed inside the eagles, and then with a groan and trumpeting racket, they came alive and flew up in the air again. That left no doubt in my mind that they were men's chariots, and when I knew that I felt relieved.

"Though everything looked strange at first, it ceased to be so after we got used to it; yet the problem of sleeping soundly under the continual booming and barking noises remained unsolved. All those months in the army I never slept well. No wonder Hira and I were nervous and fidgety, like newly hatched snakes.

"My first adventure consisted of taking a message from the Rasseldar at the front where all kinds of dogs barked and spat fire day and night. I must tell you a word about the Rasseldar. He was in charge of a lot of Indian warriors from Calcutta. He took me in a cage completely covered with black canvas, and with his forty men set out for the front trench. After going for hours and nights—for that is what it felt like in my darkened cage—we reached our destination. There the canvas was removed. Now I could see nothing but walls around me where turbaned men from India crawled like little insects. Overhead flew the mechanical eagles trumpeting with terror. Here for the first time I began to grasp sounds. Instead of one confused boom, boom, boom, there were as many grades of explosion as the ear could distinguish. The hardest one to make out was the talk of the men about me. Under the deafening sounds their talk sounded like the whisper of a lazy breeze in the grass. Now and then they unmuzzled a metal dog that barked—spitting out fire for a long stretch of time. Then came the laughter of a hyena. Hundreds of men goaded those little pups to an awful coughing—puck puff, puck puff, puck puff! That sound was drowned in the deep-toned cry of the eagles above who flew in flocks and barked as well as screeched like mad, slaying each other like so many sparrows. The Rasseldar who was in charge of me pointed the face of his pup at the sky, then let off—puck puff—some fire, and lo! It brought down one of those eagles as if it were a rabbit. Now the deepest tone was heard. The boom bazoom buzz bum! The tiger-roar of the large ones' mammoth majesty rose and spread like a canopy of divine chords, drowning under its engulfing immensity all other petty sounds. Oh, the excruciating enchantment of that organ tone! Can I ever forget? Roar upon roar, titanic tonality on tonality, like cataclysmic boulders of sounds crashed and clamoured!

"Why does beauty lie so close to death? Hardly had the ineffable glory of that supernal music overhead seized my soul when balls of fire fell about us like a torrential rain. Men fell and succumbed like rats in flooded holes. The Rasseldar, who was bleeding and red, wrote hastily on a piece of paper, tied it to my feet, and uncaged me. I knew by the look in his eyes that he was in dire distress and wanted Ghond to bring him succour.

"Of course you know, my master, I flew up; but what I beheld almost froze my wings. The air above the trenches was one sheet of flying fire. How to rise above it was my problem. I used my tail rudder, and steered my flight in every direction. But no matter which way I rose, above me ran a million shuttles of flame, weaving the garment of red destruction on the loom of life. But I had to rise, I, Gay-Neck, the son of my father. And soon I struck a pocket of air that was full of a current that sucked and whirled me up as if my wing were broken and I were as light as a leaf. It turned me up and down and up again till I had torn my way through the fabric of fire that kept on weaving itself with ever-increasing rapidity. But I had no eye for anything now. 'To Ghond, to Ghond,' I kept saying to myself. Every time I said that, it dug like a fresh goad into my spirit and made me put forth my greatest effort. Now that I had risen very high, I made my observations and flew westwards. Just then a shot pierced and broke my rudder. Half of my tail was burned and torn away from me. And you know that made me furious! My tail is my point of honour. I can't bear it to be touched, let alone shot at. Well, I flew safely home, but just about the moment I was getting ready to do down, two eagles started a fight above me. I had not heard their trumpeting or seen their faces. Had they killed each other I would not have minded, but they let loose a hurricane of flames after me. The more they fought, the more fire fell from their beaks. I dived and ducked as well as I could. If only they had had some trees there. Of course, there had been trees, but most of them had been shot and mutilated so that they stuck out like stumps, with no shade-giving gracious foliage or any prodigious boughs. So I had to zigzag my way round and about those dilapidated spikes like a man fleeing from elephants in the jungle. At last I reached home and perched on Ghond's wrist. He cut the thread and took the message with me to the Commander-in-Chief, who looked like a ripe cherry and exuded a pleasant odour of soap. Probably, unlike most soldiers, he bathed and soaped himself clean three or four times a day. After he had read what was scribbled on that paper by the Rasseldar, he patted me on the head and grunted like a happy ox."

Chapter Five Second Adventure

"The next time we were taken to the front was after the Rasseldar recovered from his slight wounds. On this occasion he took both Hira and me. I knew at once that the message we were to carry was so important that two had to be trusted with it so that at least one might succeed.

"It was very cold. I felt as if I were living in a kingdom of ice. It rained all the time. The ground was so foul that every time you stepped on it your feet got caught in mud like quicksand, and your feet felt so cold, as if you had stepped on a corpse.

"Now we reached a strange place. It was not a trench, but a small village. Around it beat and burst the tides of burning destruction. It was, by the look on the men's faces, a very sacred and important place, for they did not want to give it up, though the red tongues of death licked almost every roof, wall and tree of this place. I was very glad to be in an open space. One could see the grey sky low, oh, so very low. And one could see the frost-whited patches of ground where no shell had yet fallen. Even there, in that very heart of pounding and shooting, where houses fell as birds' nests in tempests, rats ran from hole to hole, mice stole cheese, and spiders spun webs to catch flies. They went on with the business of their lives as if the slaughtering of men by their brothers were as negligible as the clouds that covered the sky.

"After a while the booming stopped. And it looked as if the village—that is, what was left of it—were safe from attack. It grew darker and darker. The sky lowered so far that I could put my beak into it. The dank cold seized every feather of my body and began to pull it out, as it were. I found it utterly impossible to sit still in our cage. Hira and I hugged each other tight in order to keep warm.

"Again firing broke out. This time from every direction. Our little village was an island surrounded by the enemy. Apparently under cover of the fog that had enwrapped everything, the enemy had cut off our connection from the rear. Then they started shooting the sky-rockets. It was dark and clammy like a Himalayan night, though it was hardly past noon. I wondered how men knew it was anything but night. Men, after all, know less than birds.

"Hira and I were released to carry our respective messages. We flew up, but not very far, for in a short time we were devoured by a thick fog. Our eyes could see nothing. A cold clammy film pressed itself on them, but I had anticipated something like this. I did what I would do under such circumstances, whether on a field of battle or in India. I flew upwards. It seemed as if I could go no farther than a foot at a time. My wings were wet. My breathing was caught in a long process of sneezing. I thought I should drop dead in an instant. Thank the Gods of the pigeons I could see for a few yards now! So I flew higher. Now my eyes began to smart. Suddenly I realized I must draw down my film—my second eyelids that I use in flying through a dust-storm—if I were to save myself from blindness, for we were not in a fog—it was an evil-smelling, eye-destroying smoke let out by men. My eyes pained as if somebody had stuck pins into them. My films now covered my eyes, and, holding my breath, I struggled upwards. Hira, who was accompanying me, rose too. He was choking to death with that gas. But he was not going to give up his flight. At last we rose clear of the sheet of poison smoke. The air was pure here, and as I removed the film from my eyes I saw, far away against the grey sky, our line. We flew towards it.

"Hardly had we flown half-way homeward when a terrible eagle with black crosses all over it flew nearer and spat fire at us—puck puff, puck puff, pop pa.…We ducked and did the best we could. We flew back to its rear. There the machine could not hit us. Imagine us flying over the tail of that machine-eagle. It could do nothing. It began to circle. So did we. It turned somersaults. So did we. It could do nothing without wriggling its tail; unlike that of a real eagle, its tail was as stiff as a dead fish. We knew that if we once came in front of it again, we would be killed instantaneously.

"Time was passing. I realized that we could not go on staying over the tail of that machine-eagle forever. The village covered with poison gas that we had left behind held the Rasseldar and our friends. We must get our message through for their safety and succour.

"Just then the machine-eagle played a trick. It flew back towards its home. We did not wish to go into the enemy's line flying over its tail in order to be sniped by sharpshooters. Now that we were half-way to our own home and in sight of our line, we gave up being careful; we turned away from the machine-eagle and flew at our highest speed, rising higher every few wing-beats. No sooner had we done that than the miserable beast turned and followed. Fortunately, it took him a little time. There was no doubt now that we were flying over our own lines. Just the same that plane rose to our level and kept on pouring fire on us—puff puff pop pa! Now we were forced to duck and dive. I made Hira fly under me. That protected him. So we flew, but fate is fate. From nowhere came an eagle and fired at the enemy. We felt so safe now that Hira and I flew abreast of each other. Just then a bullet buzzed by me and broke his wings. Poor wounded Hira! He circled and fell through the air like a silver leaf, fortunately in our line. Seeing that he was dead, I flew at lightning speed; never turning back to see the duel of the two eagles.

"When I got home I was taken to the Commander-in-Chief. He patted my back. Then, for the first time, I realized what an important message I had brought, for as soon as the old man had read the piece of paper he touched some queer ticking things, and he lifted a piece of horn and growled into it. Now Ghond took me to my nest. There, as I perched, thinking of Hira, I felt the very earth shake under me. Machine-eagles flew in the air as thick as locusts. They howled, whirred and barked. Below, from the ground, boomed and groaned innumerable metal dogs. Then came the deep-toned howl of the big spitfires like a whole forest of tigers gone mad. Ghond patted my head and said, 'You have saved the day.' But there was no day in sight. It was a darkening grey sky under which death coiled and screamed like a dragon, and crushed all in its grip. How bad it was you may gauge from this: when I flew near our base for exercise next morning I found that hardly a mile from my nest the ground was ploughed up by shells. And even rats and field-mice did not manage to escape: dozens of them had been slaughtered and cut to pieces. Oh! It was terrible. I felt so melancholy. Now that Hira was dead I was alone, and so weary!"

Chapter Six Ghond Goes Reconnoitring

About the first week of December, Ghond and Gay-Neck were to go on a reconnaissance trip all by themselves. The place they went to was a forest not far from Ypres, Armentieres and Hazebrouck. If you take a map of France and draw a line from Calais south almost in a straight line, you will come across a series of places where the British and Indian armies were situated. Near Armentieres there are many graves of Indian Mohammedan soldiers. There are no graves of Indian Hindu soldiers because the Hindus from time immemorial have cremated their dead, and those that are cremated occupy no grave. Their ashes are scattered to the winds, and no place is marked or burdened with their memory.

To return to Ghond and Gay-Neck. They were sent to a forest near Hazebrouck, which was behind the enemy's line, to find out the exact location of an enormous underground ammunition dump. If found, Ghond and the pigeon, singly or together, were to return to the British Army Headquarters with an exact map of the place. That was all. So one clear December morning, Gay-Neck was taken on an aeroplane. It flew about twenty miles over a forest, part of which was held by the Indian Army and the rest by the Germans. When they had gone beyond the German line, Gay-Neck was released. He flew all over the woods; then having gained some knowledge of the nature of the land, he flew back home. This was done to make sure that Gay-Neck knew his route and had some inkling of what was expected of him.

That afternoon when the sun had gone down, which happened at about four o'clock at this latitude ten degrees north of New York, Ghond, most warmly dressed, with Gay-Neck under his coat, started. They went on an ambulance as far as the second line of the Indian Army in the great forest. In utter darkness they proceeded to the front, conducted by some members of the Intelligence Service.

Soon they found themselves in what is called No Man's Land, but fortunately it was covered with trees, most of which had not yet been destroyed by shell-fire. Ghond, who did not know French or German and whose knowledge of English was confined to three words, "yes," "no" and "very well," was now left to find a German ammunition dump in a forest, accompanied only by a pigeon fast asleep under his coat.

First of all he had to remind himself that he was in a country of the cold Himalayan climate where, during the winter, trees stood bare and the ground was covered with dry autumn leaves and frost. Since there was very little foliage on tree or sapling, concealment of himself proved not an easy task. The night was dark, and as cold as a corpse, but since he could see in the dark better than any living man, and because his sense of smell was as keen as the keenest of all animals, he knew how to steer his course in No Man's Land. Fortunately, that night the wind was from the east.

Edging his way between tree-trunks, he pushed forward as fast as possible. His nose told him minutes before their arrival that a company of Germans was passing his way. Like a leopard he crawled up a tree, and waited. They never heard even the flicker of a sound. Had it been daylight they would have found him, for his bare feet bled as he walked on the frost-stricken ground, leaving distinct marks behind.

Once he had a very close shave. As he went up a tree and sat on a branch to let a couple of German sentries pass below him, he heard someone whisper from a branch into his ear. He knew at once that it was a German sharpshooter. But he bent his head, and listened. The German said, "Guten nacht," then stepped over and slid down the tree. No doubt he had taken Ghond for one of his fellow-soldiers who had come to relieve him. After a while Ghond descended to the ground and followed the footprint of that German. Dark though it was, his bare feet could feel where the ground had been worn down by the feet of man. No difficult task that, for him.

At last he reached a place where a lot of men were bivouacking. He had to skirt around them softly, still pressing forward. He heard a strange noise right at his feet. He stopped and listened. No mistake, this was a familiar sound! He waited. The steps of an animal: Patter pat, patter-r-r! Ghond moved towards the sound, and a suppressed growl ensued. Instead of fear, joy gripped his heart. He who had spent nights at a time in the tiger-infested jungles of India was not to be deterred by the growl of a wild dog. Soon enough two red eyes greeted his vision. Ghond sniffed the air before him carefully as he stood there, and lo! He could not detect there was the slightest odour of man about that dog; the creature had gone wild. The dog, too, was sniffing the air to find out what kind of being he was facing, for Ghond did not exude the usual human odour of fear, and so the animal came forward and rubbed against him and sniffed vigorously. Fortunately, Ghond carried Gay-Neck above the dog's nose, and the odour of the bird's presence was carried up by the wind, so the wild dog perceived in the man before him nothing but a friendly fearless fellow. He wagged his tail, and whined. Ghond, instead of patting his head with his hand, slowly put it before the dog's eyes to see and smell. A moment of suspense followed. Was the dog going to bite the hand? Another moment passed. Then… the dog licked it. He now whined with pleasure. Ghond said to himself: "So this hunter's dog is without a master. Probably his master is dead. The poor beast has become as wild as a wolf. He lives by preying on the food supply of the German Army, for it is evident he had not yet eaten any human flesh. So much the better."

Ghond whistled softly, the call of all hunters of all ages no matter in what country. It meant "Lead." And the dog led. He skirted all the bivouacs of the German soldiers as deftly as a stag slips by a tiger's den. After hours of wandering, they reached their destination. There was no mistake about it; Ghond had found the very depot not only of munitions but also of German food supplies. His leader, the wild dog, went through a secret hole in the ground, then after half an hour emerged with a large leg of veal between his jaws. That it was bovine meat Ghond could tell by its odour. The dog sat down to his dinner on the frosty ground, while the man put on his boots, which he had carried slung over his shoulder all night long, and then looked up and took observations. By the position of the stars he could tell where he was. He waited there some time.

Slowly the day began to break. He took a compass from his pocket. Yes, he felt quite sure that he could draw a map of the place. Just then the dog jumped up and grabbed Ghond's coat with his teeth. There was no doubt in the man's mind that the dog wanted to lead him on again. He ran ahead, and Ghond followed as fast. Soon they reached a spot so thickly covered with thorns and frozen vines that passage through it was possible only for an animal. The dog crawled under a lot of sharp thorns, and disappeared.

Now Ghond drew a diagram showing the position of the stars, and the exact position of this compass, and tied both to Gay-Neck's foot, and let him go. He watched the pigeon fly from tree to tree, resting on each for a minute or so, and preening his wings. Then he struck the message tied to his foot with his beak—probably he was making sure that it was securely tied—flew up to the top of the tallest tree, and sat there examining the lay of the land. That moment Ghond, who was looking up, felt something pull him. He looked down at his feet; the dog was dragging him to a hole under the thorns. Ghond bent low, low enough to follow his mentor's direction, but at that moment he heard the flutter of wings overhead, then the barking of rifles. He had no desire to get up and investigate whether Gay-Neck had been killed or not. He crawled down under the thorns till he felt as if his stomach were glued against his backbone, and both sewed tightly to the ground. He pushed and crawled till suddenly he slid down, falling about eight feet into a dark hole. It was pitch dark, but Ghond hardly noticed that at first, for he was occupied in rubbing his bruised head.

When finally he tried to discover where he was, he made out that he must be sitting on a frozen water-hole covered, like a thieves' den, by impenetrable thorn-bushes. Even in winter when no leaf clad the branches and vines overhead, the darkness in daytime was thick there. The dog was still with him, and had evidently dragged him there to safety. The poor beast was so happy to have a friend with him that he wanted to play by the hour with Ghond, but the latter, being sleepy, dozed off into perfect slumber in spite of the noise of the guns not very far away.

After about three hours the dog suddenly whined and then yelled as if he were stricken with madness, after which the earth rocked under terrific sounds of explosion. Unable to bear it, the animal kept tugging the sleeve of Ghond's coat. The detonations rose crescendo upon crescendo till the place where Ghond lay literally swayed like a cradle, but he would not leave his hiding. All he said to himself was: "O Gay-Neck, thou incomparable bird, how well thou hast done thy task! Already thou hast borne the message to the cherry-faced chief, and this is his thunderous reply. O thou pearl among winged creatures!" So on he mumbled while the bombs dropped by aeroplanes ignited the German munitions dump.

Then the dog, who had been trying to pull him away by the sleeve of his coat, whined and shivered like one in high fever, and that instant something sizzled through the air and fell near by with a thud. With a desperate yell the poor dog dashed out of his hiding place. Ghond followed. But too late. For hardly had he crept half way under the thorns when an ear-splitting explosion seemed to cut the ground from under him, and a violent pain pierced his shoulder. He felt borne up by some demoniac power and flung to the ground with great force. Scarlet diamonds of light danced before his eyes for a few moments, followed by quenching darkness.

An hour later when he regained consciousness the first thing that he became aware of was a sound of Hindustani voices. In order to hear his native language more distinctly, he tried to raise his head. That instant he felt a shooting pain like the sting of a thousand cobras. There was no doubt in his mind now that he had been hit and probably mortally wounded. All the same his soul rejoiced every time he heard Hindustani spoken near him, for that meant that Indian troops, and not the enemy, were in possession of the forest now. "Ah," he said to himself, "my task is accomplished. I can die in peace."

Chapter Seven Gay-Neck Tells How He Carried the Message

"All that night preceding the eventful day I slept very little. Though I lay under his coat, Ghond had no knowledge that I was awake. You cannot sleep next to the heart of a man who runs like a stag, climbs trees like a squirrel or picks up strange dogs for company every half-hour.… Ghond's heart thumped so hard now and then that you might have heard it yards away. He did another thing that was not conducive to sleep at such close quarters; he breathed irregularly all that night. Sometimes he inhaled long breaths. Sometimes he breathed as fast as a mouse fleeing from a cat. I might as well have tried to sleep on a storm in the sky as under the coat of such a man.

"Then that dog! Shall I ever forget him? I was frightened when Ghond first annexed him, but he got no scent from my body, and the air that rose from below told me that somehow, like a clean-smelling ghost, he had come to befriend us. His footsteps I shall remember all my life. He walked as softly as a cat. He must have been a savage dog, for dogs that live in civilization are noisy. They cannot even walk quietly. Man's company is corrupting: every animal, excepting cats, becomes careless and noisy in human society. But that dog was quite wild. He walked without noise. He breathed without any sound. Then how did I know that he was there? It was that odour that came up from the ground and greeted my nostrils.

"After a sleepless and most uncomfortable night Ghond let me go, and I could hardly recognize the place where he had released me. So I flew from tree to tree to find my bearings, which only drove fright into my very soul. For now that day had broken, the trees were filling up with eyes. Strange blue eyes were looking through tubes in different directions. There were men behind them, and one was looking from a tree-top about a foot from where I perched. He had not heard my coming, on account of all those metal dogs barking around us—puff papapa pack!

"But as I flew up, he saw me. I felt that if I did not make haste and hide under other trees he would shoot me; and he did fire many times, but I was behind a copse as thick as the matted hair of a hermit. I decided to hop from tree to tree, not flying until the prospect was free of danger. I spent no little time in going about half a mile that way. At last my feet felt very fatigued, and I decided to fly, danger or no danger.

"Fortunately, no one had seen me fly up. I rose high after making large circles in the air. From a place whence the forest of trees appeared as small as saplings, I looked in different directions. Far off in the east, like chariots of gold, flew a flock of aeroplanes against the dawning sky. That meant the enemy's coming upon me if I waited much longer. So I started westwards. That seemed to be the signal for a thousand sharpshooters on tree-tops to fire at me.

"I think that when I circled up and above their trees, the Germans were uncertain whether I was their carrier or not, but the moment the sharpshooters perceived that I was going west they were sure that I was not their messenger, and so they shot at me to bring me down and find out what I carried on my foot.

"I could not go up for ever in the clear winter air without being frozen and anyway, I did not want those enemy planes to gain on me. Again I dashed westwards, and again the wall of bullets spread before me like barbs of death. But I had no choice left; either pierce my way through, or be killed by the oncoming aeroplanes, who were so near that I could see their passengers. So I dashed towards the west. Fortunately, by now my tail, which was hurt about a month ago, had grown almost to its normal size. Without that rudder my task would have been twice as hard. As I kept on going towards our line, the fusillade increased. There was no doubt now that all the sharpshooters and men in the trenches far off were taking a shot at me. But I zigzagged, circled, tumbled and in fact did all the stunts and tricks I knew to cheat the ever-augmenting swarm of bullets, but all that zigzagging business lost me time. One of the aeroplanes had come within striking distance of even so small a mark as I made, and began to pour loads of fire from above and behind. There was nothing to do but go forward, so I dashed on. Oh! How hard I flew— fast as the fastest storm. Then—ftatattafut—I was hit! My leg was broken right near the groin, and it, with its message, dangled under me like a sparrow in a single talon of a hawk. Oh! The pain, but I had no time to think of that, for that aeroplane was still after me, and I flew harder than before.

"At last our own line came into view. I fled lower. The machine dived down too. I tried to tumble, but failed. My leg prevented me from trying any of my tricks. Then pa-pa-pat-pattut—my tail was hit, and a shower of feathers fell below, obscuring for a moment the view of the men in the German trenches. So I shot down in a slanting flight towards our line and—passed it, making a circle. Then I beheld a strange sight—the aeroplane had been hit by our men. It swayed, lurched, and fell. But it had done its worst ere it went down in flames—it had hit my right wing and broken it. It gave me satisfaction to see it catch fire in the air and fall, yet my own pain had increased so that I felt as if twenty buzzards were tearing me to pieces, but, thanks to the Gods of my race, I lost consciousness of either pain or pleasure, and felt as if a mountainous weight were pulling me down.…

"They kept me at the pigeon hospital for a month. Though my wing was repaired and my leg sewn up where it belonged, they could not make me fly again. Every time I hopped up in the air my ears, I know not how, were filled with terrible noises of guns, and my eyes saw nothing but flaming bullets. I was so frightened that I would dash immediately to the ground. You may say that I was hearing imaginary guns and seeing imaginary walls of bullets: maybe, but their effect on me was the same as that of real ones. My wings were paralysed, my entrails frozen with terror.

"Besides, I would not fly without Ghond. Why should I spring from the hands of a man whose complexion was not brown and whose eyes were blue? I had not known such people before. We pigeons don't take to any and every outsider. At last they brought me in a cage to the hospital where Ghond was, and left me beside him. When I saw him I hardly recognized him, for his eyes—Ghond's eyes—wore a look of real fear! Yes, he too had been frightened out of his wits for once. I know, as all birds and beasts do, what fear looks like, and I felt sorry for Ghond.

"But on seeing me, that film of terror left his eyes, and they burned with a light of joy. He sat up in bed, took me in his hands and kissed my foot that had held the message that he had sent. Then he patted my right wing, and said: 'Even in great distress, O thou constellation of divine feathers, thou hast borne thy owner with his message among friends and won glory for all pigeons and the whole Indian Army. Again he kissed my foot. His humility touched me and by example humbled me. I felt no more pride when I remembered how I fell in the trenches of an Indian brigade after that aeroplane had partly smashed my wing, for had I fallen in a German trench, then…they would have seized the message on my leg; they would have surrounded the forest where Ghond lay hid with that wild dog—I shuddered to think of what they would have done! Alas! The dog, our true friend and saviour, where was he now?"

Chapter Nine The Wisdom of the Lama

After about the tenth day of strict and most sincere meditation in the manner he had prescribed, the lama sent for Gay-Neck and myself. So with the pigeon between my hands, I climbed up to his cell. The lama's face, generally yellow, today looked brown and very powerful. A strange poise and power shone in his almond-shaped eyes. He took Gay-Neck in his hands, and said:

May the north wind bring healing unto you,
May the south wind bring healing unto you,
May the winds of east and west pour healing into you.
Fear flees from you,
Hate flees from you,
And suspicion flees from you.
Courage like a rushing tide gallops through you;
Peace possesses your entire being,
And serenity and strength have become your two wings.
In your eyes shines courage;
Power and prowess dwell in your heart!
You are healed,
You are healed,
You are healed!
Peace, peace, peace.

We sat there meditating on those thoughts till the sun set, smiting the Himalayan peaks into multi-coloured flames. The valleys, the hollows and the woods about us put on a mantle of purple glory.

Slowly Gay-Neck hopped down from the lama's hands, walked out to the entrance of the cell and looked at the sunset. He opened his left wing, and waited. Then softly and ever so slowly he opened his right wing, feather by feather, muscle by muscle, until at last it spread out like a sail. Instead of doing anything theatrical such as instantly flying off, he carefully shut his two wings as if they were two precious but fragile fans. He too knew how to salute the sunset. With the dignity of a priest he walked downstairs, but hardly had he gone out of sight when I heard—I fancied I heard—the flapping of his wings. I was about to get up hastily and see what had really happened, but the holy man put his hand on my shoulder and restrained me while an inscrutable smile played on his lips.

The next morning I told Ghond what had happened. He replied tartly: "Gay-Neck opened his wings to salute the setting sun, you say. There is nothing surprising in that. Animals are religious, though man in his ignorance thinks they are not. I have seen monkeys, eagles, pigeons, leopards and even the mongoose adore the dawn and sunset."

"Can you show them to me?"

Ghond answered, "Yes. But not now; let us go and give Gay- Neck his breakfast."

When we reached his cage we found its door open—and no pigeon within. I was not surprised, for I had left the cage unlocked every night that we had been at the lamasery. But where had he gone? We could not find him in the main building, so we went to the library. There in a deserted outer cell we found some of his feathers, and nearby Ghond detected a weasel's footprints. That made us suspect trouble. But if the weasel had attacked and killed him, there would be blood on the floor. Then, whither had he fled? What had he done? Where was he now? We wandered for an hour. Just as we had decided to give up the search, we heard him cooing, and there he was on the roof of the library, talking to his old friends the Swifts, who were clinging to their nest under the eaves. We could make out their answer to his cooing. Mr. Swift said, "Cheep, cheep, cheep!" I cried to Gay-Neck in joy, and gave him his call to breakfast: "Aya— á—ay." He curved his neck, and listened. Then, as I called again, he saw me, and instantly flapped his wings loudly, then flew down and sat on my wrist, as cool as a cucumber. During the earliest dawn he must have heard the priests' footsteps going up to their morning meditation, and got out of his cage, then gone astray to the outer cell where no doubt a young and inexpert weasel had attacked him. A veteran like Gay-Neck could easily outwit the weasel by presenting him with a few feathers only. While the young hopeful was looking for the pigeon inside a lot of torn feathers, his would-be victim flew up into the sky. There he found his old friend Swift, flying to salute the rising sun. And after they had performed their morning worship together, they had come down for a friendly chat on the roof of the monastery library.

That day very terrible news reached the lamasery. A wild buffalo had attacked the village that the lama had spoken of the day before. He had come there during the previous evening and killed two people who were going home from a meeting of the village elders that was held around the communal threshing floor. The villagers had sent up a deputation to the abbot to say a prayer for the destruction of the beast and begging him to exorcise the soul out of the brute. The holy man said that he would use means that would kill the murderous buffalo in twenty-four hours. "Go home in peace, O beloved ones of Infinite Compassion. Your prayers will be answered. Do not venture out of doors after nightfall. Stay home and meditate on peace and courage." Ghond, who was present, asked, "How long has this fellow been pestering your village?" The entire deputation affirmed that he had been coming every night for a week. He had eaten up almost half of their spring crop. Again begging for strong and effective incantation and exorcism to kill the buffalo, they went down to their village.

After the deputation had left, the lama said to Ghond, who was standing by, "O chosen one of victory, now that you are healed, go forth to slay the murderer."

"But, my Lord!"

"Fear no more, Ghond. Your meditations have healed you. Now test in the woods what you have acquired here by this means. In solitude men gain power and poise that they must test in the multitude. Ere the sun sets twice from now, you shall return victorious. As an earnest of my perfect faith in your success, I request you to take this boy and his pigeon with you. Surely I would not ask you to take a boy of sixteen with you if I doubted your powers or the outcome of your mission. Go, bring the murderer to justice."

That afternoon we set out for the jungle. I was overjoyed at the prospect of spending at least one night in there again. What a pleasure it was to go with Ghond and the pigeon, both whole and well once more, in quest of a wild buffalo! Is there any boy on earth who would not welcome such an opportunity?

So, thoroughly equipped with rope ladders, a lasso and knives, with Gay-Neck on my shoulder, we set out. The British Government forbids the use of firearms to the common people of India, and so we carried no rifles.

About three in the afternoon we reached the village north- west of the lamasery. There we took up the trail of the buffalo. We followed it through dense woods and wide clearings. Here and there we crossed a brook or had to climb over mammoth fallen trees. It was extraordinary how clear the buffalo's hoof-prints were, and how deep!

Ghond remarked: "He must have been frightened to death, for see how heavily he had trodden here. Animals in their normal unafraid state leave very little trace behind, but when frightened, they act as if the terror of being killed weighed their bodies down. This fellow's hoofs have made prodigious and clear marks wherever he went. How frightened he must have been!"

At last we reached an impassable river. Its current, according to Ghond, was sharp enough to break our legs had we stepped into it. Strangely enough, the buffalo too had not dared to cross it. So we followed his precedent, looking for more hoof-prints on the bank. In twenty more minutes we found that they swerved off the stream bank and disappeared into a thick jungle that looked as black as a pit, although it was hardly five in the afternoon. This place could not have been more than half an hour's run from the village, for a wild buffalo of any age.

Ghond asked, "Do you hear the song of the water?" After listening for several minutes I heard the sound of water kissing the sedges, and other grass not far off, with gurgling groaning sounds. We were about twenty feet from a lake into which the river ran. "The murderous buffalo is hiding—probably asleep somewhere between here and the lagoon," cried Ghond. "Let us make our home on one of the twin trees yonder. It is getting dark, and I am sure he will be here soon. We should not be found on the floor of the jungle when he turns up. There is hardly a space of four feet between the trees!"

His last words struck me as curious. So I examined the space between the trees. They were tall and massive, and between them lay a piece of earth just broad enough to afford room for both of us walking abreast of each other.

"Now I shall lay down my fear-soaked tunic half-way between these Twins." Then Ghond proceeded to take from under his tunic a bundle of old clothes that he had been wearing until today. He placed them on the ground, then climbed one of the trees. After Ghond had gone up, he swung down a rope ladder for me. I climbed up on it with Gay-Neck fluttering and beating his wings on my shoulders in order to keep his balance. Both of us safely reached the branch on which Ghond was sitting, and since the evening was coming on apace, we sat still for a while.

The first thing I noticed as the dusk fell was bird-life. Herons, hornbills, grouse, pheasant, song-sparrows and emerald flocks of parrots seemed to infest the forest. The drone of the bee, the cut-cut- cut of the woodpecker and the shrill cry of the eagle far overhead blended with the tearing, crying noises of the mountain torrent and the staccato laughter of the already waking hyenas.

The tree on which we made our home for the night was very tall. We went farther up in order to make sure that no leopard or serpent was above us. After a close inspection we chose a couple of branches between which we hung our rope ladder in the shape of a strong hammock. Just as we had made ourselves secure on our perch, Ghond pointed to the sky. I looked up at once. There floated on wings of ruby a very large eagle. Though darkness was rising like a flood from the floor of the jungle, in the spaces above the sky burned "like a pigeon's throat," and through it circled again and again that solitary eagle who was no doubt, according to Ghond, performing his worship of the setting sun. His presence had already had a stilling effect on the birds and insects of the forest. Though he was far above them, yet like a congregation of mute worshippers, they kept silent while he, their King, flew backwards and forwards, and vaulted before their God, the Father of Lights, with the ecstasy of a hierophant. Slowly the ruby fire ebbed from his wings. Now they became purple sails fringed with sparks of gold. As if his adoration was at last concluded, he rose higher and, as an act of self- immolation before his deity, flew towards the flaming peaks burning with fire, and vanished in their splendour like a moth.

Below, a buffalo's bellowing unlocked the insect voices one by one, tearing into shreds and tatters the stillness of the evening. An owl hooted near by, making Gay-Neck snuggle closely to my heart under my tunic. Suddenly the Himalayan Doël, a night-bird, very much like a nightingale, flung abroad its magic song. Like a silver flute blown by a God, trill upon trill, cadenza upon cadenza, spilled its torrential peace that rushed like rain down the boughs of the trees, dripping over their rude barks to the floor of the jungle, then through their very roots into the heart of the earth.

The enchantment of an early summer night in the Himalayas will remain forever indescribable. In fact it was so sweet and lonely that I felt very sleepy. Ghond put an extra rope around me that held me secure to the trunk of the tree. Then I put my head on his shoulder in order to sleep comfortably. But before I did so, he told me of his plan:

"Those cast-off garments of mine are what I wore while my heart was possessed of fear. They have a strange odour. If that brother-in-law (idiot) of a buffalo gets their scent, he will come hither. He who is frightened responds to the odour of fear. If he comes to investigate my cast-off dress, we shall do what we can to him. I hope we can lassoo and take him home as tame as a heifer…" I did not hear the rest of his words, for I had fallen asleep.

I do not know how long I slept, but suddenly I was roused by a terrific bellowing. When I opened my eyes, Ghond, who was already awake, undid the rope around me and pointed below. In the faint light of the dawn at first I saw nothing, but I heard distinctly the groaning and grunting of an angry beast. In the tropics the day breaks rapidly. I looked down most intently. Now in the growing light of day I saw…There could be no two opinions about what I saw. Yes, there was a hillock of shining jet rubbing its dark side against the tree on which we sat. It was about ten feet long, I surmised, though half of its bulk was covered by the leaves and boughs of the trees. The beast looked like a black opal coming out of a green furnace, such was the glitter of the newly grown foliage under the morning sun. I thought, "The buffalo that in nature looks healthy and silken, in a zoo is a mangy creature with matted mane and dirty skin. Can those who see buffalo in captivity ever conceive how beautiful they can be? What a pity that most young people instead of seeing one animal in nature—which is worth a hundred in any zoo-must derive their knowledge of God's creatures from their appearance in prisons! If we cannot perceive any right proportion of man's moral nature by looking at prisoners in a jail, how do we manage to think that we know all about an animal by gazing at him penned in a cage?"

However, to return to that murderous buffalo at the foot of our tree. Gay-Neck was freed from under my tunic and left to roam on the tree, which Ghond and I descended by a number of branches, like the rungs of a ladder, till we reached a branch that was about two feet above the buffalo. He did not see us. Ghond swiftly tied around the tree-trunk one end of the long lassoo. I noticed that the buffalo was playing underneath by putting his horns now and then through a tattered garment, what was left of Ghond's clothes. No doubt the odour of man in them had attracted him. Though his horns were clean, there were marks of fresh blood on his head. Apparently he had gone to the village and killed another person during the night. That roused Ghond. He whispered into my ear: "We shall get him alive. You slip this lassoo over his horns from above." In a trice Ghond had leaped off the branch near the rear of the buffalo. That startled the beast. But he could not turn round, for close to his right was a tree that I mentioned before, and to his left was the tree on which I stood. He had to go back or forward between the twins in order to get out from them, but before this happened I had flung the lassoo over his head. The touch of the rope acted like electricity upon him. He hastened backwards, in order to slip off the lassoo, so fast that Ghond, had he not already gone around the next tree, would have been trampled and cut to death by the sharp hoofs of the beast. But now, to my utter consternation, I noticed that instead of gripping his two horns at the very root, I had succeeded in lassoing only one of them. That instant I shrieked to Ghond in terror: "Beware! Only one of his horns is caught. The rope may slip off that one any time. Run! Run up a tree."

But that intrepid hunter ignored my advice. Instead he stood facing the enemy a short distance away from him. Then I saw the brute lower his head and plunge forward. I shut my eyes in terror. When I opened them again, I saw that the bull was tugging at the rope that held him by the horn and kept him from butting into the tree behind which Ghond stood. His monstrous bellowing filled the jungle with a fearful racket. Echoes of it coursed one after another like frightened shrieking children.

Since the bull had not yet succeeded in reaching him, Ghond drew his razor-sharp dagger, about a foot and a half long and two inches broad. He slowly slipped behind another tree to the right, then vanished out of sight. The bull just ran straight at the spot where he had seen Ghond last. Fortunately, the rope was still clinging tightly to his horn.

Here Ghond changed his tactics. He ran away in the opposite direction, zigzagging in between different trees. This he did to go where his odour could not reach the bull, blown down to him by the wind. But though he was bewildered, yet the bull turned and followed. He again saw the bundle of Ghond's clothes on the ground under our tree. That maddened him. He sniffed, and then worried it with his horns.

By now Ghond was down wind. Though I could not see him, I surmised that he could tell by the odour where the bull was in case the trees hid him from view. The beast bellowed again, as he put his horns through Ghond's clothes, which raised a terrific tumult in the trees all around. From nowhere came flocks of monkeys running from branch to branch. Squirrels ran like rats from trees to the jungle-floor, then back again. Swarms of birds, such as jays, herons and parrots, were flying about and shrieking in unison with crows, owls and kites. Suddenly the bull charged again. I saw that Ghond was standing there calmly facing him. If ever I saw a man as calm as calmness itself, it was Ghond. The bull's hind legs throbbed and swept on like swords. Then something happened. He reared in the air; no doubt it was the pull of the lassoo rope, of which one end was tied to our tree. He rose several feet above the ground, then fell. That instant, like a dry twig snapped by a child, his horn cracked and flew up in the air. The breaking created an irresistible momentum that flung him sideways on the ground. He almost rolled over, his legs kicking the air violently. Instantly Ghond leaped forward like a spark from the flint. Seeing him, the buffalo balanced himself and sat on his haunches, snorting. He almost succeeded in rising to his feet, but Ghond struck near his shoulder with the dagger. Its deadly edge dug deep, and Ghond pressed on it with his entire weight. A bellow like a volcanic eruption shook the jungle, and with it a fountain of liquid ruby spurted up. Unable to bear the sight any longer, I again shut my eyes.

In a few minutes, when I came down from my perch, I found that the buffalo had died of a haemorrhage. It lay in a deep pool of blood. And near by sat Ghond on the ground, wiping himself from the stain of his encounter. I knew that he wished to be left alone. So I went to the old tree and called to Gay-Neck. He made no response. I went all the way up to the topmost branch of the tree. But in vain— he was not there.

When I came down, Ghond had cleansed himself. He pointed at the sky. We beheld nature's scavengers. Kites below, and far above them vultures flew. They had already learned that someone had died and they must clean up the jungle.

Ghond said: "We shall find the pigeon in the monastery. He flew with the rest of the birds, doubtless. Let us depart hence soon." But before starting homeward, I went to measure the dead buffalo, to whom flies had been swarming from every direction. He was ten feet and a half in length, and his forelegs measured over three feet.

Our trudge back towards the monastery was made in silence that was broken only when, about noonday, we had reached the stricken village and informed its headman that their enemy was dead. He was relieved to hear of it, though he was very sad because during the previous evening the buffalo had killed his aged mother, who was going to the village temple to her worship before sunset.

We were very hungry and walked fast, and soon we reached the monastery. At once I made inquiries about my pigeon. Gay- Neck was not there! It was terrible. But the old holy man said, as we chatted in his cell, "He is safe as are you, Ghond." After a pause of several minutes he asked, "What is troubling your peace of mind?"

The old hunter thought out quietly what he was going to say. "Nothing, my Lord, save this: I hate to kill anything. I wanted to catch that bull alive, and alas! I had to destroy him. When the horn of his broke, and there was nothing between him and me, I had to put my knife through a vital vein. I am so sorry I could not get him alive in order to sell him to a zoo."

"O you soul of commercialism!" I exclaimed. "I am not sorry that the bull died. Better death than to be caged for the rest of his life in a zoo. Real death is preferable to living death."

"If you had only slipped the lassoo over both horns!" Ghond retorted.

The holy one ejaculated, "Both of you should be concerned about Gay-Neck, not about what is already dead."

Ghond said, "True. Let us search for him on the morrow."

But the holy one replied: "No. Return to Dentam, my son. Your family is anxious about you. I hear their thoughts."

The next day we left for Dentam on a pair of ponies. By forced march and changing ponies twice a day at different posts, we reached Dentam in three day's time. As we were going up towards our house, we encountered a very excited servant of my family. He said that Gay-Neck had returned three days before. But since we had not come back with him, my parents had begun to worry, and they had sent out parties searching after us, alive or dead.

He and I almost ran up to the house. In another ten minutes my mother's arms were around me, and Gay-Neck, with his feet on my head, was fluttering his wings in order to balance himself.

I cannot begin to describe how overjoyed I was to hear that Gay-Neck had flown at last. He had winged all the way from the lamasery to our home in Dentam. He had not faltered or failed! "O thou soul of flight, thou pearl among pigeons," I exclaimed to myself as Ghond and I accelerated our steps.

Thus ended our pilgrimage to Singalila. It healed both Gay- Neck and Ghond of the disease of fear and hate that they had caught on the battle-fields. No labor would be in vain if it could heal a single soul of these worst ills of life.

Instead of spinning out a sermon at the end of this story, let me say this:

"Whatever we think and feel will colour what we say or do. He who fears, even unconsciously, or has his least little dream tainted with hate, will inevitably, sooner or later, translate these two qualities into his action. Therefore, my brothers, live courage, breathe courage and give courage. Think and feel love so that you will be able to pour out of yourselves peace and serenity as naturally as a flower gives forth fragrance.

"Peace be unto all!"

狮子、狐狸和雄鹿

有一只狮子生病了，躺在洞穴中，没有办法自己出去觅食。于是对过来探望的朋友狐狸说：“我亲爱的朋友啊，希望你能够去那远处的森林里，把生活在那里的大雄鹿骗到我的洞穴来，我真的希望餐桌上能有鹿心和鹿脑吃。”狐狸去了森林，找到雄鹿，对他说：“亲爱的先生，你可真幸运。你认识我们的国王狮子吧，唉，他正奄奄一息，想要将你任命为他的继任者，由你来掌管百兽。希望你不要忘了我是第一个来告诉你这好消息的。我现在可得回去见狮子国王了，如果你愿意听我一言，最好能和我一起过去，在他临死前和他待在一起。”雄鹿听了十分欢喜，便跟着狐狸去了狮子的洞穴，一点也没起疑心。雄鹿一进入狮子的洞穴，狮子便扑向他，但是狮子因病对自己的弹跳能力估计不足，雄鹿只是耳朵受伤，逃过了一劫，便转身飞跑回森林中。狐狸感到很羞耻，狮子也失望至极，因为尽管生着病，他也已经饿坏了。所以他求狐狸再去试一次。“这次是几乎不可能了，不过我会去试试。”狐狸说完便又去了树林里，发现雄鹿正在休息，想要从惊恐中复原。一看到狐狸，他就大叫：“你这个坏蛋，你把我骗去送死到底是为了什么啊！快走，要不我就拿角顶死你。”但是狐狸特别无耻，说道：“你可真是个胆小鬼！你肯定不知道狮子其实没有任何恶意吧？哎呀，他只是想凑到你耳朵边跟你说些神圣的秘密，你却跟个吓坏的兔子一样跑走了。你可真把他给惹火了，现在我真不肯定，他可能会选狼王来做继任者，除非你立刻回去，证明你的胆量。我跟你保证，他不会伤害你，我会是你忠实的仆人。”雄鹿不太聪明，被狐狸给说服了，跟着他回到了狮子的洞穴。这次狮子没有犯错，一下子扑到了雄鹿身上，大吃特吃了一通。狐狸趁着狮子不注意，将鹿脑偷走当作给自己的犒赏。等狮子开始找鹿脑来吃的时候，当然没有找到。狐狸在一边看着，说：“我觉得你还是别找什么鹿脑了，这家伙两回都被我骗到了狮子的洞穴，根本不会有脑子。”

THE ASS AND HIS BURDENS

A Pedlar who owned an Ass one day bought a quantity of salt, and loaded up his beast with as much as he could bear. On the way home the Ass stumbled as he was crossing a stream and fell into the water. The salt got thoroughly wetted and much of it melted and drained away, so that, when he got on his legs again, the Ass found his load had become much less heavy. His master, however, drove him back to town and bought more salt, which he added to what remained in the panniers, and started out again. No sooner had they reached a stream than the Ass lay down in it, and rose, as before, with a much lighter load. But his master detected the trick, and turning back once more, bought a large number of sponges, and piled them on the back of the Ass. When they came to the stream the Ass again lay down: but this time, as the sponges soaked up large quantities of water, he found, when he got up on his legs, that he had a bigger burden to carry than ever.

You may play a good card once too often.

THE FOX AND THE GOAT

A Fox fell into a well and was unable to get out again. By and by a thirsty Goat came by, and seeing the Fox in the well asked him if the water was good. “Good?” said the Fox, “it's the best water I ever tasted in all my life. Come down and try it yourself.” The Goat thought of nothing but the prospect of quenching his thirst, and jumped in at once. When he had had enough to drink, he looked about, like the Fox, for some way of getting out, but could find none. Presently the Fox said, “I have an idea. You stand on your hind legs, and plant your forelegs firmly against the side of the well, and then I'll climb on to your back, and, from there, by stepping on your horns, I can get out. And when I'm out, I'll help you out too.” The Goat did as he was requested, and the Fox climbed on to his back and so out of the well; and then he coolly walked away. The Goat called loudly after him and reminded him of his promise to help him out: but the Fox merely turned and said, “If you had as much sense in your head as you have hair in your beard you wouldn't have got into the well without making certain that you could get out again.”

Look before your leap.

THE EAGLE, THE JACKDAW, AND THE SHEPHERD

One day a Jackdaw saw an Eagle swoop down on a lamb and carry it off in its talons. “My word,” said the Jackdaw, “I'll do that myself.” So it flew high up into the air, and then came shooting down with a great whirring of wings on to the back of a big ram. It had no sooner alighted than its claws got caught fast in the wool, and nothing it could do was of any use: there it stuck, flapping away, and only making things worse instead of better. By and by up came the Shepherd. “Oho,” he said, “so that's what you'd be doing, is it?” And he took the Jackdaw, and clipped its wings and carried it home to his children. It looked so odd that they didn't know what to make of it. “What sort of bird is it, father?” they asked. “It's a Jackdaw,” he replied, “and nothing but a Jackdaw: but it wants to be taken for an Eagle.”

If you attempt what is beyond your power, your trouble will be wasted and you court not only misfortune but ridicule.

THE EAGLE AND THE BEETLE

An Eagle was chasing a hare, which was running for dear life and was at her wits' end to know where to turn for help. Presently she espied a Beetle, and begged it to aid her. So when the Eagle came up the Beetle warned her not to touch the hare, which was under its protection. But the Eagle never noticed the Beetle because it was so small, seized the hare and ate her up. The Beetle never forgot this, and used to keep an eye on the Eagle's nest, and whenever the Eagle laid an egg it climbed up and rolled it out of the nest and broke it. At last the Eagle got so worried over the loss of her eggs that she went up to Jupiter, who is the special protector of Eagles, and begged him to give her a safe place to nest in: so he let her lay her eggs in his lap. But the Beetle noticed this and made a ball of dirt the size of an Eagle's egg, and flew up and deposited it in Jupiter's lap. When Jupiter saw the dirt, he stood up to shake it out of his robe, and, forgetting about the eggs, he shook them out too, and they were broken just as before. Ever since then, they say, Eagles never lay their eggs at the season when Beetles are about.

The weak will sometimes find ways to avenge an insult, even upon the strong.

THE EAGLE AND THE FOX

An Eagle and a Fox became great friends and determined to live near one another: they thought that the more they saw of each other the better friends they would be. So the Eagle built a nest at the top of a high tree, while the Fox settled in a thicket at the foot of it and produced a litter of cubs. One day the Fox went out foraging for food, and the Eagle, who also wanted food for her young, flew down into the thicket, caught up the Fox's cubs, and carried them up into the tree for a meal for herself and her family. When the Fox came back, and found out what had happened, she was not so much sorry for the loss of her cubs as furious because she couldn't get at the Eagle and pay her out for her treachery. So she sat down not far off and cursed her. But it wasn't long before she had her revenge. Some villagers happened to be sacrificing a goat on a neighbouring altar, and the Eagle flew down and carried off a piece of burning flesh to her nest. There was a strong wind blowing, and the nest caught fire, with the result that her fledglings fell half-roasted to the ground. Then the Fox ran to the spot and devoured them in full sight of the Eagle.

False faith may escape human punishment, but cannot escape the divine.

CHAPTER III　HOW THEY FOUND UNDINE AGAIN

The longer Huldbrand sought Undine beneath the shades of night, and failed to find her, the more anxious and confused did he become. The idea that Undine had been only a mere apparition of the forest, again gained ascendancy over him；indeed, amid the howling of the waves and the tempest, the cracking of the trees, and the complete transformation of a scene lately so calmly beautiful, he could almost have considered the whole peninsula with its cottage and its inhabitants as a mocking illusive vision；but from afar he still ever heard through the tumult the fsherman's anxious call for Undine, and the loud praying and singing of his aged wife.At length he came close to the brink of the swollen stream, and saw in the moonlight how it had taken its wild course directly in front of the haunted forest, so as to change the peninsula into an island.

“Oh God！”he thought to himself，“if Undine has ventured a step into that fearful forest, perhaps in her charming wilfulness, just because I was not allowed to tell her about it；and now the stream may be rolling between us, and she may be weeping on the other side alone, among phantoms and spectres！”A cry of horror escaped him, and he clambered down some rocks and overthrownpine-stems, in order to reach the rushing stream and by wading or swimming to seek the fugitive on the other side. He remembered all the awful and wonderful things which he had encountered, even by day, under the now rustling and roaring branches of the forest.Above all it seemed to him as if a tall man in white, whom he knew but too well, was grinning and nodding on the opposite shore；but it was just these monstrous forms which forcibly impelled him to cross the flood, as the thought seized him that Undine might be among them in the agonies of death and alone.

He had already grasped the strong branch of a pine, and was standing supported by it, in the whirling current, against which he could with difficulty maintain himself；though with a courageous spirit he advanced deeper into it. Just then a gentle voice exclaimed near him：“Venture not, venture not, the old man, the stream, is full of tricks！”

He knew the sweet tones；he stood as if entranced beneath the shadows that duskily shrouded the moon, and his head swam with the swelling of the waves, which he now saw rapidly rising to his waist. Still he would not desist.“If thou art not really there, if thou art only foating about me like a mist, then may I too cease to live and become a shadow like thee, dear, dear Undine！”

Thus exclaiming aloud, he again stepped deeper into the stream.

“Look round thee, oh！look round thee, beautiful but infatuated youth！”cried a voice again close beside him, and looking aside, he saw by the momentarily unveiled moon, a little island formed by the food, on which he perceived under the interweaved branches of the overhanging trees, Undine smiling and happy, nestling in the fowery grass.

Oh！how much more gladly than before did the young man now use the aid of his pine-branch！With a few steps he had crossed the flood which was rushing between him and the maiden, and he was standing beside her on a little spot of turf, safely guarded and screened by the good old trees. Undine had half-raised herself, and now under the green leafy tent she threw her arms round his neck, and drew him down beside her on her soft seat.

“You shall tell me your story here, beautiful friend，”said she, in a low whisper；“the cross old people cannot hear us here：and our roof of leaves is just as good a shelter as their poor cottage.”

“It is heaven itself！”said Huldbrand, embracing the beautiful girl and kissing her fervently.

The old fisherman meanwhile had come to the edge of the stream, and shouted across to the two young people；“Why, sir knight, I have received you as one honest-hearted man is wont to receive another, and now here you are caressing my foster-child in secret, and letting me run hither and thither through the night in anxious search of her.”

“I have only just found her myself, old father，”returned the knight.

“So much the better，”said the fisherman；“but now bring her across to me without delay upon frm ground.”

Undine, however, would not hear of this；she declared she would rather go with the beautiful stranger, into the wild forest itself, than return to the cottage, where no one did as she wished, and from which the beautiful knight would himself depart sooneror later. Then, throwing her arms round Huldbrand, she sang with indescribable grace：—

A stream ran out of the misty vale

Its fortunes to obtain，

the ocean’s depths it found a home

And ne’er returned again.

The old fisherman wept bitterly at her song, but this did not seem to affect her particularly. She kissed and caressed her new friend, who at last said to her：“Undine, if the old man's distress does not touch your heart, it touches mine—let us go back to him.”

She opened her large blue eyes in amazement at him, and spoke at last, slowly and hesitatingly：“If you think so—well, whatever you think is right to me. But the old man yonder must frst promise me that he will let you, without objection, relate to me what you saw in the wood, and—well, other things will settle themselves.”

“Come, only come，”cried the fsherman to her, unable to utter another word：and at the same time he stretched out his arms far over the rushing stream toward her, and nodded his head as if to promise the fulflment of her request, and as he did this, his white hair fell strangely over his face, and reminded Huldbrand of the nodding white man in the forest. Without allowing himself, however, to grow confused by such an idea the young knight took the beautiful girl in his arms, and bore her over the narrow passage which the stream had forced between her little island and the shore.The old man fell upon Undine's neck and could not satisfy the exuberance of his joy；his good wife also came up and caressed the newly-found in the heartiest manner.Not a word of reproach passed their lips；nor was it thought of, for Undine, forgetting all her waywardness, almost overwhelmed her foster-parents with affection and fond expressions.

When at last they had recovered from the excess of their joy, day had already dawned, and had shed its purple hue over the lake；stillness had followed the storm, and the little birds were singing merrily on the wet branches. As Undine now insisted upon hearing the knight's promised story, the aged couple smilingly and readily acceded to her desire.Breakfast was brought out under the trees which screened the cottage from the lake, and they sat down to it with contented hearts—Undine on the grass at the knight's feet, the place chosen by herself.

Huldbrand then proceeded with his story.

CHAPTER IV OF THAT WHICH THE KNIGHT ENCOUNTERED IN THE WOOD

“It is now about eight days ago since I rode into the free imperial city, which lies on the other side of the forest. Soon after my arrival, there was a splendid tournament and running at the ring, and I spared neither my horse nor my lance.Once when I was pausing at the lists, to rest after my merry toil, and was handing back my helmet to one of my squires, my attention was attracted by a female fgure of great beauty, who was standing richly attired on one of the galleries allotted to spectators.I asked my neighbor, and learned from him, that the name of the fair lady was Bertalda, and that she was the foster-daughter of one of the powerful dukes living in the country.I remarked that she also was looking at me, and, as it is wont to be with us young knights, I had already ridden bravely, and now pursued my course with renovated confdence and courage.In the dance that evening I was Bertalda's partner, and I remained so throughout the festival.”

A sharp pain in his left hand, which hung down by his side, here interrupted Huldbrand's narrative, and drew his attention to the aching part. Undine had fastened her pearly teeth upon one of his fingers, appearing at the same time very gloomy and angry.Suddenly, however, she looked up in his eyes with an expression of tender melancholy, and whispered in a soft voice：“It is your own fault.”Then she hid her face, and the knight, strangely confused and thoughtful, continued his narrative.

“This Bertalda was a haughty, wayward girl. Even on the second day she pleased me no longer as she had done on the frst, and on the third day still less.Still I continued about her, because she was more pleasant to me than to any other knight, and thus it was that I begged her in jest to give me one of her gloves.‘I will give it you when you have quite alone explored the ill-famed forest，'said she，‘and can bring me tidings of its wonders.'It was not that her glove was of such importance to me, but the word had been said, and an honorable knight would not allow himself to be urged a second time to such a proof of valor.”

“I think she loved you，”said Undine, interrupting him.

“It seemed so，”replied Huldbrand.

“Well，”exclaimed the girl, laughing，“she must be stupid indeed. To drive away any one dear to her.And moreover, into an ill-omened wood.The forest and its mysteries might have waited long enough for me！”

“Yesterday morning.”continued the knight, smiling kindly at Undine，“I set out on my enterprise. The stems of the trees caught the red tints of the morning light which lay brightly on the green turf, the leaves seemed whispering merrily with each other, and in my heart I could have laughed at the people who could have expected anything to terrify them in this pleasant spot.‘I shall soon have trotted through the forest there and back again，'I said to myself, with a feeling of easy gayety, and before I had even thought of it I was deep within the green shades, and could no longer perceive the plain which lay behind me.Then for the frst time it struck me that I might easily lose my way in the mighty forest, and that this perhaps was the only danger which the wanderer had to fear.I therefore paused and looked round in the direction of the sun, which in the mean while had risen somewhat higher above the horizon.While I was thus looking up I saw something black in the branches of a lofty oak.I thought it was a bear and I grasped my sword；but with a human voice, that sounded harsh and ugly, it called to me from above：‘If I do not nibble away the branches up here, Sir Malapert, what shall we have to roast you with at midnight?'And so saying it grinned and made the branches rustle, so that my horse grew furious and rushed forward with me before I had time to see what sort of a devil it really was.”

“You must not call it so，”said the old fsherman as he crossed himself；his wife did the same silently. Undine looked at the knight with sparkling eyes and said：“The best of the story is that they certainly have not roasted him yet；go on now, you beautiful youth！”

The knight continued his narration：“My horse was so wild that he almost rushed with me against the stems and branches of trees；he was dripping with sweat, and yet would not suffer himself to be held in. At last he went straight in the direction of a rocky precipice；then it suddenly seemed to me as if a tall white man threw himself across the path of my wild steed；the horse trembled with fear and stopped：I recovered my hold of him, and for the first time perceived that my deliverer was no white man, but a brook of silvery brightness, rushing down from a hill by my side and crossing and impeding my horse's course.”

“Thanks, dear Brook，”exclaimed Undine, clapping her little hands. The old man, however, shook his head and looked down in deep thought.

“I had scarcely settled myself in the saddle，”continued Huldbrand，“and seized the reins firmly, when a wonderful little man stood at my side, diminutive, and ugly beyond conception. His complexion was of a yellowish brown, and his nose not much smaller than the rest of his entire person.At the same time he kept grinning with stupid courtesy, exhibiting his huge mouth, and making a thousand scrapes and bows to me.As this farce was now becoming inconvenient to me, I thanked him briefy and turned about my still trembling steed, thinking either to seek another adventure, or in case I met with none, to fnd my way back, for during my wild chase the sun had already passed the meridian；but the little fellow sprang round with the speed of lightning and stood again before my horse.‘Room！'I cried, angrily；‘the animal is wild and may easily run over you.'—‘Ay, ay！'snarled the imp, with a grin still more horribly stupid.‘Give me frst some drink-money, for I have stopped your horse；without me you and your horse would be now both lying in the stony ravine；ugh！'—‘Don't make any more faces，’said I，‘and take your money, even if you are telling lies；for see, it was the good brook there that saved me, and not you, you miserable wight！And at the same time I dropped a piece of gold into his grotesque cap, which he had taken off in his begging.I then trotted on；but he screamed after me, and suddenly with inconceivable quickness wasat my side.I urged my horse into a gallop；the imp ran too, making at the same time strange contortions with his body, half-ridiculous, half-horrible, and holding up the gold-piece, he cried, at every leap，‘False money！false coin！false coin！false money！’—and this he uttered with such a hollow sound that one would have supposed that after every scream he would have fallen dead to the ground.

“His horrid red tongue moreover hung far out of his mouth. I stopped, perplexed, and asked：‘What do you mean by this screaming?take another piece of gold, take two, but leave me.'He then began again his hideous burlesque of politeness, and snarled out：‘Not gold, not gold, my young gentleman.I have too much of that trash myself, as I will show you at once?'

“Suddenly it seemed to me as if I could see through the solid soil as though it were green glass and the smooth earth were as round as a ball；and within, a multitude of goblins were ranking sport with silver and gold；head over heels they were rolling about, pelting each other in jest with the precious metals, and provokingly blowing the gold-dust in each other's eyes. My hideous companion stood partly within and partly without；he ordered the others to reach him up heaps of gold, and showing it to me with a laugh, he then fung it back again with a ringing noise into the immeasurable abyss.

“He then showed the piece of gold I had given him to the goblins below, and they laughed themselves half-dead over it and hissed at me. At last they all pointed at me with their metal-stained fngers, and more and more wildly, and more and more densely, and more and more madly, the swarm of spirits came clambering up to me.I was seized with terror as my horse had been before：I put spursto him, and I know not how far I galloped for the second time wildly into the forest.

“At length, when I again halted, the coolness of evening was around me. Through the branches of the trees I saw a white foot-path gleaming, which I fancied must lead from the forest toward the city.I was anxious to work my way in that direction；but a face perfectly white and indistinct, with features ever changing, kept peering at me between the leaves；I tried to avoid it, but wherever I went it appeared also.Enraged at this, I determined at last to ride at it, when it gushed forth volumes of foam upon me and my horse, obliging us half-blinded to make a rapid retreat.Thus it drove us step by step ever away from the foot-path, leaving the way open to us only in one direction.When we advanced in this direction, it kept indeed close behind us, but did not do us the slightest harm.

“Looking around at it occasionally, I perceived that the white face that had besprinkled us with foam belonged to a form equally white and of gigantic stature. Many a time I thought that it was a moving stream, but I could never convince myself on the subject.Wearied out, the horse and his rider yielded to the impelling power of the white man, who kept nodding his head, as if he would say，‘Quite right, quite right！'And thus at last we came out here to the end of the forest, where I saw the turf, and the lake, and your little cottage, and where the tall white man disappeared.”

“It's well that he's gone，”said the old fsherman；and now he began to talk of the best way by which his guest could return to his friends in the city. Upon this Undine began to laugh slyly to herself；Huldbrand observed it, and said：“I thought you were glad to see mehere；why then do you now rejoice when my departure is talked of?”

“Because you cannot go away，”replied Undine.“Just try it once, to cross that overfowed forest stream with a boat, with your horse, or alone, as you may fancy. Or rather don't try it, for you would be dashed to pieces by the stones and trunks of trees which are carried down by it with the speed of lightning.And as to the lake, I know it well；father dare not venture out far enough with his boat.”

Huldbrand rose, smiling, in order to see whether things were as Undine had said；the old man accompanied him, and the girl danced merrily along by their side. They found every thing, indeed, as Undine had described, and the knight was obliged to submit to remain on the little tongue of land, that had become an island, till the food should subside.As the three were returning to the cottage after their ramble, the knight whispered in the ear of the little maiden“Well, how is it, my pretty Undine—are you angry at my remaining?”

“Ah！”she replied, peevishly，“let me alone. If I had not bitten you, who knows how much of Bertalda would have appeared in your story?”

CHAPTER VII　WHAT FURTHER HAPPENED ON THE EVENING OF THE WEDDING

Both before and during the ceremony, Undine had shown herself gentle and quiet；but it now seemed as if all the wayward humors which rioted within her, burst forth all the more boldly and unrestrainedly. She teased her bridegroom and her foster-parents, and even the holy man whom she had so lately reverenced, with all sorts of childish tricks；and when the old woman was about to reprove her, she was quickly silenced by a few grave words from the knight, speaking of Undine now as his wife.Nevertheless, the knight himself was equally little pleased with Undine's childish behavior：but no signs, and no reproachful words were of any avail.It is true, whenever the bride noticed her husband's dissatisfaction—and this occurred occasionally—she became more quiet, sat down by his side, caressed him, whispered something smilingly into his ear, and smoothed the wrinkles that were gathering on his brow.But immediately afterward, some wild freak would again lead her to return to her ridiculous proceedings, and matters would be worse than before.At length the priest said in a serious and kind tone：“My fair young maiden, no one indeed can look at you without delight；but remember so to attune your soul betimes, that it may everharmonize with that of your wedded husband.”

“Soul！”said Undine, laughing；“that sounds pretty enough, and may be a very edifying and useful caution for most people. But when one hasn't a soul at all, I beg you, what is there to attune then?and that is my case.”

The priest was silent and deeply wounded, and with holy displeasure he turned his face from the girl. She, however, went up to him caressingly, and said：“No！listen to me frst, before you look angry, for your look of anger gives me pain, and you must not give pain to any creature who has done you no wrong—only have patience with me, and I will tell you properly what I mean.”

It was evident that she was preparing herself to explain something in detail, but suddenly she hesitated, as if seized with an inward shuddering, and burst out into a food of tears. None of them knew what to make of this ebullition, and flled with various apprehensions they gazed at her in silence.At length, wiping away her tears, and looking earnestly at the reverend man, she said：“There must be something beautiful, but at the same time extremely awful, about a soul.Tell me, holy sir, were it not better that we never shared such a gift?”She was silent again as if waiting for an answer, and her tears had ceased to fow.All in the cottage had risen from their seats and had stepped back from her with horror.She, however, seemed to have eyes for no one but the holy man；her features wore an expression of fearful curiosity, which appeared terrible to those who saw her.“The soul must be a heavy burden，”she continued, as no one answered her，“very heavy！for even its approaching image overshadows me with anxiety and sadness.And, ah！I was so light-hearted and so merry till now！”

And she burst into a fresh food of tears, and covered her face with the drapery she wore. Then the priest went up to her with a solemn air, and spoke to her, and conjured her by the name of the Most Holy to cast aside the veil that enveloped her, if any spirit of evil possessed her.But she sank on her knees before him, repeating all the sacred words he uttered, praising God, and protesting that she wished well with the whole world.Then at last the priest said to the knight：“Sir bridegroom, I will leave you alone with her whom I have united to you in marriage.So far as I can discover there is nothing of evil in her, but much indeed that is mysterious.I commend to you—prudence, love, and fdelity.”

So saying, he went out, and the fsherman and his wife followed him, crossing themselves.

Undine had sunk on her knees：she unveiled her face and said, looking timidly round on Huldbrand：“Alas！you will surely now not keep me as your own；and yet I have done no evil, poor child that I am！”As she said this, she looked so exquisitely graceful and touching, that her bridegroom forgot all the horror he had felt, and all the mystery that clung to her, and hastening to her he raised her in his arms. She smiled through her tears；it was a smile like the morning-light playing on a little stream.

“You cannot leave me，”she whispered, with confdent security, stroking the knight's cheek with her tender hand. Huldbrand tried to dismiss the fearful thoughts that still lurked in the background of his mind, persuading him that he was married to a fairy or to some malicious and mischievous being of the spirit world, only the singlequestion half unawares escaped his lips：“My little Undine, tell me this one thing, what was it you said of spirits of the earth and of Kuhleborn, when the priest knocked at the door?”

“It was nothing but fairy tales！—children's fairy tales！”said Undine, with all her wonted gayety；“I frightened you at frst with them, and then you frightened me, that's the end of our story and of our nuptial evening.”

“Nay！that it isn't，”said the knight, intoxicated with love, and extinguishing the tapers, he bore his beautiful beloved to the bridal chamber by the light of the moon which shone brightly through the windows.

CHAPTER XI　THE ANNIVERSARY OF BERTALDA’S NAME-DAY

The company were sitting at dinner；Bertalda, looking like some goddess of spring with her flowers and jewels, the presents of her foster-parents and friends, was placed between Undine and Huldbrand. When the rich repast was ended, and the last course had appeared, the doors were left open, according to a good old German custom, that the common people might look on, and take part in the festivity of the nobles.Servants were carrying round cake and wine among the spectators.Huldbrand and Bertalda were waiting with secret impatience for the promised explanation, and sat with their eyes fxed steadily on Undine.But the beautiful wife still continued silent, and only kept smiling to herself with secret and hearty satisfaction.All who knew of the promise she had given could see that she was every moment on the point of betraying her happy secret, and that it was with a sort of longing renunciation that she withheld it, just as children sometimes delay the enjoyment of their choicest morsels.Bertalda and Huldbrand shared this delightful feeling, and expected with fearful hope the tidings which were to fall from the lips of Undine.Several of the company pressed Undine to sing.The request seemed opportune, and ordering her lute to bebrought, she sang the following words：—

Bright opening day，

Wild flowers so gay，

Tall grasses their thirst that slake，

On the banks of the billowy lake！

What glimmers there so shining

The reedy growth entwining?

Is it a blossom white as snow

Fallen from heav’n here below?

It is an infant, frail and dear！

With flowerets playing in its dreams

And grasping morning’s golden beams；

Oh！whence, sweet stranger, art thou here?

From some far-off and unknown strand，

The lake has borne thee to this land.

Nay, grasp not tender little one，

With thy tiny hand outspread；

No hand will meet thy touch with love，

Mute is that flowery bed.

The flowers can deck themselves so fair

And breathe forth fragrance blest，

Yet none can press thee to itself，

Like that far-off mother’s breast.

So early at the gate of life，

With smiles of heav’n on thy brow，

Thou hast the best of treasures lost，

Poor wand’ring child, nor know’st it now.

A noble duke comes riding by，

And near thee checks his courser’s speed，

And full of ardent chivalry

He bears thee home upon his steed.

Much, endless much, has been thy gain！

Thou bloom’st the fairest in the land！

Yet ah！the priceless joy of all，

Thou’st left upon an unknown strand.

Undine dropped her lute with a melancholy smile, and the eyes of Bertalda's foster-parents were flled with tears.“Yes, so it was on the morning that I found you, my poor sweet orphan，”said the duke, deeply agitated；“the beautiful singer is certainly right；we have not been able to give you thatpriceless joy of all.'”

“But we must also hear how it fared with the poor parents，”said Undine, as she resumed her lute, and sang：—

Thro’every chamber roams the mother，

Moves and searches everywhere，

Seeks, she scarce knows what, with sadness，

And finds an empty house is there.

An empty house！Oh, word of sorrow，

To her who once had been so blest，

Who led her child about by day

And cradled it at night to rest.

The beech is growing green again，

The sunshine gilds its wonted spot，

But mother, cease thy searching vain！

Thy little loved one cometh not.

And when the breath of eve blows cool，

And father in his home appears，

The smile he almost tries to wear

Is quenched at once by gushing tears.

Full well he knows that in his home

He naught can find but wild despair，

He hears the mother’s grieved lament

And no bright infant greets him there.

“Oh！for God's sake, Undine, where are my parents?”cried the weeping Bertalda；“you surely know；you have discovered them, you wonderful being, for otherwise you would not have thus torn meheart. Are they perhaps already here?Can it be?”

Her eyes passed quickly over the brilliant company and lingered on a lady of high rank who was sitting next her foster-father. Undine, however, turned toward the door, while her eyes overfowed with the sweetest emotion.

“Where are the poor waiting parents?”she inquired, and, the old fsherman and his wife advanced hesitatingly from the crowd of spectators. Their glance rested inquiringly now on Undine, now on the beautiful girl who was said to be their daughter“It is she，”said the delighted benefactress, in a faltering tone, and the two old people hung round the neck of their recovered child, weeping and praising God.

But amazed and indignant, Bertalda tore herself from their embrace. Such a recognition was too much for this proud mind, at a moment when she had surely imagined that her former splendor would even be increased, and when hope was deluding her with a vision of almost royal honors.It seemed to her as if her rival had devised all this on purpose signally to humble her before Huldbrand and the whole world.She reviled Undine, she reviled the old people, and bitter invectives, such as“deceiver”and“bribed impostors，”fell from her lips.Then the old fsherman's wife said in a low voice to herself：“Ah me, she is become a wicked girl；and yet I feel in my heart that she is my child.”The old fisherman, however, had folded his hands, and was praying silently that this might not be his daughter.Undine, pale as death, turned with agitation from the parents to Bertalda, and from Bertalda to the parents；suddenly cast down from that heaven of happiness of which she had dreamed, andoverwhelmed with a fear and a terror such as she had never known even in imagination.

“Have you a soul?Have you really a soul, Bertalda?”she cried again and again to her angry friend, as if forcibly to rouse her to consciousness from some sudden delirium or maddening nightmare. But when Bertalda only became more and more enraged, when the repulsed parents began to weep aloud, and the company, in eager dispute, were taking different sides, she begged in such a dignifed and serious manner to be allowed to speak in this her husband's hall, that all around were in a moment silenced.She then advanced to the upper end of the table, where Bertalda has seated herself, and with a modest and yet proud air, while every eye was fxed upon her, she spoke as follows：—

“My friends, you look so angry and disturbed and you have interrupted my happy feast by your disputings. Ah！I knew nothing of your foolish habits and your heartless mode of thinking, and I shall never all my life long become accustomed to them.It is not my fault that this affair has resulted in evil；believe me, the fault is with yourselves alone, little as it may appear to you to be so.I have therefore but little to say to you, but one thing I must say：I have spoken nothing but truth.I neither can nor will give you proofs beyond my own assertion, but I will swear to the truth of this.I received this information from the very person who allured Bertalda into the water, away from her parents, and who afterward placed her on the green meadow in the duke's path.”

“She is an enchantress！”cried Bertalda，“a witch, who has intercourse with evil spirits. She acknowledges it herself.”

“I do not，”said Undine, with a whole heaven innocence and confdence beaming, in her eyes.“I am no witch；only look at me.”

“She is false and boastful，”interrupted Bertalda，“and she cannot prove that I am the child of these low people. My noble parents, I beg you to take me from this company and out of this city, where they are only bent on insulting me.”

But the aged and honorable duke remained unmoved, and his wife, said：“We must thoroughly examine how we are to act. God forbid that we should move a step from this hall until we have done so.”

Then the old wife of the fisherman drew near, and making a low reverence to the duchess, she said：“Noble, god-fearing lady, you have opened my heart. I must tell you, if this evil-disposed young lady is my daughter, she has a mark, like a violet, between her shoulders, and another like it on the instep of her left foot.If she would only go out of the hall with me！”

“I shall not uncover myself before the peasant woman！”exclaimed Bertalda, proudly turning her back on her.

“But before me you will.”rejoined the duchess, very gravely.“Follow me into that room, girl, and the good old woman shall come with us.”

The three disappeared, and the rest of the company remained where they were, in silent expectation. After a short time they returned；Bertalda was pale as death.“Right is right.”said the duchess；“I must therefore declare that our hostess has spoken perfect, truth.Bertalda is the fisherman's daughter, and that is as much as it is necessary to inform you here.”

The princely pair left with their adopted daughter；and at a sign from the duke, the fsherman and his wife followed them. The other guests retired in silence or with secret murmurs, and Undine sank weeping into Huldbrand's arms.

CHAPTER XIV　HOW BERTALDA RETURNED HOME WITH THE KNIGHT

The Black Valley lies deep within the mountains. What it is now called we do not know.At that time the people of the country gave it this appellation on account of the deep obscurity in which the low land lay, owing to the shadows of the lofty trees, and especially firs, that grew there.Even the brook which bubbled between the rocks wore the same dark hue, and dashed along with none of that gladness with which streams are wont to fow that have the blue sky immediately above them.Now, in the growing twilight of evening, it looked wild and gloomy between the heights.The knight trotted anxiously along the edge of the brook, fearful at one moment that by delay he might allow the fugitive to advance too far, and at the next that by too great rapidity he might overlook her in case she were concealing herself from him.Meanwhile he had already penetrated tolerably far into the valley, and might soon hope to overtake the maiden, if he were on the right track.The fear that this might not be the case made his heart beat with anxiety.Where would the tender Bertalda tarry through the stormy night, which was so fearful in the valley, should he fail to find her?At length he saw something white gleaming through the branches on the slope of the mountain.He thought he recognized Bertalda's dress, and he turned his course in that direction.But his horse refused to go forward；it reared impatiently；and its master, unwilling to lose a moment, and seeing moreover that the copse was impassable on horseback, dismounted；and, fastening his snorting steed to an elm-tree, he worked his way cautiously through the bushes.The branches sprinkled his forehead and cheeks with the cold drops of the evening dew；a distant roll of thunder was heard murmuring from the other side of the mountains；everything looked so strange that he began to feel a dread of the white fgure, which now lay only a short distance from him on the ground.Still he could plainly see that it was a female, either asleep or in a swoon, and that she was attired in long white garments, such as Bertalda had worn on that day.He stepped close up to her, made a rustling with the branches, and let his sword clatter, but she moved not.

“Bertalda！”he exclaimed, at first in a low voice, and then louder and louder—still she heard not. At last, when he uttered the dear name with a more powerful effort, a hollow echo from the mountain-caverns of the valley indistinctly reverberated“Bertalda！”but still the sleeper woke not.He bent down over her；the gloom of the valley and the obscurity of approaching night would not allow him to distinguish her features.Just as he was stooping closer over her, with a feeling of painful doubt, a fash of lightning shot across the valley, and he saw before him a frightfully distorted countenance, and a hollow voice exclaimed：“Give me a kiss, you enamoured swain！”

Huldbrand sprang up with a cry of horror, and the hideousfgure rose with him.“Go home！”it murmured；“wizards are on the watch. Go home！or I will have you！”and it stretched out its long white arms toward him.

“Malicious Kuhleborn！”cried the knight, recovering himself，“What do you concern me, you goblin?There, take your kiss！”And he furiously hurled his sword at the fgure. But it vanished like vapor, and a gush of water which wetted him through left the knight no doubt as to the foe with whom he had been engaged.

“He wishes to frighten me back from Bertalda，”said he aloud to himself；“he thinks to terrify me with his foolish tricks, and to make me give up the poor distressed girl to him, so that he can wreak his vengeance on her. But he shall not do that, weak spirit of the elements as he is.No powerless phantom can understand what a human heart can do when its best energies are aroused.”He felt the truth of his words, and that the very expression of them had inspired his heart with fresh courage.It seemed too as if fortune were on his side, for he had not reached his fastened horse, when he distinctly heard Bertalda's plaintive voice not far distant, and could catch her weeping accents through the ever-increasing tumult of the thunder and tempest.He hurried swiftly in the direction of the sound, and found the trembling girl just attempting to climb the steep, in order to escape in any way from the dreadful gloom of the valley.He stepped, however, lovingly in her path, and bold and proud as her resolve had before been, she now felt only too keenly the delight, that the friend whom she so passionately loved should rescue her from this frightful solitude, and that the joyous life in the castle should be again open to her.She followed almost unresisting, but soexhausted with fatigue that the knight was glad to have brought her to his horse, which he now hastily unfastened, in order to lift the fair fugitive upon it；and then, cautiously holding the reins, he hoped to proceed through the uncertain shades of the valley.

But the horse had become quite unmanageable from the wild apparition of Kuhleborn. Even the knight would have had diffculty in mounting the rearing and snorting animal, but to place the trembling Bertalda on its back was perfectly impossible.They determined, therefore, to return home on foot.Drawing the horse after him by the bridle, the knight supported the tottering girl with his other hand.Bertalda exerted all her strength to pass quickly through the fearful valley, but weariness weighed her down like lead, and every limb trembled, partly from the terror she had endured when Kuhleborn had pursued her, and partly from her continued alarm at the howling of the storm and the pealing of the thunder through the wooded mountain.

At last she slid from the supporting arm of her protector, and sinking down on the moss, she exclaimed：“Let me lie here, my noble lord；I suffer the punishment due to my folly, and I must now perish here through weariness and dread.”

“No, sweet friend, I will never leave you！”cried Huldbrand, vainly endeavoring to restrain his furious steed；for, worse than before, it now began to foam and rear with excitement, until at last the knight was glad to keep the animal at a suffcient distance from the exhausted maiden lest her fears should be increased. But scarcely had he withdrawn a few paces with the wild steed, than she began to call after him in the most pitiful manner, believing that he was really goingto leave her in this horrible wilderness.He was utterly at a loss what course to take.Gladly would he have given the excited beast its liberty and have allowed it to rush away into the night and spend its fury, had he not feared that is this narrow defle it might come thundering with its iron-shod hoofs over the very spot where Bertalda lay.

In the midst of this extreme perplexity and distress, he heard with delight the sound of a vehicle driving slowly down the stony road behind them. He called out for help；and a man's voice replied, bidding him have patience, but promising assistance；and soon after, two gray horses appeared through the bushes, and beside them the driver in the white smock of a carter；a great white linen cloth was next visible, covering the goods apparently contained in the wagon.At a loud shout from their master, the obedient horses halted.The driver then came toward the knight, and helped him in restraining his foaming animal.

“I see well，”said he，“what ails the beast. When I frst travelled this way, my horses were no better.The fact is, there is an evil water-spirit haunting the place, and he takes delight in this sort of mischief.But I have learned a charm；if you will let me whisper it in your horse's ear, he will stand at once just as quiet as my gray beasts are doing there.”

“Try your luck then, only help us quickly！”exclaimed the impatient knight. The wagoner then drew down the head of the rearing charger close to his own, and whispered something in his ear.In a moment the animal stood still and quiet, and his quick panting and reeking condition was all that remained of his previous unmanageableness.Huldbrand had no time to inquire how all thishad been effected.He agreed with the carter that he should take Bertalda on his wagon, where, as the man assured him, there were a quantity of soft cotton-bales, upon which she could be conveyed to castle Ringstetten, and the knight was to accompany them on horseback.But the horse appeared too much exhausted by its past fury to be able to carry its master so far, so the carter persuaded Huldbrand to get into the wagon with Bertalda.The horse could be fastened on behind.

“We are going down hill，”said he，“and that will make it light for my gray beasts.”The knight accepted the offer and entered the wagon with Bertalda；the horse followed patiently behind, and the wagoner, steady and attentive, walked by the side.

In the stillness of the night, as its darkness deepened and the subsiding tempest sounded more and more remote, encouraged by the sense of security and their fortunate escape, a confidential conversation arose between Huldbrand and Bertalda. With fattering words he reproached her for her daring fight；she excused herself with humility and emotion, and from every word she said a gleam shone forth which disclosed distinctly to the lover that the beloved was his.The knight felt the sense of her words far more than he regarded their meaning, and it was the sense alone to which he replied.Presently the wagoner suddenly shouted with loud voice，—

“Up, my grays, up with your feet, keep together！remember who you are！”

The knight leaned out of the wagon and saw that the horses were stepping into the midst of a foaming stream or were already almost swimming, while the wheels of the wagon were rushinground and gleaming like mill-wheels, and the wagoner had got up in front, in consequence of the increasing waters.

“What sort of a road is this?It goes into the middle of the stream.”cried Huldbrand to his guide.

“Not at all, sir.”returned the other, laughing，“it is just the reverse, the stream goes into the very middle of our road. Look round and see how everything is covered by the water.”The whole valley indeed was suddenly flled with the surging food, that visibly increased.

“It is Kuhleborn, the evil water-spirit, who wishes to drown us！”exclaimed the knight.“Have you no charm, against him, my friend?”“I know indeed of one，”returned the wagoner，“but I cannot and may not use it until you know who I am.”“Is this a time for riddles?”cried the knight.“The food is ever rising higher, and what does it matter to me to know who you are?”

“It does matter to you, though，”said the wagoner，“for I am Kuhleborn.”So saying, he thrust his distorted face into the wagon with a grin, but the wagon was a wagon no longer, the horses were not horses—all was transformed to foam and vanished in the hissing waves, and even the wagoner himself, rising as a gigantic billow, drew down the vainly struggling horse beneath the waters, and then swelling higher and higher, swept over the heads of the foating pair, like some liquid tower, threatening to bury them irrecoverably.

Just then the soft voice of Undine sounded through the uproar, the moon emerged from the clouds, and by its light Undine was seen on the heights above the valley. She rebuked, she threatened the floods below；the menacing, tower-like wave vanished, mutteringand murmuring, the waters flowed gently away in the moonlight, and like a white dove, Undine flew down from the height, seized the knight and Bertalda, and bore them with her to a fresh, green, turfy spot on the hill, where with choice refreshing restoratives, she dispelled their terrors and weariness；then she assisted Bertalda to mount the white palfrey, on which she had herself ridden here, and thus all three returned back to castle Ringstetten.

CHAPTER XV　THE JOURNEY TO VIENNA

After this last adventure, they lived quietly and happily at the castle. The knight more and more perceived the heavenly goodness of his wife, which had been so nobly exhibited by her pursuit, and by her rescue of them in the Black Valley, where Kuhleborn's power again commenced；Undine herself felt that peace and security, which is never lacking to a mind so long as it is distinctly conscious of being on the right path, and besides, in the newly-awakened love and esteem of her husband, many a gleam of hope and joy shone upon her.Bertalda, on the other hand, showed herself grateful, humble and timid, without regarding her conduct as anything meritorious.Whenever Huldbrand or Undine were about to give her any explanation regarding the covering of the fountain or the adventure in the Black Valley, she would earnestly entreat them to spare her the recital, as she felt too much shame at the recollection of the fountain, and too much fear at the remembrance of the Black Valley.She learned therefore nothing further of either；and for what end was such knowledge necessary?Peace and joy had visibly taken up their abode at castle Ringstetten.They felt secure on this point, and imagined that life could now produce nothing but pleasant fowers and fruits.

In this happy condition of things, winter had come and passed away, and spring, with its fresh green shoots and its blue sky, was gladdening the joyous inmates of the castle. Spring was in harmony with them, and they with spring.What wonder then, that its storks and swallows inspired them also with a desire to travel?

One day when they were taking a pleasant walk to one of the sources of the Danube, Huldbrand spoke of the magnificence of the noble river, and how it widened as it fowed through countries fertilized by its waters, how the charming city of Vienna shone forth on its banks, and how with every step of its course it increased in power and loveliness.

“It must be glorious to go down the river as far as Vienna！”exclaimed Bertalda, but immediately relapsing into her present modesty and humility, she paused and blushed deeply.

This touched Undine deeply, and with the liveliest desire to give pleasure to her friend, she said：“What hinders us from starting on the little voyage?”

Bertalda exhibited the greatest delight, and both she and Undine began at once to picture the tour of the Danube in the brightest colors. Huldbrand also gladly agreed to the prospect；only he once whispered anxiously in Undine's ear，—

“But Kuhleborn becomes possessed of his power again out there！”

“Let him come，”she replied with a smile，“I shall be there, and he ventures upon none of his mischief before me.”

The last impediment was thus removed；they prepared for the journey, and soon after set out upon it with fresh spirits and thebrightest hopes.

But wonder not, oh man, if events always turn out different to what we have intended. That malicious power, lurking for our destruction, gladly lulls its chosen victim to sleep with sweet songs and golden delusions；while on the other hand the rescuing messenger from Heaven often knocks sharply and alarmingly at our door.

During the first few days of their voyage down the Danube they were extremely happy. Everything grew more and more beautiful as they sailed further and further down the proudly fowing stream.But in a region otherwise so pleasant, and in the enjoyment of which they had promised themselves the purest delight, the ungovernable Kuhleborn began, undisguisedly, to exhibit his power of interference.This was indeed manifested in mere teasing tricks, for Undine often rebuked the agitated waves, or the contrary winds, and then the violence of the enemy would be immediately humbled；but again the attacks would be renewed, and again Undine's reproofs would become necessary, so that the pleasure of the little party was completely destroyed.

The boatmen too were continually whispering to each other in dismay, and looking with distrust at the three strangers, whose servants even began more and more to forebode something uncomfortable, and to watch their superiors with suspicious glances. Huldbrand often said to himself：“This comes from like not being linked with like, from a man uniting himself with a mermaid！”Excusing himself as we all love to do, he would often think indeed as he said this：“I did not really know that she was a sea-maiden, mine is the misfortune, that every step I take is disturbed andhaunted by the wild caprices of her race, but mine is not the fault.”

By thoughts such as these, he felt himself in some measure strengthened, but on the other hand, he felt increasing ill-humor, and almost animosity toward Undine. He would look at her with an expression of anger, the meaning of which the poor wife understood well.Wearied with this exhibition of displeasure, and exhausted by the constant effort to frustrate Kuhleborn's artifices, she sank one evening into a deep slumber, rocked soothingly by the softly gliding bark.

Scarcely, however, had she closed her eyes than every one in the vessel imagined he saw, in whatever direction he turned, a most horrible human head；it rose out of the waves, not like that of a person swimming, but perfectly perpendicular as if invisibly supported upright on the watery surface, and floating along in the same course with the bark. Each wanted to point out to the other the cause of his alarm, but each found the same expression of horror depicted on the face of his neighbor, only that his hands and eyes were directed to a different point where the monster, half-laughing and half-threatening, rose before him.When, however, they all wished to make each other understand what each saw, and all were crying out：“Look there！No, there！”the horrible heads all at one and the same time appeared to their view, and the whole river around the vessel swarmed with the most hideous apparitions.The universal cry raised at the sight awoke Undine.As she opened her eyes, the wild crowd of distorted visages disappeared.But Huldbrand was indignant at such unsightly jugglery.He would have burst forth in uncontrolled imprecations had not Undine said to him with a humblemanner and a softly imploring tone：“For God's sake, my husband, we are on the water, do not be angry with me now.”

The knight was silent, and sat down absorbed in revery. Undine whispered in his ear：“Would it not be better, my love, if we gave up this foolish journey, and returned to castle Ringstetten in peace?”

But Huldbrand murmured moodily：“So I must be a prisoner in my own castle, and only be able to breathe so long as the fountain is closed！I would your mad kindred”—

Undine lovingly pressed her fair hand upon his lips. He paused, pondering in silence over much that Undine had before said to him.Bertalda had meanwhile given herself up to a variety of strange thoughts.She knew a good deal of Undine's origin, and yet not the whole, and the fearful Kuhleborn especially had remained to her a terrible but wholly unrevealed mystery.She had indeed never even heard his name.Musing on these strange things, she unclasped, scarcely conscious of the act, a gold necklace, which Huldbrand had lately purchased for her of a travelling trader；half dreamingly she drew it along the surface of the water, enjoying the light glimmer it cast upon the evening-tinted stream.Suddenly a huge hand was stretched out of the Danube, it seized the necklace and vanished with it beneath the waters.Bertalda screamed aloud, and a scornful laugh resounded from the depths of the stream.The knight could now restrain his anger no longer.Starting up, he inveighed against the river；he cursed all who ventured to interfere with his family and his life, and challenged them, be they spirits or sirens, to show themselves before his avenging sword.Bertalda wept meanwhile for her lost ornament, which was so precious to her, and her tearsadded fuel to the flame of the knight's anger, while Undine held her hand over the side of the vessel, dipping it into the water, softly murmuring to herself, and only now and then interrupting her strange mysterious whisper, as she entreated her husband：“My dearly loved one, do not scold me here；reprove others if you will, but not me here.You know why！”

And indeed, he restrained the words of anger that were trembling on his tongue. Presently in her wet hand which she had been holding under the waves, she brought up a beautiful coral necklace of so much brilliancy that the eyes of all were dazzled by it.

“Take this，”said she, holding it out kindly to Bertalda；“I have ordered this to be brought for you as a compensation, and don't be grieved any more, my poor child.”

But the knight sprang between them. He tore the beautiful ornament from Undine's hand, hurled it again into the river, exclaiming in passionate rage：“Have you then still a connection with them?In the name of all the witches, remain among them with your presents, and leave us mortals in peace, you sorceress！”

Poor Undine gazed at him with fxed but tearful eyes, her hand still stretched out, as when she had offered her beautiful present so lovingly to Bertalda. She then began to weep more and more violently, like a dear innocent child bitterly afficted.At last, wearied out she said：

“Alas, sweet friend, alas！farewell！They shall do you no harm；only remain true, so that I may be able to keep them from you. I must, alas！go away；I must go hence at this early stage of life.Ohwoe, woe！what have you done！Oh woe, woe！”

She vanished over the side of the vessel. Whether she plunged into the stream, or flowed away with it, they knew not；her disappearance was like both and neither.Soon, however, she was completely lost sight of in the Danube；only a few little waves kept whispering, as if sobbing, round the boat, and they almost seemed to be saying：“Oh woe, woe！oh remain true！oh woe！”

Huldbrand lay on the deck of the vessel, bathed in hot tears, and a deep swoon soon cast its veil of forgetfulness over the unhappy man.

CHAPTER XVIII　HOW THE KNIGHT HULDBRAND IS MARRIED

If I were to tell you how the marriage-feast passed at castle Ringstetten, it would seem to you as if you saw a heap of bright and pleasant things, but a gloomy veil of mourning spread over them all, the dark hue of which would make the splendor of the whole look less like happiness than a mockery of the emptiness of all earthly joys. It was not that any spectral apparitions disturbed the festive company, for we know that the castle had been secured from the mischief of the threatening water-spirits.But the knight and the fsherman and all the guests felt as if the chief personage were still lacking at the feast, and that this chief personage could be none other than the loved and gentle Undine.Whenever a door opened, the eyes of all were involuntarily turned in that direction, and if it was nothing but the butler with new dishes, or the cup-bearer with a fask of still richer wine, they would look down again sadly, and the fashes of wit and merriment which had passed to and fro, would be extinguished by sad remembrances.The bride was the most thoughtless of all, and therefore the most happy；but even to her it sometimes seemed strange that she should be sitting at the head of the table, wearing a green wreath and gold-embroidered attire, while Undine was lying at the bottom of the Danube, a cold and stiff corpse, or foating away with the current into the mighty ocean.For, ever since her father had spoken of something of the sort, his words were ever ringing in her ear, and this day especially they were not inclined to give place to other thoughts.

The company dispersed early in the evening, not broken up by the bridegroom himself, but sadly and gloomily by the joyless mood of the guests and their forebodings of evil. Bertalda retired with her maidens, and the knight with his attendants；but at this mournful festival there was no gay, laughing train of bridesmaids and bridesmen.

Bertalda wished to arouse more cheerful thoughts；she ordered a splendid ornament of jewels which Huldbrand had given her, together with rich apparel and veils, to be spread out before her, in order that from these latter she might select the brightest and most beautiful for her morning attire. Her attendants were delighted at the opportunity of expressing their good wishes to their young mistress, not failing at the same time to extol the beauty of the bride in the most lively terms.They were more and more absorbed in these considerations, till Bertalda at length, looking in a mirror, said with a sigh：“Ah, but don't you see plainly how freckled I am growing here at the side of my neck?”

They looked at her throat, and found the freckles as their fair mistress had said, but they called them beauty-spots, and mere tiny blemishes only, tending to enhance the whiteness of her delicate skin. Bertalda shook her head and asserted that a spot was always a defect.

“And I could remove them，”she sighed a last，“only the fountain is closed from which I used to have that precious and purifying water. Oh！if I had but a fask of it to-day！”

“Is that all?”said an alert waiting-maid, laughing, as she slipped from the apartment.

“She will not be mad，”exclaimed Bertalda, in a pleased and surprised tone，“she will not be so mad as to have the stone removed from the fountain this very evening！”At the same moment they heard the men crossing the courtyard, and could see from the window how the officious waiting-woman was leading them straight up to the fountain, and that they were carrying levers and other instruments on their shoulders.“It is certainly my will，”said Bertalda, smiling，“if only it does not take too long.”And, happy in the sense that a look from her now was able to effect what had formerly been so painfully refused her, she watched the progress of the work in the moonlit castle-court.

The men raised the enormous stone with an effort；now and then indeed one of their number would sigh, as he remembered that they were destroying the work of their former beloved mistress. But the labor was far lighter than they had imagined.It seemed as if a power within the spring itself were aiding them in raising the stone.“It is just，”said the workmen to each other in astonishment，“as if the water within had become a springing fountain.”And the stone rose higher and higher, and almost without the assistance of the workmen, it rolled slowly down upon the pavement with a hollow sound.But from the opening of the fountain there rose solemnly a white column of water；at frst they imagined it had really become aspringing fountain, till they perceived that the rising form was a pale female fgure veiled in white.She was weeping bitterly, raising her hands wailingly above her head and wringing them, as she walked with a slow and serious step to the castle-building.The servants fed from the spring；the bride, pale and stiff with horror, stood at the window with her attendants.When the figure had now come close beneath her room, it looked moaningly up to her, and Bertalda thought she could recognize beneath the veil the pale features of Undine.But the sorrowing form passed on, sad, reluctant, and faltering, as if passing to execution.Bertalda screamed out that the knight was to be called, but none of her maids ventured from the spot；and even the bride herself became mute, as if trembling at her own voice.

While they were still standing fearfully at the window, motionless as statues, the strange wanderer had reached the castle, had passed up the well-known stairs, and through the well-known halls, ever in silent tears. Alas！how differently had she once wandered through them！

The knight, partly undressed, had already dismissed his attendants, and in a mood of deep dejection he was standing before a large mirror；a taper was burning dimly beside him. There was a gentle tap at his door.Undine used to tap thus when she wanted playfully to tease him“It is all fancy，”said he to himself；“I must seek my nuptial bed.”

“So you must, but it must be a cold one！”he heard a tearful voice say from without, and then he saw in the mirror his door opening slowly—slowly—and the white figure entered, carefullyclosing it behind her.“They have opened the spring，”said she softly，“and now I am here, and you must die.”

He felt in his paralyzed heart that it could not be otherwise, but covering his eyes with his hands he said：“Do not make me mad with terror in my hour of death. If you wear a hideous face behind that veil, do not raise it, but take my life, and let me see you not.”

“Alas！”replied the figure，“will you then not look upon me once more?I am as fair as when you wooed me on the promontory.”

“Oh, if it were so！”sighed Huldbrand，“and if I might die in your fond embrace！”

“Most gladly, my loved one，”said she；and throwing her veil back, her lovely face smiled forth divinely beautiful.

Trembling with love and with the approach of death, she kissed him with a holy kiss；but not relaxing her hold she pressed him fervently to her, and as if she would weep away her soul. Tears rushed into the knight's eyes, and seemed to surge through his heaving breast, till at length his breathing ceased, and he fell softly back from the beautiful arms of Undine, upon the pillows of his couch—a corpse.

“I have wept him to death，”said she to some servants who met her in the ante-chamber；and, passing through the affrighted group, she went slowly out toward the fountain.

引子

引子里面绝无要紧话，爱听故事不爱听空谈诸君，可以不必白费时光，从第一章看起就是。

我一年前看了“Undine”（涡堤孩）那段故事以后，非但很感动，并觉其结构文笔并极精妙，当时就想可惜我和母亲不在一起，否则若然我随看随讲，她一定很乐意听。此次偶尔兴动，一口气将它翻了出来，如此母亲虽在万里外不能当面听我讲，也可以看我的译文。译笔很是粗忽，老实说我自己付印前一遍都不曾复看，其中错讹的字句，一定不少，这是我要道歉的一点。其次因为我原意是给母亲看的，所以动笔的时候，就以她看得懂与否作标准，结果南腔北调杂格得很，但是她看我知道恰好，如其这故事能有幸传出我家庭以外，我不得不为译笔之芜杂道歉。

这篇故事，算是西欧文学里有名的浪漫事（Romance）之一。大陆上有乐剧（Undine opera），英国著名剧评家W.L.Courtney将这故事编成三幕的剧本。此外英译有两种，我现在翻的是高斯（Edmund Gosse）的译本[1]。高斯自身是近代英国文学界里一个重要分子，他还活着。他是一诗人，但是他文学评论家的身份更高。他读书之多、学识之博，与Edward Dowden和George Saintsbury齐名，他们三人的评论，都是渊源于19世纪评坛大师法人圣佩韦（Sainte-Beuve），而高斯文笔之条畅精美，尤在Dowden之上，（Saintsbury文学知识浩如烟海，英法文学，几于全欧文学，彼直一气吸尽，然其文字殊晦涩，读者皆病之。）其Undine译文，算是译界难得之佳构，惜其书已绝版耳。

高斯译文前有一长篇La Motte Funqué的研究，讲他在德文学界的位置及其事略，我懒得翻，简要一提就算。

这段故事作者的完全名字是Friedrich Heinrich Karl, Baron de la Fouqué，我现在简称他为福凯，他生在德国，祖先是法国的贵族。他活了65岁，从1777年到1843年。

他生平只有两样嗜好——当兵的荣耀和写浪漫的故事。他自己就是个浪漫人。

他的职业是军官，但他文学的作品，戏曲、诗、小说、报章文字等类，也着实可观，不过大部分都是不相干的，他在文学界的名气，全靠三四个浪漫事——Sintram, Der Zauberring, Thiodulfs, Undine，末了一个尤其重要。

福凯算是19世纪浪漫派最后也是最纯粹的一个作者。他谨守浪漫派的壁垒，丝毫不让步，人家都叫他Don Quixote。他总是全身军服，带着腰剑，顾盼自豪，时常骑了高头大马，在柏林大街上出风头。他最崇拜战争，爱国。他曾说：“打仗是大丈夫精神身体的唯一完美真正职业。”岂不可笑？

他的Undine是1811年出版。那故事的来源，是希腊神话和中世纪迷信。歌德（Goethe）曾经将水火木土四原行假定作人，叫火为Salamander，水为Undine，木为Sylphe，土为Kobold。福凯就借用Undine，以及Melusine和Lohengirn（Wagners Opera，瓦格纳著名的乐剧）的神话关联起来写成这段故事。那大音乐家瓦格纳很看重福凯，他临死那一晚，手里还拿着一本Undine。

福凯发表了这篇故事，声名大震，一霎时Undine传遍全欧，英、法、意、俄不久都有译文。歌德和席勒都认识福凯，他们不很注意他的诗文。但是歌德读了Undine，大为称赞，说可怜的福凯这回居然撞着了纯金。海涅（Heine，大诗家）平常对福凯也很冷淡，但是这一次也出劲地赞美。他说Undine是一篇非常可爱的诗：“此是真正接吻；诗的天才和眠之春接吻，春开眼一笑，所有的蔷薇玫瑰，一齐呼出最香的气息，所有的黄莺一齐唱起他们最甜的歌儿——这是我们优美的福凯怀抱在他文字里的情景，叫作涡堤孩。”

所以这篇故事虽然情节荒唐，身份却是很高，曾经瓦格纳崇拜，歌德称羡，海涅鼓掌，又有人制成乐，编成剧，各国都有译本，现在所翻的又是高斯的手笔——就是我的译手太不像样罢了。

现今国内思想进步，各事维新，在文学界内大众注意的是什么自然主义、象征主义、将来主义、新浪漫主义，也许还有立方主义、球形主义，怪不得连罗素都啧啧称赞说中国少年的思想真敏锐前进，比日本人强多了（他亲口告诉我的，但不知道他这话里有没有Irony，我希望没有）。在这样一日万里情形之下，忽然出现了一篇稀旧荒谬的浪漫事，人家不要笑话吗？但是我声明在前，我译这篇东西本来不敢妄想高明文学先生寓目；我想世界上不见得全是聪明人，像我这样旧式腐败的脾胃，也不见得独一无二，所以胆敢将这段译文付印——至少我母亲总会领情的。

第六章　结婚

正在大家觉得尴尬，忽然一阵轻轻的叩门声从静空气里传了过来，屋子里的人一齐骇然。这是我们都有经验的，一桩很无足轻重的事实，因为他突然而来，往往引起绝大的恐慌，但是这一回我们应该记得那奥妙的森林就在他们附近，而且他们这块地是人迹不到的地方，所以他们相顾惶惶。又听见叩了几下，跟着一声深深的叹息。骑士就起来去拿刀，但是老人悄悄说道：“假使来的是我所虑的，有兵器也不中用。”

同时涡堤孩已经走近门边，厉声叫道：“你若来不怀好意，你地鬼，枯尔庞自会教训你好样子。”

其余屋里的人，听见她古怪的话，更吓了；他们都看着她，黑尔勃郎正要开口问她，门外有人说道：“我不是地鬼，我是好好的人。要是你们愿意救我，要是你们怕上帝，你村舍里面的人，赶快让我进来！”

但是他话还没有说完，涡堤孩早已呀的一声把门打开，手里拿着灯往外面黑夜里一照。他们看见一个年老的牧师，他无意见这样神仙似的一个少女，倒吓得缩了回去。他心里想这样荒野地方，一间小茅屋发现了如此美丽的幻象，一定是什么精怪在那里作弄他，所以他就祷告：“一切善灵，颂扬上帝！”

涡堤孩笑起来了，说道：“我不是鬼，难道我长来丑得像鬼？无论如何，你明明看见你的圣咒没有吓我。我也知道上帝，知道赞美他。神父，进来吧，屋子里都是好人。”

牧师战兢兢鞠了一躬，走了进来，他神气很和善可敬。但是他的长袍上，他的白胡子上，他的白发上，处处都在那里滴水。渔人同骑士立即引他到内房，拿衣服给他换，一面将他的湿衣交给老太太去烘干。这老牧师至至诚诚地谢他们，但是不敢穿那骑士取给他的锦绣的披肩。他另外选了渔人一件旧灰色外套穿上。等他回到外房，主妇赶快将她自己的太师椅让他坐，再也不许他客气。“因为，”她说，“你年高又‘累’了，而且是上帝的人。”涡堤孩老规矩将她平常坐在黑尔勃郎身旁的小凳子推到牧师的脚边，并且很殷勤地招呼这老人。黑尔勃郎轻轻向她说了一句笑话，但是她正色答道——

“他是服侍创造我们一切的他。这并不是闹着玩的事。”

于是骑士和渔人拿酒食给他，牧师吃过喝过，开头讲他昨天从大湖的对面的修道院动身，打算到僧正管区去告诉大水为灾，修道院和邻近村落都受损失。但是他走到傍晚辰光，有一处被水冲断了，他只得雇了两个船家渡他过去。

“但是，”他接着说，“我们的小船刚划得不远，大风雨忽然发作，水势既狂，旋涡更凶。一不小心，船家的桨都叫浪头打劫了去，转瞬不知去向。我们只得听天由命，几阵浪头将我们漂到湖的这边。后来我神魂飘荡，只觉得去死不远，但是我知觉回复的时候，我身子已被浪头送到你们岛上的树下。”

“你说我们岛上！”渔人说道，“本来连着对面的。但是这几天森林里的急流同湖水发了疯，我们连自己都不知道在哪里了。”

牧师说：“我在水边黑暗里爬着，满耳荒野的声音，看见一条走熟的路，领到那边咆哮的水里。后来我见到你们屋子里的光，我就摸了过来，我不知道怎样感谢天父，他从水里救了我出来，又送我到你们这样虔敬的人家；况且我不知道我这辈子除了你们四位以外，会不会再见人类呢？”

“你这话怎样讲？”渔人问道。

牧师说：“谁知道这水几时才能退？我是老衰了。也许水还没有静下去，我的老命倒用到头了。而况水势要是尽涨，你这里离陆地愈远，你的小小渔舟又不能过湖，也许我们从此再不能与世人接触也未可知。”

老主妇听了用手支着十字说道：“上帝不许！”但是渔人望她笑笑，答道——

“那也并没有什么稀奇，尤其于你不相干，老妻是不是？这几年来你除了森林到过哪里？除了涡堤孩和我，你又见过什么人呢？骑士先生来了没有几时，神父刚刚到得。假使我们果真同世间隔绝了，他们两位也和我们同住，那岂不是更好吗？”

老太太说：“难说得很，同世界上隔绝，想想都可怕。”

“但是你要和我们住了，你要和我们住了。”涡堤孩挨到黑尔勃郎身边轻轻地唱着。

但是他正在那里出神。自从牧师讲了最后一番话，那森林背后的世界，好像愈退愈远；这花草遍地的岛上愈觉得青青可爱，似乎对他笑得加倍的鲜甜。他的新娘在这大地一点上好比一朵最娇艳的蔷薇婷婷开着，并且如今牧师都在身边。他一头想，那老太太见涡堤孩在牧师面前和黑尔勃郎黏得如此紧，露出一脸怒气，似乎一顿骂就要发作。骑士再也忍不住，转过来对牧师说道——

“神父呀！你看在你的跟前一个新郎和新妇。如其这孩子和她父母不反对，请你今晚就替我们结婚。”

这对老夫妇吓了一大跳。他们固然早已想到这件事体，但是他们都放在肚里，就是老夫妻间彼此也没有明讲过，现在骑士忽然老老实实说了出来，他们倒觉得非常离奇。涡堤孩顿然正色不语，呆钝钝看着地上，一面牧师在那里打听仔细实际情形，又问老夫妻主意如何。讲了好一阵子，一切都很满意的决定。主妇就起身去替小夫妻铺排新房，又寻出一对神烛来。同时骑士拿下他的金链来，打算拗成两个戒指，预备结婚时交换。但是她一看见忽然好像从她思想的底里泅了上来，说道——

“不必！我的父母并没有打发我到世上来要饭。他们的确想到迟早这么一晚总要临到我的。”

说着，她奔出门去，一会儿回来手里拿着两个宝贵的戒指，一个递给新郎，一个自己戴上。老渔人很惊骇地注视她，老太太更觉稀奇，因为他们从来不知道小孩子有这对戒指。

涡堤孩说：“我的父母将这些小物事缝在我来时穿的衣服里。但是他们不许我告诉随便哪个，除非我结婚。所以我一声不响将它们藏在门外，直到今晚。”

牧师已经将神烛点起，放在桌上，打断他们的问答，吩咐那两口子站在他跟前。然后他替他们结婚，老夫妻祝福小夫妻，新娘倚在新郎身上微微颤动，在那里想心事。突然牧师喊道：“你们这群人好古怪！为什么你们告诉我这岛上除了你们四人，再也没有生灵？但是我行礼的时候我见对着我一个高大穿白袍的人在窗外望。他这时候一定到了门口，或者他要这屋子里什么东西。”

老太太跳将起来叫道：“上帝禁止！”渔人一声不发摇摇头，黑尔勃郎跳到窗口，他似乎看见一道白光，突然遁入黑夜里去了。但是他告诉牧师一定是他偶尔眼花，看错了，于是大家欢欢喜喜围着炉火坐了下来。

第七章　结婚以后当晚的情形

那晚结婚行礼涡堤孩始终很知礼节，但是等得一完结，她的顽皮立刻发作，而且比往常加倍放肆。新郎，她的养父母，和她方才很敬礼的牧师，她一一都开玩笑，直到老妇人真耐不过去，放下脸来想发话。但是骑士很严肃地止住了她，意思说涡堤孩现在是他的妻子，不应随便听申斥。在事实上骑士心里也觉得她闹得太过分，但是他用尽种种方法再也不能收束她。有时新娘觉得新郎不愿意，她稍为静一点，坐在他旁边，笑着吹几句软话到他耳边，结果将他皱紧的眉山重新平解了去。但是一波未平一波又起，她不多一会儿又是无法无天地闹将起来。后来牧师也看不过，正色说道：“我年轻的好友，看了你谁也觉得你活泼有趣，但是你要记住总得调剂你灵魂的音乐，使他抑扬顿挫，与你最爱丈夫的和谐一致才好。”

“灵魂！”涡堤孩喊道，她笑了起来，“你说得很中听，也许是大多数人应该服从的规则。但是一个人若然连灵魂都没有，那便怎么样呢？我倒要请教，我就是这么一回事。”

牧师还以为她和他顽皮，听了大怒，默然不语，很忧愁地将他的眼光别转了去。但是她盈盈地走到他面前，说道——

“不要如此，你要生气，也先听我讲讲明白，因为你不高兴我也不痛快，人家对你好好的，你更不应该让人家难过。你只要耐耐心心，让我讲给你听我究竟什么意思。”

大家正在等她解释，她忽然顿了下来，好像内部一种恐怖将她抓住，她眼泪同两条瀑布似的泻了出来。这一突如其来，大家也不知怎样才好，各人都踌躇不安地向她望着。过了一会儿她收干眼泪，很诚恳地朝着牧师，说道——

“有灵魂一定是一桩很欢喜的事，也是一件最可怕的事。是不是——先生用上帝名字告诉我——是不是爽性没有它倒还好些？”

她又顿了下来，似乎她眼泪又要突围而出，等着回答。屋子里的人现在都站了起来，吓得都往后退。但是她只注意牧师，同时她面貌上出现一种非常离奇的表情——这表情使得大家心里都充满了绝对的恐怖。

大家没有做声，她又接着说：“灵魂一定是一个很重的负担，真是重。我只想到它快临到我，我就觉到悲愁和痛苦。你看，方才我多快活，多没有心事！”

她又大放悲声，将衣服把脸子蒙住。牧师很严肃地向着她，用圣咒吩咐，如其她心里有什么恶魔的变相，叫她用上帝的威灵驱他出去。但是她跪了下来，将他的圣咒背了一遍，并且赞美感谢上帝，因为她心里很平安清洁。然后牧师向骑士说：“新郎先生，你的新妇，我现在听你去管她。照我看来，她一点没有邪恶。虽然有些怪僻，我保举她，望你小心，忠实爱她。”

说着他出去了，老夫妇也跟着出去，用手架着十字。

涡堤孩仍旧跪在地下，她仰起头，羞怯怯瞅着黑尔勃郎，说道：“如今你也不要我了，但是我苦命孩子并没有闹乱子。”

她说得楚楚可怜，万分妩媚，黑尔勃郎原来一肚子恐怖和疑心，顿时飞出九霄之外，赶快过去将她抱了起来，温存了一会儿。她也从眼涕里笑了出来，好比阳光照着晶莹的涧水。

她轻轻用手拍着他脸子，私语道：“你离不了我，你舍不得我。”他毅然决然连肚肠角角里所有的疑惧一齐消灭——因为他曾经想他新娘或者是鬼怪的变相。但是还有一句话，他忍不住问她——

“涡堤孩我爱，告诉我一件事，那牧师敲门的时候，你说什么地鬼，又是什么枯尔庞，究竟什么意思？”

“童话！童话！”涡堤孩说，她笑将起来，重新又乐了。“开头我吓你，收梢你吓我。这算是尾声，也是结束我们新婚夜！”

“不是，这哪里是收梢。”骑士说着，早已神魂飞荡。他吹灭了烛，涡堤孩先要开口，她一朵樱桃早已被他紧紧噙住，害她气都透不过来。恰好月光如泻照着这一对情人喜孜孜地进房归寝。

第十章　他们在城中居住的情形

黑尔勃郎骑士的失踪早已传遍皇城，所有曾经瞻仰过他的风采或是见过他比艺的人都觉得非常忧虑。他的仆人还在城里守着，但是谁也没有胆子进林去冒险寻他，接着又是大水为灾，骑士依旧音信毫无，人人都以为他已遭不幸，培儿托达也自悲蹇运，懊悔当初不该诱他进林探险。她的养父母公爵和爵夫人要来领她回家，但是她劝他们陪她一起，住在城里等骑士是死是生有了确实消息再说。同时另外有许多骑士也和她相识，她也怂恿他们进森林。但是她希望黑尔勃郎生回，所以不敢冒昧以身许人。因此她的悬赏无非是缎带、手套，至多不过一吻，谁也不愿意用性命去拼，而况去寻他们自己的情敌呢？

所以等到黑尔勃郎突然回来，他的仆人不用说，所有城里的居民，单除了培儿托达，没有一个不惊喜交集。尤其因为他带回了一个绝美的新娘，哈哀尔孟神父证婚，大家更觉得高兴，但是培儿托达别有一腔心事，万分忧急。第一因为她到这个时候实在一心一意地爱这青年的骑士，再兼之他失踪期内她焦急的情形大家知道，如今骑士带了妻子回来，大家更要注意她的态度。但是她行为非常大方，丝毫不露痕迹，待涡堤孩也很和气。讲到涡堤孩，人家都以为是哪里国王的公主大概被什么术士咒禁在森林里，此次被骑士救了出来。他们要是再问下去，这对小夫妻或是不答或是将话岔了开去。牧师的口也是金人三缄，并且黑尔勃郎一到就叫人送他回修道院去，所以再也没有人泄露真情，大家只得瞎猜算数，就是培儿托达也想不出其中奥妙。

涡堤孩同培儿托达的交情一天密如一天。她总说：“我们从前一定相识，否则你我之间定有一种很深妙的同情连锁，因为若然没有隐秘的理由，我决计不会得初次见面就这样亲切地爱你。”培儿托达也承认她一见涡堤孩就发生奇样的感情，虽然表面涡堤孩似乎是她得胜的情敌。她们两个人一密切就不愿意分离，一个劝她的养父母，一个劝她的丈夫，大家暂缓行期。后来甚至提议培儿托达送涡堤孩到林斯推顿城堡，在但牛勃河的发源处。

一天愉快的晚上，他们在皇城市场上徘徊，周围都是高树，商量动身的事。时候已经不早，三人尽在星光下散步闲谈，市场中间有一石坛上面一个绝大的喷泉，雕刻也很美丽，水声奔洒沥淅，好比音乐一般，他们看着都说好。树影的背后露出附近人家的光亮，一面一群小孩在那里玩耍，其余偶尔路过的人也很快活。他们三个人说说笑笑，非常得意，日间他们讲起这事似乎觉得还有问题，但是现在一谈，所有困难都完美解决，培儿托达定当和他们同行。但是他们光在那里决定哪一天动身，忽然一个身量高大的人从市场中间走近他们，向他们很客气地鞠了一躬，往涡堤孩耳边轻轻说了句话。她虽然很不愿意这人来打断他们话头，她还是跟了他走开几步，他们开始用很古怪的言语谈话。黑尔勃郎猛然觉得曾经见过这人，他瞪着眼尽向他望出了神，一面培儿托达不懂怎么一回事，很慌张地问他，他也没有听见。一会儿涡堤孩很高兴地拍拍手走了回来。那人一路点头匆匆地退后，走入喷泉里面去了。如今黑尔勃郎心里想他已经明白这意思，但是培儿托达问道：“亲爱的涡堤孩，那‘喷泉人’问你要什么？”

涡堤孩很奥妙地笑着，回答说：“后天你生日你就知道了，你这可爱的孩子！”她再也不能多说。她请培儿托达和她的养父母那天吃饭，他们就分别了。

培儿托达一走开，黑尔勃郎就问他妻子：“枯尔庞吗？”不觉打了一个寒噤，他们慢慢从黑暗的街上走回了家去。

涡堤孩答道：“是的，是他，他想出种种诡计要费我的时光。但是他今夜可告诉我一件事，我听了很欢喜。假使你一定立刻要知道这新闻，我亲爱的主公，你只要命令一声，我就一字不遗地讲给你听。但是你若然愿意给你的涡堤孩一个很大很大的欢喜，请你等到后天，听我出其不意当众报告。”

骑士乐得做个人情，当时也就不追问。那天晚上涡堤孩睡梦中，还在那里呓语道：“后天她要知道了这‘喷泉人’的新闻，培儿托达这孩子不知道是多少欢喜，多少惊异哩！”

第十二章　他们从皇城动身旅行

林斯推顿的爵士（黑尔勃郎）并不愿意那天纷乱的情形。但是事实上既已如此，他反而觉得很满意，因为他的娇妻临事如此忠实、恳切、尊严。他心里想：“如其我果然给了她一个灵魂，我给她一个比我自己的还强些。”他所以赶快来慰藉悲伤的涡堤孩，打算明天就动身，因为出了这桩事体以后，她对于这地方也不会再有多大兴趣。但是舆情对于她还是没有改变。非常事实的发现往往有些预兆，所以培儿托达来源的证明也没有引起多大的惊异，众人很多反对她，因为那天她行为过于暴烈。但是他们夫妻不很知道这情形。他们再也不愿多麻烦，所以三十六策走为上策。

明天一早一驾清洁的马车已经在客寓门口等涡堤孩。黑尔勃郎和他从人的马也都预备好了。骑士刚领着他夫人走出门来，一个渔装女郎走了上来。

黑尔勃郎说道：“我们不要你的货，我们正在动身。”

女郎啜泣起来，他们才觉察她是培儿托达。他们领了她重新进去，一问才知道公爵夫妇怪她那天行为过于焦躁，不愿意继续养她，虽然给了她一份很厚的嫁奁。渔人夫妇受了他们奖赏，那天晚上已经回他们天地去了。

“我想跟他们同回去，”她接着说，“但这老渔人，人家说他是我父亲——”

“他们说的不错，培儿托达，”涡堤孩插口道，“那天你以为‘喷泉人’者确实对我说的。他叫我不要领你一起回林斯推顿城堡去，所以他泄露这机密。”

“然则，”培儿托达说，“我的父——既然如此——我的父说道：‘我不要你，除非你脾气改过。你要跟我们独身穿过这树林，那才证明你爱我们。但是不要再摆女爵主架子，你要来就是个渔娘。’我很想听他吩咐，因为全世界都已经不认识我，我愿意和我穷苦的父母独自过一世渔家女的生活。但是，老实说，我实在不敢进森林去。里面多是妖精鬼怪，我又如此胆小。但是有什么办法呢？我此时无非来向林斯推顿的贵妇赔罪，求她饶恕我前天种种无礼。夫人呀！我知道你是一番好意，但是你不知道我听了你的话好像受伤一样，我又骇又怒，忍不住滚出了许多鲁莽疯狂的说话。宽恕我吧！宽恕我吧！我是如此十分倒运。你只要替我设身处地想想，昨天开宴之前，我是如何身份，但是我今天呢？”

她涕泗滂沱说了这一番话，她的手抱住了涡堤孩的项颈。她也感动得半晌说不出话来，但是末了她说——

“你跟我们一起到林斯推顿去吧，一切都照我们前天的预算，只要你仍旧叫我的名字，不要什么夫人呀、贵妇呀闹不清楚。你要知道我们从小的时候彼此交换，但是从今以后我们住在一起，再没有人力能够分散我们。但是第一件事就是你陪我们去林斯推顿。我们犹如姊妹一样，有福同享，快在此决定吧。”

培儿托达满面羞容瞟过眼去望着黑尔勃郎。他看她受了这样委屈，早动了恻隐之心，连忙伸出手来挽住了她，亲亲切切地请她放心，他们夫妇总不会亏待她。

他说：“我们会派人去关照你父母为什么你不回家。”他接着替那对老夫妇想法子，但是他觉得培儿托达一听见提起她父母就双眉紧蹙，他就将话岔了开去，再也不提。他就携着她手，送她上车，其次涡堤孩，自己骑上马，并着她们的车欣欣上路，一会儿出了皇城，将种种不快意的经历一起弃在后面。二位女眷坐在车上也说说笑笑，吸着新鲜空气，浏览着乡间景色。

赶了几天路程，他们一天傍晚到了林斯推顿的城堡。所有的侍从一齐上来拥住了他们幼主，交待一切，所以涡堤孩独自和培儿托达一起。她们爬上了堡塞的高墙，赏玩下面希华皮亚的景色。忽然一个高人走了上来，对她们恭恭敬敬行了个礼，培儿托达猛然记起了那晚皇城市场上所见的喷泉人。涡堤孩旋过去向他一看，露出不愿意带着威吓的神色，培儿托达想一定就是那怪，正在惊疑，那人一路点头，匆匆退下，隐入邻近一座灌木林中去了。但是涡堤孩说道：“不要怕，亲爱的小培儿托达，这一次他再也不会来缠你了。”

她于是从头至尾将这段故事一齐讲了出来，她自己是谁，培儿托达如何离开她的父母，她自己如何到他们那里去。培儿托达开头听了很吓，她以为她朋友忽然疯了，但是她愈听愈信，恍然明白。她想想真奇怪，从小听见的荒唐故事，如今非但亲身经历，而且自身受了一二十年的播弄，方才打破这谜。她很尊敬地看着涡堤孩，但是禁不住发了一个寒噤，总觉得她是异类。一直等到他们坐下吃夜饭，她心里还在那里疑虑黑尔勃郎如何会得同鬼怪一类东西发生恋爱。

第十三章　他们居住在林斯推顿城堡时的情形

写下这故事来的人，因为他自己心里很受感动，所以希望人家看了也可以一样感动，但是他要向读者诸君道一个歉。他要请你们原谅，如其他现在用很简的话报告你们在一长时期内所发生的事件。他明知道他很可以描写如何一步一步黑尔勃郎的爱情渐渐从涡堤孩移到培儿托达，如何培儿托达的热度逐渐增高和他做爱，如何他们合起非但不可怜涡堤孩，而且视为异族，逐渐地疏忽她，如何涡堤孩悲伤，如何她的眼泪和骑士良心上戳刺，再也不能回复他从前对她的恋爱，所以虽然他有时对她还和气，一会儿又发了一个寒噤，抛开了她，去和真人的女郎培儿托达寻欢谈爱。作者很知道这几点都可以，并且也许是应该，从详叙述，但是他心肠硬不起来，因为他生平也有过同样的经验，如今想起了，心里还像锥刺，眼泪如面条一般挂将下来，何况动手来写呢？亲爱的读者呀！大概你们也免不了有同样的感觉吧？人世间的趣味原应该用痛苦来测量。假使你在这行业里面，你所得的痛苦比你给人的痛苦来得多，你就赚了钱，发了财。因为在这类情形之下，所有唯一的感觉，无非你灵魂中心窝里蜿蜒着几丝蜜甜的悲伤，精美的幽郁，或者你想到了那一处园里湖上从前是你销魂的背景，如今都如梦如寐，渺若山河，你鼻脊里就发出一阵奇酸，两朵水晶似泪花，从眼眶里突了出来，慢慢在你双颊上开了两条水沟。好了，我也不再多说下去，我并不愿意将你们的心刺成千疮百孔，让我言归正传，简简地接着讲吧。

可怜的涡堤孩异常悲伤，而他们两个也并不真正快乐，但是培儿托达还不满意。她于是逐渐地专制跋扈起来，涡堤孩总是退让，再加之一个情热的黑尔勃郎处处总袒护她。同时城堡里生活也反常起来，到处有鬼灵出现，黑尔勃郎和培儿托达时常碰到，但是以前从来也没有听见过。那个高白人，黑尔勃郎是很熟悉了，认识是枯尔庞，培儿托达也知是喷泉怪，也时常在他们二人跟前出现恫吓，尤其欺凌培儿托达，她有一次甚至吓得害病，所以她时常决意要离开这城堡。但是她依旧住下去，一部分为她恋爱黑尔勃郎，一部分因为她自恃清白，就有鬼怪也没奈何她，并且她也不知道往哪里去好。这老渔人自从接到了林斯推顿爵士的信告诉他培儿托达和他一起住着，他就乱七八糟写了一封回信，他一辈子也不知写过几封信，他的文字之难读可想而知。他信里说道——

“我现在变了一个孤身老头，因为我亲爱忠信的妻子已经到上帝那里去了。但是我虽然寂寞！我情愿有培儿托达的空房不希望她回来。只要你警戒她不要伤损我亲爱的涡堤孩，否则我就咒她。”

这几句话培儿托达只当耳边风，但是她可记得她父亲叫她住在外面，这种情形本来很普通的。

有一天黑尔勃郎骑马去了，涡堤孩召集了家里的仆役，吩咐他们去拿一大块石头来盖塞了堡庭中间华美的喷泉。仆役们抗议因为喷泉塞住了，他们要到下边山石里去取水。涡堤孩显出忧伤的笑容，说道——

“我很抱歉使你们要多忙些，我很情愿自己下山去取水，但是这喷泉非关塞不可。听我的话，再没有旁的办法。我们虽然有些不方便，但是我们可以免了很大的不幸。”

所有的仆役都高兴女主人如此和气诚恳，他们再也不抗议，一齐下去扛了一块大的石块上来。他们刚放下地，预备去盖住泉眼，培儿托达跑将过来，喊着止住他们。她每天自己也用这泉水洗涤，所以她不答应将它关塞。但是平常虽然总是涡堤孩让步，这一步她却不放松。她说她既然是一家的主妇，一切家里的布置当然要照她吩咐，除了爵主以外她不准第二人干涉。

“但是你看，哼！看吧！”培儿托达叫道，又恼又急——“看，这可怜的水缠绕地喷着，似乎它知道要遭劫，它再也不得见阳光，再也不能像镜子似的反照人面。”她正说着，这水突然高冲，发出尖利的响，好像有东西在里面挣扎着要冲出来似的，但是涡堤孩益发坚定地命令立刻下手封盖。这班下人很愿意一面讨好女主人，一面惹怒培儿托达，也不管她大声狂吼恫吓，他们七手八脚一会儿将这泉口掩住。涡堤孩倚在上面沉思了一会儿，伸出她尖尖的玉指在石面上写了好些。但是她一定在手中藏着一种尖利的器具，因为她一走开，人家过去看的时候只见上面刻着种种奇形的文字，谁都不认识。

黑尔勃郎晚上回家，培儿托达接住了他，淌着眼泪抱怨涡堤孩的行径。他怒目向着他妻子，但是她，可怜的涡堤孩，很忧伤地敛下了她的眼睫。然后她平心静气地说道——

“我的主公和丈夫，就是定罪，一奴仆也给他一声辩的机会。何况他自己正式的妻子呢？”

“那么你说，为什么你有这样奇异行为？”骑士说着，满面霜气。

涡堤孩叹口气说道：“我不能在人前对你说。”

他答道：“培儿托达在这里你告诉我还不是一样？”

“是，假使你如此命令我，”涡堤孩说，“但是你不要命令。我求恳你，不要如此命令。”

她说得又谦卑，又和气，又顺从，骑士的心里忽然回复了从前快乐日子的一线阳光。他执住了她的手，引她到他的房里，她于是说道——

“你知道我们凶恶的枯尔庞伯父，我亲爱的主公，你也时常在堡塞的廊下受他的烦扰，是不是？他有时甚至将培儿托达吓出病来。看起来他并没有灵魂，他无非是一个外界原行的镜子，在这里面照不出内部的境界。他只见你时常和我不和睦，见我一个人为此时常哭泣，见培儿托达偏拣那个时候欢笑。结果是他想象了许多愚笨的见解，要动手来干涉我们。我就是抱怨他叫他走，又有什么用？他完全不相信我的话。他卑微的本性估量不到爱情的苦乐有这样的密切关系，两件事差不多就是一件事，要分开他们是不成功的。笑是从泪湿的心里出来，泪是从喜笑的眼里出来。”

她仰起来望着黑尔勃郎，娇啼欢笑，一霎那从前恋爱的速力又充满了骑士的心坎。她也觉得，将他搂紧在胸前，依旧淌着欢喜的眼泪接着说道——

“既然扰乱治安的人不肯听话，我没有法想，只得将门堵住不许他再进来。而他接近我们唯一的路就是那喷泉。他和邻近的水灵都有仇怨。从再过去的一个山谷，一直到但牛勃河如其他的亲知流入那河，那边又是他的势力范围了。所以我决定将喷泉封盖起，我在上面还写着符咒，如此他也不会来干涉你，或是我，或是培儿托达。固然只要小小用些人力就可以将那块石盖移去，又没有什么拦阻。假使你愿意，尽管照培儿托达主意做去，但是你要知道她再也想不到她执意要的是什么东西。枯尔庞那福（祸）根尤其特别注意她，要是他时常对我所预言的果然有朝发现，难说得很，我爱，要知道事体不是儿戏呢！”

黑尔勃郎听了很感激他妻子的大量，她想尽种种方法，将她自己的亲人摒斥，为的非但是一家的安宁，并且也体谅到培儿托达。

他将她抱入怀中很动感情地说道：“那块石头准它放上，从此谁也不许移动，一切听你，我最甜美的小涡堤孩。”

她也软软地抱紧他，心里觉得天堂似的快乐，因为夫妻生疏了好久，难得又听见了这样爱膏情饯的口吻。二人着实绸缪了一下，最后她说道——

“我最亲爱的一个，你今天既然这样甜美温和，可否让我再恳一个情？你只要自己知道，你同夏天一样，就是阳光照耀的时光，说不定云章一扯起，风雨雷电立刻就到眼前。这固然是自然的威灵，犹之人间的帝王。你近来动不动就发脾气，开口看人都是严厉得很，那固然很合你身份，虽然我总免不了孩子气，往往一个人哭泣，但是请你从今以后千万不要在近水地方和我发气，因为水里都是我的亲戚，他们无知无识只见我被人欺凌就要来干涉，他们有力量将我劫了回去，那时我再也不得出头，这一辈子就离不了水晶宫殿，再也不能和你见面，就是他们再将我送回来，那时我更不知如何情形。所以求你，我的甜心，千万不要让这类事发生，因为你爱你可怜的涡堤孩。”

他郑重答应听她的话，于是夫妇一同走出房来，说不尽的畅快，彼此充满了恋爱。培儿托达走过来，带了好几个工人，一脸怒容说道——

“算了，秘密会议已经完毕，石头也可以搬走了。去，你们去扛下来。”

但是骑士很不满意她如此跋扈，放了脸子，简简说道：“石头准她盖上。”他接着说培儿托达不应与涡堤孩龌龊。那群工人一看如此形景，暗暗好笑，各自搭讪着走了开去。培儿托达气得面色发青，旋转身奔向她自己房中去了。

晚饭时间到了，培儿托达还不出来。他们就差人去看她，但是她房中空空，只留下一封信给骑士。他骇然拆封，读道——

“渔家贱婢，安敢忘形。孟浪之罪，无可祷也。径去穷舍，忏悔余生。夫人美慧，君福无涯。”

涡堤孩深为愁闷。她很热心地催黑尔勃郎赶快去寻回他们的逃友。其实何必她着急呢？他从前对培儿托达的感情重新又醒了过来。他立刻电掣似的遍查堡内，问有人曾见女郎下山否。大家都不知道，他已经在庭中上了马，预备沿着他们当初来路寻去。刚巧有人上山来报告说，有一女郎下山，向“黑谷”而去。箭离弦似的，骑士已经驰出了堡门，往“黑谷”追去，再也听不见窗口涡堤孩很焦急地喊道——

“到黑谷去吗？不是那边，黑尔勃郎，不是那边！就是要去也领我同去！”

但是他早已影踪毫无，她赶快叫人预备她的小马，放足缰绳，独自追他去了。

第十八章　黑尔勃郎举行婚礼的情形

黑尔勃郎和培儿托达举行婚礼那一天，林斯推顿城堡中贵客到了不少，外面看来，很是热闹欢喜，但是当事人的心里，恰有一种说不出的不舒服，良心上不安宁。出神见鬼的事倒没有，因为那喷池依旧塞住，枯尔庞的徒党无从进身。新郎自己不用说，就是老渔人乃至于曾经见过涡堤孩的亲友，都觉得似乎少了一个主要人物，因为涡堤孩在时待人和善得众人欢心，如今不明不白地失了踪，偏是隔上不多时发现了这头亲事，也难怪旁人心里一半诧异一半不平。那天喜筵的时候大家表面上虽然应酬谈笑，心里谁也离不了涡堤孩的印象，偶然呀的一声有人推门进来，大家都张皇注视，疑心是涡堤孩来了，等得看明白进来的人是掌礼或是酒仆，他们都显出失望的神情，本来满席的笑语喧闹，也忽然沉了下去，变成忧郁的寂静。新娘要算最活泼，最满足，但是连她也有时觉得有些诧异这林斯推顿堡内主妇一席如何轮到了她，一面又想起涡堤孩冰冷的尸体，僵卧在但牛勃河底，或是已经随流入海不知去向。神父那番不吉利的警告又不住地在他们三人脑筋中烦扰，并且引起种种奇异的幻想。

天还没有黑喜筵就散了，不是因为新郎不耐烦——普通新郎总是不耐烦的——而为上面所说的几层缘故，宾主都觉得有兴不能尽，空气中似乎布满了不愉快的预兆、愁惨的情景。培儿托达陪着女客去了，骑士也进内室，一群侍从侍候他换衣服。那天结婚连照例跟随新娘新郎的一群青年男女都没有。

培儿托达想变换她思想的潮流。她吩咐侍女展览黑尔勃郎此次替她预备的衣服面网首饰，打算选出几件，预备明日晓妆。一群侍女就高高兴兴来出主意，这个说新娘应该满头珠翠红衣绿袜，那个说太华丽了也不好，不如单戴白金珠花的面网和白缎银镶的衣裙，配着淡灰丝袜和绿丝绒鞋，一面大家又争着称赞新娘的貌美。培儿托达正在镜里端详自己的倩影，忽然叹道：“但是你们难道没看见这边颈上那些雀斑吗？”

她们一看，果然新娘左边颈皮上有几块黑影子，但是她们只说是“美人斑”，有了这一丝深色，愈显出肤色之白嫩。培儿托达摇摇头，心里想那总是斑点。

她叹口气道：“其实我可以想法子去了它。但是堡庭里的喷泉封闭在那里，从前我总欢喜用那泉水，很有匀净肤色的功效。真的，我只要弄得到一小瓶已经足够！”

“那就够了吗？”一个快捷的侍女笑道，说着溜了出去。

“她总不会得那样冒昧，”培儿托达说，露出半惊半喜的神情，“今天晚上就去撇开那块盖住泉眼的石头吧？”但是一阵子她们就听见一群人走入堡庭，从窗格里望得见那活泼的侍女领头，他们扛着杠杆等类，去重开那喷泉。培儿托达说道：“我实在很愿意他们去打开，只要手续不太麻烦时间不过长就没有什么。”她心里其实很得意，因为如今做了主妇，居然要什么就有什么，开口要闭口到，她欣欣伏在窗口，看他们在庭中月光底下动手。

那群人“杭好旱好”使尽气力，开掘那石块。间或有人叹息，以为旧主妇当初一番心机，如今新主妇当家，头一天就有变更。但是事实上他们用不到费那么大劲。因为等得他们一动手，这喷泉内部似乎有势力帮着他们掀开那块笨石。他们骇然相顾说道：“难道这喷泉压得日久，力量大得连石头都冲得动？”说着，那石块愈起愈高，简直自做主，不用人力轻轻地滚了下来。同时泉眼里迸出一个极高的白水柱。工人们在旁边正在惊异，忽然觉察这水柱变成了一个素衣缟服白网盖面的妇人。她涕泗交流地悲泣，举起双手摇着表示哀痛，慢慢儿，慢慢儿下了喷泉台，往城堡正屋走去。一霎时堡里的人吓得狂奔的狂奔，狂叫的狂叫，新娘在窗内也吓得硬挺挺站着，面无人色，她身旁的侍女也都像触了电一般，动弹不得。等得这形象走近了她房，培儿托达猛然觉得那白网底下的眉目仿佛是涡堤孩。但是这一路悲泣的形象走了过去，迟顿顿，慢吞吞，似乎犯人上刑场的光景。培儿托达高声喊人去寻骑士，但是侍女们只突出一双眼呆看，理也不理，新娘也发了噤，似乎她自己的声音骇住了她。

她们正在石像似的塑着，话也说不出，脚也移不动，这可怕的异客已经走到了城堡正厅，步上那白石的台阶，走进大堂，哀哀地哭，一路尽哭着。伤哉！她初次来到此地何等欢喜呢？

其时骑士在内室已经辞退了侍从。他衣服半解，独自站在一座大衣镜前出神，旁边点着一支很缓的小烛。忽然门上有一个小指弹着，很轻地弹着，那是当初他们夫妻和睦时候的一种记号，涡堤孩要他去的时候，就来用小指轻轻弹门。黑尔勃郎跳将起来，但是他又自语道：“这无非是妄想。我应该登新床去了。”

“是的，你应该，但是一张冷床而已！”他听得门外一个悲泣的声音回答，他从镜子里看见门开了，慢慢儿，慢慢儿，这白色游行的形象移了进来，重复谨谨慎慎将门掩上。“他们已经将喷泉打开，”她软软说道，“如今我已到此，你生命完尽了。”

他觉得他的心停止了跳动，知道数不可逃，但他将手掩面说道——

“不要使我死于恐怖。如其你网后是一鬼相，那就请你不必再揭开，你一下杀了我就算，再不要让我见你。”

“唉！”这形象答道，“难道你不愿意再对我一看吗？我依旧和初次你在湖边发现我的辰光一样美丽，我爱，哟！你还怕我来吓你不成？”

“哟，但愿如此，”黑尔勃郎叹道，“但愿我能死在你吻上！”

“当然，只要你愿意，我最爱的亲亲呀！”她说着，就将手揭去了面罩，一张蜜甜的脸笑了出来，顿时室内好像充满了万道霞光。

恋爱——死！骑士浑身战栗，无量数的情电子从骨髓皮肉五脏六腑四肢百骸里迸射出来，将他的生命灵魂躯壳，一股脑儿地恋爱化——他浑身战栗，展开双手，涡堤孩直扑了进来，泪如泉涌，两片香甜情热颤动的樱唇立刻和骑士的黏在一起，她再也不放，愈搂愈紧，愈紧愈搂，眼泪如潮水般横流，几乎将她的灵魂都冲了出来。她的眼泪泻满他一脸一胸，他还是紧紧抱着，直等到骑士在甜美的不幸中，蜜甜的香唇上，气绝身亡，从她可爱的玉臂圈中漏出，倒卧在长眠的榻上。

“我已经哭死了他。”涡堤孩告诉她在前房碰到的侍役，她慢慢从惶骇无措的人群中走入喷泉中去了。

第十九章　骑士黑尔勃郎埋葬的情形

林斯推顿爵主的死讯一传出去，头一个到门的就是那等办丧事的神父哈哀尔孟，刚巧上一天特请来结婚的牧师仓皇逃走，二人在大门口撞一个满怀。

神父听他们说了详情以后说道：“命该如此，这丧礼如今落在老人身上，我也不要什么伙伴。”他就过去用例话安慰那新娘寡妇，但是培儿托达尘心烦重，如何能听得进老牧师不入耳之谈。老渔翁倒很明白，虽然他女婿女儿遭此不幸，他也不免悲悼，但当培儿托达咒骂涡堤孩为女妖鬼怪时，老人总摇头叹道：“这场公案也只有如此了结一法。我只看见上帝公平的判决，况且，黑尔勃郎死后受苦痛最深者无过执行死刑那人，我们可怜被摒的涡堤孩。”他帮着料理丧务，一切排场都按照死者的身份。他们林斯推顿家的葬地在邻近一乡村，是他们的领地，骑士的尸体照例要与他的祖先合葬。城堡里所有的仪仗都已排列起来，预备一起葬人，因为黑尔勃郎是林司推顿的末裔，送葬的人也都跟着棺柩上路，在青天底下迤逦走着，口里唱丧歌，神父哈哀尔孟手执一高大的十字架在前领路，后面跟着培儿托达，她父亲老渔人在旁边扶住她。其时大家忽然觉察培儿托达的侍从一片黑服中间，发现了一个雪白的形象，头面罩得很密，双手绞扭显出极端痛苦悲伤。那形象旁边的人都暗暗吃吓，或向旁闪，或往后退，她们这么一动，那白像又发现在后面一群人中间，他们又起恐慌，纷纷躲避，所以结果这长串送殡的仪从，闹得不成体统。其中有几个军士胆子很大，走近去向那白影说话，想将她推挤出去，但是他们的手一触到，形象就融灭，一转眼又只见她于于徐徐跟在丧会中进行。直到后来所有的女侍从都逃避干净，所以这白影悠悠荡荡贴紧了培儿托达。但是她移得很慢，前面的新孀简直没有觉得，自此她缓缓跟着前进。

他们到了墓地，所有的丧仪和人列成圆形围住墓坑。培儿托达方才觉到了这不速之客，她又骇又恼将身倒退，要她离开骑士的葬所。但是罩面的白影轻轻摇头不允，伸手向着培儿托达似乎款求的模样，孀妇不禁感动，她顿时想起了从前涡堤孩待她的好处，和在但牛勃河上给她那串珊瑚项珠。但是神父哈哀尔孟吩咐禁声，大家一起在尸体前默祷。培儿托达跪了下来，其余送葬的人连坟上做工的也都跪下。他们祷完站起来的时候，白色的异客已经不见，在她跪的一点上忽然从泥土里涌起一柱珠泉，洁白如银，将骑士的新坟浇洒一周，然后平流到墓地旁边，积成一个美丽的小潭。后世那村上的人还时常对着这泉水嗟叹，相信是可怜的涡堤孩的不昧精灵，展开她仁爱的手臂永远抱住她心爱的人。

译者序

普拉斯诗集《艾丽尔》的真相探析

引言

美国当代女性诗人西尔维娅·普拉斯（Sylvia Plath，1932—1963）是继艾米莉·狄金森（Emily Dickinson，1830—1886）后美国文学史上最有影响力的女诗人，一直被视为美国自白派诗人的重要代表人物。诗人生前只出版过一部诗集《巨人及其他诗歌》（The Colossus and Other Poems，1962）和一部自传体小说《钟形罩》（The Bell Jar，1963），小说被誉为第一部塞林格风格的女性小说。1981年由诗人的丈夫、英国桂冠诗人特德·休斯（Ted Hughes，1930—1998）编辑出版普拉斯《诗全集》（The Collected Poems），共收录诗人短暂一生所创作的二百七十四首诗，该书获得1982年的普利策诗歌奖，普拉斯成为身后获得此奖的第一人。《诗全集》显示了“普拉斯为何改变了当代诗歌的方向，所有的诗歌，不仅仅是女性创作的诗歌”。[1]美国学者伊莱恩·肖沃尔特（Elaine Showalter）赞誉普拉斯为“20世纪美国的偶像人物，女性诗人”。[2]普拉斯成为“20世纪英美文学和文化的领军人物之一”。[3]

后期诗集《艾丽尔》（Ariel）是诗人自尽两年后，由休斯编辑，最早于1965年在英国出版，次年在美国出版。《艾丽尔》是普拉斯成就最高、最有影响的诗集。诗人在《艾丽尔》诗集中采用了当时流行的第一人称“我”的言说者，用生活中的事件作为想象和主题发展的开始，运用灵活多样的诗歌艺术表现手法，将个人经历的梦幻和历史事件的记忆转化成戏剧性的表现，塑造了丰富多彩、性格各异的女性人物形象。诗集展示了这些女性人物力争彻底改变自我、构建女性主体和寻求性别写作身份的艰难历程。《艾丽尔》诗集中的诗句法清晰简单，韵律动听，意象生动，灵活多变的意象与声音相互作用，而诗中的真实意义却隐而不露。鲜活的意象和强烈的韵律形成了诗人独特的诗学声音和诗学意义，展示了她后期诗歌的独创性和诗艺的精湛技巧，标志着诗人诗歌创作的顶峰成就，诗集《艾丽尔》成为英美诗坛的经典之作，对美国女权运动的第二次浪潮产生了巨大的影响。诗集《艾丽尔》对当代美国诗歌具有持久的影响力：“在二十年中，《艾丽尔》与《荒原》一起成为20世纪英语诗歌的杰作。”[4]

然而，诗集《艾丽尔》有两种不同的版本，最早与英美读者见面的《艾丽尔》诗集是由诗人丈夫休斯编辑出版的英美版，而诗人生前自己编排的版本到2004年才由其女儿弗丽达·休斯（Frieda Hughes）编辑出版，两种诗集前后出版时间相距达四十年之久。这两种不同版本的诗集给普拉斯研究带来了不同的影响，探究其背后的真相具有重要的诗学意义。

一、休斯编辑出版的《艾丽尔》诗集（英美版）

1963年，伦敦五十年间最冷的冬天，普拉斯忧郁症加重，2月11日上午九时她被发现开煤气自杀身亡在她与孩子居住的伦敦公寓里。两年后的1965年，由休斯编辑并作序的诗集《艾丽尔》在英国出版，共收录了四十首诗；第二年在美国出版，在英国版的基础上增加了三首诗，共收录四十三首诗，由美国著名自白派诗人、普拉斯在波士顿诗歌讲习班的教师罗伯特·洛威尔（Robert Lowell）作序。英美两个版本的共同特点是，诗集的最后收录了普拉斯在生命最后十天内写的四首诗，其次序是：《仁慈》（“Kindness”）、《瘀伤》（“Contusion”）、《边缘》（“Edge”）和《词语》（“Words”）。

创作于1963年2月1日的《仁慈》是一首讽喻诗，由四节五行诗组成。全诗以“仁慈夫人”的视角来审视言说女子的家庭生活。诗中的言说女子不仅在家辛苦忙碌地照顾孩子，还是一位有强烈诗歌创作欲望的母亲。《仁慈》最后一节包含了普拉斯的著名诗句：“诗是血的喷涌，/根本无法停止。”[5]普拉斯一直挣扎于传统慈母与职业诗人这两种截然不同的角色之间，而诗歌创作对于普拉斯而言是生命中最重要的部分，犹如人体的心脏不停地给全身提供生命之血液。与《仁慈》创作于同一天的是《词语》一诗，英美版《艾丽尔》诗集的最后一首诗，由四节五行诗组成。《词语》全诗以“现在”与“将来”时间的跨越分为两部分，在第一部分“现在”中，诗人将“创作”比作“斧子砍伐于树”，而发出的回声就是诗。第二部分“将来”描写多年之后“我”再读这些诗，感叹词语已经干枯，毫无意义，如同树的回声已经销声匿迹。诗的最后一节预言“词语”永恒的力量：“词语干枯，马背无人，/只有永不怠倦的马蹄声/而/不变的星辰，从水池底映出/主宰生命。”[6]“不变的星辰”，诗中最后一个意象，成为诗歌命运的主宰者。此诗显示了诗人借助于诗歌创作，让自我增添新的活力和希望，也是诗人对自己所创作诗歌命运的思考。

英美版《艾丽尔》诗集中的倒数第三首诗《瘀伤》写于1963年2月4日，由四节三行诗、共五十八个词组成。诗第一节描写已死女子的躯体：“颜色涌出斑点，暗紫色。/身体全部被冲洗干净，/珍珠般的颜色。”在诗的结尾，“瘀伤”，受伤心灵的外在表现，最终导致了极度的悲伤和绝望：“心房关闭，/海水退潮，/床单覆盖多重镜子。”[7]此诗简短却给读者展示了停滞、死亡、荒凉，一切都归于寂静的凄凉情景。诗集最后第二首诗《边缘》创作于2月5日，直接描写“完美女子”的死亡：“这个女子完美无缺。/她已死的//身体带着圆满的微笑。”[8]一切都已经结束，在诗人奇特的隐喻中，死去的女人变成了玫瑰花，她的孩子变成了花瓣，母亲将他们折叠送回她的身体。《边缘》暗示了作为女人的普拉斯在生命的边缘，放弃生命回归大自然才是希腊式的自然规律。

英美版《艾丽尔》诗集最后的四首诗给读者传递了这样的信息：作为诗人的普拉斯，其诗歌创作的才情已经耗尽，开始担心自己诗的命运；作为母亲、女人的普拉斯，其生命走到了尽头，放弃生命才是圆满的结局。20世纪60—70年代，评论家普遍视《艾丽尔》诗歌为自白诗，并对它们做自传性解读。英美版《艾丽尔》诗集刚出版时，编者并没有注明诗人创作这些诗的时间，普拉斯学者更多地关注这最后四首诗与诗人自杀的情形非常“吻合”，因此也就忽视了与《边缘》创作于同一天的《气球》（诗集倒数第六首），是诗人献给孩子们的爱，描写圣诞期间诗人家中颜色鲜艳、形状各异的气球，诗人将气球比作“诚实，清爽/椭圆的灵性动物”，“仿佛快乐的心充满希冀”[9]。这些圣诞期间陪伴孩子们的气球显然是流动在诗人心中冬天的希望、春天的生命。

二、普拉斯生前编排的《艾丽尔：修复版》诗集

1981年普拉斯《诗全集》出版，第二年此诗集荣获普利策诗歌奖，评论界一致公认普拉斯是她那个时代最杰出的诗人之一。《诗全集》收录了诗人在1956—1963年间创作的二百二十四首诗以及1956年之前少年时期创作的五十首诗。在“注释”中，编者休斯提供了普拉斯生前自己为出版诗集《艾丽尔》而准备的四十一首诗歌目录。[10]至此，有关《艾丽尔》诗集的真相大白，休斯对英美版《艾丽尔》诗集的出版做了任意删减和增加，使读者、普拉斯学者对诗集产生误读，也令这些诗蒙上阴影长达三十年之久。按照普拉斯生前自己安排的诗稿顺序，诗集《艾丽尔》以诗《晨歌》（“Morning Song”）的首句“爱将你送来像胖乎乎的金表”，赞美女儿的出生开始，以诗《过冬》（“Wintering”）的尾句“蜜蜂在飞，它们体味春天”结束。自成一体的“养蜂组诗”（“beekeeping poems”），也称为“蜜蜂组诗”（“bee poems”） 置于诗集最后，反映了诗人各种情感的纠结：孤独和疏远、怀疑和背叛、悲伤和骄傲。更为重要的是，“蜜蜂组诗”是女性创作能力、独立、自信和新生的象征，象征了女性独立生活的开始，象征了孕育女性诗歌创作的新阶段。

2004年11月，诗人的女儿弗丽达按照母亲生前留下的手稿重新出版《艾丽尔：修复版》（Ariel：The Restored Edition）并作序。此诗集恢复了普拉斯原有的诗选和诗歌顺序，还包括全部手稿的影印副本、诗集同名诗《艾丽尔》的全部修改手稿、诗人为BBC广播公司的节目而撰写的有关八首诗的评论文字等相关资料。诗集共收集四十首诗，比《诗全集》中的《艾丽尔》诗歌目录少一首诗《蜂群》（“The Swarm”），因为在诗人留下的手稿中，此诗是诗人用了括号的。弗丽达认为母亲的诗集《艾丽尔》叙说的故事与小说《钟形罩》有很多相似之处：一个年轻女子与自己的忧郁症做顽强的斗争，最后在婚姻破裂后艰难地开始重建独立的生活。因此《艾丽尔：修复版》是有关诗歌中女主人公“我”如何顽强抗争求生存的故事，不是有关诗人自杀、毁灭的故事。普拉斯对自己的诗集做这样的安排本身就有其重要的象征意义。正如弗丽达在前言中所言，首先，母亲“非常明显地从婚姻的破裂中调整自己的生活，以寻求一种新的生活，尽管带着伤痛和愤怒”。[11]其次，母亲在此时期的诗歌创作有别于前期的诗歌创作，她找到了真正属于自己的诗学声音，逐渐形成了自己新的风格并趋于完美。“这些诗是为耳朵写的，不是为眼睛写的，是大声地写出来的。这是它们的共同之处。”[12]

关于诗集的命名，普拉斯曾想用其他诗名《对手》（“The Rival”）、《捕兔陷阱》（“The Rabbit Catcher”）、《生日礼物》（“A Birthday Present”）或《爸爸》（“Daddy”）来命名，但是诗人自己清楚，若采用这些作为诗集名，诗集就指向了她破裂的婚姻、分居、对父亲的怨恨或其他个人因素。最后诗人决定用《艾丽尔》作为诗集名，这样的命名就将她个人生活的遭遇抛在了身后，她只想“强调艺术转变生活的力量”。[13]诗集名Ariel既指莎士比亚的作品《暴风雨》中的火之精灵“艾丽尔”，也指普拉斯于1962年住在英国德文郡时每周骑的雄性马的名字，而普拉斯自己在诗集同名诗的手稿右上端写着“lioness of God[14]”（“神之母狮”）。“Ariel”是“神之狮”（“lion of God”），这是出自《圣经》的典故，《以赛亚书》第29章，“Ariel”是指城市“耶路撒冷”，是“神的祭坛”（“altar/hearth of God”），是祭品被大火吞噬的地方。[15]普拉斯采用这个包含多重含义的“Ariel”作为诗集名，蕴含了重要的诗学意义，因为《艾丽尔》诗集在风格和主题上都超越了普拉斯早期的自白诗，展现了自己独特的风格。

1962年10月27日诗人为自己三十岁生日创作了《艾丽尔》，诗中骑马女子将自己与雄性马“艾丽尔”融为一体，不断变换的意象“白色的葛黛娃”“海的闪烁”“孩子的哭声”“露珠”“箭”“早晨的大锅”展示了骑马女子翻天覆地的变化，揭示了诗人寻求女性主体和诗人身份的艰难过程。普拉斯在创作《艾丽尔》诗集的过程中找到了自己的诗学声音，诗歌风格和创作技巧达到炉火纯青的水平。弗丽达在序言中说明，母亲在1962年11月中旬完成了《艾丽尔》诗集的手稿，放在一个黑色的弹簧活页夹里。写于11月14日的《死亡与伴侣》（“Death & Co.”）是母亲放入此诗集的最后一首诗歌。诗集完成后到诗人去世前的这段时间内，普拉斯为另一本新诗集创作了十九首诗，六首诗是她独自带着一双儿女从德文郡移居伦敦的公寓前创作的（12月12日前），还有十三首诗创作于1963年1月底至2月5日期间，是诗人生命中的遗作。不幸的是，诗人的忧郁症加重，夺走了她的生命，她没有等到《艾丽尔》诗集和新诗集的出版。

三、被休斯删除的“侵犯婚姻隐私”的七首诗

在编辑出版英美版《艾丽尔》诗集时，休斯将诗人置于诗集末尾的“养蜂组诗”更换成了普拉斯生前创作的最后四首诗，并将组诗移至诗集的中间位置。除了对诗集做这样的“篡改”，休斯还删去了普拉斯原先安排在诗集中的七首诗，第三首《捕兔陷阱》（“The Rabbit Catcher”），第九首《一个秘密》（“A Secret”），第十首《狱卒》（“The Jailer”），第十四首《侦探》（“The Detective”），第二十二首《闭嘴的勇气》（“The Courage of Shutting-Up”），第二十八首《深闺》（“Purdah”）和第三十二首《遗忘》（“Amnesiac”）。除了《捕兔陷阱》创作于1962年5月，其他六首诗都属于诗人著名的“十月诗”系列。普拉斯在1962年10月创作了著名的“十月诗”共二十五首，包括“蜜蜂组诗”五首、被休斯删去的六首诗以及普拉斯最著名的诗作《爸爸》（“Daddy”）、《美杜莎》（“Medusa”）、《高烧103度》（“Fever 103°”）、《艾丽尔》（“Ariel”）、《女拉撒路》（“Lady Lazarus”）等。休斯在普拉斯《全诗集》的前言中说这些诗“侵犯他的个人生活”，[16]指责普拉斯写那些诗践踏了不可将隐私和家庭生活爆料给公众审视的禁忌。

按照普拉斯《艾丽尔》诗集的顺序，《捕兔陷阱》是被删去的第一首诗。《捕兔陷阱》揭示了婚姻对女性的压制，《深闺》揭露了女性在婚姻中的隐身地位。在这两首诗中，诗人通过揭露现代社会中女性在婚姻关系中的不平等地位，描写了诗人对理想婚姻破灭的内心感受和挣扎，体现了诗人的女性主义思想。《一个秘密》描写一个“高级秘密”千方百计地要暴露，而另一位人物“你”却想阻止这个秘密的外泄，他好比阻止汽车通行的交通警察。秘密不太清晰，只是“淡淡的水印”，[17]难以辨认，但依然是泄露秘密的证据。《狱卒》挖掘的是“残暴狱卒与脆弱的囚犯之间的共生关系”，[18]诗人毫无掩饰地直接描写了言说女子在这个残暴狱卒的控制下遭遇的各种不幸和痛苦的折磨：“我会有各种死法——/被绞死，饿死，烧死，吊死。”[19]《侦探》是诗人著名的“十月诗”的第一首诗，诗人用“谋杀”来比喻“家庭犯罪”，从侦探的视角来调查发生在一所房子里的“谋杀案”。“家庭犯罪”对于普拉斯而言，最严重的莫过于在婚姻生活中“谋杀”女性的想象力和创作欲望，使其身份隐匿，使其思想消失。为惩罚女性“贪得无厌的嘴”，它“被挂起晾晒、风干”；身体被“凶手”的双手“筑成一堵墙”；[20]房子里的“谋杀案”不留痕迹，一切都被蒸发。

既然女性的想象力和创作欲望在传统婚姻中会被扼杀，那么女性保持沉默就是一种美德。《闭嘴的勇气》中诗人将“无声的嘴”与“有声的唱片”并置，闭嘴需要勇气，因为潜藏于沉默不语的表层之下是积聚压抑的满腔愤怒，不可缓解的痛苦记忆。“灌满的唱片”被比作“储存记忆的大脑”；“唱片在旋转，它们渴望被听见”。诗中最重要的意象“舌头”被赋予了多个致命的形式：“古老的钩镰”，中世纪具有杀伤力的武器；长着“九条尾巴”的危险怪物，像是锋利的刀，“一旦它行动，它会在空中鞭打出噪音！”[21]然而，因为“舌头”的威力无穷，它会遭遇自己悲惨的命运：“舌头”必须被切除。《遗忘》一诗的开始，言说妻子认识到祈求是根本无用，只剩下“美丽的空白”，因为与过去生活相关的东西全部“被抹去了”：“姓名，房子，汽车钥匙，//那个小玩偶妻子——”；因为言说者的丈夫想要一种新的生活，“他梦想着一位新人”，[22]而“遗忘”是他将来新生活的主要内容。

休斯编辑的《艾丽尔》于1965年首次在英国出版，2004年普拉斯生前自编的《艾丽尔：修复版》正式面世，时隔将近四十年之久，英美版和修复版之间最大的差异：休斯的英美版暗示了普拉斯的才情枯竭和生命的终结，创作这些诗歌是为一步一步走向死亡/自杀而做准备。而修复版给读者提供了一条清晰的脉络：诗人经历了愤怒、绝望、抗争和悲哀，最终趋于安静并十分渴望结束所有的痛苦，重新开始自己独立的生活，开启自己孜孜以求的职业诗人的生涯。休斯版误导读者在这些诗中寻找各种预兆或迹象来证实诗人最后的自杀行为，而不是了解诗人所处的各种进退两难的困境，这是对诗人和诗集最严重、最有害的误读。普拉斯所遭遇的困境、抑郁症的折磨以及她所面临的各种压力不是她个人所特有的，而是那个时代女性作家共同面对的难题和遭遇。当别的作家还保持沉默时，普拉斯却以自己的方式揭示女性所面临的种种矛盾和困惑，并以坚韧和决心坚持抗争，这是普拉斯的独特之处。正如英国学者苏姗·巴斯奈特（Susan Bassnett）所指出的《艾丽尔》对于普拉斯最重要的意义所在：“《艾丽尔》特别显示出生存下去的坚韧，这种坚韧凌驾于所有死亡和恐惧的意象之上。”[23]

本诗集共收录普拉斯后期诗五十五首，包括《艾丽尔》两个版本的全部诗歌：普拉斯生前自己编排、2004年由女儿弗丽达编辑出版的《艾丽尔：修复版》诗四十首，加上原本属于“蜜蜂组诗”中的《蜂群》一诗（“The Swarm”）以及休斯在英美版本中添加的十四首诗。

本书诗歌均译自普拉斯《诗全集》（The Collected Poems，2008），美国纽约哈珀柯林斯出版社（HarperCollins Publishers Inc.）推出的永恒现代经典版。英文版诗末尾括号中的数字是诗人自己标注的诗歌创作的年、月、日以及每首诗在《诗全集》中的页码和编号。

[1]Linda Wagner-Martin edited, Critical Essays on Sylvia Plath, Boston: G. K. Hall & Company, 1984. p.1.

[2]Elaine Showalter edited, The Vintage Book of American Women Writers, New York: A Division of Random House, Inc., 2011. p.766.

[3]Jo Gill, The Cambridge Introduction to Sylvia Plath, New York: Cambridge UP, 2008. p.ix.

[4]Diane Middlebrook, Her Husband: Hughes and Plath—A Marriage, New York: Viking, 2003. p.227.

[5]Sylvia Plath, The Collected Poems, Edited by Ted Hughes. New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 2008. p.270.

[6]Sylvia Plath, The Collected Poems, Edited by Ted Hughes. New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 2008. p.270.

[7]The Collected Poems, p.271.

[8]The Collected Poems, p.272.

[9]The Collected Poems, p.271—272.

[10]The Collected Poems, p.295.

[11]Sylvia Plath, Ariel: The Restored Edition, Edited by Frieda Hughes, New York: HarperCollins Publishers Inc., 2004. p.xiv.

[12]Ariel: The Restored Edition, p.195.

[13]Linda Wagner-Martin edited, Sylvia Plath: The Critical Heritage, London and New York: Routledge, 1997. p.7.

[14]Ariel: The Restored Edition, p.224.

[15]Raymond C. Ortlund Jr., Study Notes on Book of Tsaiah, edited by Lane T. Dennis etc., The ESV Study Bible, Wheaton, Illinois: Crossway Books and Bibles, 2007. p.1290.

[16]The Collected Poems, p.15.

[17]The Collected Poems, p.219.

[18]Jo Gill, The Cambridge Introduction to Sylvia Plath, New York: Cambridge UP, 2008. p.65.

[19]The Collected Poems, p.227.

[20]The Collected Poems, p.208.

[21]The Collected Poems, pp.209—210.

[22]The Collected Poems, pp.232—233.

[23]Susa Bassnett, Sylvia Plath: An Introduction to the Poetry, Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005. p.135.

申请人

首先，你是我们的同类人？
你用不用
玻璃眼珠，假牙或拐杖，
牙套或钩子，
橡胶乳房或橡胶胯部，

针疤表示缺了什么？没，没缺？那么
我们如何给你一样东西？
别再哭泣。
伸出你的手。
空的？空的。给你一只手

来填满它，它愿意
端来茶杯，驱散头痛
你要它干什么它都干。
你愿意娶它吗？
它保证

临终时，用拇指合上你的双眼，
消除忧愁。
我们用盐制成新产品。
我注意到你赤身裸体，
这套衣服如何——

黑色，硬挺，还算合身。
你愿意娶它吗？
防水，防碎，防止
火、炸弹穿透屋顶。
相信我，你下葬时也穿这衣。

请原谅，你的头，是空的。
我有那张入场券。
来这儿，宝贝，走出密室[1]吧。
嗯，那事你看如何？
婚姻开始赤裸如纸

但二十五年后她将是银的，
五十年后，金的。
一个活玩偶，随你怎么端详。
它会缝纫，它会烹调，
它会说话，说话，说话。

它很有效，什么事都不会做错。
你有个伤口，它就是敷药，
你有个眼睛，它就是影像。
我的小伙，它是你最后的依靠。
你可愿意娶它，娶它，娶它。

[1]“out of the closet”在此诗中译作“走出密室”，因为按照上下文，此短语没有“公开同性恋身份”之意。

女拉撒路[1]

我又做了一次。
每十年一次
我设法做到——

可真是鲜活又神奇，我的皮肤
明亮如纳粹的灯罩[2]，
我的右脚

是一块镇纸，
我的脸平淡无奇，盖着精制的
犹太亚麻布。

揭开那块遮脸布
哎，我的敌人。
我可怕吗？——

鼻子，两个眼坑，满口牙齿？
酸臭的气味
将在一天之内消失。

墓穴吞食的肉体
会很快，很快
回到我身上

而我，一个微笑的女人。
我只有三十岁。
可我像猫可以死九次。

这是第三次。
多无用的废物
每十年就要消灭。

真是千丝万缕。
嚼着花生的人群
挤进来看

他们解开我的手和脚——
盛大的脱衣表演。
先生们，女士们，

这是我的双手，
我的双膝。
也许我皮包骨头，

但我，还是原来的、同一个女人。
第一次发生，我十岁。
那是一次意外。

第二次，我想要
坚持住，一点不想回来。
我摇晃着

像海贝闭紧。
他们喊了又喊，
摘除我身上的蠕虫，像黏黏的珍珠。

死去
是一种艺术，就像其他任何事。
我做得格外精彩。

我这样做，好像它在地狱。
我这样做，感觉它很真实。
我猜想你们会说我得到召唤。

非常容易做，在单间里。
非常容易做，呆着不动。
真是戏剧性

在大白天活过来
回到同一地方，同一张脸，同样残忍
滑稽地叫喊：

“一个奇迹！”
那喊声使我不省人事。
观看要收费

为看我的伤疤，这要收费
为听我的心跳——
它真的没了。

还是要收费，收很高的费，
为说句话或一次触摸
或一点点血

或我的一根头发，我的衣服。
好吧，好吧，医生先生。
好吧，敌人先生[3]。

我是你的艺术品，
我是你的珍宝，
纯金的婴儿

溶化成一声尖叫。
我翻转，我燃烧。
别以为我低估了你的极大关注。

灰烬，灰烬——
你戳着，拨着，
血肉，骨头，所剩无几——

一块肥皂，
一枚婚戒，
一颗金牙。

上帝先生，撒旦先生，
警惕
警惕。

我从灰烬中升起[4]
披着一头红发
我像空气一样吃男人。

[1]Lazarus：拉撒路，《圣经》中的人物，男性，死后四天被基督唤醒，从坟墓中走出。此诗中死而复活的拉撒路是女性，因此题目译作《女拉撒路》。

[2]Lampshade：在纳粹死亡营，犹太人的皮肤被纳粹用来做灯罩。

[3]“医生先生”“敌人先生”，原文为德语：Herr Doktor，Herr Enemy。

[4]out of the ash：神话传说中的凤凰鸟浴火死亡，然后从灰烬中复活。

郁金香

时逢冬天，郁金香却太艳丽。
瞧，一切被雪覆盖，雪白，多安静。
我正在适应这宁静，独自安静地躺着
光线散落在白色墙上，床上和双手上。
我是小人物；我与突然冒出的艳丽[1]无关。
我已把我的名字、白天穿的衣服交给了护士
我的历史给了麻醉师，我的身体给了外科医生。

他们将我的头支撑好，在枕头与床单之间
仿佛一只眼，嵌在两层白色眼皮间。
愚蠢的眼球，必须将这一切收入眼中。
护士们来来去去，她们并不找我麻烦。
她们带着白色帽子，与海鸥经过海岛一样，
双手忙碌着，一个与另一个相同，
因此不可能知道她们有几个。

我的身体如鹅卵石，她们处理它
仿佛水轻柔地、冲刷滑过鹅卵石。
她们用铮亮的针给我麻醉，带我入睡。
我已迷失自己，我厌倦这个行李——
我的漆皮手提箱像黑色的药片盒，
家庭照片中丈夫和孩子冲我微笑；
他们的微笑抓住我的皮肤，微笑的小钩子。

我已让它们溜走，三十年的老货船
顽固地挂着我的名字和地址。
它们已清除了我充满爱意的联想。
赤裸躺在铺有绿色塑料垫子的推车上，我害怕
我看着我的茶具、铺着亚麻布的书桌，我的书
退出视线，而那水从我的头流过。
现在我是修女，我从未如此纯洁。

我并不要什么花，我只想
躺着毫无牵挂，双手朝上放好。
多么自由，你真想不到多么自由——
如此的宁静让你恍惚不安，
而它不求什么，不求姓名牌，或小饰品。
最终，死者在逼近；我想象它们
正闭上它们的嘴，像一个圣餐[2]薄饼。

郁金香从一开始就太红艳，它们伤害我。
即使透过礼品包装纸，我仍听见它们轻柔的
呼吸，像难受的婴儿，透过白色的襁褓纸。
红色对着我的伤口说话，伤口附和着。
它们很巧妙：它们似在漂浮，却使我沉重，
它们突然闯入，舌状花瓣和颜色使我不安，
仿佛一打红色铅锚绕着我的脖子下沉。

从未有人注意过我，而现在，有人看护我。
郁金香转向我，而我身后的窗户
每天一次光线缓慢变宽又缓慢变细，
我发觉自己，扁平、可笑，剪纸的影子
在太阳之眼和郁金香的眼睛之间，
但我没有脸，我已经将自己抹去。
鲜活的郁金香吞食我的氧气。

郁金香送来之前空气很安静，
流动着，我一口接一口地呼吸，没有忙乱。
后来郁金香像大声的噪音填满了空气。
现在空气缠住它们并围绕着它们旋转
如同河水缠住围绕下沉的锈红色引擎。
它们吸引我的注意力，那样快乐地
玩耍、休息，并没有承担任何义务。

那些墙，似乎，也在温暖它们自己。
郁金香应该关在笼子里，危险的动物；
它们却盛开仿佛某只非洲巨猫张开的嘴，
而我意识到我的心脏：张开又关闭
红色的心房涌出我纯粹的爱。
我尝到的水温暖带咸味，仿佛大海，
从陌生的国度涌来，遥远如我的健康。

[1]explosion：此诗中指“鲜艳的郁金香突然闯入病房”，没有“爆炸”之意。

[2]Communion：基督教的圣餐仪式，纪念基督的死亡。

一个秘密

一个秘密！一个秘密！
多么高级。
你衣着蓝色，高大，交通警察。
举起一只手掌——

我们之间的差异？
我有一只眼睛，你有两只。
秘密印在你身上，
淡淡的、波状的水印。

它会显示在黑色检测器上？
它会出来
波状的，难以抹去，却是真实
从非洲的长颈鹿，伊甸园的葱绿草木，

从摩洛哥的河马出来？
它们从方形的、僵硬的皱皮中瞪眼。
它们为出口准备的，
这个是傻瓜，另一个也是傻瓜。

一个秘密……一根琥珀色
白兰地手指
栖息着，咕咕地叫“你，你”
双眼后面什么也没有，只照出几只猴子。

可以拔出一把刀
修剪指甲，
剔除污垢。
“不会伤着。”

一个私生婴儿——
那蓝色的大头——
在办事处的抽屉里喘息！
“那是女式内衣，宝贝？

“有咸鳕鱼味，你最好
在苹果上插入几个丁香
做个香袋或者
消灭那个杂种。

“全部消灭它！”
“不，不，它在这很开心。”
“但它想要出去！
瞧，瞧！它正在爬！”

我的上帝，来了阻拦者！
协和广场上的汽车——
当心！
人群蜂拥，争先恐后！

汽车喇叭鸣叫，人群里的低吼声！
打开了一瓶烈性黑啤酒，
松弛泡沫喷出，在膝盖上。
你跌跌撞撞走出，

侏儒婴儿，
刀在你的背上。
“我感觉虚弱。”
秘密泄露了。

狱卒

我的睡衣给他早餐的盘子抹上油。
蓝色雾般的相同布告牌滚动到位
缠绕着相同的树木和墓碑。
他可以拿出的只是
那串叮当响的钥匙？

我被用了麻醉药，被强奸。
我被击昏，神志不清七个小时
被塞进一只黑色的麻袋
可以放松的地方，胎儿或是猫，
他多次梦遗的操纵杆。

某样东西不见了。
我的安眠胶囊，红蓝相间似飞艇
从可怕的海拔将我抛下。
外壳摔得粉碎，
我飞散成众鸟之食。

唉，小小的螺丝锥——
薄纸似的日子早已布满了空洞！
他一直用他的烟在烫我，
佯称我是黑女人长着粉色的手爪。
我是我自己。但这不够。

高烧似水滴落，我的头发僵硬。
我露出肋骨。我吃了什么？
各种谎言和微笑。
想必天空不是那颜色，
想必青草正随风摇曳。

整天，我用燃烧过的火柴杆黏合我的教堂，
我整个儿梦想另一个人。
而他，为了颠覆这梦想，
伤害我，他
带着假意之盔甲，

极其冷酷，遗忘的面罩。
我如何抵达此地？
不确定的罪犯，
我会有各种死法——
被绞死，被饿死，被烧死，被钩死。

我想象他
仿佛远处的雷声一样虚弱，
在他的阴影中我吃了小份口粮。
我希望他已死或远离。
那，似乎，是不可能之事。

那会是自由。没有高烧可吞食
黑暗会做什么？
没有眼睛似刀穿透
光明会做什么？没有我
他会做，做，做什么？

残片

给苏珊·奥尼尔·罗伊

好惊险啊——
我的拇指不是洋葱。
顶端就没了
除了粘连的

一点皮，
偏平如帽子，
惨白。
然后是红色长毛绒。

小小清教徒，
印第安人斧子砍下的头皮。
你火鸡似的肉垂
仿佛地毯

直接从心脏卷起。
我踩上去，
抓紧我的瓶子
装有粉色液体。

这是，一次庆祝。
百万士兵冲出了
伤口
穿红色风衣，每个人。

他们站在谁的一边？
哦，我的
小矮人[1]，我病了。
我必须吃药来消除

那种单薄
纸的感觉。
怠工者，
神风特攻队员[2]——

你纱布上的
污点，三K党[3]的
三角头巾[4]，
玷污而变黑，此刻

你心脏的
球状肉质
遭遇它小小的
沉默之磨坊

你如何跳起——
陷入圈套的老兵，
肮脏姑娘，
拇指残片。

[1]Homunculus：小矮人，侏儒。

[2]Kamikaze man：神风特攻队员。第二次世界大战末期，日本为抵御美国军队强大的优势，挽救自身战败的局面，组建了自杀式袭击的神风特别攻击队（或称敢死队）。

[3]Ku Klux Klan：三K党，美国南部的白人秘密组织，利用暴力反对社会变革和黑人的平等权利，美国种族主义的代表性组织。

[4]Babushka：俄语，意为“老祖母”，此处指三K党人佩戴的三角巾。

榆树

给露丝·费恩莱特

我清楚这根部，她说。凭我的主根我了解它：
这是你所害怕的。
我不怕它：我一直在那里。

你在我内心听到大海，
它的种种不满？
或者什么声响都没有，只是你的疯狂？

爱是一个影子。
爱过之后，你就这样躺下、哭泣
倾听：它的马蹄：它走远了，如一匹马。

整夜我将飞奔，风驰电掣，
直至你的头变成石头，你的枕变成赛马场，
马蹄声回响着，回响着。

或许我给你带来有毒之声？
现在是雨天，多安静。
这是它的果实：白如锡，毒如砒。

我已承受落日的残暴。
烤焦至根部
我的红色花丝灼伤，承受痛苦，一串金属丝。

我现在分裂成碎片，像草花飞舞。
一股狂暴之风
绝不袖手旁观：我必须尖叫。

月亮，也是，冷酷无情：她残忍地
拖着我，变得枯萎。
她的光亮伤害我。或许我已抓住了她。

我让她走，让她变得
弱小、扁平，一如大手术之后。
你的种种噩梦占有我，缠住我。

我被一种叫喊声所占据。
每个夜晚，它飘出
寻找它相爱之物，带着许多钩子。

这个黑色的东西让我恐惧
它沉睡在我体内；
整天我感到它在旋转，柔软似羽毛，满怀恶意。

云团飘来又散落。
那些爱之面容，苍白却不可逆转的神色？
就为这，我的心，焦虑不安？

我不可能了解更多。
这是什么，这张脸
如此凶残，隐藏在缠绕的树枝中？——

它的酸味在嘶嘶作响。
它使意志僵化。这些孤立、缓慢的错误
会残杀，会残杀，会残杀。

侦探

她在做什么？当风吹过
七座丘陵，红色犁沟，青色山脉？
她在准备杯子吗？这很重要。
她在窗户边，倾听？
山谷里回荡着火车的尖啸，仿佛魂被钩住。

那是死亡山谷，只有牛群生机勃勃。
她的花园里，谎言抖平潮湿的真丝
那个杀手的眼睛像鼻涕虫似的斜视，
无法面对那些手指，自私自利者。
那些手指将一个女子塞进一堵墙，

将身体填进管道，然后烟雾升起。
多年烹饪的味道，这是在厨房里，
还有谎言，犹如家庭照片被收藏，
就是这个男人，瞧他的微笑，
死亡武器？没人死亡。

那房子里根本没有尸体。
那儿只有豪华地毯，精美的味道。
那儿阳光闪烁，锋利如刀片，
红色房间里厌倦的恶棍
收音机好像上了年纪的亲戚自言自语。

它来时像箭，它来时像刀？
它是哪种毒？
哪个神经曲卷器，抽搐器？它带电吗？
这是一个没有尸体的案子。
尸体根本没有出现在这个案子里。

这案子蒸发得毫无痕迹。
首先是嘴，它不存在
第二年才有报道。它曾经贪得无厌
而为了惩罚它，像不新鲜的水果
它被挂起、风干。

接着是双乳。
已经变硬，两块白色石头。
乳汁变黄，然后变蓝，甜如水。
不缺少嘴巴，还有两个孩子，
但他们骨瘦如柴，月亮却微笑了。

然后是干枯的树木，几重大门，
棕色、慈母般的犁沟，所有财产。
我们得意扬扬，华生[1]。
只有月亮发出磷光，涂抹防腐香膏。
只有树上的一只乌鸦。做笔记吧。

[1]Watson：华生，大侦探夏洛克·福尔摩斯（Sherlock Holmes）的好友和助手。福尔摩斯是19世纪末英国侦探小说家阿瑟·柯南·道尔爵士小说中塑造的一个才华横溢的侦探，此诗就是从这位大侦探的视角来调查发生在这所房里的谋杀案。

莱斯博斯岛[1]

厨房里的邪恶！
土豆嘶嘶作响。
典型的好莱坞式，没有窗户，
日光灯或明或暗像可怕的偏头痛，
害羞的纸条遮着门——
舞台幕布，寡妇的乱发。
而我，亲爱的，是个病态的撒谎者，
我的孩子——瞧她，脸朝下趴在地板上，
断了线的小木偶，踢着腿就会消失似的——
为何她神情紧张，
她的脸又红又白，惊慌失措，
你将她的猫仔困于你家窗外
像是困在水泥井里
它们在那里拉屎、呕吐、叫喊，她听不见。
你说不能容忍她，
那个混蛋的女儿。
你开着电视机却像只坏收音机
没有各种观点、历史，不变的
新的噪音。
你说我该溺死那些猫仔。它们有气味！
你说我该溺死我的女儿。
若她两岁时疯癫，十岁她将割自己的喉咙。
那婴儿微笑着，肥蜗牛，
橘黄色油毡布上抛光的菱形。
你可以吃了他。他是个男孩。
你说你的丈夫对你一无用处。
他那犹太妈妈珍视他的性别贵如珍珠。
你有一个婴儿，我有两个。
我该坐在康沃尔[2]的岩石上，梳理我的头发。
我该穿虎裤，我该有风流韵事。
我们该相遇于另一生命中，我们真不该相遇，
我和你。

那期间散发出肥胖婴儿粪便的气味。
我吞下的最后一片安眠药让我昏昏沉沉。
烹饪的烟雾，地狱的烟雾
我们的头脑飘浮，两个心怀恶意对立的人，
我们的骨头，我们的头发。
我称你孤儿，孤儿。你病了。
太阳让你得溃疡，风儿让你得肺结核。
你曾经多么美丽。
在纽约，在好莱坞，男人们说：“完了？
哇，甜心，你很特别。”
你为惊险表演，表演，表演。
无能的丈夫消沉露脸，为一杯咖啡。
我试图让他待着，
产生闪电的古老电线杆，
满天空的酸性雨水倾泻而下，刻薄的你。
他将它摔在塑料鹅卵石铺成的山丘，
被抽打的手推车。冒出蓝色的火星。
蓝色的火星溅散，
仿佛石英分裂成百万碎片。

啊，宝石！啊，珍宝！
那晚，月亮
拖着它血红的袋子，病态
似动物
悬挂于港口众灯之上。
然后变得正常，
硬朗，苍白，与众不同。
沙地上鱼鳞的光泽将我吓死。
我们不停地捡，满手都是，
像面团般地揉弄它，一个黑白混血儿，
丝绸般沙沙响。
狗带着你那像狗的丈夫。他向前走。

现在我沉默了，憎恨
强烈的憎恨，
沉重，沉重。
我不说话。
我将坚硬的土豆打包，仿佛优质衣服，
我将孩子们打包，
我将病猫们打包。
啊，刻薄的花瓶，
你满怀的是爱。你清楚你恨谁。
他抱着球，走到大门边
大门朝大海敞开
海水涌入，黑白一片，
然后海水涌出。
每天你用灵魂之物填满他，如同大水壶。
你如此筋疲力尽。
你的声音，我的耳环，
拍动着，吮吸着，嗜血的蝙蝠。
那就是，那就是。
你从门缝中窥视，
悲哀的丑妇。“每个女人都是娼妇。
我不能交流。”

我看见你漂亮的饰品
紧贴你身上像婴儿的小拳
或像银莲花，那大海
宝贝，那爱情神偷。
我依然毫无经验。
我说我可能回来。
你明白谎言为何而生。

即使在你禅宗天堂我们也不会相遇。

[1]莱斯博斯岛，希腊第三大岛，地中海第八大岛。20世纪80年代开始，莱斯博斯岛逐渐打破了它本来的宁静，成为女同性恋者的度假胜地。该岛因古希腊著名女诗人萨福而闻名于世。传说萨福是同性恋者，英语中“女同性恋”（Lesbian）即由此岛名转化而来。

[2]Cornwall：康沃尔，英格兰郡名，英国的天涯海角。康沃尔郡毗邻德文郡（Devon）。

闭嘴的勇气

闭嘴需要勇气，尽管大炮在眼前！
一条粉色的幼虫，安静地晒太阳。
它身后是黑色的唱片，愤怒的唱片，
还有苍天之愤怒，储存记忆的大脑。
那些唱片在旋转，它们渴望被听见——

它们已灌满，众多私生子的记录。
私生子，惯例，背弃，双重性，
那针在凹槽里滑行，
两个幽暗峡谷中的银色野兽，
伟大的外科医生，现在是文身师。

针刺在反复，悲伤的苦衷也在重复，
在美人鱼，有双腿的梦幻女孩身上
文刺各种蛇，许多婴儿、乳头。
外科医生保持沉默，他不说话。
他见过太多的死亡，双手沾满死亡。

于是唱片似的大脑在旋转，犹如多个大炮口。
还有那古老的钩镰，那舌
不知疲倦、紫色的舌。它必须被切除？
它有九条尾巴，它非常危险。
一旦它行动，它可在空中鞭打出噪音！

不，那舌，已经被存放一边，
挂在图书馆，连同仰光的雕刻作品
还有狐狸头、水獭头、死兔的头颅。
它是一个非凡之物品——
它在自己的岁月里刺穿了那些东西。

但那些眼睛怎么了，那些眼睛，眼睛？
镜子能说话，能残杀，可怕的房间里
所持续的折磨，人只能观看。
曾活在镜中的脸是死亡男子的脸。
不用担心那些眼睛——

它们或许苍白又害羞，不是密探鸽子。
它们死亡之光束犹如一个国家的
旗子一样被折叠，无人再听说过，
一种独立顽固不化
却在群山中无能为力。

贝尔克海滩[1]

（1）

这片海域，这儿，宽阔的海湾浅滩。
阳光仿佛敷药正吸收我的炎症。

色彩诱人的果冻，苍白女孩用暴晒的手，
从冷冻箱舀出，穿梭在空气中。

为何那么平静啊？她们在隐藏什么？
我有两条腿，我微笑着走动。

沙土似减震器延绵数英里；
减弱了各种振荡声，各种衰弱的声音

无助地颤抖着，只剩原来的一半。
这只眼的周围，被这些裸露的表面灼伤，

回飞镖像锚定的橡皮圈，击伤它的主人。
他戴着墨镜奇怪吗？

他穿着教士的黑袍奇怪吗？
现在他来到这儿，在收集马鲛鱼的人群中

他们背部形成的墙对着他。
他们在处理墨绿菱形鱼如同身体的各个部分。

大海，养育了这些鱼，
悄然离开，曲折蛇行，发出悠长痛苦的嘶嘶声。

（2）

这只黑靴对谁都不怜悯。
为什么它应该，它是死亡之脚的灵柩，

牧师无脚趾的脚，高傲、冷漠
他正探索圣书之源泉，

弯曲的字体呈现他面前犹如风景。
低俗的比基尼掩藏在沙丘里，

乳房，臀部，糖果商的砂糖
颗颗细小晶体，闪烁着挑逗之光，

而绿色海水睁开眼，
厌恶它所吞咽的一切——

肢体，意象，尖叫声。混凝土的掩体后面
一对情侣刚分开。

呵，白色海洋似陶器，
盛着怎样的叹息，喉咙里品出怎样的咸味……。

那个旁观者，哆嗦着，
好似被长长的东西拉着

穿过一片死气沉沉的恶意，
一丛野草，毛茸茸如阴部。

（3）

旅馆的阳台上，各种东西都在发光，
各种东西，各种东西——

钢管轮椅，铝制拐杖。
如此咸的甜味。为何我该越过

防波堤，沾着斑斑点点的甲壳动物？
我不是护士，白色护理人员，

我不是一个微笑。
孩子们在追赶什么，带着钩子，喊叫着，

我的心脏太小无法包扎他们可怕的伤口。
这是一个男人的侧面：红色肋骨，

神经像树枝般膨胀，这是外科医生：
镜子般的一只眼睛——

知识的一个方面。
房子里带条纹的床垫上

一个老年男子正在死去。
妻子的哭泣也无济于事。

石头般的双眼，黄色而珍贵，
还有舌头，灰色的蓝宝石。

（4）

婚宴蛋糕似的脸安放在花边纸里。
现在他多么高傲啊。

仿佛拥有了一位圣人。
带着檐帽的护士们不再那么漂亮；

她们无精打采，像碰落的栀子花。
床从墙那边移动。

这将是所谓的圆满。令人恐惧。
他穿着睡衣还是晚礼服？

黏胶床单下，他那抹满粉的嘴
白花花地翘起，未经反复拍打？

他们用一本书支撑他的下颚，直至僵硬。
并把他的双手合上，好像在招手：再见，再见。

现在洗过的床单在阳光里飘动，
枕套散发着香甜气味。

这是一种祝福，一种祝福：
皂色的橡木，长长的灵柩，

好奇的抬棺者，阴冷的日子
刻入银色日期，出奇的宁静。

（5）

灰色天空低垂，丘陵如碧绿海洋，
层层叠叠消失在远方，隐匿于山谷中，

冥冥中妻子思绪万千——
迟钝，实用的一只只小船

装满连衣裙、帽子和瓷器，已婚的女儿。
石屋的客厅里

打开的窗户，窗帘在飘动，
飘动，倾泻，一支可怜的蜡烛。

似乎是已死男人的话：记住，记住。
现在他有多远，他身边的

种种行为像客厅里的家具，一种装饰。
各种苍白凝聚——

双手的苍白，邻居脸的苍白，
飞翔的鸢尾得意的苍白。

它们正在飞离，消逝了：记住我们。
记忆似空空的长凳越过这些石块，

大理石表面，蓝色纹理，盛满胶状水仙花的玻璃杯。
这儿却很美：一个歇息的地方。

（6）

这些椴树叶子天生阔大！——
修剪成绿色球状，这些树运进教堂。

牧师的声音，在稀薄的空气中
与门口的尸体相遇，

向它致辞，而丘陵回荡着死亡的钟声；
闪烁的麦浪，原始的大地。

那个颜色叫什么来着？——
墙上沾满旧血迹，太阳治愈了，

残肢上的旧血迹，受伤的心灵。
寡妇带上黑色手提包，三个女儿，

花丛中的必需品，
仿佛细亚麻布蒙着她的脸，

别再凌乱。
一片天空，却因积攒的微笑蚕食，

朵朵云彩飘过。
新娘花儿的清新消散了，

那么灵魂就是新娘
在一个安静的地方，新郎红润又健忘，他平淡无奇。

（7）

车窗后面的世界
发出低沉的颤动声，轻轻地熄灭。

我衣着黑色，送葬队伍中安静的一位，
在灵车后面缓慢随行。

牧师是一个器皿，
涂了焦油的织物，伤悲而又沉闷，

跟在铺满鲜花的灵车后面，仿佛一位美丽女子，
一对峰乳，眼睑和嘴唇

山顶刮起狂风。
随后，有栅栏的庭院里，孩子们

闻到了鞋子烧焦熔化的气味，
他们脸色在变，无语而缓慢，

他们睁大眼睛
注视这奇妙场景——

草地上六顶圆形黑帽，一块菱形的木头，
一张裸露的嘴，红润却笨拙。

瞬间，那天空仿佛血浆倾泻入洞。
毫无希望，永被放弃。

[1]贝尔克海滩位于法国北部海岸鲁昂（Rouen，法国港市），著名的度假胜地，收治残疾人士的康复医院也在这个海滩。1961年夏，普拉斯夫妇游览过贝尔克海滩。

去那里

它有多远？
现在它有多远？
这个巨大猩猩的
车轮在滚动，它们使我恐惧——
那些克虏伯[1]可怕的
头脑，黑色的炮口
在旋转，那声音
冲压出空无！像加农炮。
我必须穿越俄罗斯，某个战争或其他。
我拖着我的身体
悄悄穿过装着稻草的闷罐车。
现在是行贿的时机。
车轮吃什么，这些车轮
像上帝固定在它们的弧线上，
意志的银色链条——
铁面无私。它们的骄傲！
所有上帝都知道目的地。
我是这个狭缝里的一封信——
我飞向一个名字，两只眼睛。
那边有火，有面包吗？
而这儿有泥浆。
这是火车站，护士们
正用修道院里的自来水，还有面纱，面纱，
清洗受伤男人的
伤口，鲜血还在涌出，
大腿，手臂堆放在帐篷
外面，无休止的哭喊——
玩偶们的医院。
可男人们，男人们还剩下什么
这些活塞将鲜血输送，向前
到下一个英里
下一个小时——
断剑的皇朝！

它有多远？
我的双脚沾着泥巴，
厚重，红色，黏滑。这是亚当的侧面，
我从这泥土出生，我极度痛苦。
我不能重塑自己，火车呼啸着。
呼啸着，冒着蒸汽，它的车轮
像魔鬼的牙，准备吞噬。
最终结束还有一分钟
一分钟，一滴露珠。
它有多远？
我将去的地方
如此小，为何有这些障碍物——
这个女子的尸体，
烧焦的裙子、死亡面具
宗教人物、戴花环的孩子们在哀悼。
现在有爆炸声——
雷声、枪声。
战火在我们之间。
可有安静的地方
在半空中转动着，转动着，
未遭破坏，也不可以破坏。
火车拖着自己，呼啸着——
一只动物
疯狂地驶向目的地。
那血斑，
烈火燃烧之后的那张脸。
我要埋葬像蛹似的伤痛，
我要清点埋葬那些死者。
让他们的魂在露水中翻滚，
香熏我的行踪。
节节车厢摇晃着，它们是摇篮。
而我，正从这张皮
古老的枷锁、厌倦、陈旧的脸中走出

从遗忘河[2]的黑色车厢走向你
纯洁像婴儿。

[1]Krupp：克虏伯，指德国军火制造商。

[2]Lethe：遗忘河（又译忘川，勒忒河），希腊神话中冥界的五条河流之一，凡是喝了这条河水的鬼魂就会忘了忧愁，忘记一切。

美杜莎

海岬角处，嘴似的石头塞子，
双眼由白浪推着翻滚，
双耳盛满了大海的混乱，
你藏着令人胆怯的头——上帝之球，
怜悯之镜头，

你的帮手们
在我龙骨的阴影里疯狂繁殖它们的细胞，
像心脏那样鼓动，
经过中心处的红色圣伤[1]，
乘着激浪驶向最近的出发地，

拖着他们耶稣的头发。
我想知道，我逃脱了吗？
我的心思缠绕着你
藤壶黏着的古老脐带，大西洋的电缆线，
似乎，使自己，处于神奇般的修复状态中。

任何情况下，你总在那儿，
电话线尽头颤抖的呼吸，
海水荡漾的弧线
跳跃到我的鱼竿，耀眼、充满感激，
触摸着、吮吸着。

我没有打你电话。
我根本没有打你电话。
尽管如此，尽管如此
你乘船越过大洋来见我，
丰满、红色，一只胎盘

使犯错的情侣麻木。
眼镜蛇的光
从倒挂的血红金钟中
挤出呼吸。我根本无法呼吸，
死气沉沉，一文不值，

暴露无遗，像X射线。
你以为你是谁？
一个圣餐饼[2]？哭泣的玛丽？
我绝不会撕咬你的身体，
我生活的瓶子，

幽灵般的罗马教皇。
我对热盐极度厌恶。
嫉妒如阉人，你的渴望
因我的罪孽嘶嘶作响。
滚开，滚开，鳗鱼似的触角！

你我之间没有任何关联。

[1]Stigmata：圣痕，圣伤，指耶稣被钉在十字架上身体出现的伤痕。

[2]Communion：基督教的圣餐仪式，纪念耶稣的死亡。

生日礼物

这是什么，藏在面纱后面，它丑陋吗，它漂亮吗？
它在闪烁，它有乳房，它有边缘吗？

我肯定它是独特的，我肯定它就是我要的。
我在安静地烹饪，我感觉它在看，我感觉它在思考

“这就是我要去见的人？
这就是挑选的人，有黑眼眶、伤疤的人？

她在称面粉，去掉多余的，
遵守规定，守规定，守规定。

就是要对这个人宣布吗？
我的上帝，多么可笑啊！”

但它在闪烁，它不停止，我想它要我。
我不会在意它是否是尸骨，或一颗珍珠纽扣。

我并不需要许多礼物，至少，今年。
毕竟，我活着纯属偶然。

那次我原本很乐意自杀了事，什么方法都行。
现在这些面纱，像窗帘在闪烁，

一月的窗，半透明的绸缎
洁白如婴儿的被褥，却散发死亡气息。啊，象牙！

它定是一根长牙，幽灵般的圆柱。
你不明白，我并不在乎它是什么。

你不会把它给我吧？
不要感到羞愧——我不在意它是否小。

不要小气，我乐意它是巨大的。
让我俩挨着它坐下，一边一个，欣赏那亮光，

那光泽，它折射出多样化。
让我俩共享最后的晚餐，它多像医院的餐具。

我知道你为何不把它给我，
你很害怕

这世界会在尖叫声中上升，你会随后，
浮雕式，黄铜制作，一个古老盾牌，

你曾孙儿女以为是个奇迹。
不用担心，并非如此。

我只带上它，悄悄地离开。
你不会听见我打开它，没有纸的沙沙声，

没有丝带的散落，没有最后的惊呼。
我以为你不会称赞我如此小心翼翼。

但愿你能了解这些面纱是如何毁掉我的生活。
对你而言，它们只是些透明物体，清爽空气。

可我的上帝，那些云朵像棉花。
它们很多很多。它们是一氧化碳。

舒服地，舒服地，我吸入，
成千上万，隐形却注满我的静脉

可能出现的斑点蚕食我生命的岁月。
你为此穿着银色。啊，加算器——

你怎可能放手，让它完整地离去？
你必须在每件物品上盖上紫色章，

你必须消灭你可以消灭的？
今天我只要这一样东西，只有你可以给我。

它站在我窗户边，宏大若天空。
它在我床单下呼吸，严寒如死亡中心

溢出的生命变稠、凝固成历史。
不让它邮寄过来，一根根手指。

不让它口头转述，全部转述完
我将六十岁，太迟钝不能用它了。

只有放下那面纱，那面纱，那面纱。
倘若它是死亡

我愿欣赏它的庄重，它恒久的双眼。
我愿了解你是认真的。

那时会有一种崇高，会有一个生日。
那刀不是切开，而是插入

纯洁干净如婴儿的哭声，
于是宇宙从我身边溜走。

爸爸

你不要，你不要做
再也不做，黑色的鞋子
我像只脚，住在里面
已经三十年，贫困又苍白，
我不敢呼吸也不敢打喷嚏。

爸爸，我早该杀了你，
我有时间前你就死了——
沉重如大理石，装满上帝的袋子，
可怕的雕像长着一个灰脚趾
像旧金山[1]的海豹那样大

而头倚在畸形的大西洋上
那儿大西洋将豆绿抛向蓝色
的水域，美丽的瑙塞特[2]。
我过去常祈求你复活。
啊，你。

说德国话，住波兰镇
那个被战争，战争，战争的
滚压机碾平的小镇。
而小镇的名却也普通。
我的波兰朋友

说有一打或两打之多。
所以我从来无法说清
你到过何处，根在何处。
我从来无法跟你说话
那语言卡在我的下颌。

卡在有倒钩的钢丝圈里。
我，我，我，我，
我几乎无法说话。
我原以为每个德国人是你
但这语言污秽

火车头，火车头
把我带走，像犹太人。
去达豪[3]、奥斯维辛[4]、贝尔森[5]的犹太人。
我开始说话，像犹太人。
我想我很可能是犹太人。

蒂罗尔[6]的雪，维也纳的清啤酒
不太纯也不真实。
我有吉卜赛女祖先，我的奇特命运
我有塔罗克纸牌[7]，我的塔罗克纸牌
我也许有几分像犹太人。

我一直都害怕你，
你的德国空军[8]，你的官腔，
还有你整齐的胡子
你的雅利安[9]眼睛，明亮的蓝，
装甲兵[10]，装甲兵，哦你——

不是上帝，而是卐[11]字饰，
漆黑得连夜空也无法比拟。
每个女人崇拜法西斯分子，
野蛮的靴子，踢在人脸上
野蛮的心长在野兽身上像你。

你就站在黑板旁，爸爸，
我有你的这张照片，
你的下巴有裂痕，不是脚，
但你依然是魔鬼，不比
那黑衣人差劲，那个人

将我红色的心咬成两半。
我十岁时他们埋葬了你。
二十岁时我尝试去死
想回到，回到，回到你的身边。
我原想变成白骨也情愿。

但他们把我从袋里拖出，
他们用胶水把我拼粘好。
那时我才清楚该做什么。
我以你为原型做了一个，
黑衣男人，带着《我的奋斗》[12]之神色

而且酷爱刑架和螺丝钉。
于是我说，我愿，我愿。
但爸爸，我最终了结了。
黑色的电话线连根断开，
声音再也无法缓慢通过。

若我杀死一个男人，我杀了俩——
那吸血鬼曾说他就是你
他吸我的血也有年头了，
告诉你吧，已有七年了。
爸爸，你现在可以安息。

木桩插在你肥胖的黑色心脏上，
村民们从来不曾喜欢你。
他们踩在你身上跳着舞，
他们一直清楚这就是你。
爸爸，爸爸，你这混蛋，我受够了。

[1]Frisco：旧金山（San Francisco）的简称。

[2]Nauset：波士顿北部的沙滩，也指诗人的父亲去世前，诗人与父母一家住处附近的港口。

[3]Dachau：达豪，德国城市，曾建有纳粹集中营。

[4]Auschwitz：奥斯维辛，纳粹集中营。

[5]Belsen：贝尔森，纳粹集中营。

[6]Tyrol：蒂罗尔，奥地利境内的阿尔皮斯山。

[7]Taroc：吉卜赛人玩的塔罗克纸牌，可预测命运。与犹太人一样，吉卜赛人也受到纳粹的迫害，许多人死于纳粹集中营。

[8]Luftwaffe：纳粹时代的德国空军。

[9]Arya：雅利安人，长有金色头发，蓝色眼睛，是希特勒鼓吹的优质德国人。

[10]Panzer-man：二次大战期间的德语装甲兵。

[11]swastika：纳粹党的党徽。

[12]Meinkampf：德语，纳粹独裁者希特勒写的自传的书名。

高烧103度[1]

纯洁？它什么意思？
地狱之舌
呆滞，呆滞如长着三头的

冥府守门狗[2]，呆滞，肥胖
它在门口喘息。无法
舔干净

那发热的腱，罪孽，罪孽。
引火物在哭喊。
熄灭的蜡烛

难忘的气味！
亲爱的，低迷的烟雾从我身边
翻滚，像伊莎多拉[3]的披肩，惊恐中的我

一条披肩被钩住并卡进轮子里。
如此黄色的愠怒烟雾
构成它们自己的原理。它们不会上升，

但绕着地球滚动
窒息年老和体弱的人，
体弱的人

婴儿床上的温室婴儿，
幽灵般的兰花
垂挂在半空中的花园，

邪恶的美洲豹！
辐射将它变成白色
一小时后就将它杀死。

在通奸者的身体抹着油
像广岛的灰，淹没一切。
罪孽，罪孽。

亲爱的，整夜
我在颤抖，高烧忽升忽降。
床单变得沉重如色鬼之吻。

三天。三夜。
柠檬水，鸡肉
水，水让我恶心。

我太纯洁，对你或任何人。
你的身体
伤害我如世界伤害上帝。我是一只灯笼——

我的头，日本纸
做成的月亮，我的皮肤如锤薄的金子
极其脆弱，极其昂贵。

我的头让你吃惊了。还有我的光亮。
我独自一人，变成巨大的山茶花
灼热，发烧，上升，红彤彤。

我想我在上升，
我想我可升起——
炽热金属的小珠在飞翔，我，亲爱的，

我是纯乙炔
童贞。
由玫瑰呵护，

由小天使亲吻，
无论这些粉色之物意味着什么
不是你，不是他

不是他，不是他
（我的自我在溶解，陈旧的淫妇衬裙）——
升入天堂。

[1]“103度”指华氏，相当于摄氏39.4度。

[2]Cerberus：刻耳柏洛斯，指古希腊罗马神话中的冥府守门狗，或称地狱三头犬。

[3]Isadora：Isadora Duncan，伊莎多拉·邓肯（1878—1927），美国舞蹈家，现代舞的创始人。1927年9月14日，邓肯在法国乘坐朋友的汽车，途中她的长围巾被汽车轮绞住，她因此意外身亡。

蜜蜂会议

桥上迎接我的那些人是谁？他们是村民——
教区长，助产婆，教堂司事，蜜蜂代理商。
我穿着夏天无袖的连衣裙，我没有任何保护，
而他们都戴着手套，全身遮住，为何没人告诉我？
他们微笑着，拿出脸罩固定在老式的帽子上。

我像鸡脖子那样光裸，有人喜欢我吗？
有，穿着白色商店工作服的养蜂会秘书，
扣上我双腕袖口上的纽扣，拉上脖子到膝盖的缝口。
我像乳草般单薄，蜜蜂不会注意。
它们不会嗅出我的害怕，我的害怕，我的害怕。

哪位是教区长，穿黑衣的男子？
哪位是助产婆，穿蓝衣的那位？
每个人都在点着方形的黑头，他们像带着面罩的骑士，
干酪包布做成胸甲在腋窝下打结。
他们的微笑和声音在变化。他们领着我穿过豆田。

一条条闪光的锡纸好像在眨眼，
羽毛掸子在大片豆花中煽动它们的手，
乳色豆花嵌着黑色的眼，而叶子像疲惫的心。
卷须在那根藤向上拖着的是血块吗？
不，不是，而是将来可食用的深红色花。

他们给我戴上时尚的白色意大利草帽
黑色的脸罩遮盖脸，我成为他们中的一员。
他们带我到山楂树丛，蜂巢围成圈。
是山楂闻起来如此恶心？
山楂赤裸的身体，迷醉它的孩子们。

正在进行某种手术？
外科医生正是我邻居等待的人，
戴着绿色头盔的幽灵，
闪亮的手套，白色的套装。
是屠夫，杂货商，邮递员，我认识的某个人？

我不能跑，我已长根，金雀花伤了我。
以其黄色的小包，带刺的锦囊。
我一旦奔跑就永远地跑下去。
白色的蜂巢舒适像处女，
封隔她的孵房，她的蜜，轻声嗡嗡响。

烟雾萦绕，树丛里的头巾。
聪明的蜂巢以为一切都结束了。
它们挪动着，先驱者，情绪激动仿佛松紧带。
若我站着不动，它们认为我是峨参植物，
轻信的头脑不为它们的憎恨所打动，

即使点头也不，树篱里的名人。
村民们打开小房，他们在找寻蜂后。
她藏起来了？她在吃蜜？她非常聪明。
她太老了，老了，老了，她必须再活一年，她知道。
而在它们指关节宽的蜂房里，新的处女蜂

梦想一场它们必然会赢的决斗，
一道蜡帘将它们与新娘腾飞阻隔，
女凶手向上飞进天堂去爱她。
村民们在移动处女蜂，不会有残杀。
老蜂后没有现身，她这样不懂感激吗？

我筋疲力尽，我筋疲力尽——
白色的柱仿佛刀光中的昏暗。
我是魔术师的女儿，我不会退缩。
村民们在脱去他们的保护装，他们在握手。
树林里的白色长箱是谁的，他们完成了什么，为何我发冷。

蜂蜇

双手赤裸，我掌管蜂窝。
白衣男子微笑着，双手赤裸，
我们的粗棉布手套干净香甜，
我们手腕袖口是漂亮的百合花
我与他

我们之间有一千只干净的蜂房，
八个黄色杯状蜂窝，
蜂巢本身像白色茶杯，
上面有粉色花儿朵朵，
我曾经给它涂磁漆，太多的爱

心想着“甜蜜，甜蜜”。
孵房灰白如贝壳的化石
让我感到害怕，它们太老了。
我在买什么，虫蛀的桃花心木？
那里面果真有蜂后吗？

若有的话，她老了，
翅膀像破旧的披肩，修长的身躯
磨掉了绒毛——
可怜、赤裸、不体面的被废蜂后。
我站在一队

极普通的女子中，仿佛长翅的蜜蜂，
采蜜苦工。
我并非苦工
虽说我吞食灰尘已经多年
用我浓密的头发擦干盘子。

而我的怪异蒸发，
危险皮肤中渗出蓝色露水。
她们会恨我吗？
这些妇女只是奔忙，
只关心樱桃开花，苜蓿开花的消息？

几乎结束了。
我在掌控中。
这是我的采蜜器，
无须思考便可工作，
在春天里，打开，像勤劳的处女蜂

冲刷乳色羽冠
正如月亮，为象牙色的粉末，冲刷海洋。
第三个人在注视。
他与卖蜂人或我都无关。
现在他走了

迈了八大步，了不起的替罪羊。
这是他的一只拖鞋，那是另一只，
还有白色亚麻方巾，
他用方巾代替帽子。
他是温柔的，

他挥汗如雨地劳动
想让大地结出果实。
蜜蜂找到了他
像谎言蜇了他的双唇，
毁坏了他的容貌。

他们认为死是值得的，但我
要恢复自我，一只蜂后。
她死了，还是在沉睡？
她在哪里，
狮子般红色的身躯，透明的翅膀？

现在，她在飞
比过去的她更可怕，天空中
红色的疤痕，红色的彗星
在曾经杀死她的机器上空——
大陵墓，蜡制的房子。

蜂群

有人在我们镇上射击某物——
周日的街上响起沉闷的砰砰声。
嫉妒会引发流血事件，
会让玫瑰变黑。
他们在射击谁？

刀拔出对付的是你
在滑铁卢，滑铁卢，拿破仑，
你背上的驼峰，厄尔巴岛，
还有那雪，排列着铮亮刀剑
一堆又一堆，发出嘘嘘声！

嘘！你玩耍的是些象棋人，
象牙制的没有活力的人物。
泥浆在喉咙间挪动，
法国人皮靴底下的垫脚石。
俄罗斯镀金粉色圆顶融化了，漂浮

在贪婪的熔炉里。烟雾，烟雾。
蜂群抱成球状，逃走
躲在黑色的松树上，七十英尺高。
必须将它击落。砰！砰！
沉闷的枪声，蜂群以为是雷声。

蜂群以为是上帝的声音
纵容那狗咧着嘴笑，那嘴，那爪，
黄色腰腿，一只领头狗
在象牙色骨头上咧嘴笑
像那只狗，那只狗，像每个人。

蜜蜂躲得很高。七十英尺高！
俄罗斯，波兰，德国！
缓和的山丘，相似的陈旧紫红色
田野缩成一个便士
旋转流进河，河流交叉。

卷成黑球的蜜蜂，就像，
一只飞翔的刺猬，浑身长刺。
有灰色双手的男子站在蜂窝下面
它们的梦想，蜂拥的车站
火车，忠实于它们的钢铁弧线，

离开，到达，驶向没有尽头的国家。
砰！砰！它们跌落
松解了，一团常青藤。
战车驭手，骑马侍从，雄伟的部队，不过如此！
红色破旧碎片，拿破仑！

胜利的最后一块奖章。
蜂群被击落，掉进三角草帽，
厄尔巴[1]，厄尔巴，大海中的小水泡！
陆军元帅，海军将军，陆军将军将自己白色
半身像挪进壁龛。

非常有教育意义！
木讷，带条纹的尸体
在饰有法国母亲软垫的木板上移动
进入新的陵墓，
一座象牙宫殿，叉枝松树。

有灰色双手的男人微笑着——
一个生意人的微笑，非常实际。
它们根本不是手
而是石膏容器。
砰！砰！“他们原本会杀了我。”

蜂蜇大如图钉！
蜜蜂似乎有荣誉之感，
黑色的难对付的头脑。
拿破仑满意了，他对一切都满意！
啊，欧洲！啊，大量的蜜！

[1]Elba：厄尔巴岛，意大利中部托斯卡纳大区西边海域的一个岛屿，意大利的第三大岛。1841年3月拿破仑被流放在这个岛上。

过冬[1]

这是轻松时光，无事可做。
我摇动那接生婆的采蜜器，
我采到了蜂蜜，
六罐蜜，
酒窖里的六只猫眼。

在无窗户的黑暗中过冬，
这所房子的中心。
紧挨着前一个房客腐臭的果酱，
而空空的瓶子闪烁——
某某先生的杜松子酒。

这个房间我从未来过，
这个房间令我难以呼吸。
黑色积聚，像一只蝙蝠，
没有光线
只有手电筒，它微弱的

中国黄落在恐怖物体上——
黑色的愚钝。腐烂。
附着鬼魂。
是它们拥有我，
既不残忍也不漠然，

只有忽视。
这是蜜蜂坚持的时光——蜜蜂们
非常慢，我几乎没有注意它们，
像战士们那样
钻进糖浆罐

去填补我取过的蜂蜜。
泰特莱尔白糖使它们维持生命，
这精制的雪。
它们赖以生存的是泰特莱尔，不是花朵。
它们吃了它。寒冷降临。

现在它们聚成球状一团，
黑乎乎
对抗着所有的白色。
雪的微笑是白色的。
它伸展自己，一英里长犹如迈森[2]

瓷器的躯体，温暖的日子，
它们运送死去的蜜蜂。
蜜蜂都是雌的，
工蜂和身躯修长的蜂后。
它们已经消灭了雄蜂，

呆板的、笨拙的蹒跚者，粗野的人。
冬天是女人的——
那个女子，仍在编织，
在西班牙式的胡桃木摇篮旁，
她的身体似寒冷中的球茎，麻木而无法思考。

蜂群会活下来吗？菖兰将会
成功地贮存它们的火种
进入另一年？
它们将品尝什么，黑儿波花吗？
蜜蜂在飞。它们体味春天。

[1]此诗汉译首次发表在《译林》2013年第2期，现稍作修改。

[2]Meissen：迈森，一种产自德国的瓷器。

小赋格曲

紫杉黑色的树枝摇摆；
寒冷的云朵飘过。
那个又聋又哑的人
示意盲人，却被忽视了。

我喜欢忧郁的陈述。
瞧，那朵云平淡无奇！
苍白仿佛一只眼！
盲人钢琴师的那只眼

在船上，我的桌上。
他摸索着找食物
他的手指像鼬鼠的鼻子。
我忍不住瞧着。

他可以听见贝多芬：
黑色紫杉，白色云朵，
可怕的多种并发症。
手指受阻——琴键的凌乱声。

如空盘那般愚蠢，
因此盲人微笑了。
我讨厌大声喧哗，
紫杉树篱般的大赋格曲。

耳聋是另一回事。
如此黑暗的烟囱，我的父亲！
我听见你的声音
忧郁而叶茂，仿佛我的童年。

紫杉树篱一样的各种秩序
哥特式、野蛮的，纯粹的德国人。
已死的男人为此哭泣。
我毫无内疚。

紫杉树，我的耶稣。
它没有受折磨？
而你，在大战中
在加利福尼亚的熟食店

在切那些香肠！
它们使我的睡眠有趣，
红色，斑驳，仿佛切下的脖子。
然后一片寂静！

另一种秩序的无声寂静。
我那时七岁，一无所知。
人生却开始了。
你有一条腿，还有普鲁士人的头脑。

相似的云朵
正飘散在无聊的床单上。
你没说什么？
我的记忆缺损。

我记得一只蓝眼，
装满柑橘的手提包。
就是这个人！
死亡呈现，抑郁地，像一棵黑色树。

那刻我幸存了，
正在安排我的早晨。
这些是我的手指，这是我的婴儿。
云朵是结婚礼服，那种苍白。

译后记

“普拉斯诗歌研究”是我于2011—2012年间在美国东华盛顿大学访学期间的课题，我在图书馆阅读了普拉斯不同时期创作的诗以及大量英美普拉斯研究的资料，开始撰写普拉斯诗歌研究方面的文章，才发现当时国内还没有普拉斯诗集的汉译本，可以找到的汉译诗又比较少，比如《美国现代诗选》[1]中有普拉斯的诗作9首，《美国现代诗钞》[2]中有4首，《美国自白派诗选》[3]有28首。对照英语原诗读这些译诗，感觉有不少译诗与原诗差异比较大，自己就开始试着翻译。2013年首次在《译林》2013年第2期发表了译诗《过冬》（“Wintering”）；2015年第1期发表了《晨歌》（“Morning Song”）和《气球》（“Ballons”）、第3期发表了《仁慈》（“Kindness”）和《话语》（“Words”）。我集中翻译普拉斯后期诗歌，日积月累，最终完成了本诗集的翻译。虽说理解、翻译普拉斯的诗绝非易事，但是每一次阅读、翻译一首诗都有不同的体验和惊喜，将它们结集出版，能与喜欢普拉斯诗歌的读者分享，不胜愉悦。

诗集Ariel是普拉斯后期重要诗集，标志着诗人诗歌创作的顶峰成就。汉译《艾丽尔》这三个字并不是随意的音译，而是有意而为。虽说普拉斯诗集英文名Ariel与莎士比亚《暴风雨》中的火之精灵“Ariel”（通常译为“爱丽儿”）同名，但诗集名的汉译必须与精灵“爱丽儿”有所区分，因为普拉斯将自己的诗集取名Ariel具有更为丰富的内涵，这在“译者序”中已有说明。在诗人眼里，她的诗集《艾丽尔》仿佛浴火重生的凤凰，《女拉撒路》诗的结尾小节就有这样的描述：“我从灰烬中升起/披着一头红发/我像空气一样吃男人。”（“Out of the ash/I rise with my red hair/And I eat men like air.”）。普拉斯采用这个包含多重含义的Ariel作为诗集名，蕴含了重要的诗学意义。《艾丽尔》诗集在风格和主题上与她同时代的自白派诗人的诗歌作品不一样，与普拉斯早期的自白诗也有明显的不同，《艾丽尔》诗集是普拉斯后期诗歌创作过程中形成自己独特风格和诗学声音的一个重要里程碑。

同样，诗集中有些诗名的翻译也经过再三斟酌，在此举三个例子。第一首诗“The Rabbit Catcher”，译成汉语《捕兔人》或《捕兔器》，从纯粹翻译的角度来评判都无可厚非。“catcher”这个词既可以指人也可以指物，比如“捕捉器”“接球手”，还有塞林格的名著《麦田里的守望者》（The Catcher in the Rye）。但是普拉斯的这首诗具有双重意义，既指英国农民为抓捕野兔在野外设置的陷阱，同时也暗示婚姻对女性的窒息犹如陷阱困住野兔，而《捕兔人》《捕兔器》各自包含了一层意思。细心的读者会发现，此诗第三节第四行出现了“陷阱”（“the snares”）：“那些陷阱几乎隐藏得无形——”（“And the snares almost effaced themselves—”），此处的“snares”应该指诗名中的“catcher”。因此，我觉得将诗名翻译成《捕兔陷阱》比较合适。另一首诗，“Death & Co.”，此诗名与位于纽约东区第六街433号的酒吧同名，纯属偶然还是诗人有意而为？这需要进一步研究考证。根据普拉斯在为英国广播公司朗读这首诗时解释：“这首诗是关于死亡的双重或精神分裂的性质——布莱克的死亡面具仿佛大理石般的冰冷，蠕虫、水和其他分解代谢物质令人害怕的柔软，这两种特性密不可分。我将死亡的这两个方面想象成两位男子，两位拜访过我们的生意上的朋友。”[4]所以我将此诗名译为《死亡与伴侣》。第三首诗，“Cut”开始翻译为《伤口》，但一直感觉有些不妥。“伤口”是“切割”的动作造成的后果，而此诗主要描写言说者不小心将拇指顶端割伤后的“拇指残片”，它“带领”读者回顾了美国简短的历史。所以我最后将此诗名译成《残片》，虽说“残片”这个词与英文词“cut”看似相差甚远，但是“cut”这个词作名词使用，可以表示“切片”。

诗中涉及人名、地名，按照翻译界约定俗成的音译方法，首先考虑音译，有时便于读者更好地理解，可以考虑在音译的基础上再加注。比如诗名“Lesbos”译作《莱斯博斯岛》，又如普拉斯的唯一长诗“Berck-Plage”汉译成《贝尔克海滩》。诗名“Magi”的汉译，历经周折考虑，若沿用《麦琪的礼物》读者都熟悉的翻译，可译作《麦琪》。但是“Magi”毕竟不是人名，采用这种类似的音译会引起误解。“Magi”若译作《东方三博士》《东方三贤士》，则此译名在字数上与原诗名相差甚远，应该考虑译诗名的字数与原诗名的字数最接近。因此，“Magi”译作《贤士》，意义明了，用词简洁。

还有这两首诗名的汉译也值得思考：“Daddy”和“Poppies in October”。“Daddy”应该译成《爹地》《爹爹》还是《爸爸》？“爸爸”是普通话词汇，口语，孩子对父亲的称呼；“爹爹”和“爹地”也是口语，但它们是方言词汇，不合适。从文体上来分析，普拉斯的“Daddy”一诗肯定不是用英语中的某种方言创作的，所以“Daddy”应该译成《爸爸》比较合适。

有时，翻译不仅仅是纯粹的语言问题，而且还涉及文化甚至政治问题。诗名“Poppies in October”（还有一首“ Poppies in July”）就是值得认真探究的一例。

“Poppies in October”应该译作《十月的罂粟花》还是《十月的虞美人》？罂粟和虞美人都属于罂粟植物大科目，但它们是两种不同的植物。在英国，每年的11月11日被称为“Remembrance Day”，译作“国殇纪念日”或“战争纪念日”，这一天也叫“Poppy Day”，即“虞美人花义卖日”，人们佩戴人工制作的虞美人小红花来纪念在二次世界大战中牺牲的战士，义卖所得用于帮助那些幸存的残疾人士或死亡者的遗孤。虞美人小红花，英文名corn poppy（学名Papaver rhoeas），而罂粟的英文名opium poppy（学名为Papaver somniferum，其中somniferum意为“催眠”，具有麻醉性）。罂粟是制取鸦片的主要原料，其提取物也是多种镇静剂的来源；而虞美人作为观赏花，在英国和欧洲其他国家的公共场所和家庭花园都有大片种植。2011年11月英国首相卡梅伦访华期间的11日，首相及其随从人员佩戴小红花，被国内媒体误译成“罂粟花”，英国访华团成员曾被要求摘下小红花，但是遭到拒绝。由于中英之间的“鸦片战争”（译作“First Opium War”）以及鸦片对中国人曾经的危害，“小红花”事件因这个翻译的错误引起了官方与民间的误会。时隔两年之后，中央电视台新闻频道在2013年11月11日晚间播出的新闻中对此争议做了解释，新闻题为“英国：罂粟花还是虞美人？ 纪念红花引发争议”。在英国的央视记者采访了伦敦的花店老板，他介绍了这个纪念日的来历以及两种花的区分，英国人在国殇纪念日佩戴的虞美人小红花是一种观赏花，与制作鸦片的罂粟没有任何关系。因此，在英语中虞美人花既与死亡有密切关联，也蕴含死亡中的生命之意。普拉斯的诗“Poppies in October”就蕴含死亡与生命之双重意义：“鲜红的血从心脏涌出渗透大衣，令人惊骇——”（“Whose red heart blooms through her coat so astoundingly——”）虞美人花的样子特别像一颗子弹打进了身体，而红色花瓣就像是渗透出来的鲜血。因此 “Poppies in October”应该翻译成《十月的虞美人》。

翻译诗歌所遵循的原则，取决于诗歌本身所具有的特点。《艾丽尔》诗集中质朴的词语、丰富的意象和独特的音乐性是《艾丽尔》诗歌的三大特点。诗行的长短不受约束，也没有规律性的押韵；短诗行中蕴含的力量与长诗行的诗句之间构成一种张力，独特的音乐性又增强了这种力量。诗歌中视觉意象、听觉意象、动觉意象令人目不暇接，自由而快速变化着的意象流畅地跳跃、转换，而诗歌真正的含义需要细读才可理解。因此，翻译《艾丽尔》诗歌所遵循的首要原则是忠实，译诗必须在形式和意义都忠实于原诗。译诗以词为翻译单位，选用汉语普通词汇，尽可能避免套用汉译成语、民间俗语、惯用语等具有中国文化或宗教色彩的词语。比如《女拉撒路》诗中第七节最后一行：“And like the cat I have nine times to die.”翻译成“可我像猫可以死九次。”，而不是套用汉语俗语“我像猫一样有九条命”。有时直译会造成上下文意思不清楚或者译诗给人莫名奇怪的感觉，那就采用意译的方法给予设当的补救，加上灵活的变通方法，或调整词序，或改变词性。比如《气球》中的最后两节，诗人在描写“小弟弟”玩气球时的情景，第三人称“他”就成为这两节诗描写的中心，因此翻译时将最后两句诗行做了句子前后的调整：“他的小拳/捏住了一片红色的碎皮。”（“A red / Shred in his little fist.”）这也符合英汉翻译时词语词性的转换变通方法，即将静态的英语介词“in”翻译成汉语的动词“捏住”。

《艾丽尔》诗歌中丰富新颖的意象，极少数为诗人随意摘取，大多数意象是诗人精心设计的。比如，《一个秘密》第三、第四节中的“长颈鹿”“伊甸园”和“河马”是诗人随意从孩子的连环画中摘取的意象。诗中的意象自然也是采用直译，保留其原汁原味。有些意象，若采用直译的翻译方法，汉语读起来不知所云，就舍去其喻体词，将其本体词翻译出来。比较《美杜莎》诗开篇第一节的英诗和译诗，不难发现这一节第二行中的“white sticks”译成了“白浪”，就是舍去“白棍”这个喻体词，将其本体词“白浪”译出：“海岬角处，嘴似的石头塞子，/双眼由白浪推着翻滚，/双耳盛满了大海的混乱，……。”（“Off that landspit of stony mouth-plugs，/Eyes rolled by white sticks，/Ears cupping the sea’s incoherences，….”） 又如《慕尼黑时装模特》诗中的第九节、第十节：“放下/鞋子将它们擦得乌黑锃亮”（“setting / Down shoes for a polish of carbon”），其中的“carbon”（直译为“碳”），而在译诗中将此意象的比喻意义译出，这是最低要求。有时，译者多加一个词，译诗意义会有所不同，比如《晨歌》第四节中母亲描写小婴儿晚间的呼吸声：“整个晚上你蛾虫般的呼吸/在扁平的粉色玫瑰中颤动。”（“All night your moth-breath / Flickers among the flat pink roses.”） 此诗句中的“pink roses”比喻婴儿“粉色的嘴唇”，若译成了“粉色玫瑰花丛中”多一个词“花丛”，意义就有所不同了。

普拉斯在《艾丽尔》诗集中塑造了丰富多彩、性格各异的女性人物形象，她们力争彻底改变自我、构建女性主体和寻求性别写作身份的渴望和挣扎在《艾丽尔》诗歌中形成一种独特的声音，宣言性的呐喊和受抑制的诉说相互渗透。无论是愉悦还是愤怒，诙谐还是讽刺，这些女性声音都显示出她们自身强烈的情感力量和音韵魅力。但是《艾丽尔》诗歌的音乐性在翻译过程中最难重现，比如《爸爸》一诗开始的童谣节奏；比如《深闺》诗中可数名词、不可数名词后面添加的“s”，诗人让这种持续不断、咝咝流动之声贯穿整首诗，既暗示女性的附属地位，又发出女性不安和骚动的警告。正如美国著名诗人弗罗斯特的名句“Poetry is what gets lost in translation.”，我将之理解为“诗意乃翻译中失去的东西”。那么《艾丽尔》诗歌之音韵特色就是在翻译过程中最容易丢失的诗意、最无法再现的诗意。

译诗，必须在形式和意义都忠实于原诗。诗之形，即诗的外在的形式，它首先是一首诗的开篇第一句、第一个词。其次，一首诗由几个小节组成，每节由几个诗行；每个小节的诗行数是否均等以及诗行的长短；诗行何时停顿，何时跨行等等。第三，诗人刻意选择的词语和句型的重复，也是构成诗之形的主要特征。诗歌的形式不仅仅是诗歌的外部形态，而且是诗歌内容的主要组成部分，具有特殊的意义。翻译《艾丽尔》诗集，基本不改动诗篇的第一行诗，第一个字，因为这是诗人精心选择的；翻译时尽可能不要与后面的诗行进行调整，这是必须遵循的重要原则。众所周知，普拉斯生前自己安排的《艾丽尔》诗集，是由诗《晨歌》中的首行首字 “爱”为开篇第一词。

《艾丽尔》诗歌中的跨行句独具特色，为了强调，有一个词构成的跨行句，比如《女拉撒路》诗中有关死亡的名句：“死去/是一种艺术，就像其他任何事。”（“Dying / Is an art，like everything else.”）。虽说“Dying”是一个词，但它是动词“die”的现在分词形式，诗人讲述的是“死亡”的过程，因此翻译成汉语为“死去”。又如：《艾丽尔》诗的结尾两行诗：“冲进红色的/眼，早晨的大锅。”（“Into the red / Eye，the cauldron of morning.”）这样的句型尽可能完整保留。

《艾丽尔》诗歌中有不少重复的句型，翻译时应该尽可能保留句型的重复。比如《女拉撒路》诗中诗人重复相同的句型在汉译中得到了重现，如第十六节：“我这样做，好像它在地狱。/我这样做，感觉它很真实。”（“I do it so it feels like hell. / I do it so it feels real.”） 又如第十七节：“非常容易做，在单间里。/非常容易做，呆着不动。”（“It’s easy enough to do it in a cell. / It’s easy enough to do it and stay put.”）《女拉撒路》诗中用重复的句型描写自杀，给读者的印象就是这种自杀行为对叙说者而言是既单调又平常，重复必然有其特殊意义。再看《过冬》诗中第三节：“这个房间我从未来过，/这个房间令我难以呼吸。”（“This is the room I have never been in. / This is the room I could never breathe in.”）句型“这个房间”的重复暗示了单调的生活，陌生的房间也会带来窒息和恐惧。

翻译诗歌，既不可人云亦云，也不提倡标新立异，而是努力做到在形式和意义这两个方面最贴近原诗。瓦尔特·本雅明在其著名的《译者的任务》一文中指出：“真正的译文是透明的；这样的译文不会遮蔽原文，也不阻挡原文的光芒，而是仿佛通过加强自身媒介，让纯语言更加圆满地照射在原文上。实现这一点的方法首先是对句法的直译，这种方法证明，译者需要关注的因素是词而不是句子。假如句子是墙，直译的意义就是拱廊。”[5]

这本诗集翻译完成之后，我读到了本雅明这段经常被译者学者引用的话，虽然它没有指导我做诗歌翻译，却非常恰当地总结了我的翻译实践。感谢译林出版社推出普拉斯这本诗集的双语版，让普拉斯的诗作以它们“原有的光芒”照亮读者，呈现给中国读者它本来的面目。

这本译诗集能够顺利出版，首先要感谢译林出版社王理行老师的推荐、常熟理工学院洪庆福教授的鼓励。在诗歌翻译和修改过程中，东南大学王翠红老师、常熟理工学院戴新蕾老师给予我极大的帮助，在此非常感谢！特别是戴老师，对诗歌的理解和感悟给了我很多的启发和灵感。在译诗修改和校对过程中，感谢编辑赵丽娟老师、王秀莉老师认真校对并提出修改意见！

[1]赵毅衡编译《美国现代诗选》（下），外国文学出版社1985年版，第602—617页，共收录9首诗：《穿黑衣的人》《浮雕》《晨歌》《申请人》《十月的罂粟花》《词儿》《爹爹》《渡湖》和《快邮》。

[2]江枫译《美国现代诗钞》，青海人民出版社1986年版，第290—300页，共收录4首：《晨曲》《拉扎勒女士》《申请者》和《词》。

[3]赵琼、岛子译《美国自白派诗选》，漓江出版社1987年版，共收录28首：《晨歌》《边缘》《十月的罂粟》《爹爹》等。

[4]Sylvia Plath, The Collected Poems, New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 2008. p.294.

[5]Walter Benjamin, The Task of The Translator, trans. by Harry Zohn, edited by Lawrence Venuti, The Translation Studies Reader, London and New York: Routledge, 2000, p.21.

Morning Song

Love set you going like a fat gold watch.
The midwife slapped your footsoles, and your bald cry
Took its place among the elements.

Our voices echo, magnifying your arrival. New statue.
In a drafty museum, your nakedness
Shadows our safety. We stand round blankly as walls.

I’m no more your mother
Than the cloud that distills a mirror to reflect its own slow
Effacement at the wind’s hand.

All night your moth-breath
Flickers among the flat pink roses. I wake to listen:
A far sea moves in my ear.

One cry, and I stumble from bed, cow-heavy and floral
In my Victorian nightgown.
Your mouth opens clean as a cat’s. The window square

Whitens and swallows its dull stars. And now you try
Your handful of notes;
The clear vowels rise like balloons.

(1961/02/19. pp.156—157. No.138)

The Rabbit Catcher

It was a place of force—
The wind gagging my mouth with my own blown hair,
Tearing off my voice, and the sea
Blinding me with its lights, the lives of the dead
Unreeling in it, spreading like oil.

I tasted the malignity of the gorse,
Its black spikes,
The extreme unction of its yellow candle-flowers.
They had an efficiency, a great beauty,
And were extravagant, like torture.

There was only one place to get to.
Simmering, perfumed,
The paths narrowed into the hollow.
And the snares almost effaced themselves—
Zeros, shutting on nothing,

Set close, like birth pangs.
The absence of shrieks
Made a hole in the hot day, a vacancy.
The glassy light was a clear wall,
The thickets quiet.

I felt a still busyness, an intent.
I felt hands round a tea mug, dull, blunt,
Ringing the white china.
How they awaited him, those little deaths!
They waited like sweethearts. They excited him.

And we, too, had a relationship—
Tight wires between us,
Pegs too deep to uproot, and a mind like a ring
Sliding shut on some quick thing,
The constriction killing me also.

(1962/05/21. pp.193—194. No. 164)

The Applicant

First, are you our sort of a person?
Do you wear
A glass eye, false teeth or a crutch,
A brace or a hook,
Rubber breasts or a rubber crotch,

Stitches to show something’s missing? No, no? Then
How can we give you a thing?
Stop crying.
Open your hand.
Empty? Empty. Here is a hand

To fill it and willing
To bring teacups and roll away headaches
And do whatever you tell it.
Will you marry it?
It is guaranteed

To thumb shut your eyes at the end
And dissolve of sorrow.
We make new stock from the salt.
I notice you are stark naked.
How about this suit——

Black and stiff, but not a bad fit.
Will you marry it?
It is waterproof, shatterproof, proof
Against fire and bombs through the roof.
Believe me, they’ll bury you in it.

Now your head, excuse me, is empty.
I have the ticket for that.
Come here, sweetie, out of the closet.
Well, what do you think of that?
Naked as paper to start

But in twenty-five years she’ll be silver,
In fifty, gold.
A living doll, everywhere you look.
It can sew, it can cook,
It can talk, talk, talk.

It works, there is nothing wrong with it.
You have a hole, it’s a poultice.
You have an eye, it’s an image.
My boy, it’s your last resort.
Will you marry it, marry it, marry it.

(1962/10/11. pp.221—222. No.182)

Lady Lazarus

I have done it again.
One year in every ten
I manage it——

A sort of walking miracle, my skin
Bright as a Nazi lampshade,
My right foot

A paperweight,
My face a featureless,fine
Jew linen.

Peel off the napkin
O my enemy.
Do I terrify?——

The nose, the eye pits, the full set of teeth?
The sour breath
Will vanish in a day.

Soon, soon the flesh
The grave cave ate will be
At home on me

And I a smiling woman.
I am only thirty.
And like the cat I have nine times to die.

This is Number Three.
What a trash
To annihilate each decade.

What a million filaments.
The peanut-crunching crowd
Shoves in to see

Them unwrap me hand and foot——
The big strip tease.
Gentlemen, ladies

These are my hands
My knees.
I may be skin and bone,

Nevertheless, I am the same, identical woman.
The first time it happened I was ten.
It was an accident.

The second time I meant
To last it out and not come back at all.
I rocked shut

As a seashell.
They had to call and call
And pick the worms off me like sticky pearls.

Dying
Is an art, like everything else.
I do it exceptionally well.

I do it so it feels like hell.
I do it so it feels real.
I guess you could say I’ve a call.

It’s easy enough to do it in a cell.
It’s easy enough to do it and stay put.
It’s the theatrical

Comeback in broad day
To the same place, the same face, the same brute
Amused shout:

‘A miracle!’
That knocks me out.
There is a charge

For the eyeing of my scars, there is a charge
For the hearing of my heart——
It really goes.

And there is a charge, a very large charge
For a word or a touch
Or a bit of blood

Or a piece of my hair or my clothes.
So, so, Herr Doktor.
So, Herr Enemy.

I am your opus,
I am your valuable,
The pure gold baby

That melts to a shriek.
I turn and burn.
Do not think I underestimate your great concern.

Ash, ash—
You poke and stir.
Flesh, bone, there is nothing there——

A cake of soap,
A wedding ring,
A gold filling.

Herr God, Herr Lucifer
Beware
Beware.

Out of the ash
I rise with my red hair
And I eat men like air.

(1962/10/23—29. pp.244—247. No. 198)

A Secret

A secret! A secret!
How superior.
You are blue and huge, a traffic policeman,
Holding up one palm—

A difference between us?
I have one eye, you have two.
The secret is stamped on you,
Faint, undulant watermark.

Will it show in the black detector?
Will it come out
Wavery, indelible, true
Through the African giraffe in its Edeny greenery,

The Moroccan hippopotamus?
They stare from a square, stiff frill.
They are for export,
One a fool, the other a fool.

A secret... An extra amber
Brandy finger
Roosting and cooing‘You, you’
Behind two eyes in which nothing is reflected but monkeys.

A knife that can be taken out
To pare nails,
To lever the dirt.
‘It won’t hurt.’

An illegitimate baby—
That big blue head—
How it breathes in the bureau drawer!
‘Is that lingerie, pet?

‘It smells of salt cod, you had better
Stab a few cloves in an apple,
Make a sachet or
Do away with the bastard.

‘Do away with it altogether.’
‘No, no, it is happy there.’
‘But it wants to get out!
Look, look! It is wanting to crawl.’

My god, there goes the stopper!
The cars in the Place de la Concorde—
Watch out!
A stampede, a stampede!

Horns twirling and jungle gutturals!
An exploded bottle of stout,
Slack foam in the lap.
You stumble out,

Dwarf baby,
The knife in your back.
‘I feel weak.’
The secret is out.

(1962/10/10. pp.219—220. No. 181)

The Jailor

My night sweats grease his breakfast plate.
The same placard of blue fog is wheeled into position
With the same trees and headstones.
Is that all he can come up with,
The rattle of keys?

I have been drugged and raped.
Seven hours knocked out of my right mind
Into a black sack
Where I relax, foetus or cat,
Lever of his wet dreams.

Something is gone.
My sleeping capsule, my red and blue zeppelin
Drops me from a terrible altitude.
Carapace smashed,
I spread to the beaks of birds.

O little gimlets—
What holes this papery day is already full of!
He has been burning me with cigarettes,
Pretending I am a negress with pink paws.
I am myself. That is not enough.

The fever trickles and stiffens in my hair.
My ribs show. What have I eaten?
Lies and smiles.
Surely the sky is not that color,
Surely the grass should be rippling.

All day, gluing my church of burnt matchsticks,
I dream of someone else entirely.
And he, for this subversion,
Hurts me, he
With his armor of fakery,

His high cold masks of amnesia.
How did I get here?
Indeterminate criminal,
I die with variety—
Hung, starved, burned, hooked.

I imagine him
Impotent as distant thunder,
In whose shadow I have eaten my ghost ration.
I wish him dead or away.
That, it seems, is the impossibility.

That being free. What should the dark
Do without fevers to eat?
What should the light
Do without eyes to knife, what would he
Do, do, do without me?

(1962/10/17. pp.226—227. No. 185)

Cut

For Susan O’Neil Roe

What a thrill——
My thumb instead of an onion.
The top quite gone
Except for a sort of hinge

Of skin,
A flap like a hat,
Dead white.
Then that red plush.

Little pilgrim,
The Indian’s axed your scalp.
Your turkey wattle
Carpet rolls

Straight from the heart.
I step on it,
Clutching my bottle
Of pink fizz.

A celebration, this is.
Out of a gap
A million soldiers run,
Redcoats, every one.

Whose side are they on?
O my
Homunculus, I am ill.
I have taken a pill to kill

The thin
Papery feeling.
Saboteur,
Kamikaze man——

The stain on your
Gauze Ku Klux Klan
Babushka
Darkens and tarnishes and when

The balled
Pulp of your heart
Confronts its small
Mill of silence

How you jump——
Trepanned veteran,
Dirty girl,
Thumb stump.

(1962/10/24. pp.235—236. No. 191)

Elm

For Ruth Fainlight

I know the bottom, she says. I know it with my great tap root:
It is what you fear.
I do not fear it:I have been there.

Is it the sea you hear in me,
Its dissatisfactions?
Or the voice of nothing, that was you madness?

Love is a shadow.
How you lie and cry after it
Listen:these are its hooves:it has gone off, like a horse.

All night I shall gallop thus, impetuously,
Till your head is a stone, your pillow a little turf,
Echoing, echoing.

Or shall I bring you the sound of poisons?
This is rain now, the big hush.
And this is the fruit of it: tin-white, like arsenic.

I have suffered the atrocity of sunsets.
Scorched to the root
My red filaments burn and stand, a hand of wires.

Now I break up in pieces that fly about like clubs.
A wind of such violence
Will tolerate no by standing:I must shriek.

The moon, also, is merciless:she would drag me
Cruelly, being barren.
Her radiance scathes me. Or perhaps I have caught her.

I let her go. I let her go
Diminished and flat, as after radical surgery.
How your bad dreams possess and endow me.

I am inhabited by a cry.
Nightly it flaps out
Looking, with its hooks, for something to love.

I am terrified by this dark thing
That sleeps in me;
All day I feel its soft, feathery turnings, its malignity.

Clouds pass and disperse.
Are those the faces of love, those pale irretrievables?
Is it for such I agitate my heart?

I am incapable of more knowledge.
What is this, this face
So murderous in its strangle of branches?——

Its snaky acids hiss.
It petrifies the will. These are the isolate, slow faults
That kill, that kill, that kill.

(1962/04/19. pp.192—193. No. 163)

The Night Dances

A smile fell in the grass.
Irretrievable!

And how will your night dances
Lose themselves. In mathematics?

Such pure leaps and spirals——
Surely they travel

The world forever, I shall not entirely
Sit emptied of beauties, the gift

Of your small breath, the drenched grass
Smell of your sleeps, lilies, lilies.

Their flesh bears no relation.
Cold folds of ego, the calla,

And the tiger, embellishing itself——
Spots, and a spread of hot petals.

The comets
Have such a space to cross,

Such coldness, forgetfulness.
So your gestures flake off——

Warm and human, then their pink light
Bleeding and peeling

Through the black amnesias of heaven.
Why am I given

These lamps, these planets
Falling like blessings, like flakes

Six-sided, white
On my eyes, my lips, my hair

Touching and melting.
Nowhere.

(1962/11/06. pp.249—250. No. 201)

The Detective

What was she doing when it blew in
Over the seven hills, the red furrow, the blue mountain?
Was she arranging cups? It is important.
Was she at the window, listening?
In that valley the train shrieks echo like souls on hooks.

That is the valley of death, though the cows thrive.
In her garden the lies were shaking out their moist silks
And the eyes of the killer moving sluglike and sidelong,
Unable to face the fingers, those egotists.
The fingers were tamping a woman into a wall,

A body into pipe, and the smoke rising.
This is the smell of years burning, here in the kitchen,
These are the deceits, tacked up like family photographs,
And this is a man, look at his smile,
The death weapon? No one is dead.

There is no body in the house at all.
There is the smell of polish, there are plush carpets.
There is the sunlight, playing its blades,
Bored hoodlum in a red room
Where the wireless talks to itself like an elderly relative.

Did it come like an arrow, did it come like a knife?
Which of the poisons is it?
Which of the nerve-curlers, the convulsors? Did it electrify?
This is a case without a body.
The body does not come into it at all.

It is a case of vaporization.
The mouth first, its absence reported
In the second year. It had been insatiable
And in punishment was hung out like brown fruit
To wrinkle and dry.

The breasts next.
These were harder, two white stones.
The milk came yellow, then blue and sweet as water.
There was no absence of lips, there were two children,
But their bones showed, and the moon smiled.

Then the dry wood, the gates.
The brown motherly furrows, the whole estate.
We walk on air, Watson.
There is only the moon, embalmed in phosphorus.
There is only a crow in a tree. Make notes.

(1962/10/01. pp.208—209. No.174)

Death&Co.

Two, of course there are two.
It seems perfectly natural now——
The one who never looks up, whose eyes are lidded
And balled, like Blake’s,
Who exhibits

The birthmarks that are his trademark——
The scald scar of water,
The nude
Verdigris of the condor.
I am red meat. His beak

Claps sidewise:I am not his yet.
He tells me how badly I photograph.
He tells me how sweet
The babies look in their hospital
Icebox, a simple

Frill at the neck,
Then the flutings of their Ionian
Death-gowns,
Then two little feet.
He does not smile or smoke.

The other does that,
His hair long and plausive.
Bastard
Masturbating a glitter,
He wants to be loved.

I do not stir.
The frost makes a flower,
The dew makes a star,
The dead bell,
The dead bell.

Somebody’s done for.

(1962/11/14. pp.254—255. No. 205)

Lesbos

Viciousness in the kitchen!
The potatoes hiss.
It is all Hollywood, windowless,
The fluorescent light wincing on and off like a terrible migraine,
Coy paper strips for doors—
Stage curtains, a widow’s frizz.
And I, love, am a pathological liar,
And my child—look at her, face down on the floor,
Little unstrung puppet, kicking to disappear—
Why she is schizophrenic,
Her face is red and white, a panic,
You have stuck her kittens outside your window
In a sort of cement well
Where they crap and puke and cry and she can’t hear.
You say you can’t stand her,
The bastard’s a girl.
You who have blown your tubes like a bad radio
Clear of voices and history, the staticky
Noise of the new.
You say I should drown the kittens. Their smell!

You say I should drown my girl.
She’ll cut her throat at ten if she’s mad at two.
The baby smiles, fat snail,
From the polished lozenges of orange linoleum.
You could eat him. He’s a boy.
You say your husband is just no good to you.
His Jew-Mama guards his sweet sex like a pearl.
You have one baby, I have two.
I should sit on a rock off Cornwall and comb my hair.
I should wear tiger pants, I should have an affair.
We should meet in another life, we should meet in air,
Me and you.

Meanwhile there’s a stink of fat and baby crap.
I’m doped and thick from my last sleeping pill.
The smog of cooking, the smog of hell
Floats our heads, two venomous opposites,
Our bones, our hair.
I call you Orphan, orphan. You are ill.
The sun gives you ulcers, the wind gives you T.B.
Once you were beautiful.
In New York, in Hollywood, the men said:‘Through?
Gee baby, you are rare.’
You acted, acted, acted for the thrill.
The impotent husband slumps out for a coffee.

I try to keep him in,
An old pole for the lightning,
The acid baths, the skyfuls off of you.
He lumps it down the plastic cobbled hill,
Flogged trolley. The sparks are blue.
The blue sparks spill,
Splitting like quartz into a million bits.

O jewel! O valuable!
That night the moon
Dragged its blood bag, sick
Animal
Up over the harbor lights.
And then grew normal,
Hard and apart and white.
The scale-sheen on the sand scared me to death.
We kept picking up handfuls, loving it,
Working it like dough, a mulatto body,
The silk grits.
A dog picked up your doggy husband. He went on.

Now I am silent, hate
Up to my neck,
Thick, thick.
I do not speak.
I am packing the hard potatoes like good clothes,
I am packing the babies,
I am packing the sick cats.
O vase of acid,
It is love you are full of. You know who you hate.
He is hugging his ball and chain down by the gate
That opens to the sea
Where it drives in, white and black,
Then spews it back.
Every day you fill him with soul-stuff, like a pitcher.
You are so exhausted.
Your voice my ear-ring,
Flapping and sucking, blood-loving bat.
That is that. That is that.
You peer from the door,
Sad hag.‘Every woman’s a whore.
I can’t communicate.’

I see your cute décor
Close on you like the fist of a baby
Or an anemone, that sea
Sweetheart, that kleptomaniac.
I am still raw.
I say I may be back.
You know what lies are for.
Even in your Zen heaven we shan’t meet.

(1962/10/18. pp.227—230. No.186)

The Other

You come in late, wiping your lips.
What did I leave untouched on the doorstep—

White Nike,
Streaming between my walls?

Smilingly, blue lightning
Assumes, like a meathook, the burden of his parts.

The police love you, you confess everything.
Bright hair, shoe-black, old plastic,

Is my life so intriguing?
Is it for this you widen your eye-rings?

Is it for this the air motes depart?
They are not air motes, they are corpuscles.

Open your handbag. What is that bad smell?
It is your knitting, busily

Hooking itself to itself,
It is your sticky candies.

I have your head on my wall.
Navel cords, blue-red and lucent,

Shriek from my belly like arrows, and these I ride.
O moon-glow, o sick one,

The stolen horses, the fornications
Circle a womb of marble.

Where are you going
That you suck breath like mileage?

Sulfurous adulteries grieve in a dream.
Cold glass, how you insert yourself

Between myself and myself.
I scratch like a cat.

The blood that runs is dark fruit—
An effect, a cosmetic.

You smile.
No, it is not fatal.

(1962/07/02. pp.201—202. No.168)

Stopped Dead

A squeal of brakes.
Or is it a birth cry?
And here we are, hung out over the dead drop
Uncle, pants factory Fatso, millionaire.
And you out cold beside me in your chair.

The wheels, two rubber grubs, bite their sweet tails.
Is that Spain down there?
Red and yellow, two passionate hot metals
Writhing and sighing, what sort of a scenery is it?
It isn’t England, it isn’t France, it isn’t Ireland.

It’s violent. We’re here on a visit,
With a goddam baby screaming off somewhere.
There’s always a bloody baby in the air.
I’d call it a sunset, but
Whoever heard a sunset yowl like that?

You are sunk in your seven chins, still as a ham.
Who do you think I am,
Uncle, uncle?
Sad Hamlet, with a knife?
Where do you stash your life?

Is it a penny, a pearl—
Your soul, your soul?
I’ll carry it off like a rich pretty girl,
Simply open the door and step out of the car
And live in Gibraltar on air, on air.

(1962/10/19. p.230. No.187)

The Courage of Shutting-Up

The courage of the shut mouth, in spite of artillery!
The line pink and quiet, a worm, basking.
There are black disks behind it, the disks of outrage,
And the outrage of a sky, the lined brain of it.
The disks revolve, they ask to be heard—

Loaded as they are, with accounts of bastardies.
Bastardies, usages, desertions and doubleness,
The needle journeying in its groove,
Silver beast between two dark canyons,
A great surgeon, now a tattooist,

Tattooing over and over the same blue grievances,
The snakes, the babies, the tits
On mermaids and two-legged dreamgirls.
The surgeon is quiet, he does not speak.
He has seen too much death, his hands are full of it.

So the disks of the brain revolve, like the muzzles of cannon.
Then there is that antique billhook, the tongue,
Indefatigable, purple. Must it be cut out?
It has nine tails, it is dangerous.
And the noise it flays from the air, once it gets going!

No, the tongue, too, has been put by,
Hung up in the library with the engravings of Rangoon
And the fox heads, the otter heads, the heads of dead rabbits.
It is a marvelous object—
The things it has pierced in its time.

But how about the eyes, the eyes, the eyes?
Mirrors can kill and talk, they are terrible rooms
In which a torture goes on one can only watch.
The face that lived in this mirror is the face of a dead man.
Do not worry about the eyes—

They may be white and shy, they are no stool pigeons,
Their death rays folded like flags
Of a country no longer heard of,
An obstinate independency
Insolvent among the mountains.

(1962/10/02. pp.209—210. No. 175)

Nick and the Candlestick

I am a miner. The light burns blue.
Waxy stalactites
Drip and thicken, tears

The earthen womb
Exudes from its dead boredom.
Black bat airs

Wrap me, raggy shawls,
Cold homicides.
They weld to me like plums.

Old cave of calcium
Icicles, old echoer.
Even the newts are white,

Those holy Joes.
And the fish, the fish——
Christ! They are panes of ice,

A vice of knives,
A piranha
Religion, drinking

Its first communion out of my live toes.
The candle
Gulps and recovers its small altitude,

Its yellows hearten.
O love, how did you get here?
O embryo

Remembering, even in sleep,
Your crossed position.
The blood blooms clean

In you, ruby.
The pain
You wake to is not yours.

Love, love,
I have hung over cave with roses,
With soft rugs——

The last of Victoriana.
Let the stars
Plummet to their dark address,

Let the mercuric
Atoms that cripple drip
Into the terrible well,

You are the one
Solid the spaces lean on, envious.
You are the baby in the barn.

(1962/10/29. pp.240—242. No. 196)

Berck-Plage

(1)

This is the sea, then, this great abeyance.
How the sun’s poultice draws on my inflammation.

Electrifyingly-colored sherbets, scooped from the freeze
By pale girls, travel the air in scorched hands.

Why is it so quiet, what are they hiding?
I have two legs, and I move smilingly.

A sandy damper kills the vibrations;
It stretches for miles, the shrunk voices

Waving and crutchless, half their old size.
The lines of the eye, scalded by these bald surfaces,

Boomerang like anchored elastics, hurting the owner.
Is it any wonder he puts on dark glasses?

Is it any wonder he affects a black cassock?
Here he comes now, among the mackerel gatherers

Who wall up their backs against him.
They are handling the black and green lozenges like the parts of a body.

The sea, that crystallized these,
Creeps away, many-snaked, with a long hiss of distress.

(2)

This black boot has no mercy for anybody.
Why should it, it is the hearse of a dead foot,

The high, dead, toeless foot of this priest
Who plumbs the well of his book,

The bent print bulging before him like scenery.
Obscene bikinis hide in the dunes,

Breasts and hips a confectioner’s sugar
Of little crystals, titillating the light,

While a green pool opens its eye,
Sick with what it has swallowed——

Limbs, images, shrieks. Behind the concrete bunkers
Two lovers unstick themselves.

O white sea-crockery,
What cupped sighs, what salt in the throat….

And the onlooker, trembling,
Drawn like a long material

Through a still virulence,
And a weed, hairy as privates.

(3)

On the balconies of the hotel, things are glittering.
Things, things——

Tubular steel wheelchairs, aluminum crutches.
Such salt-sweetness. Why should I walk

Beyond the breakwater, spotty with barnacles?
I am not a nurse, white and attendant,

I am not a smile.
These children are after something, with hooks and cries,

And my heart too small to bandage their terrible faults.
This is the side of a man:his red ribs,

The nerves bursting like trees, and this is the surgeon:
One mirrory eye——

A facet of knowledge.
On a striped mattress in one room

An old man is vanishing.
There is no help in his weeping wife.

Where are the eye-stones, yellow and valuable,
And the tongue, sapphire of ash.

(4)

A wedding-cake face in a paper frill.
How superior he is now.

It is like possessing a saint.
The nurses in their wing-caps are no longer so beautiful;

They are browning, like touched gardenias.
The bed is rolled from the wall.

This is what it is to be complete. It is horrible.
Is he wearing pajamas or an evening suit

Under the glued sheet from which his powdery beak
Rises so whitely, unbuffeted?

They propped his jaw with a book until it stiffened
And folded his hands, that were shaking:goodbye, goodbye.

Now the washed sheets fly in the sun,
The pillow cases are sweetening.

It is a blessing, it is a blessing:
The long coffin of soap-colored oak,

The curious bearers and the raw date
Engraving itself in silver with marvelous calm.

(5)

The gray sky lowers, the hills like a green sea
Run fold upon fold far off, concealing their hollows,

The hollows in which rock the thoughts of the wife——
Blunt, practical boats

Full of dresses and hats and china and married daughters.
In the parlor of the stone house

One curtain is flickering from the open window,
Flickering and pouring, a pitiful candle.

This is the tongue of the dead man:remember, remember.
How far he is now, his actions

Around him like living room furniture, like a décor.
As the pallors gather——

The pallors of hands and neighborly faces,
The elate pallors of flying iris.

They are flying off into nothing:remember us.
The empty benches of memory look over stones,

Marble facades with blue veins, and jelly-glassfuls of daffodils.
It is so beautiful up here:it is a stopping place.

(6)

The natural fatness of these lime leaves!——
Pollarded green balls, the trees march to church.

The voice of the priest, in thin air,
Meets the corpse at the gate,

Addressing it, while the hills roll the notes of the dead bell;
A glittler of wheat and crude earth.

What is the name of that color?——
Old blood of caked walls the sun heals,

Old blood of limb stumps, burnt hearts.
The widow with her black pocketbook and three daughters,

Necessary among the flowers,
Enfolds her face like fine linen,

Not to be spread again.
While a sky, wormy with put-by smiles,

Passes cloud after cloud.
And the bride flowers expend a freshness,

And the soul is a bride
In a still place, and the groom is red and forgetful, he is featureless.

(7)

Behind the glass of this car
The world purrs, shut-off and gentle.

And I am dark-suited and still, a member of the party,
Gliding up in low gear behind the cart.

And the priest is a vessel,
A tarred fabric, sorry and dull,

Following the coffin on its flowery cart like a beautiful woman,
A crest of breasts, eyelids and lips

Storming the hilltop.
Then, from the barred yard, the children

Smell the melt of shoe-blacking,
Their faces turning, wordless and slow,

Their eyes opening
On a wonderful thing——

Six round black hats in the grass and a lozenge of wood,
And a naked mouth, red and awkward.

For a minute the sky pours into the hole like plasma.
There is no hope, it is given up.

(1962/06/30. pp.196—201. No. 167)

Medusa

Off that landspit of stony mouth-plugs,
Eyes rolled by white sticks,
Ears cupping the sea’s incoherences,
You house your unnerving head—God-ball,
Lens of mercies,

Your stooges
Plying their wild cells in my keel’s shadow,
Pushing by like hearts,
Red stigmata at the very center,
Riding the rip tide to the nearest point of departure,

Dragging their Jesus hair.
Did I escape, I wonder?
My mind winds to you
Old barnacled umbilicus, Atlantic cable,
Keeping itself, it seems, in a state of miraculous repair.

In any case, you are always there,
Tremulous breath at the end of my line,
Curve of water upleaping
To my water rod, dazzling and grateful,
Touching and sucking.

I didn’t call you.
I didn’t call you at all.
Nevertheless, nevertheless
You steamed to me over the sea,
Fat and red, a placenta

Paralyzing the kicking lovers.
Cobra light
Squeezing the breath from the blood bells
Of the fuchsia. I could draw no breath,
Dead and moneyless,

Overexposed, like an X-ray.
Who do you think you are?
A Communion wafer? Blubbery Mary?
I shall take no bite of your body,
Bottle in which I live,

Ghastly Vatican.
I am sick to death of hot salt.
Green as eunuchs, your wishes
Hiss at my sins.
Off, off, eely tentacle!

There is nothing between us.

(1962/10/16. pp.224—226. No. 184)

Purdah

Jade—
Stone of the side,
The agonized

Side of green Adam, I
Smile, cross-legged,
Enigmatical,

Shifting my clarities.
So valuable!
How the sun polishes this shoulder!

And should
The moon, my
Indefatigable cousin

Rise, with her cancerous pallors,
Dragging trees—
Little bushy polyps,

Little nets,
My visibilities hide.
I gleam like a mirror.

At this facet the bridegroom arrives
Lord of the mirrors!
It is himself he guides

In among these silk
Screens, these rustling appurtenances.
I breathe, and the mouth

Veil stirs its curtain
My eye
Veil is

A concatenation of rainbows.
I am his.
Even in his

Absence, I
Revolve in my
Sheath of impossibles,

Priceless and quiet
Among these parakeets, macaws!
O chatterers

Attendants of the eyelash!
I shall unloose
One feather, like the peacock.

Attendants of the lip!
I shall unloose
One note

Shattering
The chandelier
Of air that all day flies

Its crystals
A million ignorants.
Attendants!

Attendants!
And at his next step
I shall unloose

I shall unloose—
From the small jeweled
Doll he guards like a heart—

The lioness,
The shriek in the bath,
The cloak of holes.

(1962/10/29. pp.242—244. No. 197)

The Moon and the Yew Tree

This is the light of the mind, cold and planetary.
The trees of the mind are black. The light is blue.
The grasses unload their griefs on my feet as if I were God,
Prickling my ankles and murmuring of their humility.
Fumy, spiritous mists inhabit this place
Separated from my house by a row of headstones.
I simply cannot see where there is to get to.

The moon is no door. It is a face in its own right,
White as a knuckle and terribly upset.
It drags the sea after it like a dark crime;it is quiet
With the O-gape of complete despair. I live here.
Twice on Sunday, the bells startle the sky——
Eight great tongues affirming the Resurrection.
At the end, they soberly bong out their names.

The yew tree points up.It has a Gothic shape.
The eyes lift after it and find the moon.
The moon is my mother. She is not sweet like Mary.
Her blue garments unloose small bats and owls.
How I would like to believe in tenderness——
The face of the effigy, gentled by candles,
Bending, on me in particular, its mild eyes.

I have fallen a long way. Clouds are flowering
Blue and mystical over the face of the stars.
Inside the church, the saints will all be blue,
Floating on their delicate feet over the cold pews,
Their hands and faces stiff with holiness.
The moon sees nothing of this. She is bald and wild.
And the message of the yew tree is blackness—blackness and silence.

(1961/10/22. pp.172—173. No. 153)

A Birthday Present

What is this, behind this veil, is it ugly, is it beautiful?
It is shimmering, has it breasts, has it edges?

I am sure it is unique, I am sure it is what I want.
When I am quiet at my cooking I feel it looking, I feel it thinking

‘Is this the one I am to appear for,
Is this the elect one, the one with black eye-pits and a scar?

Measuring the flour, cutting off the surplus,
Adhering to rules, to rules, to rules.

Is this the one for the annunciation?
My god, what a laugh!’

But it shimmers, it does not stop, and I think it wants me.
I would not mind if it were bones, or a pearl button.

I do not want much of a present, anyway, this year.
After all, I am alive only by accident.

I would have killed myself gladly that time any possible way.
Now there are these veils, shimmering like curtains,

The diaphanous satins of a January window
White as babies’ bedding and glittering with dead breath. O ivory!

It must be a tusk there, a ghost-column.
Can you not see I do not mind what it is.

Can you not give it to me?
Do not be ashamed—I do not mind if it is small.

Do not be mean, I am ready for enormity.
Let us sit down to it, one on either side, admiring the gleam,

The glaze, the mirrory variety of it.
Let us eat our last supper at it, like a hospital plate.

I know why you will not give it to me,
You are terrified

The world will go up in a shriek, and your head with it,
Bossed, brazen, an antique shield,

A marvel to your great-grandchildren.
Do not be afraid, it is not so.

I will only take it and go aside quietly.
You will not even hear me opening it, no paper crackle,

No falling ribbons, no scream at the end.
I do not think you credit me with this discretion.

If you only knew how the veils were killing my days.
To you they are only transparencies, clear air.

But my god, the clouds are like cotton.
Armies of them. They are carbon monoxide.

Sweetly, sweetly I breathe in,
Filling my veins with invisibles, with the million

Probable motes that tick the years off my life.
You are silver-suited for the occasion. O adding machine——

Is it impossible for you to let something go and have it go whole?
Must you stamp each piece in purple,

Must you kill what you can?
There is this one thing I want today, and only you can give it to me.

It stands at my window, big as the sky.
It breathes from my sheets, the cold dead center

Where spilt lives congeal and stiffen to history.
Let it not come by the mail, finger by finger.

Let it not come by word of mouth, I should be sixty
By the time the whole of it was delivered, and too numb to use it.

Only let down the veil, the veil, the veil.
If it were death

I would admire the deep gravity of it, its timeless eyes.
I would know you were serious.

There would be a nobility then, there would be a birthday.
And the knife not carve, but enter

Pure and clean as the cry of a baby,
And the universe slide from my side.

(1962/09/30. pp.206—208. No. 173)

Letter in November

Love, the world
Suddenly turns, turns color. The streetlight
Splits through the rat’s tail
Pods of the laburnum at nine in the morning.
It is the Arctic,

This little black
Circle, with its tawn silk grasses—babies’ hair.
There is a green in the air,
Soft, delectable.
It cushions me lovingly.

I am flushed and warm.
I think I may be enormous,
I am so stupidly happy,
My wellingtons
Squelching and squelching through the beautiful red.

This is my property.
Two times a day
I pace it, sniffing
The barbarous holly with its viridian
Scallops, pure iron,

And the wall of old corpses.
I love them.
I love them like history.
The apples are golden,
Imagine it——

My seventy trees
Holding their gold-ruddy balls
In a thick gray death-soup,
Their million
Gold leaves metal and breathless.

O love, O celibate.
Nobody but me
Walks the waist high wet.
The irreplaceable
Golds bleed and deepen, the mouths of Thermopylae.

(1962/11/11. pp.253—254. No.204)

Amnesiac

No use, no use, now, begging Recognize!
There is nothing to do with such a beautiful blank but smooth it.
Name, house, car keys,

The little toy wife—
Erased, sigh, sigh.
Four babies and a cooker!

Nurses the size of worms and a minute doctor
Tuck him in.
Old happenings

Peel from his skin.
Down the drain with all of it!
Hugging his pillow

Like the red-headed sister he never dared to touch,
He dreams of a new one—
Barren, the lot are barren!

And of another color.
How they’ll travel, travel, travel, scenery
Sparking off their brother-sister rears

A comet tail!
And money the sperm fluid of it all.
One nurse brings in

A green drink, one a blue.
They rise on either side of him like stars.
The two drinks flame and foam.

O, sister, mother, wife,
Sweet Lethe is my life.
I am never, never, never coming home!

(1962/10/21. pp.232—233. No. 189)

The Rival

If the moon smiled, she would resemble you.
You leave the same impression
Of something beautiful, but annihilating.
Both of you are great light borrowers.
Her O-mouth grieves at the world;yours is unaffected,

And your first gift is making stone out of everything.
I wake to a mausoleum;you are here,
Ticking your fingers on the marble table, looking for cigarettes,
Spiteful as a woman, but not so nervous,
And dying to say something unanswerable.

The moon, too, abases her subjects,
But in the daytime she is ridiculous.
Your dissatisfactions, on the other hand,
Arrive through the mailslot with loving regularity,
White and blank, expansive as carbon monoxide.

No day is safe from news of you,
Walking about in Africa maybe, but thinking of me.

(1961/07. pp.166—167. No. 147)

Fever 103°

Pure? What does it mean?
The tongues of hell
Are dull, dull as the triple

Tongues of dull, fat Cerberus
Who wheezes at the gate. Incapable
Of licking clean

The aguey tendon, the sin, the sin.
The tinder cries.
The indelible smell

Of a snuffed candle!
Love, love, the low smokes roll
From me like Isadora’s scarves, I’m in a fright

One scarf will catch and anchor in the wheel.
Such yellow sullen smokes
Make their own element. They will not rise,

But trundle round the globe
Choking the aged and the meek,
The weak

Hothouse baby in its crib,
The ghastly orchid
Hanging its hanging garden in the air,

Devilish leopard!
Radiation turned it white
And killed it in an hour.

Greasing the bodies of adulterers
Like Hiroshima ash and eating in.
The sin. The sin.

Darling, all night
I have been flickering, off, on, off, on.
The sheets grow heavy as a lecher’s kiss.

Three days. Three nights.
Lemon water, chicken
Water, water make me retch.

I am too pure for you or anyone.
Your body
Hurts me as the world hurts God. I am a lantern——

My head a moon
Of Japanese paper, my gold beaten skin
Infinitely delicate and infinitely expensive.

Does not my heat astound you. And my light.
All by myself I am a huge camellia
Glowing and coming and going,flush on flush.

I think I am going up,
I think I may rise——
The beads of hot metal fly, and I, love, I

Am a pure acetylene
Virgin
Attended by roses,

By kisses, by cherubim,
By whatever these pink things mean.
Not you, nor him.

Not him, nor him
(My selves dissolving, old whore petticoats)——
To Paradise.

(1962/10/20. pp.231—232. No. 188)

The Bee Meeting

Who are these people at the bridge to meet me? They are the villagers——
The rector, the midwife, the sexton, the agent for bees.
In my sleeveless summery dress I have no protection,
And they are all gloved and covered, why did nobody tell me?
They are smiling and taking out veils tacked to ancient hats.

I am nude as a chicken neck, does nobody love me?
Yes, here is the secretary of bees with her white shop smock,
Buttoning the cuffs at my wrists and the slit from my neck to my knees.
Now I am milkweed silk, the bees will not notice.
They will not smell my fear, my fear, my fear.

Which is the rector now, is it that man in black?
Which is the midwife, is that her blue coat?
Everybody is nodding a square black head, they are knights in visors,
Breastplates of cheesecloth knotted under the armpits.
Their smiles and their voices are changing. I am led through a beanfield.

Strips of tinfoil winking like people,
Feather dusters fanning their hands in a sea of bean flowers,
Creamy bean flowers with black eyes and leaves like bored hearts.
Is it blood clots the tendrils are dragging up that string?
No, no, it is scarlet flowers that will one day be edible.

Now they are giving me a fashionable white straw Italian hat
And a black veil that molds to my face, they are making me one of them.
They are leading me to the shorn grove, the circle of hives.
Is it the hawthorn that smells so sick?
The barren body of hawthorn, etherizing its children.

Is it some operation that is taking place?
It is the surgeon my neighbors are waiting for,
This apparition in a green helmet,
Shining gloves and white suit.
Is it the butcher, the grocer, the postman, someone I know?

I cannot run, I am rooted, and the gorse hurts me
With its yellow purses, its spiky armory.
I could not run without having to run forever.
The white hive is snug as a virgin,
Sealing off her brood cells, her honey, and quietly humming.

Smoke rolls and scarves in the grove.
The mind of the hive thinks this is the end of everything.
Here they come, the outriders, on their hysterical elastics.
If I stand very still, they will think I am cow-parsley,
A gullible head untouched by their animosity,

Not even nodding, a personage in a hedgerow.
The villagers open the chambers, they are hunting the queen.
Is she hiding, is she eating honey? She is very clever.
She is old, old, old, she must live another year, and she knows it.
While in their fingerjoint cells the new virgins

Dream of a duel they will win inevitably,
A curtain of wax dividing them from the bride flight,
The up flight of the murderess into a heaven that loves her.
The villagers are moving the virgins, there will be no killing.
The old queen does not show herself, is she so ungrateful?

I am exhausted, I am exhausted——
Pillar of white in a blackout of knives.
I am the magician’s girl who does not flinch.
The villagers are untying their disguises, they are shaking hands.
Whose is that long white box in the grove, what have they accomplished, why am I cold.

(1962/10/03. pp.211—212. No. 176)

The Arrival of the Bee Box

I ordered this, this clean wood box
Square as a chair and almost too heavy to lift.
I would say it was the coffin of a midget
Or a square baby
Were there not such a din in it.

The box is locked, it is dangerous.
I have to live with it overnight
And I can’t keep away from it.
There are no windows, so I can’t see what is in there.
There is only a little grid, no exit.

I put my eye to the grid.
It is dark, dark,
With the swarmy feeling of African hands
Minute and shrunk for export,
Black on black, angrily clambering.

How can I let them out?
It is the noise that appalls me most of all,
The unintelligible syllables.
It is like a Roman mob,
Small, taken one by one, but my god, together!

I lay my ear to furious Latin.
I am not a Caesar.
I have simply ordered a box of maniacs.
They can be sent back.
They can die, I need feed them nothing, I am the owner.

I wonder how hungry they are.
I wonder if they would forget me
If I just undid the locks and stood back and turned into a tree.
There is the laburnum, its blond colonnades,
And the petticoats of the cherry.

They might ignore me immediately
In my moon suit and funeral veil.
I am no source of honey
So why should they turn on me?
Tomorrow I will be sweet God, I will set them free.

The box is only temporary.

(1962/10/04. pp.212—213. No. 177)

Stings

Bare-handed, I hand the combs.
The man in white smiles, bare-handed,
Our cheesecloth gauntlets neat and sweet,
The throats of our wrists brave lilies.
He and I

Have a thousand clean cells between us,
Eight combs of yellow cups,
And the hive itself a teacup,
White with pink flowers on it,
With excessive love I enameled it

Thinking ‘sweetness, sweetness’.
Brood cells gray as the fossils of shells
Terrify me, they seem so old.
What am I buying, wormy mahogany?
Is there any queen at all in it?

If there is, she is old,
Her wings torn shawls, her long body
Rubbed of its plush——
Poor and bare and unqueenly and even shameful.
I stand in a column

Of winged, unmiraculous women,
Honey-drudgers.
I am no drudge
Though for years I have eaten dust
And dried plates with my dense hair.

And seen my strangeness evaporate,
Blue dew from dangerous skin.
Will they hate me,
These women who only scurry,
Whose news is the open cherry, the open clover?

It is almost over.
I am in control.
Here is my honey-machine,
It will work without thinking,
Opening, in spring, like an industrious virgin

To scour the creaming crests
As the moon, for its ivory powders, scours the sea.
A third person is watching.
He has nothing to do with the bee-seller or with me.
Now he is gone

In eight great bounds, a great scapegoat.
Here is his slipper, here is another,
And here the square of white linen
He wore instead of a hat.
He was sweet,

The sweat of his efforts a rain
Tugging the world to fruit.
The bees found him out,
Molding onto his lips like lies,
Complicating his features.

They thought death was worth it, but I
Have a self to recover, a queen.
Is she dead, is she sleeping?
Where has she been,
With her lion-red body, her wings of glass?

Now she is flying
More terrible than she ever was, red
Scar in the sky, red comet
Over the engine that killed her——
The mausoleum, the wax house.

(1962/10/06. pp.214—215. No. 178)

The Swarm

Somebody is shooting at something in our town—
A dull pom, pom in the Sunday street.
Jealousy can open the blood,
It can make black roses.
Who are the shooting at?

It is you the knives are out for
At Waterloo, Waterloo, Napoleon,
The hump of Elba on your short back,
And the snow, marshaling its brilliant cutlery
Mass after mass, saying Shh!

Shh! These are chess people you play with,
Still figures of ivory.
The mud squirms with throats,
Stepping stones for French bootsoles.
The gilt and pink domes of Russia melt and float off

In the furnace of greed. Clouds, clouds.
So the swarm balls and deserts
Seventy feet up, in a black pine tree.
It must be shot down. Pom! Pom!
So dumb it thinks bullets are thunder.

It thinks they are the voice of God
Condoning the beak, the claw, the grin of the dog
Yellow-haunched, a pack-dog,
Grinning over its bone of ivory
Like the pack, the pack, like everybody.

The bees have got so far. Seventy feet high!
Russia, Poland and Germany!
The mild hills, the same old magenta
Fields shrunk to a penny
Spun into a river, the river crossed.

The bees argue, in their black ball,
A flying hedgehog, all prickles.
The man with gray hands stands under the honeycomb
Of their dream, the hived station
Where trains, faithful to their steel arcs,

Leave and arrive, and there is no end to the country.
Pom! Pom! They fall
Dismembered, to a tod of ivy.
So much for the charioteers, the outriders, the Grand Army!
A red tatter, Napoleon!

The last badge of victory.
The swarm is knocked into a cocked straw hat.
Elba, Elba, bleb on the sea!
The white busts of marshals, admirals, generals
Worming themselves into niches.

How instructive this is!
The dumb, banded bodies
Walking the plank draped with Mother France’s upholstery
Into a new mausoleum,
An ivory palace, a crotch pine.

The man with gray hands smiles—
The smile of a man of business, intensely practical.
They are not hands at all
But asbestos receptacles.
Pom! Pom!‘They would have killed me.’

Stings big as drawing pins!
It seems bees have a notion of honor,
A black intractable mind.
Napoleon is pleased, he is pleased with everything.
O Europe! O ton of honey!

(1962/10/07. pp.215—217. No. 179)

Wintering

This is the easy time, there is nothing doing.
I have whirled the midwife’s extractor,
I have my honey,
Six jars of it,
Six cat’s eyes in the wine cellar,

Wintering in a dark without window
At the heart of the house
Next to the last tenant’s rancid jam
And the bottles of empty glitters——
Sir So-and-so’s gin.

This is the room I have never been in.
This is the room I could never breathe in.
The black bunched in there like a bat,
No light
But the torch and its faint

Chinese yellow on appalling objects——
Black asininity. Decay.
Possession.
It is they who own me.
Neither cruel nor indifferent,

Only ignorant.
This is the time of hanging on for the bees—the bees
So slow I hardly know them,
Filing like soldiers
To the syrup tin

To make up for the honey I’ve taken.
Tate and Lyle keeps them going,
The refined snow.
It is Tate and Lyle they live on, instead of flowers.
They take it. The cold sets in.

Now they ball in a mass,
Black
Mind against all that white.
The smile of the snow is white.
It spreads itself out, a mile-long body of Meissen,

Into which, on warm days,
They can only carry their dead.
The bees are all women,
Maids and the long royal lady.
They have got rid of the men,

The blunt, clumsy stumblers, the boors.
Winter is for women——
The woman, still at her knitting,
At the cradle of Spanish walnut,
Her body a bulb in the cold and too dumb to think.

Will the hive survive, will the gladiolas
Succeed in banking their fires
To enter another year?
What will they taste of, the Christmas roses?
The bees are flying. They taste the spring.

(1962/10/09. pp.217—219. No. 180)

The Munich Mannequins

Perfection is terrible, it cannot have children.
Cold as snow breath, it tamps the womb

Where the yew trees blow like hydras,
The tree of life and the tree of life

Unloosing their moons, month after month, to no purpose.
The blood flood is the flood of love,

The absolute sacrifice.
It means:no more idols but me,

Me and you.
So, in their sulfur loveliness, in their smiles

These mannequins lean tonight
In Munich, morgue between Paris and Rome,

Naked and bald in their furs,
Orange lollies on silver sticks,

Intolerable, without minds.
The snow drops its pieces of darkness,

Nobody’s about. In the hotels
Hands will be opening doors and setting

Down shoes for a polish of carbon
Into which broad toes will go tomorrow.

O the domesticity of these windows,
The baby lace, the green-leaved confectionery,

The thick Germans slumbering in their bottomless Stolz.
And the black phones on hooks

Glittering
Glittering and digesting

Voicelessness. The snow has no voice.

(1963/01/28. pp.262—263. No. 214)

Paralytic

It happens. Will it go on?——
My mind a rock,
No fingers to grip, no tongue,
My god the iron lung

That loves me, pumps
My two
Dust bags in and out,
Will not

Let me relapse
While the day outside glides by like ticker tape.
The night brings violets,
Tapestries of eyes,

Lights,
The soft anonymous
Talkers:‘You all right?’
The starched, inaccessible breast.

Dead egg, I lie
Whole
On a whole world I cannot touch,
At the white, tight

Drum of my sleeping couch
Photographs visit me——
My wife, dead and flat, in 1920 furs,
Mouth full of pearls,

Two girls
As flat as she, who whisper‘We’re your daughters’.
The still waters
Wrap my lips,

Eyes, nose and ears,
A clear
Cellophane I cannot crack.
On my bare back

I smile, a buddha, all
Wants, desire
Falling from me like rings
Hugging their lights.

The claw
Of the magnolia,
Drunk on its own scents,
Asks nothing of life.

(1963/01/29. pp.266—267. No. 217)

Totem

The engine is killing the track, the track is silver,
It stretches into the distance. It will be eaten nevertheless.

Its running is useless.
At nightfall there is the beauty of drowned fields,

Dawn gilds the farmers like pigs,
Swaying slightly in their thick suits,

White towers of Smithfield ahead,
Fat haunches and blood on their minds.

There is no mercy in the glitter of cleavers,
The butcher’s guillotine that whispers:‘How’s this, how’s this?’

In the bowl the hare is aborted,
Its baby head out of the way, embalmed in spice,

Flayed of fur and humanity.
Let us eat it like Plato’s afterbirth,

Let us eat it like Christ.
These are the people that were important——

Their round eyes, their teeth, their grimaces
On a stick that rattles and clicks, a counterfeit snake.

Shall the hood of the cobra appall me——
The loneliness of its eye, the eye of the mountains

Through which the sky eternally threads itself?
The world is blood-hot and personal

Dawn says, with its blood-flush.
There is no terminus, only suitcases

Out of which the same self unfolds like a suit
Bald and shiny, with pockets of wishes,

Notions and tickets, short circuits and folding mirrors.
I am mad, calls the spider, waving its many arms.

And in truth it is terrible,
Multiplied in the eyes of the flies.

They buzz like blue children
In nets of the infinite,

Roped in at the end by the one
Death with its many sticks.

(1963/01/28. pp.264—265. No. 215)

Little Fugue

The yew’s black fingers wag;
Cold clouds go over.
So the deaf and dumb
Signal the blind, and are ignored.

I like black statements.
The featureless of that cloud, now!
White as an eye all over!
The eye of the blind pianist

At my table on the ship.
He left for his food.
His fingers had the noses of weasels.
I couldn’t stop looking.

He could hear Beethoven:
Black yew, white cloud,
The horrific complications.
Finger-traps—a tumult of keys.

Empty and silly as plates,
So the blind smile.
I envy the big noises,
The yew hedge of the Grosse Fuge.

Deafness is something else.
Such a dark funnel, my father!
I see your voice
Black and leafy, as in my childhood,

A yew hedge of orders,
Gothic and barbarous, pure German.
Dead men cry from it.
I am guilty of nothing.

The yew my Christ, then.
Is it not as tortured?
And you, during the Great War
In the California delicatessen

Lopping the sausages!
They color my sleep,
Red, mottled, like cut necks.
There was a silence!

Great silence of another order.
I was seven, I knew nothing.
The world occurred.
You had one leg, and a Prussian mind.

Now similar clouds
Are spreading their vacuous sheets.
Do you say nothing?
I am lame in the memory.

I remember a blue eye,
A briefcase of tangerines.
This was a man, then!
Death opened, like a black tree, blackly.

I survive the while,
Arranging my morning.
These are my fingers, this my baby.
The clouds are a marriage dress, of that pallor.

(1962/04/02. pp.187—189. No.158)

第一章

一

以前动笔写小说从未像今日这般顾虑重重。称之为“小说”，只是因为再也想不出别的名称。我所叙述的事情故事性不强，结局并非是“一命呜呼”或者“喜结连理”。死亡可以一了百了，通常讲故事都是以此作为收场，但“喜结连理”也是一种十分恰当的结局。遇见世俗的所谓幸福美满的大结局，奉劝那些老于世故者也不必嗤之以鼻。饮食男女嘛，本性使然，一切都尽在不言中。一男一女，不管经历怎样的水深火热，最终喜相逢，在生物功能完成之后，兴趣也就转移到未来一代的身上去了。至于事情的原委，我要给读者留一些悬念。这本书记录的是我跟一个人的陈年往事——此人和我关系亲密，但要隔很长时间才相会一次。在这段间隔期他有着什么样的经历我一无所知。如果叫我编出一些情节来加以弥补，我也可以写得天衣无缝，让故事一气贯通，可我不愿意这样做。我只打算将自己所了解的实情付诸笔端。

多年前，我写过一本小说叫《月亮与六便士》。在那本书里，我塑造的主人公的原型是个名叫保罗·高更[2]的名画家。关于这位法国艺术家的生平我知之甚少，只是依据一星半点的事实，使用小说家的特权添枝加叶编造出一些情节加以渲染。在本书里，我无意如法炮制。此处无任何虚构。书中角色的姓氏全都改过，并且采取了一些别的处理手法使之难以辨认，免得那些还活在世上的人看了尴尬。我写的这人并不出名，也许永远不会出名。也许，他的生命一旦结束，这一生留在世界上的痕迹并不比石子投入河中留在水面上的涟漪多。如此，如有读者青睐本书，完全是书中的内涵激发了读者的兴趣。不过，也许会出现另外一种情况——他选择的人生道路以及他那坚毅和温良的人格对同胞们产生了越来越强烈的影响。这样，可能在他久别人世之后，人们会醒悟到：原来在这个时代产生过一个如此出类拔萃的人物。至于我写的是何人，谜底将会昭然若揭。有些人对他早年的身世想略作了解，定会如愿以偿。我在本书中追溯那如烟的往事。书中所述可能有种种不足，但对有意为我友著书立传者尚可资用，不失为好的参考。

我并无意硬说书中对原谈话内容的记载一句不漏。在此类境况中，对于说话人的话语我从不做笔录，而只是将与我有关的事情谨记心间。虽说记载他们谈话的内容我用的是自己的词语，但我敢保证自己所言不虚。刚才我说书中无任何虚构，现在我想做一更正。就像希罗多德[3]希罗多德，公元前5世纪的古希腊作家，他把旅行中的所闻所见，以及第一波斯帝国的历史记录下来，著成《历史》一书，成为西方文学史上第一部完整流传下来的散文作品。

写这本书还有一点也叫我顾虑重重——书中的主人公基本上都是美国人。了解一个人是非常困难的事情。对于本国之人尚可以知根知底，对于其他国家的人恐怕就难以做到这一点了。了解一个人，不论男女，不但要了解其本身，也得了解其出生的环境、居住的城市公寓、学步的场所、儿时的游戏、外婆讲的故事、吃的饭菜、求学之处、从事的运动、吟咏的诗篇以及宗教信仰。这些因素深入他们的骨髓。你不可能听别人说说就算了解了他们，而非得跟他们同吃同住才能够知根知底。要做到真正了解，就得成为他们当中的一员。对于异国他乡的人，你只是一个旁观者，不可能真正了解，写书时就难取信于人了。即便亨利·詹姆斯①那般观察细致入微的人，在英国住了四十年，也没能在作品中创造出一个有着地道英国味的英国人来。至于我本人，除了在几个短篇里涉及外国人，我只专注于刻画本国人。敢于在短篇里写外国人，仅仅因为短篇里的人物不必精细描写，而只需泛泛一谈。你给读者一点粗浅的启示，细节由读者自己推想。也许有人要问，既然我能把保罗·高更塑造成一个英国人，这本书里的人物为什么不可以照做。回答是：恕难从命。照葫芦画瓢，那样的主人公就不伦不类了。我敢说，那样的主人公绝非美国人眼中的美国人，而成了英国人眼里的美国人。连他们的语言特点我都没有打算仿效。英国作家在这方面闯的乱子和美国作家打算模仿英国人说的英语时闯的乱子一样多。俚语简直就是个陷阱。亨利·詹姆斯在他的英国故事里经常要用俚语，可是总不像一个英国人说的那样地道，因此非但未能取得他所追求的俚语效果，反而弄巧成拙，时常使英国人读来感到别扭和不舒服。

二

一九一九年我去欧洲，途经芝加哥，为了一些与本书无关的事由在那儿待了两三个星期。当时我刚刚出版了一部小说，大获成功，一时成为新闻人物，屁股还没坐稳就有记者来采访。次日清晨电话铃便响了起来，我拿起了话筒。

“我是艾略特·邓普顿。”

“艾略特？我还以为你在巴黎呢。”

“我来这儿，是看望我姐姐的。”

“我想请你今天来，一块儿吃顿午饭。”

“乐意奉陪。”

[4]亨利·詹姆斯（1843-1916），19世纪美国继霍桑、麦尔维尔之后的著名作家。他的小说常写美国人和欧洲人之间交往的问题。

他把时间和地址告诉了我。

我认识艾略特·邓普顿已有十五个年头。此时的他年近六旬，高挑的个子，五官端正，一派儒雅的风度，乌黑浓密的卷发微染白霜，反倒使他更加气宇轩昂。他素来衣着考究，小物件可以在查维特服饰店采购，但衣帽和鞋子这套行头却一定要在伦敦添置。他在巴黎塞纳河左岸有一套公寓，位于时尚的圣纪尧姆大街。不喜欢他的人称他为掮客，这种污蔑叫他不胜愤怒。他眼光独特、学识渊博，不否认刚刚在巴黎安家的那些年曾经为有意买画的大款收藏家出过主意，助过他们一臂之力。在交际场上，他一旦耳闻某个英法破落贵族想出手一幅精品画作，碰巧又知道哪个美国博物馆的理事在访求某某大师的优秀画作，他便乐见其成，为之穿针引线。法国有许多世家，英国也是有一些的。这类人家有时深陷窘境，不得不出手某件有布尔大师①签名的柜子或者一张由齐本德尔[5]亲手制作的写字台，只要不声张出去，当然愿意有一个知识渊博、风度儒雅、办事谨慎的人代为操办。人们自然想到艾略特会从这种交易中捞上一把，但大家都是有教养的，谁也不愿明说。肚肠小的人却不客气，硬说他家样样东西都是摆出来兜售的，请美国的富佬来吃上一顿丰盛的午餐，觥筹交错之后，就会有一两幅值钱的画品不见了踪影，或者一件镶嵌细工家具被一件漆品替换。若是有人问起某样东西怎么不见了，他便头头是道地解释一通，说那东西不上品位，他拿去换了样品质远在其之上的。他还补充说，成天看一样特定的东西，哪有不烦的。

“Nous autres Américains[6]，我们美国人就喜欢换花样。这既是我们的短板，也是我们的长处。”

巴黎有些美国籍的小姐太太，自称了解他的底细，说他的家道原来很穷，之所以能过上如此阔绰的日子，只是由于他为人非常精明的缘故。

我不清楚他究竟有多少钱，可是那位有公爵身份的房东容他住这样的公寓，自然要收不菲的房租。况且，他的房间里摆的尽是值钱的物件。墙上挂着一些法国艺术大师的画作，有华多[7]的，有弗拉戈纳尔[8]的，还有克洛德·洛兰[9]等其他人的；镶木地板上铺着萨冯内里埃地毯和奥比松地毯[10]，相互争奇斗艳；客厅里摆了一套路易十五时代精工细雕的家具，制作之精，如他自己所称，说不定就是当年蓬帕杜夫人[11]香闺中的物件呢。不管怎么说，反正他不必挖空心思去赚钱，照样能把日子过得很滋润，他认为一个绅士应该讲究这种排场，至于他是如何才达到了这样的水准，智者会三缄其口，除非你希望跟他一刀两断，不再来往。对于物质生活没有了后顾之忧，他便全身心去实现一生中最大的愿望——游刃于社交圈子。初来欧洲时，他只是个拿着介绍信四处拜访名流的年轻人，后来因为帮助那些英法世家成交了几笔生意，巩固了在这之前已经取得的地位。他出身于弗吉尼亚州的一个旧世家，母系一族追溯起来，曾有一位祖先在《独立宣言》上签过字呢。他拿着介绍信拜见那些美国贵妇人时，其出身颇受重视。他如鱼得水，八面玲珑，舞跳得好，枪打得准，还打得一手好网球，什么样的派对他都是必到之客。他慷慨大方，将鲜花和昂贵的巧克力买来任意送人。他自己倒是很少请客，可是一旦设宴，必定别开生面。他会请那些阔太太到苏荷区富于人文气息的饭馆开洋荤，或者去拉丁区的酒馆小酌，使她们得到身心的愉悦。随时随地，他都愿意为人效犬马之劳，不管再怎么烦人的事，只要有求于他，他没有不乐意办的。遇见上年纪的女人，他很舍得花气力花时间曲意逢迎，没过多长时间便成了许多大户人家的新宠。他这个人太好说话了，开宴会万一有人爽约没来，请他临时凑个数，他是毫不介意的；把他安排在一个讨厌透顶的老太太身边，他一定会谈笑风生，博得老太太的欢心。

在两三年的时间里，他混迹于伦敦和巴黎，作为一个年轻的美国人，凡是能攀得上的关系，他都与之有了交往。他把家安在巴黎，社交季节之末则到伦敦去，初秋时分前往乡间去拜访一圈住在乡村别墅的名门。最初将他引入社交界的那些贵妇人发现他的交游竟然如此之广，不由颇感意外，心里五味杂陈。她们一方面感到高兴——这个受她们保护的小伙子取得了巨大的成功；另一方面，她们则有些拈酸——他跟别人混得很熟，和她们却是礼节性的交往。虽然他依然有求必应，愿意为她们效劳，但她们心里直犯嘀咕，觉得自己被他当成了跻身社交界的垫脚石，怀疑他是个唯利是图的势利眼。实际上他的确是个势利眼，一个不折不扣的势利眼，一个毫无廉耻之心的势利眼。哪家请客，他只要能上客人名单，或者跟哪个有名望的脾气乖戾的贵族老太太攀上关系，什么样的苦他都能吃，受得了侮辱谩骂，听得了冷言冷语，咽得下窝囊气。在这方面，他可以说是不屈不挠。他只要盯上一个猎物，非将其猎到手不可，就像寻找罕见种类兰花的植物学家一样执着，什么洪水、地震、热病和充满敌意的土著人啦，这种危险全不放在眼里。一九一四年的世界大战给他提供了升腾的良机。战争一爆发，他就去参加了一个救护队，先后在佛兰德斯和阿尔贡战区救死扶伤；一年后回来，他胸前多了条荣誉红丝带，并且在巴黎红十字会谋了个缺。此时的他今非昔比，手头已很宽裕，凡是名流主办的慈善事业，他必定慷慨捐赠。看见名声显赫的慈善机构，他会运用自己渊博的知识和高雅的品味鼎力相助。巴黎有两家顶级的高档俱乐部，他都成了会员。在法国那些最有名望的贵妇人眼中，他成了“了不起的艾略特”。他终于发迹了！

三

初次遇见艾略特时，我只是个名不见经传的年轻作家，他根本无视我的存在。由于他对每一张面孔都过目不忘，不管哪里遇见都跟我客气地握手，只是似乎毫无意图和我深交。在看戏的时候巧遇，如果他和某个显贵在一起，他就假装没看见我。后来我写的剧本获得了出人意料的成功，我立刻就察觉到艾略特对我的态度升温，变得热情起来。一天，我收到他的一封请柬，请我去克拉里奇酒店吃饭——此处是他在伦敦的下榻地。那是个小型的宴会，规格也不是很高。我当时有一种感觉，觉得他在试探我的深浅。后来，我的成功给我的身边增加了不少新朋友，跟他见面的机会也就多了起来。在这之后不久，正逢秋季，我去巴黎住了几个星期，有一次在一个双方都认识的熟人家和他不期而遇。他问了我的住址，过了一两天我就收到了他的一封午宴请柬——这次的午宴地点设在他的公寓里。到了那儿一看，我意外地发现这次宴会的规格相当高，不由心里暗自笑了。我知道他熟谙人情世故，晓得一个作家在英国社交界无足轻重，而在法国则备受推崇，于是我这个作家也就被他另眼相看了。这以后的若干年里，我和他来往十分密切，但始终未成为推心置腹的朋友。我怀疑艾略特恐怕跟任何人都不能成为朋友的。他对人并不感兴趣，只关心人的社会地位。不论我偶尔去巴黎，或是他来伦敦，他请客少一个人，或者有义务要招待前来旅游的美国人时，总要请我作陪。这些人，我怀疑有些是他的老主顾，有些是拿介绍信来拜见他的陌生人。他们成了他生活中的累赘。他觉得总得应酬一下，但又不情愿介绍他们和他那些显赫的朋友见面。打发他们最好的办法自然就是请客吃饭了，然后再请他们去看场戏，可这其中他也自有难处，因为他每晚都有应酬，而且早在三个星期前全约好了；即使他尽了地主之谊，料想那些人也未必就此满足。鉴于我是个作家，跟这类事情干系不大，于是他愿意将肚子里的苦水倒给我听。

“美国的那些人写什么介绍信，一点也不为别人考虑。我倒不是不乐意接待前来拜访的人，只是觉得实在不应该拖累身边的朋友。”

他用大篮子盛放玫瑰花，用大盒子装上巧克力，赠送给那些人以弥补招待上的不周。不过，有时还得设迎宾宴。也就是在这个时候，他请我来作陪的。先前他把原委告诉了我，此时又邀我来应景，未免有些幼稚了。

“他们渴望能和你见上一面。”他在邀请短柬中奉迎我，“某某夫人是个很有文学涵养的人，你写的书她逐词逐句都拜读了。”

见了面，那位“某某夫人”就会告诉我，说看了我的《培林先生和特雷尔先生》一书，简直喜欢极了，并祝贺我的《软体动物》剧本演出成功。殊不知头一本书的作者是休·沃波尔[12]，后一书的作者是哈伯特·亨利·戴维斯[13]。

四

假如我的描述让读者觉得艾略特·邓普顿是个卑鄙小人，那可就冤枉他了。

从某种意义上讲，他可以称得上法国人说的serviable。据我所知，这个词在英语词汇库里还没有完全对应的词。我查了查字典，发现该词有助人为乐、乐善好施的含意，按传统的说法就是“厚道”。艾略特正是这么一个人。他为人慷慨；虽则在早期的生涯中，那种送花、送糖、送礼的豪举无疑有他的用心，但是到后来没有这种必要时，他还是照送。赠人以物，他乐此不疲。他热情好客，所聘用的厨子能和巴黎的任何一个高厨比高低。有一点是肯定的：摆上餐桌的全都是最为可口的时令菜。他提供的酒可以证明他在这方面有很高的鉴赏力。他挑选客人看的是社会地位，而不是看客人本人如何，这是事实，可他也会至少请上一两个能说会笑的，所以他的宴会桌上几乎总是充满欢声笑语。一些人在背后嘲笑他，说他是个龌龊小人，可一旦受到他的邀请，却又会欣然接受。他讲法语字正腔圆，既流利又准确，音色很是纯正。他还曾经模仿英国人说话，使出了九牛二虎的力气，你的听力必须非常敏锐，才能听出他的英语中夹杂着一些美音。只要不以公爵和公爵夫人们为话题，他什么都说；现在即便以公爵和公爵夫人们为话题，他也放得开，敢于说些风趣的话了，特别是跟你单独在一起的时候，因为他的地位现已固若金汤。他风趣，又喜欢挖苦人，而那些高官显贵的丑闻逸事没有一件会不传到他的耳朵里来的。X公主最近产一子，其生身父亲是谁，Y侯爵的情妇是何人，这些我都是从他口中得知的。我敢断言，对于高官显贵的私生活，就连马塞尔·普鲁斯特[14]恐怕也不如艾略特·邓普顿知道的那么多。

在巴黎时，我时常跟他一起吃午饭，有时在他公寓里，有时在饭馆里。我喜欢逛古董商店，偶尔也买些，不过更多的是只看不买，而艾略特总是兴冲冲陪我一起去逛。他是个行家，真心实意地热爱艺术品。我觉得巴黎的每一家这类商店，他没有不熟悉的，并且跟每家店的老板都很熟稔。他特别爱砍价，出门前总是要叮咛我：

“你要是相中了哪样东西，先不要急着买。你只需给我使个眼色，下来就看我的了。”

我喜欢上哪样东西，他就帮着压价，最终以一半价钱成交，这会叫他高兴得不得了。看他玩这种讨价还价的游戏实在过瘾。他会争论、哄骗、发脾气、以情动人、说风凉话、挑出商品的毛病、威胁再也不迈入这家店铺的门槛、叹气、耸肩、好言相劝以及满脸怒容地朝外走，最后达到自己的理想价位之后，他还会悲哀地摇摇头，就好像他吃了败仗，只好认命一样。然后，他会压低声音用英语对我说：

“买吧。就是再多一倍的钱也还是便宜的。”

艾略特是个有激情的天主教徒。他在巴黎住下不久，就碰见一位神父。那人善于劝说异教徒皈依天主教，导引许多迷途的羊羔回到了羊圈里，因此而颇负盛名。此人饭局特多，能说会道远近闻名。他的教务活动只限于富贵人家。虽然出身寒门，却被许多大户人家尊为座上宾，艾略特见了自然便动了心思。他悄悄告诉一位在神父的劝说下皈依正教的美国阔太太，说他家里虽然一直信奉圣公会教义，而他本人却是对天主教会向往已久。一天晚上，阔太太请艾略特吃饭，跟神父见个面。饭桌旁仅有他们三人，神父说话口若悬河。女主人将话题引到天主教之上时，神父讲得天花乱坠、地涌金莲，而且丝毫不迂腐。虽则身为神父，但也是江湖上的人，对另一个江湖上的人是要说些入行的话的。艾略特发现神父竟然知道自己的来头，有点受宠若惊。

“范多姆公爵夫人那天还跟我谈起你来呢，她觉得你是个很有头脑的人。”

艾略特快活得满脸通红。公爵夫人他是拜谒过的，可是，怎么也没想到她会对他留意在心。神父心地宽广、观点入时，有着海纳百川的胸襟，一番关于天主教的议论谈得既高明又温和。根据他的高谈阔论，艾略特觉得天主教会就像个高级俱乐部，任何有教养的人如果不加入就对不起自己。六个月后，艾略特就入了教。皈依了天主教，再加上热衷于天主教的慈善事业，慷慨解囊，好多家以前对他关着的大门也被他叩开了。

他改弦更张，放弃父辈的宗教信仰，也许动机不纯，但自从皈依之后，他对天主教的虔诚之心却是无可置疑的。他每逢周日去上流社会人士经常光顾的教堂做弥撒，定期忏悔，每隔一段时间就去参拜一次罗马圣地。久而久之，教廷因他虔诚，封他做罗马教皇内侍，又见他兢兢业业、恪尽职守，奖给他一枚圣墓勋章。说实在话，他在天主教方面所取得的成功不亚于他混迹社会所获得的成果。

我时常问自己，是什么原因使得这样一个聪明、和蔼、有教养的人迷了心窍，成了一个趋炎附势者？他不是暴发户，其父在南方一个大学当过校长，祖父是名声显赫的神学家。以他的聪明机灵，决不会看不出那些应他邀请的人大多只是混一顿吃喝，有些是没脑子的，有些毫不足道。那些人响亮的头衔搞得他眼花缭乱，令他对那些人的缺点视而不见。我只能这样猜想，跟这些家世古老的绅士混个关系熟，充当贵妇人们的忠实侍卫，给他一种永不厌烦的胜利感。他的心底可能涌动着一股浪漫的激情，使得他在这些弱智的法国小公爵身上能看到当年跟随圣路易到圣地去征战的十字军战士，从外强中干、沉迷于狩猎狐狸的英国伯爵身上能看到他们侍奉亨利八世前往“金布之地”[15]的祖先。跟这些人在一起，他觉得就像生活在天地广阔、英雄气十足的古代里一样。大概他在翻阅《哥达年鉴》[16]时，心里会激情勃发，那一个又一个姓氏令他产生怀古之幽思，想到古代的战争、史册上的攻伐、外交场上的诡谲风云以及宫闱情话。艾略特·邓普顿就是这么一个性情中人。

五

我在洗脸、梳头，准备去赴艾略特约的饭局。就在这时，旅馆的前台打来电话，说他已到了楼下。我有点诧异，可是一收拾好，就下楼去了。

“我觉得还是我来接你更为稳妥些。”在我们握手时，他说道，“我不知道你对芝加哥熟不熟。”

我发现一些旅居海外多年的美国人都有他的这种顾虑，觉得美国是个很难走的国度，甚至可以说充满了危险，让一个欧洲人自己寻路是不安全的。

“时间还早，咱们可以走上一段路。”他提议说。

外面微有寒意，不过，万里无云，活动活动腿脚倒是不错的。

“我想还是在你会见家姐之前，先把她的情况介绍一下为好。”走在路上，艾略特说道，“她去巴黎我那儿小住过一两次。不过，你可能那时没到我那儿去过。今天人并不多，就是家姐和她的女儿伊莎贝尔以及格雷戈里·布拉巴宗。”

“就是那个室内装潢设计师吗？”我问。

“是的，家姐的房子糟得一塌糊涂，伊莎贝尔和我都劝她重新装修一下。碰巧听说布拉巴宗在芝加哥，所以我就叫家姐请他今天来吃午饭。他虽说算不上一个地道的上等人，但品味是有的。玛丽·奥利芬特的拉尼城堡以及圣厄茨家的圣克莱门特·大宝庄园都是他给装饰的。他很讨公爵夫人的欢心。你去看看路易莎家的房子就知道了。她怎么能在那儿一住就住这么多年，这叫我永远也理解不透。说到这里，我还无法理解的是，她怎么能在芝加哥住下去。”

他的姐姐布雷德利夫人是个寡妇，有三个孩子，二子一女，儿子们早已长大成家，一个在菲律宾政府里做事，另一个继承父业供职于外交界，现在布宜诺斯艾利斯。布雷德利夫人的丈夫曾经出使过若干国家，在罗马做了几年一等秘书，后来又被派到南美洲西岸的一个小共和国做公使，最终在那里死在任上。

“姐夫去世之后，我想让路易莎把芝加哥的房子卖掉，”艾略特继续滔滔不绝地说着，“可她对那房子有感情。那家人在那儿住了有些年头了。布雷德利家族在伊利诺伊州算得上是最古老的人家。他们一八三九年从弗吉尼亚原籍迁来这里，在离芝加哥大约有六十英里的地方置下田产，目前还保留着。”艾略特说到这里略作停顿，用眼睛瞧瞧我，看我有什么反应。“我想你也许会说他家早先是务农的。我不晓得你可知道，在上世纪中叶的时候，中西部开始搞开发，不少弗吉尼亚人——上等人家的子弟，受到未知世界的诱惑，抛弃了故乡衣食无忧的生活。我姐夫的父亲切斯特·布雷德利看出芝加哥有发展的前景，来这里进了一家律师事务所，反正他赚的钱也够儿辈丰衣足食的了。”

艾略特的话虽如此说，从他的神情却可以看出，那位已经去世的切斯特·布雷德利离开他祖传的华屋肥田，进了一家律师事务所，未免有点不划算，不过，幸好积攒了一笔财富，起码也算是一种补偿吧。后来有一回布雷德利夫人拿几张乡下所谓“祖屋”的照片给我看，艾略特显得有些不太高兴；照片上面我见到的是一座很不起眼的农家屋，有美丽的小花园，可是谷仓、牛棚和猪圈都隔开只有一箭之地，四周是一片荒芜的平畴。我不由想道，切斯特·布雷德利先生丢下老宅到城市里求发展，并不是没有成算的。

走了一会儿，我们叫住了一辆出租车，在一幢棕色的石头房子前下了车。房子窄而高，要攀上一串陡峭的石阶才到大门口。它处于一排房屋之间，坐落在湖滨大道旁边的一条街上，房屋外表就是在那天明媚的秋光里也还是阴沉沉的，真不明白一个人对这样的房子会有什么感情。开门的是个一头白发的黑人管家，又高又壮，他把我们引入了客厅。我们走进时，布雷德利夫人从椅子上站起来，艾略特为我做介绍。她年轻时一定是个美丽的女子，五官总体端正，一双眼睛生得煞是漂亮。可是，现在的她脸色灰黄，几乎未施任何粉黛，肌肉松弛，显然在跟中年发胖的战斗中已一败涂地。我猜她还不肯服输，因为她坐下时，腰杆在硬背椅子上挺得笔直；无疑，穿着那受罪的铠甲一般的紧身衣，这样坐在硬背椅子上要比坐在软垫椅子上舒服一些。她穿一件蓝色长衫，上面缀满了花边饰物，高领子用鲸鱼骨撑得硬硬的，一头白发烫成波浪纹，发式做得极其复杂，看上去挺有风度。另一位客人还未到，为了等他，我们就东一搭西一搭闲聊起来。

“艾略特告诉我，你是走南边那条路过来的，”布雷德利夫人说，“你在罗马歇脚没有？”

“歇了，我在那儿住了一个星期。”

“亲爱的玛格丽达王后还好吗？”

我被她这一问给问蒙了，只好回答说我不知道。

“哦，你没有去看看她？她真是一个大好人。我们在罗马的时候，布雷德利先生曾任使馆的一等秘书，她待我们好极了。你怎么就不去看望看望她呢？你跟艾略特又不一样，不至于懒得连奎里纳尔皇宫都不去一趟吧？”

“完全不是那回事。”我笑了笑说，“事实上，我并不认识她。”

“不认识？”布雷德利夫人说，那表情好像是她简直不敢相信自己的耳朵，“怎么能不认识呢？”

“实不相瞒，一般来说，作家跟国王和王后是没有过密交往的。”

“不过，玛格丽达王后是个和蔼可亲的人呀。”布雷德利夫人好言劝我，好像不认识这位王后完全是我摆架子，不屑似的，“我敢肯定你一定会喜欢她的。”

这时候门开了，管家把格雷戈里·布拉巴宗领了进来。

格雷戈里·布拉巴宗空有一个好名姓，并不是个风流倜傥的人。他五短身材，大腹便便，除掉耳朵根和后颈有一圈黑鬈发外，头秃得就像只鸡蛋，一张脸红得似猴屁股，好像时刻都会流淌下一大堆臭汗一样，两个灰色的眼珠滴溜溜乱转，嘴唇肥厚，下巴特长。他是英国人。在伦敦时，放荡不羁的文人聚会上，有时会遇见他。他是个乐天派，总是很开心，动不动就哈哈大笑。不过，即便你不善于观察人的本质，也会发现他那种嘻嘻哈哈亲密的样子只不过是一种外衣，下面遮盖的是精明的生意经。这些年来，他一直都是伦敦城里最成功的室内装潢设计师。他那洪亮的声音和又小又胖的手都极富表现力，能产生奇异的功效。他只要摆动摆动小手，再奉上一大串兴奋的字眼，就会叫一个犹豫不决的客户激动起来，极大刺激他的想象力，使得他简直没法拒绝那似乎是一份施舍的订单。

管家又走了进来，端来了一托盘的鸡尾酒。

“咱们就不等伊莎贝尔了。”布雷德利夫人拿起一杯酒说。

“她到哪儿去了？”艾略特问。

“跟拉里打高尔夫去了，说也许要晚一点回来。”

艾略特转向我说：“拉里就是劳伦斯·达雷尔。伊莎贝尔可能已跟他订婚了。”

“艾略特，我不知道你喝鸡尾酒。”我说道。

“我原本是不喝的。”他呷了一口杯中的酒说，“可在这么个禁酒的野蛮国度，你又能怎么样呢？”说着，他叹了口气，“巴黎的一些有身份的人家也开始喝这种玩意儿了。坏的世道把好的传统都给毁掉了。”

“纯粹是胡言乱语，艾略特。”布雷德利夫人说。

她的口气相当温和，然而坚决，让我听出来她是个有个性的人。她看艾略特时，神情怡然自得，我怀疑她没有将弟弟当作一个了不起的人物。我暗自寻思，她把格雷戈里·布拉巴宗归于哪一类人呢？布拉巴宗一进门先用专业的目光把屋子扫视了一圈，不由抬起了他那两道浓密的剑眉。这幢房子的确叫人称奇。壁纸、窗帘布、椅垫、椅套，全是一式的图案；墙上的油画镶在厚重的金相框里，显然是布雷德利这家人去罗马时买来的——有拉斐尔[17]派以及圭多·雷尼[18]派的圣母像，有苏卡莱利[19]派的风景画，还有帕尼尼[20]派的真迹。除此之外，屋里还摆着他们去北京时买的纪念品——精雕细刻的黑檀木桌子和景泰蓝大花瓶，也有从智利或者秘鲁买来的玩意儿——硬石刻的胖人儿和陶制花瓶。屋里的写字台是齐本德尔式的，玻璃橱亦是出自名匠之手。灯罩是用白绸做底料，上面不知是哪个没品位的画家画了几个身穿华多式服装[21]的牧童、牧女。屋子里的装饰不伦不类，但不知什么原因却叫人感到温馨。这是一种平凡却又安稳的生活气息，让你觉得这令人无法相信的杂乱之中自有一番情趣。所有这些互不协调的物件合为一个整体，成为布雷德利夫人生活的组成部分。

大家喝完鸡尾酒，门被推开，进来一个姑娘，身后跟着个小伙子。

“我们迟了没有？”她问，“我把拉里带回来了。有他的一份饭吃吗？”

“我想是有的。”布雷德利夫人笑着说，“你按下铃，叫尤金添个位子。”

“刚才是他给我们开的门。我已经告诉他了。”

“这是我的女儿伊莎贝尔，”布雷德利夫人转身向我说，“这是劳伦斯·达雷尔。”

伊莎贝尔匆匆跟我握了握手，然后将身子迫不及待地转向了布拉巴宗。

“你就是布拉巴宗先生吧？一直渴望见到你呢。你替克莱门蒂尼·多摩装饰的屋子我很是喜欢。这屋子是不是很糟糕？我好多年来都劝说妈妈，要把这儿收拾一下，现在你来芝加哥，正是我们千载难逢的好机会。请实言相告，我们家这房子究竟怎么样？”

我知道布拉巴宗绝不会直言相告的。只见他飞快地望了布雷德利夫人一眼，而后者脸上一点表情也没有，看不出任何名堂。后来他断定伊莎贝尔是拿事的人，于是就爆发出一阵响亮的笑声。

“我敢说这屋子是很舒服的，还有其他的优点。”他侃侃而谈，“不过，既然你让我直言相告，那我就说品味上糟得一塌糊涂。”

伊莎贝尔高个子、鹅蛋脸、直鼻梁，眼睛俊俏，嘴唇丰满，有着布雷德利这家人的特征。她长得很漂亮，只是有些偏胖，我想大概是由于年龄的关系，再过几年，可能就会苗条下来的。她的手结实、好看，不过也有点偏胖，就连短裙下露出的腿肚子也显得胖了些。她肤色健康，泛着红晕，这跟体育锻炼以及刚才开敞篷车回家显然不无关系。她容光焕发，活力四射，散发出蓬勃的朝气，一派顽皮快活的劲儿，流露出对生活的满足以及由衷的幸福感，让人见了为之感到高兴。不管艾略特多么儒雅，比较之下，她的那种自然纯真都会使之显得庸俗。由于她的朝气蓬勃的衬托，布雷德利夫人的那张惨白、满是皱纹的面孔显得疲惫和苍老。

我们下楼去吃饭。布拉巴宗一看见饭厅，眼睛眨巴了几下。壁上糊着暗红的普通纸，算是冒充壁纸，挂些脸色阴沉死板的男女肖像，画技不堪一提。这些人都是去世的那位布雷德利先生的近系祖先。他自己也在其中，留着浓密的小胡子，僵直的身体穿着双排扣常礼服，戴着浆硬的白领子。一幅布雷德利夫人的肖像，是九〇年代一个法国画家的手笔，挂在壁炉上方，穿一袭灰青缎子的晚礼服，颈挂珍珠链，头发上点缀一颗钻石星，一只戴满珠宝的手捏一条编织领巾（领巾画得极为细腻，连针脚都一一可辨），另一只手随随便便拿一柄鸵鸟羽扇子。屋内家具是黑橡木的，给人以压抑感。

“你觉得这东西怎么样？”大家落座后，伊莎贝尔问布拉巴宗。

“我敢说一定花了不少钱。”他答道。

“的确如此。”布雷德利夫人说，“这是我和布雷德利先生结婚时，他父亲送给我们的礼物，跟着我们跑遍了全世界——里斯本啊，北京啊，基多[22]啊，罗马啊。亲爱的玛格丽达王后非常艳羡它。”

“假如是你的，你把它怎么办？”伊莎贝尔问布拉巴宗，可是，不等后者回答，艾略特就替他说了。

“付之一炬。”他说。

接下来，三个人你一言我一语地开始讨论如何装饰这房子。艾略特力主装饰成路易十五时代的风格，伊莎贝尔则想要一张修道院里的那种餐桌和一套意大利式椅子。布拉巴宗认为齐本德尔式家具比较适合布雷德利夫人的性格。

“我一直都认为房子的装饰应该反映出一个人的性格，这是至关紧要的。”他说完，又将身子转向了艾略特。“你当然是认识奥利芬特公爵夫人的喽？”

“玛丽吗？老朋友了，熟得不能再熟。”

“她要我为她装饰饭厅，我一见她的面，就敲定用乔治二世那时候的风格。”

“真是英明决断。上次在她家的饭厅吃饭，我注意到了那儿的装饰，其品味无可挑剔。”

谈话继续进行。布雷德利夫人侧耳倾听，谁都不知道她心里在想什么。我很少开口，而伊莎贝尔的年轻朋友拉里（我忘记了他姓什么）简直一言不发。他坐在我对面的布拉巴宗和艾略特之间，我不时会看他一眼。他看上去十分年轻，和艾略特一般高，差不多六英尺，瘦瘦的，四肢显得柔软灵活，样子甜甜的，不俊也不丑，相当的腼腆，并无出众之处。我觉得有趣的是，根据我的记忆，自从进屋之后，他话没说上五六句，却显得十分自在，尽管不开口也像是在参加谈话，无不令人称奇。我注意到他的手很长，可是，就他的个头论，不能算大，形状看上去很美，同时又有力。我想画家一定高兴画这双手。他身板比较瘦，但是，看上去并不文弱，相反地，我敢说还颇具力量和韧劲。他的一张脸宁静庄重，晒得黝黑，要不是有这点黝黑，就看不出颜色来了；五官端正，但并不出众；颧骨相当高，太阳穴凹陷，深棕色的头发微微鬈曲，眼睛看上去比实际的要大，那是因为陷在眼窝里很深；睫毛浓而长，眼珠的颜色很特别，不是伊莎贝尔和她母亲、舅舅共有的那种淡褐色，而是一种深深的颜色，虹膜和瞳仁差不多是一个颜色，这给他的眼睛以一种特殊的魅力。他有一种动人的潇洒风度，从中看得出为什么伊莎贝尔对他倾心。她的眼光不时落到他身上，在那儿停留一下，从她的神情里我似乎看得出不但有情爱，而且有慈爱。二人四目相撞时，里面情意绵绵，好一幅美丽的图画。看见年轻男女彼此相爱，是极能感动人的。我，一个步入中年的人，觉得有点眼红，同时不知何故又为他们感到悲哀。若说悲哀，就蠢得没名堂了，因为我明知他们追求幸福的路上没有任何绊脚石——两家的家境似乎都宽裕，没有任何因素可以妨碍他们结婚，妨碍他们在婚后过上幸福的日子。

就重新装饰房屋这个话题，伊莎贝尔、艾略特和布拉巴宗说起来没个完，目的就是想让布雷德利夫人吐口，允许开工，可布雷德利夫人只是满脸慈祥地笑笑，硬是不吐这个口。

“不必操之过急嘛，我想静下心来好好想想。”随后，她转过头问伊莎贝尔的男友：“你是怎么看的，拉里？”

拉里向桌子四周环顾一下，眼中露出微笑。

“我觉得装修不装修都无所谓。”他说。

“你这个小坏蛋，拉里。”伊莎贝尔嚷嚷道，“我还特地关照过你，让你支持我们呢。”

“如果路易莎伯母满足于现状，为什么非得变变样呢？”

他的话说到了点子上，入情入理的，引得我不由大笑一声。拉里看了看我，也咧嘴笑了。

“别傻乎乎地笑行不行！你说的话愚蠢到家了。”伊莎贝尔说。

拉里没理会，反而笑得更厉害了。我留意到他有一口又白又小的牙齿，整整齐齐的。他望着伊莎贝尔的神情别有深意，叫她脸红起来，呼吸也急促了。假如我没有弄错的话，那她就是疯狂地在爱着他，可是不知道什么缘故，好像她对他的情意里面还有一种母爱的成分。在如此年轻的女孩身上竟然有母爱，让人意想不到。她嘴角浮出温柔的笑意，重又将注意力转向了布拉巴宗。

“别理他。他傻得不透气，一点文化也没有，什么都不懂，就知道开飞机。”

“开什么飞机？”我问。

“一战中，他是个飞行员呗。”

“我还以为他那时年纪太小，不能参战呢。”

“年纪是很小，而且不是一般的小。他调皮得不得了，逃离学校，跑到加拿大参军，撒了个弥天大谎，让人家相信他已满十八岁，混进了空军。都宣布停战了，他还在法国作战呢。”

“别说这些话了，会让伯母的客人厌烦的，伊莎贝尔。”拉里说。

“我从小就认识他，他还乡时穿一身军装，外套上挂那么多漂亮的勋章，非常英俊。我坐在他家门口的台阶上不走，缠得他一刻不得安宁，只好答应要娶我为妻。那时候，竞争可真激烈。”

“真的吗，伊莎贝尔？”她母亲说。

拉里冲着我探过了身子。

“希望你别信她的话，一句也别信。伊莎贝尔不是什么坏女孩，就是爱撒谎。”

吃完午饭不久，艾略特和我就告辞了。我先前告诉他打算去博物馆看看画，他说他带我去。我不大愿意有人跟我去逛博物馆，可推辞的话说不出口，无法说我喜欢一个人去，只好接受他的陪同。路上我们谈论起了伊莎贝尔和拉里。

“看见两个年轻人如此恩恩爱爱，怪叫人感动的。”我说道。

“他们还小，结婚还太早。”

“怎么早？趁年纪轻时恋爱、结婚，不是挺好嘛。”

“别说傻话啦。她今年十九岁，拉里也仅仅二十岁，连个工作也没有。他倒是有一笔小进项，一年三千块钱，这是路易莎告诉我的。路易莎不管从哪个方面讲都不算个富人，刚能凑合过日子。”

“哦，那他可以找个工作嘛。”

“说的是呀。可他没有这个心思。他好像很满意过这种无所事事的日子。”

“我敢说他在战争中一定吃了不少苦，也许现在想休息一下。”

“他休息已有一年了，时间够长的了。”

“我觉得他像是个很不错的孩子。”

“哦，我对他毫无成见。他的出身以及所有的一切都挺好的。他的父亲是巴尔的摩人，过去曾在耶鲁大学任教，是罗曼斯语[23]副教授。他的母亲出身于费城教友派的一个古老世家。”

“你口口声声提到过去，难道他的父母都去世了么？”

“是的，他母亲生孩子难产而死，父亲约在十二年前去世。他是他父亲的一个大学同学抚养大的，那人是马文的一个医生。路易莎跟伊莎贝尔就是这样才认识他的。”

“马文在哪儿？”

“布雷德利家的产业在那个地方，是路易莎的消夏之地。她见了那孩子，觉得挺可怜的。纳尔逊医生是个单身汉，对怎样带孩子连初步的常识都不知道。路易莎力主把这孩子送到圣保罗中学求学，每逢圣诞节便接他出来过节。”艾略特模仿法国人那样耸了一下肩膀，“我想她当初应该能预料到会有这样的结果。”

说话间，我们已走到博物馆，注意力也就转移到了绘画上。艾略特的见识和品味又令我拜服了一番。他领着我在画廊里转来转去，仿佛我是一群游客似的，讲解起那些画来，恐怕任何一个美术教授都不如他传授的知识多。我决定独自再来一次，那时自己可以由着性子转悠，自得其乐，现在先听他讲好了。过了一会儿，他看了一下表。

“咱们走吧。”他说，“在画廊里，我所待的时间从不超过一小时。一小时是一个人欣赏力所能坚持的极限。咱们改天再来看完它。”

分手时，我满口道谢。打道回府时，知识面也许扩大了一些，但我心里产生了几丝恼意。我和布雷德利夫人告别时，她告诉我第二天伊莎贝尔要请她几位年轻朋友来家里吃晚饭，饭后约好去跳舞；我要是愿意来的话，年轻人们走后，我还可以跟艾略特谈谈。

“你这等于是帮他的忙哩。”布雷德利夫人当时补充说，“他在外国待得太久了，回到这里觉得不合群，似乎找不到一个志同道合的人。”

我当即接受了她的邀请。此时在博物馆门口台阶上两人分手时，艾略特告诉我，他很高兴我答应了下来。

“在这座大城里，我就像一个迷途的幽灵。”他说道，“我答应路易莎跟她住六个星期。我们姐弟自从一九一二年后彼此就没有见过。可是，我盼着回巴黎真是归心似箭，在这里度日如年。在这个世界上，唯有巴黎适合于文明人居住。我亲爱的朋友，你知道他们这儿把我看作什么？在他们眼里我是一个怪物！这些野蛮人！”

我听后打了个哈哈，然后抽身走了。

六

次日，艾略特打电话来，说要接我去布雷德利夫人家，我回绝了他的好意，傍晚时分独自前往，也照样平安无事地抵达了目的地。出门前有客来访，稍微耽搁了一下。到达后上楼，客厅里人声嘈杂，我心想人数一定非常多，可终了意外地发现连我算上总共才十二个人。布雷德利夫人穿一身绿缎子衣服，戴一串细珠项链，显得仪态万方。艾略特穿的是无尾礼服，裁剪得体，一派儒雅的风度，大有超尘脱俗之风。跟他握手，他身上的阿拉伯香水味直朝我的鼻孔里钻。他把我介绍给一个身材稍胖的高个子，那人是个红脸膛，晚礼服穿在身上总显得别别扭扭的。此人就是纳尔逊医生，但当时我听了他的名字一点感觉也没有。其他的来客都是伊莎贝尔的朋友，那些人的名字被介绍后，我边听边忘。姑娘们个个年轻，人人漂亮，小伙子则都玉树临风。这些人除了当中的一个男孩，其他的没有给我留下任何印象——我记住了那男孩，只是因为他个头太高，身材太魁梧了。说起来，他一定有六英尺三四英寸高，生得虎背熊腰。伊莎贝尔看上去很漂亮，穿白绸上衣和拖地长裙（裙子长，正好遮住她的胖腿）；衣服颇显腰身，彰显她有着丰胸肥乳；露在外边的膀子略显肥胖，但脖颈是很可爱的。但见她情绪高昂，一双美眸闪闪发光。毫无疑问，她是个美丽、性感的年轻女子，但是看得出如果不当心的话，她会胖过头的。

吃饭时，我坐在布雷德利夫人和一位腼腆、拘谨的女孩中间——那女孩似乎是在场的人中最年轻的一个。落座后，布雷德利夫人引出了话头，说那女孩的祖父母住在马文，而她曾经和伊莎贝尔是校友。她的芳名叫索菲（这是我听到布雷德利夫人提起的唯一一个人的名字）。席间，客人们插科打诨，大家都可着嗓门说话，欢声笑语不绝于耳，人人好像都是知根知底的老熟人。我跟女主人聊天，抽个空就想跟邻座的女孩唠嗑，但是却讨个没趣——她不太爱跟人说话。论相貌她不算漂亮，可是脸蛋却很有趣味——小鼻头微翘，阔嘴，眼珠蓝里带绿。她的头发呈沙棕色，式样梳得很简单，身材消瘦，胸部几乎像男孩子一样平坦。别人开玩笑，她也跟着笑，但样子很勉强，叫人觉得她并没有真的被逗乐，开心的样子是装出来的。我猜想她在走过场，应付应付场面。不知她是天性愚钝还是过于拘谨，反正我频频兜起话头均落了个半路夭折，后来实在无话可说，就请她告诉我席间这些人都是些什么样的人。

“哦，纳尔逊医生你是认识的。”她指的是坐在布雷德利夫人对面的那个中年人，“他是拉里的监护人，是马文当地的一个医生，脑子很聪明，发明了许多飞机零件，只是没有人愿意买。无事可做的时候，他喜欢喝上一杯。”

说话时，她那浅色的眼睛里光彩熠熠，我不禁觉得她恐怕并不像我最初猜度的那般缺心眼。接下来，她把那些年轻人的名字一一告诉我，还告诉我那些人的父母是什么样的人。如果说的是男子，她就告诉我对方曾在何处上大学，现在干什么工作。她的介绍平淡无奇，或说“她很可爱”，或说“他高尔夫打得很好”。

“那个眉毛浓浓的大个子是什么人？”

“哪个？哦，那是格雷·马图林。他父亲在马文河畔有一所大房子，是我们那一带的百万富翁。我们都以他为荣，他把我们的身份都抬高了。马图林、霍布斯、雷纳和史密斯都是响当当的名字。在芝加哥，马图林是最有钱的了，而格雷是他的独生子。”

她讲到这一连串有钱人的名字时，语气戏谑、刻薄，使我不由得向她投去询问的目光，她见了脸发红，像块红布。

“马图林先生的情况，请你再仔细讲讲。”

“没有什么可讲的。他是个富翁，很受人尊敬，在马文为民众盖了一所新教堂，还捐了一百万给芝加哥大学。”

“他儿子长得很帅气。”

“他是个大好人。从他身上你绝想不到他祖父是个爱尔兰水手，祖母是瑞典人，曾在一家饭馆当服务员。”

格雷·马图林虽然并非英气逼人，却也气宇轩昂。他有着粗犷、豪放的气质，狮子鼻，嘴巴性感，肤色是爱尔兰人的那种红润色，一头浓密的黑发闪着光泽，眉毛粗重，清澈的眼睛湛蓝湛蓝的，虽则体格高大，却十分匀称，脱光衣服后暴露出来的一定是健美的身段。一看就知道他力大无穷，雄赳赳的样子给人以深刻的印象。坐在他身边的拉里虽则不过比他矮三四英寸，却比他显得文弱许多。

“崇拜他的人是很多的。”我的这位腼腆的邻座说，“据我所知，有好几个女孩子在拼命追他，就差没弄出人命了。可是她们一点指望也没有。”

“为什么？”

“你一点都不知道吗？”

“我怎么会知道。”

“他爱伊莎贝尔爱得都昏了头，而伊莎贝尔爱的却是拉里。”

“他完全可以争一下嘛，把伊莎贝尔从拉里手中夺过来。”

“拉里是他的铁哥们。”

“这样子可就麻烦了。”

“格雷是讲哥们义气的。”

我吃不准她这话的意思是当真，还是话中有话、夹枪带棒的。她的态度不卑不亢，一副不显山不露水的样子，而我产生了一种印象，觉得她既不缺幽默又不缺心眼。真不知她一边跟我说话一边在肚子里转什么心思。有一点我倒是知道的：我永远也别想摸透她。显而易见，她有点缺乏自信。我猜想她大概是个独生女，跟比她大许多的成年人在一起过着与世隔绝的日子。她在气质上贤淑静雅，倒是挺招人喜欢的。她常年过着孤独的生活——这一点如果我没猜错的话，那她一定在默默观察着成年人的一举一动，而且对他们形成了根深蒂固的看法。我们有些年纪的人很少觉察到年轻人对我们的判断是多么无情，然而又多么深刻。想到这里，我又瞧了瞧她那蓝里带绿的眼睛。

“你多大了？”我问道。

“十七岁。”

“你爱看书吗？”我唐突地冒出了这么一句。

可是，未等她回答，布雷德利夫人要尽地主之谊，跟我搭上了话头，我还没来得及摆脱，晚宴就结束了。那些年轻人转眼走得不知去向，剩下了我们四个人，就到楼上客厅里去坐。

我奇怪的是，不知他们为何要邀请我加入他们的谈话，因为闲聊了几句之后，他们便切入了一个话题——一个我认为他们一定愿意私下谈论的话题。我举棋不定，不知是不是应该知趣地起身告辞，或者作为局外人帮着出出主意。这个话题涉及的是拉里，说他看法古怪，不愿意参加工作。话题的核心点是：马图林先生（即刚才同席吃饭的那个叫格雷的男孩的父亲）答应给他一份工作，让他进马图林家的公司。这可是一个天赐的好机会。进了公司，只要能干和勤奋，拉里最终一定能挣很多的钱。小格雷·马图林一心希望他能接受这个工作。

我记不清那次谈话的具体内容了，但其主旨却清晰地印在了我的脑海里。拉里从法国返回，他的监护人纳尔逊医生劝他进大学深造，可是他拒绝了。他一时还不想忙碌起来，这也是很自然的——他毕竟在战争中吃了不少苦，还负了两次伤（虽然伤势并不严重）。纳尔逊医生认为他对战争的余悸还没有消除，休息休息直到完全恢复正常，这也在情理之中。可是，一星期又一星期过去了，一个月又一个月过去了，如今离他脱下军装已经一年多的时间过去了。他在空军里好像干得不错，回到芝加哥后成了个八面风光的人物，商界人士纷纷向他伸出橄榄枝，邀请他加盟。他先是表示感谢，继而婉言谢绝。他不解释原因，只说自己还没有拿定主意，尚不知干什么好。后来，他和伊莎贝尔订了婚。布雷德利夫人并不觉得意外，因为这两人密不可分，已相处多年，她知道伊莎贝尔深深爱着拉里。她本人也喜欢拉里，认为拉里能给女儿带来幸福。

“伊莎贝尔的个性比拉里强，可以弥补他的不足。”布雷德利夫人说。

尽管两人年纪都这么小，布雷德利夫人却愿意他们立刻结婚，不过有一个条件——拉里得先有份工作。拉里手头是有点钱的，但即便他的腰包比这鼓十倍，她还是要坚持这一原则。据我猜测，她和艾略特想从纳尔逊医生口中了解拉里的意图，并且希望纳尔逊医生运用他的影响力，劝说拉里接受马图林先生给他的职位。

“你知道我从来就管不了拉里，”纳尔逊医生说，“他小的时候就我行我素。”

“这我知道。你对他是大撒手。他没有变坏，完全是个奇迹。”布雷德利夫人说。

纳尔逊医生喝了不少酒，一听这话，白了她一眼，原本就红的脸变得更红了。

“我没空，有一屁股的事忙不完。当初我收留他，是因为他无处可去。谁叫他父亲跟我是朋友呢。他可不是个容易管教的主儿。”

“真不知你怎么能说出这种话。”布雷德利夫人尖刻地说，“他的性情是十分可爱的。”

“你叫我怎么办？这孩子从不跟你顶嘴，却想干什么照干什么。你气坏了的时候，他就说声对不起，然后就由着你发火。他要是我自己的儿子，我下得了手打他。可这么一个举目无亲的孩子，他父亲把他托给了我，心想我会善待他的，我总不能上巴掌吧？”

“你们净讲些不着边的话。”艾略特说，语气有点气呼呼的，“问题在于，他整日游手好闲，时间已经够长的了，现在有个好机会可以就业，能挣很多的钱；他如果想娶伊莎贝尔，就必须抓住这个机会。”

“必须让他知道，人活在世上就得有工作干。”布雷德利夫人插进来说，“他现在已恢复了元气，身体挺好的。大家都知道，南北战争之后，有些人回来从不做事，成了家庭的累赘，而且对社会毫无益处。”

就在这时，我开口说了话：

“那么多人邀请他去工作，都被拒绝了，那他给出的理由是什么呢？”

“无理由。他只说那些工作不合他的心意。”

“那么，他究竟想干什么样的工作呢？”

“显然没有他愿意干的。”

纳尔逊医生给自己又倒上一杯掺了苏打水的威士忌，喝了一大口，然后看看他的两个朋友。

“你们愿意不愿意听听我的拙见？我不敢说自己知人善辨，但毕竟行医三十余年，对人性也许还是略知一二的。这次战争改变了拉里。他从战场归来，已经不再是以前的他了，不仅增长了年岁，不知遇到什么事，连性格也变了。”

“遇到什么事了？”我问。

“这我无从得知。他对自己的战争经历总是讳莫如深。”纳尔逊医生说着，把脸转向了布雷德利夫人：“路易莎，他可跟你谈过他的经历？”

布雷德利夫人摇了摇头。

“没有。他初回来时，我们想让他讲讲战场上的经历，他却总是打个哈哈，说没有什么可讲的。甚至对伊莎贝尔，他也闭口不谈。伊莎贝尔不知问过多少次了，可一点名堂也没问出来。”

谈话就这么进行下去，效果不尽如人意。过了一会儿，纳尔逊医生看看表，说他必须告辞了。我准备跟他一同走，但艾略特硬把我留了下来。待纳尔逊医生走后，布雷德利夫人向我表示歉意，说拿这些私事搅扰我，恐怕我一定觉得腻味。

“不过，你从中也可以看到，这成了我的一件很大的心事。”她最后说道。

“毛姆先生为人很谨慎，路易莎，你不必担心，有什么事只管告诉他好啦。我并不觉得鲍勃·纳尔逊和拉里怎样亲密，不过，有些事路易莎和我都觉得不好开口跟他提。”

“艾略特。”

“话都说这么多了，何不将事情全都兜底讲出来。不知你吃饭时注意到格雷·马图林没有？”

“他块头那么大，谁都会注意到的。”

“他也是伊莎贝尔的一个追求者，拉里不在的时候，一直对伊莎贝尔殷勤备至。伊莎贝尔也喜欢他。假如战争再拖久一点，她很可能就嫁给他了。格雷倒是向她求过婚，她没有接受，也没有拒绝。路易莎猜她是不愿意在拉里回来之前就决定自己的终身大事。”

“格雷为什么不去参战呢？”我问。

“他因为踢足球，心脏出了点毛病，其实并没有什么大不了的，可是军队硬是不接受他。总之，拉里一回来，他就没戏了，伊莎贝尔彻底地拒绝了他的求婚。”

真是清官难断家务事。所以我没发表任何议论。艾略特却滔滔不绝地说了下去。以他那样的堂堂仪表和牛津口音，足可以当一名外交部的高级官员。

“当然，拉里是个好孩子，就他私自溜了去参加空军这件事来说也是一种了不起的壮举。不过，我看人只看实质，而且一看一个准……”他颇具深意地微微一笑，说了一句推心置腹的话——这是唯一的一句我所听到的揭示他从事艺术品交易发财诀窍的话，“如若不然，我现在就不会拥有一笔数额相当大的金边证券[24]了。依我看，拉里永远不会有大的出息，既不会有钱也不会有地位。格雷·马图林就全然不同了。他那古老的爱尔兰家族声望很好，出过一个主教、一个戏剧家，以及若干个出类拔萃的军人和学者。”

“这些情况你是怎么知道的？”我问。

“反正是该知道的时候就知道了。”他漫不经心地说，“其实，我是无意中知道的。那天在俱乐部里翻阅《名人大辞典》，看到了这个家族。”

我原本想把晚饭时我的邻座告诉我的情况和盘托出，说马图林的祖父是爱尔兰的穷水手，祖母是瑞典的一个饭馆服务员，可又觉得犯不着多事，便将话又咽了回去。只听艾略特仍在高谈阔论。

“我们认识亨利·马图林已经有好多年了。他人品好，而且非常有钱。格雷正要进芝加哥最好的一家经济行，天下的人没有不羡慕的。他想娶伊莎贝尔，替她着想，不能不说是一门很好的亲事。我自己完全赞成，而且我知道路易莎也赞成。”

“艾略特，你离开美国太久了。”布雷德利夫人说道，脸上挤出一个微笑，“你忘记了在这个国家里，女孩子并不因为她们母亲或者舅舅赞成她们的婚姻就去嫁人。”

“这种情况没有什么可以引以为自豪的，路易莎。”艾略特针锋相对地说，“根据我三十年的经验，我可以告诉你，一件婚事把地位、财产以及出身环境都考虑在内，要比爱情的结合强得多。法国算是世界上唯一的文明国家了吧。在法国，伊莎贝尔会毫不迟疑地嫁给格雷；婚后过上一两年，假如她愿意的话，可以把拉里当作她的情人；格雷呢，则可以置一所豪华公寓，养一个女明星嘛。那样会皆大欢喜。”

布雷德利夫人不痴不傻，眼睛望着自家兄弟，心里只觉得好笑。

“艾略特，问题在于，纽约剧团来演戏，待的时间有限，明星住进格雷那所豪华公寓里，能够住多久，没个定数。这会让不管哪一方都觉得心里不安宁。”

艾略特听后笑了。

“格雷可以在纽约证券交易所谋个缺嘛。在我看来，生活在美国，除了纽约，别的地方都是不能够住的。”

这以后不久我就辞别了。可是，在走之前，艾略特不知出于什么缘故，提出想请我跟他一道吃午饭，去会会马图林父子。

“若说美国的商人，亨利是最优秀的那一类了。”他说道，“你不妨跟他认识认识。他打理我们家的投资业已有许多个年头了。”

我并无结识此人的热情，可是一时又找不到推托之词，于是便答应了下来。

七

在芝加哥，为了消磨时光，我加入了一个俱乐部。俱乐部里有个挺不错的阅览室。赴宴的次日上午，我到阅览室想找一两本大学校刊看看——这种校刊一般只针对订阅者，平时难得一见。时间还早，阅览室里只有一个人，坐在大皮椅子上正出神地看书。我意外地发现那人竟是拉里。怎么也想不到会在这样的地方跟他不期而遇。我走近时，他抬起头来，认出是我，像是要站起来问候。

“坐着别动。”我说了一声，随后脱口问道，“你在看什么？”

“一本书。”他边说边粲然一笑——那笑容十分迷人，令他生硬的回答就完全不显得无礼了。

他把书合上，让我看不见书名，用他那简直无任何光泽的眼睛望着我。

“你昨晚玩得好吗？”我问。

“痛快极了，凌晨五点钟才回的家。”

“你这么早来这儿读书，真够刻苦的了。”

“我是这里的常客。平时的这个时候，屋子里只有我一个人。”

“我就不打搅你了。”

“你没有打搅我。”他说着又是粲然一笑。这一笑让我觉得魅力百生，绝非那种耀眼的、电光一闪的微笑，而是内心光明的展现，令他满面生辉。他坐的地方是用书架围成的一个角落，旁边还有一把椅子。他把手放在那把椅子的扶手上说：“你坐一会儿好吗？”

“好的。”

他把手里拿的书递给了我。

“我看的是这书。”

我看了看书名，原来是威廉·詹姆斯[25]写的《心理学原理》。这当然是部名著，在心理学史上占有重要位置，写得深入浅出、通俗易懂。不过，一个年轻人，一个飞行员，一个跳舞跳到凌晨五点钟的人，竟然在这儿捧读这样的一本书，就叫人意想不到了。

“为什么看这书？”我问。

“还不是因为学识太浅薄了呗。”

“你还十分年轻么。”我笑着说。

接下来，他好一会儿没有说话，我觉得局面有些尴尬，正想起身离开去找自己要读的校刊，却有一种感觉——他有话要说。只见他目光空洞地望着前方，表情庄重、专注，像是在沉思。我在等待他开口，满腹的好奇，想知道他会说些什么。他重新开始说话时，显得很连贯，仿佛中间没有出现过长时间的沉默似的。

“我从法国回来时，人人都劝我进大学深造。这我是做不到的。有了那样的人生经历，我觉得自己无法再重返校园了。在预科学校时我就没学什么东西，现在叫我上大一的课程，便是赶着鸭子上架，早晚是讨人嫌。我也不愿勉强自己做自己不想做的事。而且我不相信那些教师能教给我自己所需要的知识。”

“当然，我知道此事与我不相干，”我开口说道，“但我觉得你的想法是不对的。你的意思我想自己是理解的，也知道你打了两年的仗，现在让一个荣誉加身的中学生进大学，当一名大一大二的学生，滋味是很不好受的。至于你说自己会讨人嫌，我就不相信了。虽然我对美国的大学了解不深，但我认为美国的大学生和英国的并没有多大区别，也许只是稍微更顽皮一些，更喜欢热闹一些。总体而言，他们是些正派、懂事的孩子。我敢说，假如你不想过他们那种生活，只要稍微讲究一点策略，他们不会难为你的。我的哥哥弟弟都读过剑桥，我却没有。有过一个机会，可是我放弃了，而是一个心眼儿要到社会上闯荡。对此我一直都很后悔。当初要是上了大学，恐怕能少栽许多跟头。在有经验的大学老师指导下，学习上进步是很快的。缺乏引路人，就会糟蹋掉许多时间，盲人瞎马般乱撞。”

“也许你说得在理。但栽跟头我是不在乎的。盲人瞎马般乱撞，或许还能有所发现，找到自己的人生目标呢。”

“你的人生目标是什么？”

他迟疑了一下，然后说道：

“人生目标嘛，我也说不清道不明。”

我一时无语。对于这样的回答，你想评论似乎也是说不出什么来的。我本人少年时就有明确的人生目标，对缺乏志向的人当然会感到不耐烦的。不过，我喝止住了自己。我有个感觉，只能说是直觉：这孩子的魂魄里有一种杂乱的冲动，不知那是半明半昧的观念，还是一种隐隐约约的情绪，使得他永无宁日，刺激着他盲目地朝前冲。说来也怪，正是这样的一种东西令我顿时萌发了同情之心。此前听他说话只是只言片语，此刻始发现他的声音十分悦耳，如香膏般叫人陶醉。想想这些，再看看他那迷人的微笑和富于表情的黑眼珠，也就不难理解伊莎贝尔为什么那般爱他了。他身上的确有惹人怜爱的地方。他转过脸望着我，神态坦率，但眼睛里却有一种表情——既是挑剔，又有点玩世不恭。

“昨天晚上我们去跳舞，我想你们在背后说我了吧？”

“不错，是提到了你。”

“硬把鲍勃叔叔请来，恐怕就是因为这个理由了。他原本是很讨厌出门的。”

“好像有人给你找了一个很好的工作。”

“工作的确是很棒。”

“你打算干吗？”

“恐难从命。”

“为什么？”

“他们有心，我无意。”

我真是咸吃萝卜淡操心。不过，我有一种感觉，正是因为我来自海外，与此事无关，他才无排斥之心，愿意跟我交流交流。

“哦，你知道，一个人什么都做不了时，他就当作家。”我说完，扑哧笑了一声。

“我可没有当作家的天赋。”

“那你打算干什么呢？”

他绽出一个灿烂、迷人的微笑。

“逛大街。”他说。

我听了不由哈哈大笑。

“芝加哥恐怕不是个逛大街的好地方。”我说，“我就不打搅了。你看你的书吧，我去查阅《耶鲁季刊》。”

我起身走开了。等到我离开阅览室时，拉里还在专心致志地看威廉·詹姆斯的那本书。我独自在俱乐部里用了午餐，因为阅览室里安静，又回到那里去抽雪茄，在那儿消磨了一两个小时，看看书、写写信什么的。叫我感到诧异的是，拉里仍在聚精会神地看书，好像自打我走开后他一直就没有挪过窝。四点钟左右我走出阅览室，他还在老地方。显然，他有着很强的定力，叫我感到很是惊讶。我或来或走，他全然不加留意。下午，我因琐事缠身，直到应当换衣服去赴晚宴时，才回黑石旅馆。回旅馆的路上，我突发好奇之心，于是又去了一趟俱乐部，拐进了阅览室。此时，阅览室里已经有不少人在看报读书什么的。拉里竟然还坐在那张椅子上，还在全神贯注地看那本书！这不能不叫人称奇！

八

次日，艾略特请我去帕尔玛饭店共进午餐，同时会见马图林父子。这一席总共四人。亨利·马图林也是个大块头，差不多和他儿子一样魁梧，一张肉乎乎的红脸，大下巴，也有着一个咄咄逼人的狮子鼻，但眼睛却比儿子的小，也不如儿子的那样蓝，露出几分刁钻诡诈。论年岁，他也只不过五十开外，面相却老上十岁，头发稀得很厉害，白如霜染；初看上去，并不给人好感。看他的气派，好像这些年头混得挺不错。他给我留下的印象是一个残酷、精明、能干的人，这种人在生意场上是绝不会讲情面的。起初，他少言寡语的，我觉得他在打量我。我一眼就看得出，艾略特在他的眼中只是个可笑的人。格雷温和可亲、彬彬有礼，几乎一句话不说，如若不是艾略特交际手腕老到，滔滔不绝扯些闲话，局面一定会很僵的。我猜他过去和那些中西部商人做交易，积累了不少经验——那些人不用甜言蜜语哄着，是不会花那样惊人的价钱买一张古旧名画的。过了一会儿，马图林先生渐渐放松了下来，吐出了几句话语，这才显出他并不似表面那样严峻，而且的确还有点干巴巴的幽默感。席间有那么一会儿，话题转到了股票证券上。艾略特口若悬河，显得知识极为渊博，这一点也不叫人惊奇，因为我一向知道他虽然处事荒唐可笑，在这方面却绝非饭桶。

就在这时候，只听马图林先生说道：

“今天上午我收到格雷的朋友拉里·达雷尔写的一封信。”

“没听你讲起过呀，爸爸。”格雷说。

马图林先生转向我问：

“你认识拉里吧？”

我点点头。

“格雷做过我的工作，让我在公司里给他安排一个位置。他们是好朋友。格雷对他极为上心。”

“他是怎么说的，爸爸？”

“他向我表示感谢，说这对一个年轻人而言是千载难逢的好机会。他认真做了一番思考，最后觉得一定会辜负我的栽培，还不如最初就不接受的好。”

“简直愚蠢之极。”艾略特说。

“是这样的。”马图林先生说。

“太让人遗憾了，爸爸。”格雷说，“如果我们俩能在一起工作，那该多好呀。”

“强扭的瓜不甜呀。”

马图林先生说这话时看着儿子，那双诡诈的眼睛顿时变得温柔起来。我这才看出这位寡情的商人还有另外的一面——他对自己的那个大块头儿子有着极深的舐犊之情。随后，他将目光又一次转向了我。

“你知道这孩子星期天在场子上打了两盘标杆赛，赢了我七杆和六杆。我真该用球棒揍他一顿。想起来，他打高尔夫球，还是我一手教会的呢。”

他的表情很为儿子感到自豪，叫我开始对他有了好感。

“我只不过是运气好嘛，爸爸。”

“根本不是那回事。你把球从沙坑里打出来，落下来离洞口只有六英寸远，难道凭的是运气不成？那一杆打了三十五码远，一英寸也不会少。明年我还想叫他去参加业余锦标赛呢。”

“我恐怕抽不出时间来。”

“我是你的老板，难道不是吗？”

“我可知道你的厉害！我上班哪怕迟到一分钟，你也会暴跳如雷的。”

马图林先生扑哧一声笑了。

“看这小子把我描绘成了个专制霸王了。”他对我说道，“别信他的话。公司靠我撑着呢，我的合伙人都不行。我为自己的业绩感到自豪。我叫这孩子从底层干起，希望他跟其他的年轻员工一样一步一个脚印地干上去，一旦需要他继承我的事业时，他也就成熟了。像我的这个公司规模，可是千斤重担呢。我为有些客户打理投资业务，有长达三十年的历史了，他们对我是信任的。实不相瞒，哪怕是我自己赔钱，也不愿看客户折本。”

格雷笑了。

“那天，有个老姑娘来找他，想投资一个风险很大的项目，说是牧师建议她这么做的，他拒绝为她办理。老姑娘认死理，惹得他发了一顿脾气，结果老姑娘哭着走了。后来他又跑去找那个牧师，将牧师也训了一通。”

“别人谈论起我们经纪人，总把我们说的一无是处，殊不知经纪人也有好坏之分呢。对客户，我不想让他们折本，只想叫他们赚钱。大多数客户不领情，看他们那做派，就好像人生只有一个目标——散漫使钱，非得将钱折腾光不可。”

饭后，马图林父子辞别，回公司去了。我和艾略特离开饭店时，他突然问我：“你怎么看马图林先生？”

“我一向喜欢结交各种不同类型的人。我觉得他们父子之间感情深厚，令人感动。想来这在英国是不多见的。”

“他对儿子宠爱得不得了。他的性格的确有点古怪。他评论自己客户的那席话倒是句句真实。他的客户有好几百，都是些老太婆、退伍军人和牧师，把手里的积蓄交给他搞投资。那些人麻烦得很，我觉得为他们打理生意很划不来。可他极为看重那些人对他的信任。不过，遇到大生意，有厚利可图，他就会翻脸不认人，谁都不如他心狠手辣。这时的他是一点情面都不讲的。他要想从你身上割一磅肉，那他会不达目的誓不罢休。你要是跟他对着干，他会叫你倾家荡产，非整倒你而后快。”

回到家，艾略特对布雷德利夫人直言相告，说拉里拒绝了亨利·马图林给他的机会。伊莎贝尔正跟闺密们共进午餐，走进来时，姐弟还谈着这件事。他们将结果告诉了她。后来，艾略特把这次谈话的情况讲给我听，我觉得他把一番大道理说得头头是道。虽然他自己没有干什么艰苦的活儿，他用以发家致富的工作一点辛苦的味儿也没有，他却坚定地认为经营实业乃国之本。拉里只不过是个普普通通的青年，又没有社会背景，没有理由不按照国之常情办事。在艾略特这样有眼光的人看来，美国显然正在步入一个空前的繁荣时代。拉里现在有个入门的机会，只要他脚踏实地撒手干，到了不惑之年也许能挣几百万。那时候，他要是愿意歇手，过过上等人的日子，完全可以当个寓公，在巴黎的杜波依斯大道买一套公寓，或者在都兰购一幢别墅，他艾略特将无话可说。这时，布雷德利夫人冲着女儿说的一句话更为直截了当，叫伊莎贝尔难以回答：

“他要是爱你的话，为了你，他也应该出去工作。”

伊莎贝尔具体是怎么回应的，我无从得知。这姑娘胸藏锦绣，情知大人的话不无道理。她认识的小伙子们都有了出路，或学习深造，或进哪个行当实干，或进公司经商。拉里虽在空军有过辉煌的业绩，但也不能指望着吃一辈子呀。战争硝烟已散，人人都对战争深恶痛绝，恨不能赶快忘掉战争的创伤。经过一番讨论，伊莎贝尔答应跟拉里摊牌，把事情来个彻底了断。布雷德利夫人献计：伊莎贝尔可以求拉里开车送她去马文，就说她在给客厅定制新窗帘，一张量好的尺寸单被她丢掉，所以要叫伊莎贝尔再去量一下。

“鲍勃·纳尔逊会留你吃午饭的。”她说。

“我有个更好的主意。”艾略特说，“不如准备个午餐篮，就在门廊那儿吃，吃完好说事儿。”

“这样倒是怪有趣的。”

“自自在在来一顿野餐，是天下最美的享受了。”艾略特不失时机地补充说，“泽斯公爵老夫人曾私下对我说，再怎么执拗的男子，到了这种场合也会变得温顺服帖。路易莎，你打算给他们准备什么样的午餐？”

“煮鸡蛋和鸡肉三明治。”

“净胡来。野餐嘛，哪能没有肥鹅肝酱饼。头一道菜应该是咖喱虾仁，再下来就是鸡脯肉冻，配上生菜心沙拉，沙拉的调料由我来配制。有了肥鹅肝酱饼，如果愿意的话，可以按你们美国人的习惯，准备上一个苹果派。”

“我只给他们准备煮鸡蛋和鸡肉三明治，艾略特。”布雷德利夫人斩钉截铁地说。

“那你记住我的话：此事一定会泡汤，怪只能怪你自己。”

“拉里的胃口非常小，舅舅，”伊莎贝尔说，“而且吃进肚子里的是什么他从不注意。”

“但愿你不要把这当作他的优点，傻孩子。”做舅舅的回了一句。

至于那次野餐，布雷德利夫人硬是坚持家里有什么就让他们吃什么。事情过后，艾略特告诉我结果时，法国味十分浓地耸了耸肩膀。

“我早就有言在先，说事情会泡汤的。我战前送给路易莎一瓶蒙哈榭白葡萄酒，这次求她放进野餐篮，可是她充耳不闻。伊莎贝尔他们只用热水瓶灌了些咖啡，其他一点酒水都没有。你还能指望有什么好结果呢！”

据说，伊莎贝尔回家时，路易莎·布雷德利和艾略特正坐在客厅里。汽车吱扭一声停在大门前，伊莎贝尔走了进来。天擦黑，窗帘已拉上。艾略特懒散地坐在扶手椅上，在炉边看一本小说。布雷德利夫人在绣一块帷帘，是要当作防火屏风[26]用的。伊莎贝尔没有来客厅，而是直接回楼上她的房间去了。艾略特抬起头，目光从眼镜的上方望了望姐姐。

“我想她脱掉帽子，用不了一分钟就会下来的。”做姐姐的说。

可是伊莎贝尔没有下来，好几分钟过去了也没下来。

“可能是累了，躺在床上休息呢。”

“你难道没想到，拉里应该进来坐坐吗？”

“别说叫人生气的话，艾略特。”

“好吧，反正这是你家的事，我这是狗拿耗子多管闲事。”

说完，他又继续看他的书了。布雷德利夫人继续刺绣屏风。但半个小时后，布雷德利夫人坐不住了，突然站了起来。

“我想，还是上去看看她怎样了吧。假如休息了，我就不惊动她了。”

她离开客厅上楼去，可没过多大一会儿就又下来了。

“她哭了一场。拉里要到巴黎去，两年内回不来。她答应等他。”

“他为什么要到巴黎去？”

“问我没有用，艾略特，我无从得知。她什么都不肯告诉我。她说她理解拉里，不愿当他的绊脚石。我跟她说：‘他一别就是两年，证明他爱你爱得不十分深。’她说：‘我也没有办法。问题在于我爱他爱得十分深。’我说：‘有了今天的变化，你对他的爱还十分深吗？’她说：‘今天的变化反而叫我比以往任何时候都更加爱他了。他也爱我，对这一点我坚信不疑。’”

艾略特细细思索了一会儿。

“两年之后会出现什么情况呢？”

“我哪能知道，艾略特。”

“你不觉得这样的结局让人十分扫兴吗？”

“的确叫人十分扫兴。”

“没什么可讲的了，只能说他们还很年轻，等上两年也无妨。在这两年当中，什么事都可能发生。”

姐弟俩达成一致，最好不要去打搅伊莎贝尔。一家人原打算出去吃晚饭，于此只好作罢。

“我可不想让她听了别人的议论而感到难过。”布雷德利夫人说道，“那些人见她哭肿了眼泡，肯定会感到好奇的。”

第二天，他们在家里吃午饭，饭后布雷德利夫人旧话重提，把那件事又摆在了桌面上，可还是从伊莎贝尔嘴里问不出话来。

“能告诉你的都告诉你了，妈妈，实在没有什么可讲的了。”伊莎贝尔说。

“我问你，他到巴黎究竟想去干什么？”

伊莎贝尔微微一笑，因为她知道自己接下来的回答一定会叫母亲感到不可思议。

“他要去逛大街。”她说道。

“逛大街？这是什么鬼话？”

“他就是这么说的。”

“我真是受不了你。你要是有点骨气的话，就应该跟他一刀两断。这不明明在耍你嘛。”

伊莎贝尔看了看戴在左手上的订婚戒指，然后说道：

“我有什么办法呢？我爱他。”

后来，艾略特也加入了母女的谈话。他运用娴熟的说话技巧掺和了进去。“我可没有摆舅舅的谱，亲爱的伙计，而是作为一个通晓世情的人跟一个毫无社会经验的女孩对话。”他对我解释道。可是，他所达到的效果并不比他的姐姐强。伊莎贝尔好像叫他别管闲事，语气当然是很客气的，说得却是掷地有声。就在当天晚一些的时候，艾略特来到黑石旅馆，在我的小客厅里将事情的来龙去脉一五一十告诉了我。

“当然，路易莎是完全正确的。”他最后补充道，“此事弄得人非常窝火。男女青年仅仅是相互爱慕，除此之外什么也不懂，让他们决定自己的婚姻，这种结果是避免不了的。我叫路易莎不必为此愁肠百结，也许会有柳暗花明那一天呢。拉里走了，格雷·马图林还在嘛……如果我对自己的国人看法没错的话，结局是很明显的。十八岁的年轻人感情炽热如火，但长久不了。”

“你真是熟谙世态炎凉呀，艾略特。”我笑了笑说。

“我读拉罗什富科[27]的书，总算没有白读。你知道芝加哥社会是个小圈子。他们天天见面。女孩子家，有个男子死心塌地爱她，肯定会芳心大悦。她要是知道自己的闺密无一不心甘情愿地想嫁给这个男子，那你想想，她是不是出于人的本能也会拼一拼、争一争宠呢？这情形犹如去参加一个宴会——你明明知道去了会无聊得不行，吃的东西也只有柠檬水和饼干，然而你还是去了，因为你知道自己最好的朋友们打破头都想去，却没有受到邀请。”

“拉里何时启程？”

“不知道。行程可能还没有决定呢。”艾略特说着从口袋里掏出一个长方形的薄薄的镶金铂质烟盒，取出一支埃及烟。对于法蒂玛牌、契斯特菲尔德牌和骆驼牌那样的香烟，他是瞧不上眼的。他笑眯眯地用眼睛瞅着我，笑容含蓄，别有深意。“有些话不便讲给路易莎听，不过可以告诉你：对于那个小伙子，我暗藏同情之心。战争期间，他可能目睹了巴黎的风采。他要是被这个天下唯一适合于文明人居住的城市迷了心窍，那我一点都不感到奇怪。他年纪轻，无疑是想在结婚过小日子之前，纵情风流一把。这很正常，也很自然。我要照拂他的，引荐他认识应该认识的人。论风度，他还是能上得了席面的，稍加指点，便可以出入社交场合了。我保证能叫他看到真正的法兰西生活——能有这种机会的美国人少之又少。老伙计，请相信我的话：普通的美国人要进入圣日尔曼大道[28]，真比登天还难。他二十岁，魅力还是有的。我可以做出安排，让他跟一个年纪大一些的女人建立联系，这对他的成长大有裨益。我总觉得，一个年轻男子给一个有些岁数的女人当情郎，本身就是一种最好的教育方式。当然，我所说的女人必须是社交名媛[29]，这会叫他一步登天，步入巴黎上流社会。”

“你把这锦囊妙计告诉布雷德利夫人了吗？”我微笑着问。

艾略特嘿嘿嘿地笑了。

“我的老伙计，假如我有值得自豪之处，那就是我的处世方针。我没有告诉她，就是说出来，她也不会理解的。可怜的路易莎！她有许多地方叫我永远也吃不透，而这就是其中的一点。她半辈子都生活在外交界，世界上有一半国家的首都她都待过，可骨头缝里仍然是一个死脑筋的美国人。”

九

那天晚上，我到湖滨大道上的一所偌大的石头屋赴宴。看那房屋，好像建筑师当初打算盖一座中世纪城堡，后来中途改变主意，决定建成一幢瑞士风格的山地农舍式房子。宴会的规模很大。走进宽敞、奢华的客厅时，满眼都是雕像、棕榈树、枝形吊灯、古画，以及散布各处的家具。令我高兴的是，来宾中至少有几位是熟人。亨利·马图林给我介绍了他的老婆——一个骨瘦如柴、弱不禁风、脸上涂脂抹粉的女人。我向她问了声好，也向同在跟前的伊莎贝尔打了个招呼。伊莎贝尔穿一身红绸衣裙，和她那浓栗色头发、深褐色眼睛很相配，显得光彩照人。她看上去兴致很高，谁也猜想不到她最近在情感上刚有过一段痛苦的经历。两三个小伙子，其中包括格雷，众星捧月般围着她，而她满脸喜色地与之谈笑。吃饭时她和我不同桌，看不见她。饭后，我们男客消消停停地喝咖啡、呷酒、抽雪茄，过了许久才回到客厅里。在这儿，我有了跟她说话的机会。按说，我和她不熟，不便开门见山，将艾略特给我说的话直接端出来，可又觉得应该说些什么，也许她还乐得一听呢。

“那天在俱乐部里我看见你的男友了。”我以漫不经心的语气说道。

“哦，是吗？”

她说话时也同样漫不经心，但我发现她竖起了耳朵，注意力立刻集中了起来，眼睛在观察着我，里面似乎能看得到几分忧虑。

“他在阅览室里看书，聚精会神的，那种专注的劲儿给我留下了十分深刻的印象。十点钟刚过的时候我去阅览室，他在看书；吃过午饭后我回到那儿，他还在看书；饭馆里吃过晚饭后回家，我拐回去瞧了瞧，他仍在看书。我敢说他在椅子上足足坐了有十个小时没挪过地方。”

“他看的是什么书？”

“威廉·詹姆斯的《心理学原理》。”

她听后垂下了眼皮，我无从得知自己的一席话在她的心里激起了什么样的反应，但我隐约感到她好像既困惑不解，又松了口气。这时，主人跑来拉我去打桥牌，等到牌局散时，伊莎贝尔和她母亲已经走了。

十

过了两三天，我去向布雷德利夫人和艾略特辞行，碰到他们正在喝茶。不大一会儿，伊莎贝尔也走了进来。接下来，大家以我的行程为题目交谈了几句。随后，我对他们表示感谢，感谢他们对我在芝加哥逗留期间盛情的招待。就这么坐了不长不短的一段时间，我便起身告辞了。

“我陪你走到药店那儿，”伊莎贝尔说，“我刚想起有点东西要买。”

分别时，布雷德利夫人对我说的最后一句话是：“你下次看见亲爱的玛格丽达王后时，替我向她表示敬意，好吗？”

这次，我没有否认自己认识那位高贵的夫人，而是爽快地答应一定做到。

我和伊莎贝尔来到大街上，她笑吟吟地用眼角的余光看了看我。

“去喝一杯冰淇淋苏打水，能喝得惯吗？”她问我。

“喝喝看吧。”我想了想说。

一路上，伊莎贝尔再也没说话，我肚子里没有话，也就沉默着。到了药店走进去，我们捡一张桌子坐下，椅背和椅子腿都用铁条扭成，坐着怪不舒服的。我点了两杯冰淇淋苏打水。柜台那儿有几个人在买东西；别的桌子旁坐着两三对客人，但都忙着谈自己的事情。总之，没人注意到我们俩。我点起一支香烟等着伊莎贝尔说话，而她用一根长吸管喝着苏打水，样子不急不忙的。我却有一种感觉——她的内心并不安宁。

“我是想跟你谈谈心里话。”她猛然来了这么一句。

“我猜到是这回事。”我笑盈盈地说。

她若有所思地望着我，有那么一会儿工夫。

“前天晚上在萨特思韦特家，你为什么那样说拉里？”

“我觉得你关心他的情况。在我看来，你恐怕没有真正理解他所说的‘逛大街’的含意。”

“艾略特舅舅的嘴很碎。那天他说要上黑石旅馆找你谈谈，我就知道他要把所有的事情都告诉你的。”

“你也知道，我认识他许多年了。议论起别人的事情，他就津津有味的。”

“的确如此。”她笑了笑说。但那笑意一闪便消失了。随后，她直直地看着我，目光严肃认真。“你怎么看拉里？”

“我只见过他三次，觉得他像是个非常不错的小伙子。”

“就这么些吗？”

她的声音流露出一丝忧伤。

“不，不仅仅如此。三言两语很难说得清，也可能是我对他了解太少了。当然，他很讨人喜欢。他身上有一种谦虚、友好、温柔的东西，十分吸引人。他这么年轻，却如此有主见，跟我在这里见到的所有的小伙子都不一样。”

我搜索枯肠，找着字眼想把心中并不怎么清晰的印象讲出来，而伊莎贝尔看着我，目光专注。待我讲完，她轻轻舒了口气，仿佛是吊在嗓子眼的心落了地，然后抛给我一个微笑，迷人，还带点顽皮。

“艾略特舅舅说他时常对你的观察力感到诧异。他说什么都逃不过你的眼睛，但你作为一个作家，最大的长处则是你的判断力。”

“我看还有比这更为珍贵的呢，”我干巴巴地说，“例如才气就是其中的一种。”

“你知道我的情况——苦于找不到人商量此事。妈妈只从她自己的角度看问题。她只想让我将来过上衣食无忧的日子。”

“这很自然，可怜天下父母心。”

“艾略特舅舅只看社会地位。我自己的朋友——那些和我年龄相仿的人，认为拉里没有出息。这使我很难受。”

“当然的喽。”

“并不是说他们待他不好。谁也不可能对拉里不好。可是，他们看不起他，拿他当笑柄，老是取笑他。他却不愠不恼，只是付之一笑，让那些人感到老大没趣。事情的现状你知道吗？”

“只是听艾略特说了些。”

“我们那天去了一趟马文。我把当天发生的事情讲给你听好吗？”

“当然好了。”

我对那天的情况做如下描述，一部分根据的是对伊莎贝尔说话内容的回忆，一部分则是我想象出来的。不过，她和拉里的谈话是一次长谈，内容肯定要比我在此处陈述的丰富得多。依我看，遇到这种事情，谈话人不仅会扯些风马牛不相及的话头，还会把一些话重复来重复去的……

话说伊莎贝尔那天早晨醒来，见天气晴好，便打电话给拉里，说她母亲有点事情要她到马文去一趟，求他开汽车送她去。除了她母亲关照尤金准备的一热水瓶咖啡外，她还特地把一瓶马丁尼酒放进了野餐篮子。拉里的车是辆跑车，是才买来的，他颇为此而感到自豪。他开车风驰电掣，那速度叫二人都觉得痛快极了。抵达了目的地，伊莎贝尔给需要调换的窗帘量了尺寸，拉里用笔记了下来。随后，他俩来到门廊，将午餐摆上。这儿避风，任何一个方向的风都吹不到此处，却沐浴着小阳春的阳光，令人感到舒服惬意。这幢房子位于一条土路边，跟新英格兰那些古香古色的木屋比起来，缺乏的是雅致，顶多只能说得上宽敞舒适，可是从门廊上望出去的景色却还悦目——一座红色的大谷仓，黑屋顶；一丛老树；再过去是一片一眼望不到头的褐色田野。景色是单调的，可是，阳光和深秋的温暖色调在那一天却给眼前的景色平添一种亲切和温馨的气氛。展现在面前的那片寥廓里，洋溢着欢乐。冬天这里一定寒冷荒凉，夏天可能炎热蒸人，然而在这个季节却使人感到异常兴奋，因为开阔的景色撩人，使人内心里产生出冲动。

他们俩跟所有青年男女一样，在一块儿吃饭吃得很开心。二人能够单独相处，不胜欢喜。伊莎贝尔把咖啡斟好，拉里点上了烟斗。

“现在你可以打开天窗说亮话了，亲爱的。”拉里说道，眼睛里带着一丝开心的笑意。

伊莎贝尔被说得一愣。

“说什么亮话呀？”她问道，故作一副不明就里的样子。

拉里呵呵笑了。

“亲爱的，你难道把我当作大傻瓜不成？你母亲要是不知道客厅里窗帘的尺寸，我就把脑袋输给你。你要我开车子送你来这里，恐怕另有他因。”

伊莎贝尔恢复了镇静，给了他一个千娇百媚的微笑。

“原因嘛，是我觉得咱俩在一起待上一天比什么都强。”

“话可以这么说，但我觉得事实并非如此。依我看，是艾略特舅舅把实情告诉了你——我谢绝了亨利·马图林的好意，不愿接受他给我的工作。”

他说话时语调轻松愉快，伊莎贝尔觉得用这种口吻谈下去倒也有利于交流看法。

“格雷一定会大失所望的。能跟你在一个办公室上班，在他看来是天大的一件美事。你总有一天要找个工作做的，时间拖得越久，就越难找。”

他抽了一口烟斗，望着她，温情地笑着。她摸不着头脑，不知他葫芦里卖的是什么药。

“我有一种想法——此生想有所作为，而不仅仅局限于经营股票生意。”

“那么好吧。那你进律师事务所工作，或者去学医。”

“不，这两件事我都不想做。”

“那么，你想做什么呢？”

“逛大街。”他一本正经地回答。

“天呀，拉里，别说俏皮话了。这是件严肃认真的事情。”

她声音颤抖，眼睛泪水汪汪。

“别哭呀，亲爱的。我可不想惹你难过。”

他走过来，挨着她坐下，用胳臂搂住她。他的声音里有一种柔情，深深打动了她，于是泪水似决堤般滚滚而下。可她马上又擦干眼泪，破涕为笑，让一丝笑意浮现在嘴角。

“不想惹我难过，那是漂亮话。其实你已经在让我难过了。你知道，我是爱你的。”

“我也爱你，伊莎贝尔。”

她发出深深的一声叹息，然后从他怀里挣脱出来，把身子挪开了一些。

“识时务者为俊杰。人生在世，总得干活呀，拉里。这是一个有关于自尊的问题。咱们的国家很年轻，需要每个人都参加它的建设活动。亨利·马图林那天说，咱们正在进入一个新纪元，将会取得辉煌的成就，让人类以前所有的作为都相形见绌。他说咱们国家的成就将会是无可估量的。他坚信到了一九三〇年，我国将成为世界上最富强、最伟大的国家。你不觉得这非常振奋人心吗？”

“的确非常振奋人心。”

“对一个年轻人而言，这是个千载难逢的好机会。依我看来，你一定会为能够参加这项事业而感到自豪的。这可是一项改天换地的事业。”

他听了淡然一笑。

“我敢说你是对的。阿穆尔-斯威夫特公司将会做出更多更好的肉罐头，麦考密克公司将会造出更多更好的收割机，亨利·福特将会造出更多更好的汽车。每个人的钱包都会变得越来越鼓。”

“这不挺好吗？”

“正如你所言，这是挺好的，只是我对钱不感兴趣。”

伊莎贝尔咯咯咯地笑了。

“亲爱的，别说傻话。没有钱是活不下去的。”

“我手里是有一点钱的。这点本钱能让我按自己的意愿去行事。”

“逛大街吗？”

“是的。”他笑嘻嘻地说。

“你这是叫我为难呀，拉里。”她叹了口气说。

“很抱歉。要是有办法，我也是不愿叫你为难的。”

“你应该是有办法的。”

他摇了摇头，由于想心事，半天没吱声。等到他最后开口时，说出的话吓了伊莎贝尔一大跳：

“人死如灯灭。死了，一了百了。”

“你这话究竟是什么意思？”她不无担忧地问。

“就是这个意思。”他冲着她苦笑了一下说，“当你独自在天上飞行时，会有许多的时间思考人生，会产生一些离奇古怪的想法。”

“什么样的想法？”

“模糊、杂乱、不连贯的想法。”他笑了笑说。

伊莎贝尔想了想，然后说道：

“先找个工作干，也许就能理清头绪，从而使心情安定下来，你不觉得这是上策吗？”

“对于何去何从，我也做过一番思考。我想到过去当木匠或者汽车修理工。”

“天呀，拉里，人家会以为你疯了呢。”

“别人怎么说，有什么关系呢？”

“对我而言是有关系的。”

说到这里，二人又沉默了下来。后来，伊莎贝尔打破了沉默。只听她叹了口气说：

“跟去法国参战之前相比，你像是变了个人似的。”

“这并不奇怪。要知道，我在那儿经历了许多的事情。”

“什么事？”

“哎，说起来也只是些战场上经常发生的事情。我在空军有个最好的朋友，为了救我，他壮烈牺牲了。此事叫我怎么也难以忘怀。”

“给我讲讲，拉里。”

他看了看她，露出十分痛苦的眼神。

“还是不讲的好。说到底，这在战场上只是件小事。”

伊莎贝尔本来就容易动感情，此时早已泪水涟涟。

“你为此而感到纠结了吧，亲爱的？”

“没什么。”他笑吟吟地回答道，“要是惹你不高兴，这才会叫我纠结呢。”他拉起她的手——他那坚实有力的手使她感受到了友谊和亲密无间的感情。她咬紧嘴唇，不让自己哭出声来。“除非找到了生活的目标，否则我的一颗心恐怕永无宁日。”他表情沉重地说。之后，他停了停，才又说道：“这种心情很难用语言表达，想说也说不出口。我会在心里自责，千不该万不该，不该为过去的事情而痛苦，从而殃及别人。也许，怪只怪我自己是个顽固不化的人。我会问自己：走别人所走的路，随遇而安，是不是更好些呢？就在这时，我的脑海里会出现一个人，刚刚还生机勃勃，转眼便命赴阴间。生活就是如此残酷，如此缺乏意义。你不禁要问：人生的意义在哪里？人生的价值在哪里？难道人生是一种愚蠢的、盲目的、悲惨的过程吗？”

讲述时，拉里的声音异常悦耳，说说停停的，就好像是在强迫自己说出本不愿吐露的心事，然而样子是那般沉痛真挚，使人听了不能不受感动。伊莎贝尔动情得半天都说不出话来，最后才问道：

“你出去待一阵子，会不会好一些呢？”

话一出口，她的心便沉了下来。

拉里沉吟良久方才回答：

“我想是的。不理睬社会舆论，着实不易。当社会舆论向你压来时，会激发你的逆反之心。你的心情也会因而得不到安宁。”

“那你为什么不一走了之？”

“唔，是为了你呗。”

“咱们不妨把话说得直白些，亲爱的。就目前而言，你的生活中恐怕没有我的一席之地。”

“这是不是说，你不想和我保持订婚的关系了？”

伊莎贝尔芳唇直抖，挤出了一个笑容。

“不，别说蠢话。我的意思是等你归来。”

“也许要等一年，或者两年呢。”

“这没有关系。也许等不了那么长时间。你打算上哪儿去呢？”

他望着她，目光专注，仿佛想要看到她内心深处似的。她微微一笑，以此掩饰自己内心的悲苦。

“哦，我想先去巴黎。那边我一个人不认识。不会有人干涉我的生活的。战时休假，我去过几趟巴黎。不知怎么的，我有一种感觉：一到了那里，浑浊的大脑就会变得清晰。那是一个奇妙的地方，叫你觉得一切问题都会迎刃而解，胸中的块垒会消失得无影无踪。我想到了那里也许就能看清前进的方向了。”

“假如不能如愿，你又该如何？”

他嘻嘻嘻地笑了笑。

“那样我就改弦更张，重拾我的美国人生观，痛改前非，回到芝加哥来，有什么工作就干什么工作。”

这次深谈对伊莎贝尔触动很大。她对我讲述时，免不了有些激动。待把话说完，她望了望我，表情惹人哀怜。

“你觉得我做得对吗？”

“我觉得你做了自己力所能及的事情。另外，我还觉得你有一副菩萨心肠，待人仁厚，善解人意。”

“我爱他，希望他能够生活幸福。要知道，从某些方面来说，他离开家乡，我并不感到遗憾。我想让他摆脱这种充满敌意的环境，不仅是为了他，也是为了我自己。我不能怪那些人说他不会有什么出息；我恨他们，然而我的内心深处总有一种忧虑，觉得他们说得有道理。不过，请别说我善解人意。对于他在追求什么，我还是理解不透的。”

“也许你的心能理解，但从理智上却理解不透。”我笑笑说，“为什么你不立刻和他结婚，跟他一起到巴黎去？”

她的眼睛里微微露出了一丝笑意。

“我巴不得这样做，可是我不能。要知道，虽然我不愿承认，但我内心真实地觉得，没有我，他的境况会更好一些。如果纳尔逊医生的话说得对，他的病是一种慢性惊恐症。换换环境，接触新的事物，会使他康复如初。等到内心恢复了平静，他就会回到芝加哥来，像周围的人一样工作和生活。我可不愿嫁给一个闲汉。”

伊莎贝尔从小受环境的影响，已经接受了大人给她灌输的原则。对于金钱，她并不多加考虑，因为她从小到大从未尝过缺钱的滋味。不过，出于本能，她可以感觉到钱的重要性——钱意味着权势和社会地位。作为一个男人，挣钱是天经地义的事。这也是他一生的事业。

“要说你理解不透拉里，我并不感到奇怪。”我说，“我敢肯定，连他本人也理解不透自己。他只字不提自己的人生目标，那是因为他的人生目标是模糊不清的。实不相瞒，我跟他并无深交，此处所言仅仅是猜测——他是不是在寻找某样东西，某样他并不了解甚至都不知道是否存在的东西呢？也许，他在战争中不知经历了什么事情，才使得他躁动不安，得不到安宁。依你看，他是不是在追求一种虚无缥缈的理想——就像天文学家在寻找一颗只有数学计算说明其存在的星体一样？”

“我觉得有种什么东西在搅扰着他。”

“你指的是他的灵魂吗？也许，他所害怕的是他自己吧。也许，他隐隐约约看到了某种景象——至于这种景象是否真实，他并无把握。”

“他有时候叫我觉得他行为古怪，给我一种印象——他像是个梦游者，在一个陌生的地方突然醒过来，摸不清自己身在何处。参战之前，他是很正常的。那时，他最可爱的地方是对生活的热爱。他悠闲潇洒，乐乐呵呵的，跟他在一起十分开心。那时的他甜蜜可人，说话妙语连珠。到底发生了什么事情，才令他与以前相比判若两人了呢？”

“这种情况我也说不清。有时候，一件小事情对一个人就会有很大的影响，那要取决于他当时的处境和心情。记得有一次过全圣节（法国人称之为亡人节），我到一个村庄的教堂去做弥撒——德军最初一攻入法国，那座村庄就遭到了军队的蹂躏。教堂里挤满了军人和穿着丧服的女人；教堂墓园里看得到一排排木制的小十字架。弥撒庄严、悲伤，女人们泪流满面，男人们也伤心落泪。我当时有个感觉，认为长眠于那些小十字架下面的死人可能比活着的人还要好受些。我把自己的感受讲给一个朋友听，他问我那是什么意思，我却难以解释得清。看得出，他认为我是个十足的傻瓜。我还记得，在一次战斗之后，阵亡法军士兵的尸体被堆放在一起，像小山一样，看上去就像一堆提线木偶，被破了产的木偶剧团胡乱丢在肮脏角落里，因为它们再也派不上用场了。当时我想到的就是拉里告诉你的那句话：‘人死如灯灭。死了，一了百了。’”

我可不想让读者觉得我在故弄玄虚，给深深影响了拉里的那段战争经历蒙上一层神秘的色彩，非得等到最后才揭开谜底。对于那段经历，他恐怕给任何人都没有讲过。过去了许多年之后，他才对我们俩都认识的一个叫苏姗娜·鲁维埃的女子讲述了那段如烟的往事，说一位年轻的飞行员为了救他而牺牲了自己的生命。苏姗娜·鲁维埃把他的话转述给我，而我只能根据二手材料进行复述，而且是从她的法语翻译过来的。拉里显然跟飞行队里的另一个小伙子结下了很深的友谊。苏姗娜不知道那个小伙子的名姓，只知道他的一个很滑稽的绰号——那是拉里讲到他时提到的。

“他是个红头发的小个子，爱尔兰人，我们都叫他‘捣蛋鬼’。”拉里这样告诉苏姗娜，在我认识的人里面，他最具活力，简直可以说是生龙活虎。他长了一张滑稽的脸，脸上挂着一副滑稽的笑容，见了他，你禁不住就会发笑。他是个闯祸精，什么荒唐事都干得出来，总是挨上司的骂。他完全是个天不怕地不怕的主儿，战场上九死一生捡回一条命，他也会一脸笑嘻嘻的样子，就好像出生入死是天下最好玩的事情一样。不过，他天生就是个当飞行员的料，一上蓝天就变得冷静、机警。他教给我不少东西。他比我年纪大一点，因此将我置于他的保护伞之下。这实在具有喜剧效果——我比他要高出六英寸，论打架，我可以轻松地把他放倒。一次在巴黎，他喝得酩酊大醉，我怕他惹是生非，果真把他放倒过。

“加入飞行队时，我觉得有些跟不上趟，生怕自己干不好。他百般勉励我，让我树立自信心。他对战争的看法离奇古怪，对德国人没有丝毫敌意，只是因为爱打架，才乐颠颠地喜欢和德国人交锋。每击落一架敌机，他只是觉得好玩而已。他是个无法无天的人，行为粗野，无拘无束。但他身上有一种诚恳的素质，叫你不由得会喜欢上他。他会把你的钱拿去花，而为了你，他也愿意倾尽钱囊。如果你觉得孤独，或者想家，或者害怕，像我有时候那样，他就会看出来，让他那张丑陋的小脸上堆满笑容，然后说一些贴心的话，使你的心情恢复正常。”

说到这里，拉里抽了一口烟斗，苏姗在等着他继续说下去。

我们经常编造出一些事由，以便我俩一起出去度假。每次去巴黎，他就狂放不羁。那段时间，我们玩得真开心。一九一八年的三月，我们又准备出去度假，并提前做出了安排。我们的计划满满的，有许多事情要做。就在临行前一天，我们奉命飞越敌军防线侦察，把侦察到的情况带回来。突然，我们与几架敌机遭遇。没等我们反应过来，双方已经进入了激战。一架敌机追过来，但我先下手将其击中，然后转过脸去看它会不会坠落。就在这时，我从眼角看过去，发现又有一架敌机盯上了我。我向下俯冲想躲开它，可它一转眼就追上了我，我想这一下可完了。却看见‘捣蛋鬼’闪电般冲过来，把雨点般的子弹泼在它身上。敌机战不过我们，夹着尾巴逃跑了，我们也返回了基地。我的飞机给打得遍体鳞伤，算是挣扎着着陆了。而‘捣蛋鬼’先我一步着陆。我下飞机时，他们刚把他抬出驾驶舱。他躺在地上，在等救护车来。他看见我，咧开嘴笑了。

‘那狗日的盯住你不放，我把他打下来了。’他说道。

“你怎么啦，”捣蛋鬼？我问他。

‘哦，没什么，他打中了我的胳臂。’

“只见他脸色惨白。突然间，他的脸上浮现出一种古怪的神情。他此时才醒悟到自己快要死了。在这之前，他心里从没想到过自己竟然还会死去。没等周围的人反应过来，他一挺身坐了起来，哈哈大笑道：‘他妈的，我死啦！’说完，他就倒下去死了，年仅二十二岁。他原本打算在战争结束后回爱尔兰，跟一个爱尔兰姑娘结婚呢。”

和伊莎贝尔长谈后的第二天，我就离开芝加哥去了旧金山，准备从那儿乘船前往远东。

第二章

一

一直到第二年的六月末，艾略特来到伦敦，我才和他又见了面。我问他拉里到巴黎去了没有，他说去了。他对拉里窝了一肚子的火，这叫我听了暗自发笑。

“我对这孩子素有恻隐之心，他想来巴黎待上两年，我毫不怪他，而且还准备帮助他一把。我告诉他，一到巴黎就通知我。后来路易莎写信告诉我，说他在巴黎时，我才知道他已经来了。我让美国运通公司转给他一封信（地址是路易莎给我的），请他来吃饭，让他认识几位我觉得有必要认识的人。我一厢情愿地想让他先结交一些法裔美国人，其中有爱米丽·德·蒙塔杜尔和格拉西·德·夏托加亚尔等。你猜他是怎么回复的？他说很抱歉不能来，因为他来法国时没带晚礼服。”

艾略特眼睛盯着我，以为他的一席话会叫我的脸上出现惊讶的神情，却发现我声色不动，于是便一抬眉毛，露出了不悦。

“他的回信写在一张劣质信纸上，上面印有拉丁区一家咖啡馆的名字。我又写了封信给他，要他把住址告诉我。我觉得，看在伊莎贝尔的分上，我也得帮他一把。我当时以为他不愿来是怕见生人——我简直无法相信一个头脑正常的年轻人来巴黎怎么能不带晚礼服；而且不管怎样说，巴黎的裁缝铺也还是不错的。这次我说明是请他吃午饭，客人也不多。可是，你恐怕不会相信，他无视我的请求，没有把住址告诉我，仍托美国运通公司转来回信；这还不够，他竟然说自己从不吃午饭。这一下，叫我拿他一点办法都没有了。”

“不知道他现在在干些什么。”

“鬼才知道。实话说，他干什么我才不管呢。恐怕这个小青年是个极不成器的人。伊莎贝尔嫁给他，肯定是个大错误。如果他是个正儿八经的人，就应该出入于里茨酒吧间或者富凯饭店等场所，而非拉丁区的咖啡馆。”

这些时尚的高级场所，有时候我自己也出入，但不时尚的地方我也去。那年的初秋时分，我到马赛去，准备乘法邮公司的船前往新加坡，途中路过巴黎时在那儿住了几天。一天傍晚，我和几个朋友在蒙巴纳斯街区吃过晚饭，一同去多姆咖啡店喝杯啤酒。我四周瞧瞧，一眼看见拉里在人满为患的露台上，独自坐在一张大理石面的小桌旁。他悠闲地望着街上来往的行人——闷热的白天刚过，人们在享受晚间的凉爽。我丢下同伴朝着他走了过去。他看见我，脸上顿时放出亮光，抛给我一个迷人的微笑。他请我坐下，可我说是跟朋友们一起来的，不便多待。

“我来只是想向你问声好。”我说道。

“你住在巴黎吗？”他问。

“只住几天。”

“明天跟我一起吃午饭好吗？”

“我还以为你从不吃午饭呢？”

他哧哧地笑了。

“看来你见过艾略特了。我一般是不吃的，没有时间吃，只喝杯牛奶、吃块蛋糕对付一下。不过，我倒是想跟你一起吃顿午饭。”

“那好吧。”

我们约好次日来多姆咖啡店见，先喝杯开胃酒，然后去林荫大道找个馆子吃饭。商定之后，我便回到那几个朋友身旁谈天说地。待我转过头再去看拉里，发现他已经走了。

二

第二天上午，我度过了一段惬意的时光。先是到卢森堡博物馆去，用去一个小时观赏自己喜欢的画作，随后我就悠然散步于花园中，追忆已经逝去的青春年华。这儿一点变化都没有。但见青年学子成双成对漫步在沙砾小径上，兴奋地谈论着叫他们热血沸腾的作家；孩子们在保姆的照看下滚铁环玩耍；老人们一边晒太阳一边读晨报；几个正在服丧的中年妇女坐在公共长凳上唠嗑，议论食品的价格和用人的不端行为。眼前的人和景依稀宛如当年。后来我去了奥德昂大剧院，在剧院的长廊里浏览陈列在那儿的新书。我看见几个少年跟我三十年前一样，顶着身穿长罩衫的书亭老板那恼怒的目光，如饥似渴地阅读自己所买不起的书。出了大剧院，我迈着四方步走在那亲切、幽暗的偏街小巷，到了蒙巴纳斯街区，再走到多姆咖啡馆。拉里已在那儿等候。喝了杯酒，我们就慢慢悠悠去找吃饭的地方了，想找一家可以在室外进餐的馆子。

与上次见他时相比，他的脸色也许苍白了些，这倒让他那双深陷在眼窝里的乌黑的眸子更加炯炯有神。他还是那样矜持自重，这对一个小青年来说是很少见的；他的笑容依然坦率真诚。他点饭菜时，我留意到他说一口流利的法语，语音纯正。为此，我向他表示祝贺。

“要知道，我以前懂得一点法语。”他解释说，“路易莎伯母给伊莎贝尔请了个法国家庭女教师。在马文的时候，那位教师让我们跟她讲法语，始终坚持这么做。”

我问他喜欢不喜欢巴黎。

“非常喜欢。”

“你在蒙巴纳斯街区住吗？”

“是的。”他迟疑了一下才回答道。我猜想他这是不愿说出自己确切的住址。

“你给艾略特只留了美国运通公司业务点的地址，叫他十分生气。”

拉里笑笑，什么也没说。

“你成天干些什么呢？”

“逛大街。”

“还看书吗？”

“是的，还看。”

“跟伊莎贝尔通信吗？”

“有时候通通信。我俩都不擅于写信。她在芝加哥过得很开心。明年她们要来法国，在艾略特这儿待待。”

“这对你们俩是件好事。”

“据我所知，伊莎贝尔没来过巴黎。领着她四处走走，一定会很有趣的。”

对于我的中国之行，他充满了好奇之心，很想听我讲一讲。当我开始讲述时，他听得非常专注。可是我想让他谈谈他自己的情况时，他却三缄其口。他的沉默使我只能有一个结论——他约我吃饭仅仅是想和我一起坐坐。我虽然感到高兴，心里却百般困惑。喝完咖啡，他就叫结账，付了钱，然后站起了身子。

“哦，我得走了。”他说。

我们分了手。对于他的人生目标，我仍然知之甚少。那以后，我再没有见过他。

三

直至来年春天，我才又回到了巴黎。布雷德利夫人和伊莎贝尔将计划提前，已经抵达巴黎，在艾略特家里住了下来。这中间隔了有好几个星期，因此，我又得运用想象力，凑合着叙述母女俩这段时间的经历……她们在瑟堡上的岸，历来善于体贴人的艾略特前往迎接。过了海关之后，三个人上了火车。火车启动时，艾略特扬扬得意地宣称给她们请了个相当棒的女仆伺候她们。布雷德利夫人说完全没有这个必要，她们不需要女仆。艾略特听了，顿时变得声色俱厉起来。

“不要一来就惹人生气，路易莎。没有女仆是见不了人的。我请安托瓦内特来，不仅是为了你和伊莎贝尔，也是为了给我争面子。你们的穿戴不体面，会叫我无地自容的。”

说着，他瞥了一眼母女俩身上的衣服，一脸的瞧不起。

“当然，你们要购置点新衣服。我想来想去，认为只有沙诺尔式女装[30]店最合适。”

“我以前一直都是去沃思服装店。”布雷德利夫人说。

她这话说了也是白说，因为艾略特根本不予理睬。

“我跟沙诺尔式女装店说过了，约你们明天下午三点去那儿。另外还需要买帽子——当然是要莱伯克斯牌子的喽。”

“我不想多花钱，艾略特。”

“我知道。所有的一切花销都由我出就是了。我只想让你给我争点面子。好啦，路易莎，我特意为你安排了几场宴会。我告诉我的法国朋友，说迈伦曾经是位大使——他要是活的时间再长一些，这是板上钉钉的事情。这样说，给人的印象好一些。这件事不会有人问起的，但我觉得还是先给你打个招呼好。”

“你真是荒唐可笑，艾略特。”

“哪里的话。我懂得人情世故，深知一个大使的遗孀比一个部长的遗孀更有身份。”

火车喷着蒸汽驶进了巴黎北站。站在车窗前的伊莎贝尔叫了起来：

“拉里来了。”

没等火车停稳，她便跳下了车，迎着拉里跑去。拉里张开双臂将她搂在怀中。

“他怎么知道你们来？”艾略特酸溜溜地问姐姐。

“伊莎贝尔在船上给他发了封电报。”

布雷德利夫人疼爱地吻了吻拉里，艾略特无精打采地跟他握了握手。寒暄间，已经是晚上十点钟了。

“舅舅，拉里明天能不能来吃午饭？”伊莎贝尔高声问道。她挽着拉里的胳膊，脸上一副恳切的神情，眼睛里闪着光芒。

“这是我的荣幸。不过，我似乎听拉里说过他从不吃午饭。”

“明天他会吃的，是不是，拉里？”

“是的。”拉里莞尔一笑说。

“那么，明天一点钟恭候你大驾光临。”

艾略特又伸出手来，想把他打发走，可是拉里咧着嘴笑，厚着脸皮不肯离去。

“我要帮着搬行李，再给你们叫辆汽车。”

“我的车在等着呢，我的用人会照管行李的。”艾略特盛气凌人地说。

“那好呀。那咱们就走吧。如果汽车里有我坐的位子，我就送你们到家门口。”

“有你坐的地方。一起走，拉里。”伊莎贝尔说。

两个年轻人沿着站台走了，布雷德利夫人和艾略特跟在后面。艾略特黑着脸，一副不情愿的样子。

“没素质。[31]”他在嘴里咕哝了一句。在某种情况下，他觉得讲法语能够更有力地表达自己的情绪。

翌日上午十一点钟，艾略特起了床（他平素总睡懒觉），洗漱完毕，写了个便条，由男仆约瑟夫和女佣安托瓦内特转两道手交给他的姐姐，约她到书房来谈话。布雷德利夫人来了之后，他谨慎地关上门，把一支香烟装在一根非常长的玛瑙烟嘴上点着，然后坐下来。

“是不是可以说，伊莎贝尔和拉里还有着订婚的约定吧？”他启口问道。

“恐怕是这样的。”

“对这个小青年，我恐怕没什么好话可说的。”他冲着布雷德利夫人大倒苦水，说他怎样煞费苦心想将拉里引入上流社会，说他怎样针对拉里量体裁衣，制订了整套的计划。“我甚至还为他瞧上了一套低层的住房[32]，非常适合他住。那房子属于德·勒泰勒小侯爵，他被派驻马德里的大使馆任职，所以想把房子租出去。”

可是，拉里把他的好心当成了驴肝肺，谢绝了他的邀请，显然是不愿意接受他的帮助。

“假如你不愿利用巴黎得天独厚的条件，那你为什么要到巴黎来？实在叫人百思不得其解。不知道他在捣鼓些什么。他在这儿好像无亲无友的。你知道他的住址吗？”

“他只给了我们一个地址，那就是美国运通公司。”

“看他就像个云游四方的推销员或者来度假的教师，居无定所。他要是在蒙马特高地[33]的一间画室里跟一个下流女人同居，那我一点也不感到惊奇。”

“别胡说，艾略特！”

“他把自己的住处搞得神秘兮兮，又拒绝跟自己同阶层的人来往，除此之外，难道还会有别的解释吗？”

“拉里不像是那号子人。昨天晚上你不是也看到了，他和从前一样深爱着伊莎贝尔吗？那样的假他可是作不出来的。”

艾略特耸耸肩膀，意思是告诉他姐姐，男人们逢场作戏的手腕是极其高明的。

“格雷·马图林怎样？还在追吗？”

“只要伊莎贝尔肯答应，他恨不得马上就跟她结婚。”

接着，布雷德利夫人告诉了艾略特她们比原定计划提早来到欧洲的原因。她发现自己的健康状况不好，医生说她患上了糖尿病。病情并不严重，只要注意饮食，适当地服用胰岛素，完全能够活上好多年。可是，她在知道自己得了这种不治之症之后，急切想看见伊莎贝尔有一个好的归宿。母女俩谈过这件事。伊莎贝尔很明智，说如果拉里在巴黎住了两年之后，不遵照原议回到芝加哥，并且找个工作做，那就只有一条路可走——跟他一刀两断。可是，布雷德利夫人觉得要等到约定的时间，然后去巴黎把拉里像个逃犯一样抓回美国，有损个人的尊严。她觉得伊莎贝尔那样做很失面子。不过，母女俩来欧洲消夏却是很正常的——伊莎贝尔自从长大之后，再也没到欧洲来过。她们打算在巴黎待过之后，去一个海滨度假地让布雷德利夫人养养病，再从那里前往奥地利的蒂罗尔山区住住，然后慢慢悠悠穿过意大利。布雷德利夫人有意约拉里同行。路上，让拉里和伊莎贝尔相互了解了解，看他们在久别之后感情是否仍一如既往。至于拉里在经过了一段时间的恣意放纵的生活之后，是不是愿意承担起责任来，到时候自会明白。

“拉里拒绝了亨利·马图林提供给他的工作，叫对方觉得很不痛快，多亏格雷打圆场，才算让父亲消了气。拉里只要回芝加哥，立刻就可以有工作干。”

“格雷是个大好人。”

“一点没说的。”布雷德利夫人叹了口气说，“伊莎贝尔嫁给他，一定会幸福的。”

接下来，艾略特介绍了给她们母女安排了几场什么样的宴会。明天下午他要举办的是场大型午宴，周末安排的则是一个气势恢宏的晚宴。他还要带她们去参加查迪乌·加拉兹家的招待会，而且还给她们弄到两张舞会请帖，届时将去罗慈吉尔兹府上跳舞。

“拉里你也要请吧？”

“他告诉我，说他没有晚礼服。”艾略特哼了声鼻子说。

“哎，反正你请他一下就是了。说到底，他是个挺不错的小伙子。冷冰冰地对待他没有什么用处，只会叫伊莎贝尔更加执拗。”

“当然，你要我请我就请吧。”

拉里在约定的时间赶来赴午宴。但见艾略特热情洋溢、礼貌周到，对拉里更是和蔼可亲。对拉里待之以礼并不难，因为他满面春风、兴致勃勃的，艾略特又不是一个天性恶毒的人，哪能不产生好感。午宴上，大家以芝加哥为话题，大谈彼此都认识的朋友，把艾略特给晾在了一旁，他只好做出和和气气的样子，摆一副屈尊俯就的架势，好像很关心这些在他眼里毫无社会地位的人似的，关心他们的痛痒。听客人们海阔天空地说话，他并不排斥。其实，听到某一对年轻男女订婚了，某一对年轻男女结婚了，某一对年轻男女离婚了，他觉得怪惹人同情的。听到这样的事情，哪能不动情呢？据他所知，年轻美丽的德·科林尚特女爵曾为情试图服毒自杀——她的情人德·科龙贝亲王抛弃她，娶了个南美洲百万富翁的千金。这样的话题说起来的确津津有味。看看拉里，他不得不承认他有种异常吸引人的地方。拉里那深陷的、乌黑乌黑的眼睛，那高颧骨、苍白的皮肤和灵巧的嘴，让他联想起波提切利[34]的一幅画像，觉得如果叫拉里穿上那个时代的服装，看上去一定充满浪漫气息。他记起自己曾经打算把拉里介绍给一位显赫的法国女人，同时想到星期六晚宴邀请了玛丽·路易丝·德·弗洛里蒙，禁不住偷偷笑了。这个女人交游甚广，道德上却臭名昭著，两点兼而有之。她四十岁的年龄，看上去却要年轻十岁。纳蒂埃[35]曾经为她的一个女祖先画过像，这张像通过艾略特亲自努力，现挂在美国的一个大画廊里。玛丽生得就和她这个女祖先同样千娇百媚，而她在性生活方面欲壑难填，好像永远不能满足似的。艾略特决定让拉里坐在她身边。他知道玛丽会不失时机地叫拉里懂得她的欲望。他还请了英国大使馆的一位年轻的侍从武官，认为伊莎贝尔说不定会喜欢上的。伊莎贝尔脸蛋长得漂亮，那个英国人家境阔绰，虽然伊莎贝尔没有财产，也是没有关系的。一开始吃饭，大伙儿便觥筹交错，先喝上等蒙哈榭白葡萄酒，继而喝味道纯正的波尔多酒，喝得艾略特轻飘飘的，心里乐悠悠地遐想着各种可能出现的情况。如果事态的发展如他估计的那般，亲爱的路易莎就没有什么可焦虑的了。路易莎总是有点把他的话不当回事，可怜的人儿，怪都怪她见的世面太少。不过，他喜欢自己的这个姐姐。利用自己走南闯北积累下的经验为她把一切安排得停停当当，也是一件称心的事情。

为了不浪费时间，艾略特安排好一吃完午饭就带路易莎母女去看衣服。所以，客人们才从餐桌旁站起身，他便用自己最擅长的辞令暗示拉里可以离开了，同时又以诚恳、亲切的语气邀请他来参加自己安排的两场盛大宴会。其实他没必要多虑，因为拉里一听很痛快就答应了下来。

可是，艾略特的计划落空了。话说拉里来参加晚宴时，穿了一套很像样的晚礼服，艾略特看见后松了一口气。起初他还有点担心，怕拉里穿上次午宴时的那身蓝西装呢。晚饭后，艾略特把玛丽·德·弗洛里蒙拉到角落里，问她觉得他的这位年轻美国朋友怎么样。

“他有一双漂亮的眼睛和一口好看的牙齿。”

“仅此而已吗？我让他坐在你身边，是觉得他合你的口味。”

她疑惑地看了看他。

“他告诉我，说已经跟你漂亮的外甥女订婚了。”

“得了吧，亲爱的。[36]一个男子属于一个女子，只要你办得到，这可不会妨碍你横刀夺爱的。”

“你想让我夺人之爱？可怜的艾略特，我绝不会替你干这种卑鄙勾当的。”

艾略特嘿嘿一笑。

“听你的话音，我觉得你好像已经试过水了，只是没有进展罢了。”

“艾略特，我喜欢的就是你的这种妓院老板般的品性。你不愿意让他娶你的外甥女。为什么？他有教养，而且很讨人喜欢。不过，他未免太单纯了些，可能丝毫没有怀疑我的动机。”

“你应该把意图表现得更明确些，亲爱的朋友。”

“你是情场老手，明知这是白费气力。他的眼睛里只有你家的小伊莎贝尔。咱俩之间说说——她的优势在于她比我年轻二十岁。而且，她甜美可人。”

“你喜欢她的衣服吗？我亲自给她挑的。”

“样式漂亮，也很合身。只可惜她没有高雅的风度。”

艾略特认定后半句话是冲着他来的，觉得不能轻易放过她，非得戳一下她的痛处不可。于是他满脸堆起亲切的笑容，款款说道：

“一个人非得活到你这样成熟的年龄，才会有高雅的风度，亲爱的。”

德·弗洛里蒙夫人手里挥动的是一根大棒，而非烧火棍，杀伤力很大。她的反唇相讥让艾略特身上的弗吉尼亚血液沸腾了起来。

“我可以肯定，在你们那个土匪横行的美丽国家里（votre beau pays dapaches[37]），如此微妙、如此独特的东西，人们是不会有所欠缺的。”

虽则德·弗洛里蒙夫人横挑鼻子竖挑眼，艾略特其他的朋友对伊莎贝尔和拉里他们俩，都还是挺喜欢的。他们喜欢伊莎贝尔的青春美，喜欢她充溢的健康和蓬勃的活力；他们喜欢拉里生动的外表，喜欢他儒雅的谈吐以及他那含蓄、带有讽刺意味的幽默。二人讲一口标准、流利的法语，这也是他们的一大优点。布雷德利夫人在外交界生活多年，法语说得还算标准，只是夹带着一点美国腔调，她却不以为然。艾略特对待她们母女极为慷慨。伊莎贝尔喜欢自己的新衣新帽，也喜欢艾略特安排的各种叫人心花怒放的活动。还有，和拉里在一起，她感到很幸福。她觉得自己从来都没有如此快活过。

四

艾略特认为，只有接待生客才陪着吃早饭，那也是万不得已的事情。布雷德利夫人和伊莎贝尔只好在各自的寝室用早点了，布雷德利夫人很不情愿，伊莎贝尔却丝毫不在意。不过，有时候伊莎贝尔醒来后，会叫艾略特给她们雇的那个高贵女佣安托瓦内特把她的一份咖啡牛奶送到她母亲的寝室，母女俩好在吃早点时聊聊天。她整天忙得滴溜溜转，一天当中只有这点时间能陪母亲坐坐。她们来巴黎快一个月后的一个这样的早晨，伊莎贝尔先把昨天晚上做的事情叙述了一遍，无非是说她和拉里随一群朋友逛夜总会什么的；接着，布雷德利夫人提出了一个问题——这个问题自打来巴黎后一直压在她的心头。

“他打算什么时候回芝加哥？”

“不知道。他提都没提过。”

“你没有问过吗？”

“没有。”

“你是不是怕问？”

“不是，当然不是。”

布雷德利夫人斜倚在长靠椅上修指甲，身上穿一件正流行的晨衣——一件拉里执意要送给她的礼物。

“你俩在一起都说些什么？”

“我们一般不说话。两人在一起坐坐就很好了。你知道拉里总是沉默寡言的。交谈起来，差不多都是我一人在讲话。”

“他平时干些什么？”

“我也弄不清楚，只觉得没有干什么大事。我想他过得挺开心的。”

“他住在哪里？”

“这我也不知道。”

“他好像城府很深呀，对不对？”

伊莎贝尔点起一支香烟，从鼻孔里喷出一缕烟，静静地望着自己的母亲。

“你这话究竟是什么意思，妈妈？”

“你舅舅认为他租了一套公寓，跟一个女人同居。”

伊莎贝尔不听则已，一听笑破了肚皮。

“这话你相信吗，妈妈？”

“不相信，老实说我不相信。”布雷德利夫人望着自己的指甲，沉吟良久，“你可曾跟他谈过回芝加哥的事？”

“谈过，谈过不知多少次了。”

“他是否有所表示，说他打算回去呢？”

“恐怕没有什么表示。”

“十月份他离开家乡就满两年了。”

“这我知道。”

“这是你的事情，亲爱的，你觉得该怎么做就怎么做吧。不过，久拖不决也不是个事呀。”布雷德利夫人盯着女儿，但伊莎贝尔将目光躲开了。布雷德利夫人疼爱地冲她一笑。“去吧，去洗个澡准备准备，吃午饭可别迟了。”

“我要跟拉里去吃午饭。在拉丁区的一个什么地方。”

“好好玩去吧。”

一小时后，拉里来接她。二人叫了辆出租车去了圣米歇尔桥，然后沿着人头攒动的林荫大道转悠，最后相中了一家咖啡店。他们在这家店的露台上落座，叫了两杯杜本内开胃酒[38]。出了咖啡店，他们又叫车去了一家饭馆。伊莎贝尔胃口很好，拉里点的那些可口的饭菜她都吃得津津有味。饭馆里顾客盈门，吃客们你挨着我、我靠着你坐在一起进餐，这场面叫伊莎贝尔看了挺开心的。瞧见人们狼吞虎咽的吃相，她会禁不住笑出声来。不过，她最为开心的是能够和拉里单独在一起，卿卿我我地坐在一张小桌旁。她兴高采烈地说这说那，拉里听着眼里闪出欢快的光芒，这让她看在眼中喜在心头。跟拉里无拘无束坐在一起，让她感到陶然若醉。但她的内心深处隐隐约约有一丝不安——拉里虽然也无拘无束的，她却觉得真正给他以轻松感的与其说是她，倒不如说是周围的环境。母亲早上说的话对她有所触动。于是，她叽叽喳喳说着话，似乎一点心思也没有，实际却在观察他的每一细小表情。拉里和最初离开芝加哥时相比略有不同，但她说不清他究竟发生了什么变化。他看上去跟以前别无二致，还是那么年轻，那么坦率，只是神情却有了变化。这种神情并不是比以前更严肃（他脸上总有一副严肃的表情），而是多了一份从前所没有的安宁。他好像解决了一道人生的难题，如今寻找到了心灵的安宁——这是前所未有的现象。

吃完饭，拉里建议去逛卢森堡博物馆。

“不，我不想去看画。”

“好吧，那就去花园里坐坐。”

“不，我也不想去那里。我要去看看你住的地方。”

“没什么可看的，我住在旅馆的一个很寒酸的斗室里。”

“艾略特舅舅说你有一套公寓，跟一个画家的模特儿同居。”

“无稽之谈。那你亲眼去看看好啦。”他大笑道，“从这里去只有几步路。咱们可以步行过去。”

他带着她穿过几条狭窄的、弯弯曲曲的街道——这些街道夹在高房子中间，可以望见一抹青天，显得肮脏暗淡。走了一会儿，二人来到了一家门面寒碜的小旅馆。

“咱们到了。”

伊莎贝尔随着他走进一间狭窄的厅堂，厅堂的一侧有一张桌子，桌旁坐着个男子，穿一件衬衣和一个细黑黄条子相间的背心，系一条围裙，正在那里看报。拉里问他要房间的钥匙，那人从身后格子架里把钥匙取出交给了他，同时好奇地瞥了伊莎贝尔一眼，又转为会意的傻笑。显然他认为伊莎贝尔去拉里的房间不是干规矩事情的。

他们爬上两段楼梯，楼梯上铺着破旧的红地毯。拉里用钥匙打开房间的门。伊莎贝尔走进一间有两扇窗户的小房间。从窗口望去，街对面是一幢灰颜色的公寓楼，公寓楼的底层开着一家文具店。小房间里有一张单人床，配一个床头柜，另外还有一口镶着大镜子的笨重的衣柜，一把装了垫子但是椅背笔直的扶手椅，两扇窗子之间放一张桌子，桌子上有架打字机、一些纸张和几本书。壁炉板上堆放了些平装书。

“你坐扶手椅吧，虽然不太舒服，却是这里最好的了。”

他另外拉过来一把椅子，自己也坐下了。

“你就住在这地方？”伊莎贝尔问。

他看见她脸上的神情，扑哧一声笑了。

“可不是么。来巴黎后，我一直住在这里。”

“为什么？”

“图个方便呗。这儿靠近国家图书馆和巴黎大学。”他指指她没有注意到的一扇门说，“这里有洗澡的地方，有早餐吃。晚饭一般就在咱们吃午饭的那家饭馆解决。”

“这地方太寒酸了。”

“哦，还好吧，有这地方住就不错了。”

“这儿住的都是些什么人呢？”

“哦，不太清楚。上面阁楼里住了几个学生。其他的还有两三个在政府机关里做事的老光棍和一个奥德昂大剧院的退休女演员。另有一个房间也是带浴室的，住着一个被包了身的女人，她的男朋友每隔一个星期四来看她。除此之外，恐怕还有些暂住的客人。这地方很安静，适于居住。”

伊莎贝尔听了有点窘迫，被拉里瞧在了眼里并感到好笑，这一来就叫她有些气恼了。

“桌子上那本大厚书是什么书？”她问。

“哪本？噢，那是我的希腊字典。”

“你的什么来着？”她提高了嗓门问。

“你看看也没有关系，它不会咬你的。”

“你在学希腊语吗？”

“是的。”

“为什么？”

“可能是个人爱好吧。”

他说话时望着她，眼睛里带着微笑，她也冲他笑了笑。

“你能不能告诉我，来巴黎后这么长时间你都做了些什么？”

“我花大量时间看书，每天用去八至十个小时吧。另外还到巴黎大学听讲座。法国文学中重要的作品，我想自己都读遍了。现在我能看得懂拉丁文了，至少能看懂拉丁散文了，如今看拉丁文几乎跟看法文一样轻松了。当然，学希腊语是比较难的。不过，我有个非常好的老师。你来之前，我每周去他那儿学三个晚上。”

“这样做的目的何在？”

“掌握知识呗。”他笑了笑说。

“这好像不太实际。”

“也许不太实际，另一方面，也许却又是实际的。追求知识本身就是极大的乐趣。你想象不来，阅读原文版的《奥德赛》该是多么令人激动。你有一种感觉，好像一踮脚尖，伸出手就能够着星星似的。”

他起身离开椅子，像是兴奋得不能自已，在小房间里来来回回踱起了步。

“这一两个月我在看斯宾诺莎[39]的书。我不敢说自己理解得十分透彻，然而心里却充满了欢乐。就好像是乘飞机来到了高山之巅的一处辽阔的平原上，周围空无一人，空气清新得犹如芬芳的美酒，沁人心脾。你觉得自己就像是个极其富有的人。”

“你什么时候回芝加哥呢？”

“芝加哥？不知道。我没有想过这件事。”

“你不是说过，如果你两年之后还找不到你要找的东西，就改弦更张吗？”

“反正我现在是不能回去的。我刚刚迈过了一道门槛，看见一望无际的精神王国展现在我的面前，它在向我招手，我急切地要到那儿去瞧瞧。”

“你想到那里寻找什么呢？”

“寻找问题的答案。”他说完瞅了她一眼，眼神中带几分戏谑。她如若不是对他知根知底，也许会觉得他在开玩笑呢。“我想弄清楚到底有没有上帝，弄清楚为什么会有邪恶。我想知道灵魂是不朽的，还是人一死，灵魂也跟着消亡。”

伊莎贝尔倒抽了一口气。听见拉里这般说话，她觉得怪不舒服，幸亏他语调轻轻松松，跟平时说话别无二致，她这才没有将内心的窘迫表露出来。

“可是，拉里，”她微笑说，“这样的问题人类已经提出来几千年了，如果能够解答的话，肯定早已有答案了。”

拉里笑了一声。

“请别这么笑，弄得好像我在说蠢话似的。”她沉下脸说。

“恰恰相反，我认为你说得在理。但从另一方面看，假如人类提出这样的问题达数千年之久，那就证明这样的问题是很有必要提出的，以后还会继续提出来。至于说无人能解答这种问题，那是不对的。人类寻找到的答案已经超出了问题本身。许多人给出的答案十分完美。鲁斯布鲁克老人就是一例。”

“鲁斯布鲁克是谁？”

“哦，是大学里的，一个我不认识的人。”拉里轻描淡写地说。

伊莎贝尔不懂他是什么意思，但他继续往下说着。

“有些话听上去挺幼稚的。大学的莘莘学子为这种知识兴奋不已，可是一走出校门就将其抛在了脑后，因为他们不得不挣钱养家。”

“这也无可厚非。你知道，我幸亏还有点钱可以过活。如若不然，我也得跟其他人一样去挣钱了。”

“难道钱对你一点都不重要吗？”

“是的。”他微微一笑说。

“你这样读书学习，还要多长时间？”

“说不准。大概要五年十年吧。”

“以后呢？你准备把学到的知识怎么运用？”

“如果掌握了知识，就有了智慧，到时候一定会知道如何运用的。”

伊莎贝尔情绪激动地把两只纤手绞在一起，坐在椅子上的身子朝前一探。

“你完全错了，拉里。你是个美国人，这儿不是你安身立命的地方。你安身立命的地方是美国。”

“等我学成了，我会回去的。”

“可是，你会错过很多机会。美国正在经历着一个世界从来没有经历过的伟大时代，你怎么能忍心坐在这死气沉沉的地方一动不动呢？欧洲已到了穷途末路。美利坚民族是世界上最伟大、最强盛的民族。我们正在一日千里地前进。在美国，一切条件都已具备。人人有义务投身于祖国的建设之中。你忘记了自己的义务，不知道如今在美国生活是多么激动人心。你不愿回国，是不是就是说你缺乏勇气去面对摆在每一个美国人面前的重任呢？哎，我知道你也在从事着某种工作，但这是否就是逃避责任的一种方式呢？这恐怕不仅仅是貌似勤奋的偷懒吧？如果人人都像你这样逃避责任，美国会弄成什么样子呢？”

“你很尖酸刻薄，小心肝。”他笑着说，“我的回答是，并不是每个人都和我有同样的感受。大多数人都准备按部就班地过日子，这对他们而言也许是幸运的。你忘记了一点，我的求知欲跟格雷挣大钱的欲望同样强烈。难道我想花几年时间进行深造，真的就是背叛祖国吗？也许我学成以后，会有自己的贡献，国人会感到高兴呢。当然，这只是一种假设。万一我功败垂成，也不见得就比经商失败的人差到哪里去。”

“那么我呢？难道我对你一点不重要？”

“你对我非常重要。我要娶你做新娘呢。”

“什么时候？十年之内吗？”

“不，现在。越快越好。”

“用什么结婚？妈妈是无法给我嫁妆的。即便她有这个能力，她也不会给的。她觉得纵容你游手好闲是错误的。”

“我并不想接受你母亲的任何帮助。”拉里说道，“我每年有三千块的进项，在巴黎生活绰绰有余。咱们可以租一小套公寓房，雇一个用人[40]，日子会过得很滋润的，小宝贝。”

“可是，拉里，一年三千块过日子是不够用的。”

“够用肯定是够用的。很多人钱比这还少，也能过日子。”

“可是，我不愿意靠一年三千块钱过日子。我没必要这样做。”

“我在这儿生活，只用这一半的花销。”

“可这叫什么日子！”

她看了看眼前寒碜的斗室，不屑地耸了耸肩。

“过这日子，我积攒了一些钱。咱们可以上卡普里岛[41]去度蜜月，秋天再去希腊。我渴望去看看希腊。还记得吗，咱们经常说要一起周游世界的？”

“旅游我当然是愿意去的，但并非这样的游法。乘轮船，我不愿住二等舱；住宿，我不愿下榻于三等旅馆，那儿连个浴室都没有；吃饭，我不愿进廉价饭馆。”

“去年十月，我游历意大利，恰恰就是这样去的，不是玩得也挺开心么。靠每年三千块的进项，咱们完全可以把世界跑个遍。”

“可是，我还想生孩子呢，拉里。”

“这没有关系。有了孩子，咱们带他们一起去旅游。”

“你真傻。”她大笑着说，“你知道有个孩子要花多少钱吗？维奥莱特·汤姆林森去年生了个孩子，尽量省着花，还花掉了两千五百块。你知道请个保姆需要多少钱吗？”她心里想到一连串的事情，越想越情绪激动，“你一点不实际，不知道你要求我过什么样的日子。我年轻，需要过快乐的生活。我想跟其他人一样寻求欢乐，去赴宴、跳舞，去打高尔夫球和骑马。我想穿漂亮的衣服。你能想象得来，一个女孩子家穿戴不如自己的同伴，心里该是什么样的滋味？把你朋友穿厌了的旧衣服买来穿，或者别人可怜你，把一件新衣服送给你，而你千恩万谢，拉里呀，你可知道这会叫你心里是什么滋味？那时我甚至于连去一家像样的理发店做做头发也做不起。我出行可不愿乘坐电车和公共汽车，而是想开自己的汽车。你在图书馆里看书，那你让我干什么以度过漫长的一天？难道让我逛马路、看橱窗，还是坐在卢森堡博物馆的花园里留心自己的孩子不要闯祸？那样生活，咱们连个朋友都不会有的。”

“请别这样，伊莎贝尔！”他打断她的话头说道。

“不会有我以前的那类朋友。哦，不错，艾略特舅舅的朋友有时候会看他的面子请请咱们，但咱们去不成，一是因为没有体面的衣服，二是由于咱们回请不起。至于交朋友，我可不愿意认识一大群穷了吧唧、衣衫不整的人。我跟他们无共同语言，他们也跟我无话可说。我需要的是真正的生活，拉里。”说到这里，她突然感到他眼睛里有种神情，虽一如既往地温情脉脉，却微微含有一丝嘲笑的成分，“你觉得我愚蠢，是不是？你一定觉得我鼠目寸光、蛮不讲理。”

“不，并非如此。我觉得你说这些话都是很自然的。”

此时，他背对着壁炉站着。她立起身，走到他跟前，和他面对着面。

“拉里，如果你身无分文，却有一个年收入三千块的工作，我会毫不迟疑地嫁给你。我会替你烧饭、收拾床铺，不在乎自己穿什么样的衣服，什么都不会在乎，就是苦也是苦中有乐，因为我知道这只是一个时间问题，你总会有出头之日的。可是，现在这样结婚，就意味着我一辈子要过这种肮脏的猪狗不如的日子，连个盼头都没有。这就是说，我要苦熬日月，至死方休。意义何在？而你成年累月为那种连你自己都说无法解答的问题苦苦寻找答案。这真是大错特错。一个男子汉，应该去工作。人生的意义就在于此。工作才能够造福于社会。”

“依你之见，我有责任立足于芝加哥，进入亨利·马图林的公司。你是不是认为，动员我的朋友买亨利·马图林所关心的股票，就是造福于社会呢？”

“经纪人的工作是社会所必需的，是一种十分体面、光彩的谋生方式。”

“你把巴黎普通收入人群的生活形容得一塌糊涂。人们用不着上沙诺尔式女装店，仍旧可以穿得体体面面。并非所有风趣的人都住在凯旋门附近和福煦大街。事实上，住在那儿的风趣的人少之又少，因为风趣的人一般都没有多少钱。我在这儿认识许多人，有画家、作家、大学生，有法国人、英国人、美国人，形形色色的。我敢肯定，见了面，你会觉得他们比艾略特的那些乏味的侯爵夫人和傲慢的公爵夫人有意思得多。你思想敏锐，而且富于幽默感。和他们共进晚餐，虽然喝的只是普通的葡萄酒[42]，又没有一个管家和几个侍从在跟前伺候，但听他们指点江山，你会感到是一种享受。”

“别东拉西扯的，拉里。我当然会喜欢的。你也知道我并不是个势利小人。我是愿意结交风趣的人的。”

“是呀。如果你穿一身沙诺尔式女装，他们会不会觉得你气势凌人，好像是来视察贫民窟的呢？他们不自在，你恐怕也会如坐针毡的。过后，你可以告诉你的闺密爱米丽·德·蒙塔杜尔和格拉茜·德·夏托加亚尔，说你在拉丁区结识了一群放荡不羁的文人，十分好玩，除此之外你将一无所获。”

伊莎贝尔听了微微耸了耸肩。

“我敢说你讲得对。他们不是我自小所熟悉的那种人。我跟他们毫无相同之处。”

“此话从何说起？”

“还是咱们开头讲的。自从记事起，我就一直住在芝加哥。我的朋友以及我所关心的一切全在那儿。在那儿，我感到心情舒坦。那儿就是我的根，也是你的根。妈妈患病在身，永无康复之日。我即便想离开她的身边，也是做不到的。”

“这是不是说除非我回到芝加哥去，否则你就不愿嫁给我了？”

伊莎贝尔犹豫了一下。她爱拉里，真心实意想嫁给他。她对他的爱是发自于肺腑之爱。她很清楚，拉里也爱她。她坚信，一旦摊牌，拉里会软下来的。她虽然心里也有担忧，但这个险是必须要冒的。

“是的，拉里，事情就是这样。”

他取出一根火柴——一根老式的法国造硫黄火柴，划着之后会叫你的鼻孔里充满呛人的味道。他把火柴在壁板上划亮，用它点着了烟斗。随即，他从她的身旁走过，来到了一扇窗户跟前，将目光投向外边。他沉默着，没完没了地沉默着。伊莎贝尔站在原地没动，仍站在刚才面对拉里的地方，眼睛望着壁炉板上的镜子，对镜中的自己却视而不见。她的心狂跳不已，焦虑得都快透不过气来了。最后，拉里终于转过了身来。

“真希望你能明白，我提供给你的生活要比你想象的充实得多。真希望能让你知道，精神生活是多么地激动人心，那会是多么丰富的人生经历。精神追求是永无止境的，是一种无比幸福的人生道路。只有一种体验能与之相比——你乘飞机飞上蓝天，越飞越高，越飞越高，周围什么都没有，只有无边无际的太空。无涯的空间让你为之陶醉。你会产生极度的欢乐——这种欢乐，哪怕把全世界所有的权力和荣誉都给你，你也不肯交换的。前几天我读笛卡儿的书，就有这种感觉。他写得是那样流畅、优美、明晰，叫人不忍释卷！”

“可是，拉里，”伊莎贝尔不顾一切地插话说，“难道你不知道，让我干自己不感兴趣也不想感兴趣的事情是强人所难？真不知我对你说过多少遍了，我仅仅是个再普通不过的女孩，今年二十岁，再过十年就变老了，我要抓紧时间及时行乐。拉里呀拉里，我是非常爱你的。可你现在的生活意义不大，不会使你有什么前途的。为了你的前途，我也要恳求你放弃眼前的生活。拉里，活着就应该像个男子汉，应该有所担当。别人都在只争朝夕地干事业，而你却在糟蹋宝贵的年华。拉里，你要是爱我的话，就不会为了一个梦想而置我于不顾。你已经按自己的意愿生活过一段时间了，求你跟我们一起回美国吧。”

“恕我不能，亲爱的。那会叫我生不如死，等于出卖我的灵魂。”

“哎，拉里，何必用那样的口吻讲话呢？只有歇斯底里、卖弄嘴皮子的文人才说如此慷慨激昂的话。这有什么意思呢？一点意思都没有，只是一派空言。”

“它反映的恰恰是我内心的感受。”他回话时，眨巴了几下眼睛。

“你怎么可以笑呢？你可曾意识到，这是一个极其严肃的问题？咱们正站在十字路口，何去何从将会影响你我的一生。”

“这我清楚。请相信我，我是十分认真的。”

伊莎贝尔不由叹了口气。

“假如你不听我讲道理，我也就无话可说了。”

“可我并不认为你在讲道理，而是一派荒谬绝伦的胡言乱语。”

“你在说我？”如果不是心境凄凉，她一定会哈哈大笑起来的。

“可怜的拉里呀，你简直太愚蠢了，蠢得百窍不通。”

她慢慢把订婚戒指从手指上摘下来，放在掌心，用眼睛盯着它看。戒指细细的，用白金打造，上面镶一粒四四方方的红宝石，她一直视若珍宝。

“你假如爱我，就不应当使我这样不快活。”

“我的确爱你。不幸的是，有时候一个人想要做自己认为对的事情，却免不了要使别人不快活。”

她把放着红宝石戒指的手伸出来，颤抖着嘴唇挤出了一个微笑。

“给，还给你吧，拉里。”

“我用不着。你留下它做个纪念，以纪念你我的友谊，好吗？你可以把它戴在小拇指上。咱们的友谊没必要因此而中断，是不是？”

“我会永远想着你的，拉里。”

“那你就留着它。我对你的感情永不会改变。”

她迟疑了一下，然后把戒指套在了右手的小拇指上。

“太大了。”

“你可以调整一下。走，咱们去里茨酒吧喝杯酒。”

“好的。”

她感到有点意外，没想到她和拉里的关系就这么轻轻松松结束了。她没有为之伤心落泪。除了她将来不会嫁给拉里之外，其他的什么都没有改变。她简直不敢相信他们的关系已结束，已画上了句号。二人没有吵得脸红脖子粗，这反倒叫她遗憾。他们心平气和地把他们的关系做了个了断，差不多就像谈论租房子那样声色不变。她虽然觉得有些失望，同时却也掺杂着一丝半点满意的心情，因为他们表现得都十分文明。她真想知道拉里究竟是一种什么心态。可是，要想猜透拉里葫芦里卖的是什么药，历来都是很难的。他那张淡定的脸以及那双乌黑的眼就是一副面具，即便她这么一个认识他多年的人也难看得穿。她本来把帽子已经摘掉，放在了床上；现在站在镜子前面，将帽子重新戴上。

“只是感到好奇，”她一边说话，一边用手理了理头发，“你是不是早就想解除婚约了？”

“没有。”

“我觉得这对你也许会是一种解脱。”见他没有回应，她嘴角带着一丝做作的微笑转过了身去，“我准备好了。”

拉里出门后将门锁上。他把钥匙交给桌子旁坐的那个人时，那人瞅了他们几眼，目光狡狯，显得心领神会。伊莎贝尔不可能猜不到他把他们看成了什么货色。

“我敢说那家伙对我的贞操存有满肚子的怀疑。”她说。

他们乘出租车去里茨喝了杯酒，谈些无关痛痒的事，表面上看无拘无束的，就像两个天天见面的老朋友。尽管拉里天生沉默寡言，伊莎贝尔却很健谈，叽叽喳喳把话说了一大篓子。她决心不让他们中间出现沉默的局面，弄得双方无话可说。她不想使拉里觉察出她恨他。自尊心使然，她必须强作欢颜，叫对方看不出她受伤、难过的心情。过了一会儿，她提出要他送她回去。当汽车把她送到门前，下车时，她以轻快的语气对他说：

“别忘了明天跟我们一起吃午饭。”

“就是天塌下来也不会忘的。”

她侧过脸，叫他吻了一下，然后就走进了旅馆的大门[43]。

五

伊莎贝尔走进客厅，看见有几个客人在那儿喝茶。有两个是住在巴黎的美国女子，穿着非常考究，脖子上挂着珍珠项链，手上戴着钻石手镯，手指上套着价值昂贵的戒指。虽然有一个的头发染成了深红褐色，另一个的头发呈金黄色，颜色很不自然，二者看上去却出奇地相像。她们的眼睫毛都重重地涂了眉毛油，嘴唇都搽得红艳艳，脸蛋上都抹了胭脂，都有着由于刻苦修行而保持着的苗条身段，均是五官清爽、有棱有角，眼睛一刻不停地滴溜溜乱转。你不由得会想到，她们在拼命地挣扎，竭力想挽留住正在逝去的风韵。她们嗓门大、声音尖，说话一点内涵都没有，如连珠炮一般不停顿，仿佛生怕一停下来体内的机器就会发生故障，而她们也会像房屋一样轰然倒塌。在场的还有一个美国大使馆的秘书，彬彬有礼、八面玲珑，一直没有开口，因为他压根就插不进去话。再有就是一个皮肤黝黑的小个子罗马尼亚王子，点头哈腰，一副殷勤相，一双黑黑的老鼠眼善于察言观色，黑不溜秋的脸刮得净光。他时不时会跳起身为他人奉茶、点烟、端点心，厚颜无耻地献媚，甜言蜜语，极尽阿谀奉承之能事。他如此小心翼翼地恭维，是为了报答对方请他赴宴的恩情，并希望今后能获得更多的邀请。

布雷德利夫人坐在茶桌旁。为了让艾略特高兴，她违背自己的心愿特意打扮了一番，此时履行着女主人的义务，神情似平时那般平静、礼貌、淡然。至于她如何看待弟弟的客人，我就不得而知了。我和她不太熟悉，而她是个不显山不露水的人。她并不缺心眼，在外国的首都生活了那么多年，形形色色的人见了不计其数，想来能够根据生她养她的那座弗吉尼亚小镇的标准对来客做出明智的判断。看见几位来客丑态百出，恐怕她心里一定觉得相当可笑。对于客人们的风情万种也罢，忸怩作态也罢，她全然不当回事，就跟对待小说里的人物一样——书中人的悲伤和痛苦引不起她的共鸣，因为她一开始就知道小说的结局是圆满的（否则她就不会去读它了）。巴黎、罗马、北京对她的美国味没有产生什么影响，这情形就跟艾略特虔诚的天主教信仰没有影响到她坚定不移地信仰长老会宗教一样。

伊莎贝尔以她的青春、活力和活泼可爱的形象给客厅里庸俗的环境带来了一股清新的气息。她姗姗而至，犹如一个下凡的仙女。罗马尼亚王子慌不迭地站起来替她拉过一把椅子，手忙脚乱地向她献殷勤。两个美国女人尖着嗓子说了些亲热的话，把她从头到脚打量一番，观察着她穿戴的细微之处，面对她那生气勃勃的青春，心中也许产生了几分落寞。美国外交官看见伊莎贝尔的出现叫这两个女人显得姿态做作和面容憔悴，不由暗中一笑。可是，伊莎贝尔却觉得她们雍容华贵；她喜欢她们的华装丽服和昂贵的珍珠，而且还对她们的矫揉造作感到了一丝妒意。她不知道自己将来是不是也能够拥有如此仪态万方的风度。当然，那位小个子罗马尼亚人相当可笑，不过待人倒是挺殷勤的，就算他讲的那些好听的话言不由衷，听听也叫人高兴。她进来时打断的谈话现在又恢复了，而且说话人都是那么兴致勃勃，那样的自信笃定，好像她们谈的事情都是有价值的，让你会以为她们的谈吐富于理性。其谈话内容无非是她们参加过什么宴会，以及预备参加什么宴会。对于近来出现的花边新闻，她们津津乐道。她们把自己的朋友说得一无是处。谈到那些名人大姓，她们如数家珍。她们好像无人不晓，谁家的秘密都逃不过她们的眼睛。她们几乎可以一口气讲出一大堆爆料，有最时新的剧目、刚走红的服装设计师、最近才火起来的肖像画家、刚上台的首相才勾搭上的情妇。你会觉得天下没有她们不知道的事情。听得伊莎贝尔如痴如醉。她觉得，一切都是那样美妙和文明。这才是真正的生活，置身于其中给她一种心旷神怡的感觉。眼前的情景是真实的存在，眼前的环境完美无缺——房间宽敞，脚下铺着萨冯内里埃地毯，华美的镶板墙上挂着漂亮的画作，一把把座椅都是精雕细镂的作品，小柜子和茶几均为价钱不菲的镶嵌细工活，每一样东西都是精品，简直可以放在博物馆里展览。布置这个房间，一定花钱不少，但这笔钱花得值得。她以前从未注意到这儿竟如此美丽，品味如此高——拉里自称没有什么不好的旅馆里的那个寒碜的小房间，那儿的铁床和拉里坐的那把硬邦邦、别别扭扭的椅子，都还活跃在她的脑海里，形象是那样鲜明。拉里的房间空空如也，没有欢乐，只有悲哀，想起来就叫她不寒而栗。

客人散了，只剩下了伊莎贝尔、她母亲以及艾略特三个人。

“真是叫人着迷的女人。”艾略特把那两个涂脂抹粉的可怜蛋送到大门外之后，返回来说了这么一句，“她们刚来巴黎时，我就认识她们了。做梦也想不到她们竟有这般脱胎换骨的变化。咱们国家的女人之适应能力实在叫人惊叹。你简直看不出她们是美国人，而且是中西部来的。”

布雷德利夫人抬起眼，什么话也没说，只是瞅了瞅弟弟。对方善于察言观色，哪能不晓得姐姐的意思。

“可怜的路易莎，这你恐怕是做不到的。”他半讥讽半亲热地说，“不过，老天爷知道，你在过去完全有这个能力。”

布雷德利夫人听后噘了噘嘴。

“恐怕我让你觉得又失望又丢人，艾略特。不过，实话告诉你，我对自己现在的样子十分满意。”

“悉听尊便。”艾略特叽里咕噜来了一句法语。

“我跟拉里解除婚约了，我觉得应该告诉你们一声。”伊莎贝尔说道。

“啊？”艾略特叫出了声，“这给我明天请的午宴出了个难题。这么短的时间，你叫我去哪儿找人补他的缺？”

“哦，午宴他还是要来的。”

“解除了婚约他还来？这好像跟一般人的做法不太相同。”

伊莎贝尔咯咯笑了。她把目光聚焦在艾略特舅舅身上，因为她知道母亲在盯着她看，而她不想去直视母亲。

“我们没有吵架。今天下午我们俩谈了谈心，最后都觉得我们的婚约是个错误。他不想回美国，而是想留在巴黎，还说要到希腊去。”

“这是为什么？雅典可不是从事社交活动的好地方。事实上，我对希腊艺术从来就不大看在眼里。有些古希腊的艺术品倒是有那么一点颓废的魅力，还是可以吸引人眼球的。然而要说菲狄亚斯[44]的作品——看不得，看不得。”

“你看着我，伊莎贝尔！”布雷德利夫人说。

伊莎贝尔转过头来，唇边挂着淡淡的微笑，把脸朝向母亲。布雷德利夫人将她打量一番，最后什么也没说，只是哼了一声。布雷德利夫人看得出她没有哭过，神态安然、宁静。

“我觉得你解除婚约算是做对了，伊莎贝尔。”艾略特说，“我原本觉得也就凑合着吧，可心里总认为不是一桩美满的婚配。老实讲，他配不上你。看他在巴黎的所作所为就已经很清楚，他绝对不会有大的出息。凭你的容貌和社会关系，完全可以找一个比他强的对象。我认为这件事你处理得很有分寸。”

布雷德利夫人看了一眼女儿，眼神里有几分担忧。

“你不是为了我才这么做的吧，伊莎贝尔？”

伊莎贝尔断然摇了摇头。

“不，亲爱的妈妈，我这样做完全是出于我自己的原因。”

六

此时，我已从东方返回伦敦，准备在伦敦住一住。上述事件发生后大概有两个星期吧，一天上午艾略特打来了电话。听见他的声音，我并不感到奇怪，因为他有个习惯，总爱在交际季节落幕时来英国游一趟。他告诉我，布雷德利夫人和伊莎贝尔与他一起来了，说如果我傍晚六点钟能去他那儿喝杯酒，她们见到我一定会很高兴的。他们一家当然住的是克拉里奇酒店了。我下榻的地方离那儿不远，于是我便以步代车朝那儿走，先是漫步于公园巷，然后穿过梅菲尔区[45]那一条条静谧、高贵的街道，一直走到克拉里奇酒店。艾略特住的还是平时住过的那套房间，墙上镶着褐色壁板，壁板的材质跟雪茄盒的一样，陈设既典雅又豪华。服务生把我领进去时，房间里只有他一个人，布雷德利夫人和伊莎贝尔出去购物了，但是也快回来了。他把伊莎贝尔和拉里解除婚约的事情告诉了我。

对于如何行为、如何处世，艾略特自有一套看法，一套既浪漫又十分传统的看法。这俩年轻人的做法叫他颇为不安。解除婚约后的第二天，拉里不但照样来赴午宴，还没事人似的，就好像他的地位并没有改变。他仍像往常那样和颜悦色、彬彬有礼，还是那样安静和快活。对待伊莎贝尔，他也是一如既往，仍是那般遗情缱绻。他似乎没有感到落魄，没有情绪低落，也没有哀伤。伊莎贝尔亦没有精神低迷的迹象，而是一脸的快活，笑声朗朗，高高兴兴地插科打诨，仿佛并不曾刚刚做出了一项有关自己一生的重大、痛切的决定。艾略特如坠五里雾中，一下子摸不着头脑了。那俩年轻人说话的只言片语传进了他的耳朵，于是他得知他们无意取消以前商量好的约会。他瞅了个机会，把此事和姐姐谈了谈。

“这不成体统。”他说，“他们不能够仍旧像订婚一样，一块儿到处跑，拉里真的应该懂得一点进退。再说，这样会毁掉伊莎贝尔的机会。福瑟林厄姆，就是英国大使馆的那个小伙子很明显看上了伊莎贝尔，他可是既有钱又有社会地位。假如他知道伊莎贝尔解除了婚约，并向她伸出橄榄枝，那我一点都不会感到奇怪。依我看，你应该跟伊莎贝尔好好谈谈。”

“亲爱的，伊莎贝尔是二十岁的人了，她有套办法能够委婉地告诉你不要管她的事情。这使我一直很难对付。”

“那么，就都怪你管教太不得当了，路易莎。话又说回来，她的终身大事也是你分内的事。”

“在这一点上，你和她有着明显的分歧。”

“你简直叫我无法容忍，路易莎。”

“我可怜的艾略特，假如你有个已经长大成人的女儿，你会发现她比一匹乱尥蹶子的小马还难管。你还想知道她心里是怎么想的……算了吧，还是装糊涂的好，装作一个头脑简单、什么都不懂的老糊涂虫——你在她眼里八成就是这么个样子。”

“可你不是跟她谈过这件事了么？”

“我打算谈来着。她却冲我哈哈大笑，说实在没有什么可谈的。”

“她难过吗？”

“我也不知道，只知道她吃饭吃得香，睡觉也睡得香，睡起觉就像个小孩子一样。”

“哼，你记住我的话，如果你听任他们这样继续下去，总有一天他们会溜掉，招呼也不打就结婚的。”

布雷德利夫人忍不住笑了。

“你尽管可以放心——他们现在在这么一个国家里呢，不正常的男女关系有着种种方便，结婚却会遇到重重障碍。”

“这没什么不好的。结婚是严肃的事情，关乎家庭的安全和国家的稳定。婚外情不仅要容忍，还应该得到认可，唯有如此，才能保障婚姻的威严。嫖娼卖淫嘛，我可怜的路易莎……”

“够啦，艾略特！”布雷德利夫人打断了他的话，“你对不正常男女关系的社会价值和道德价值所发表的奇谈怪论我不感兴趣。”

就在这时，艾略特提出了一项计划，可以切断伊莎贝尔和拉里藕断丝连的关系——这种关系叫他厌恶，不符合他的人生观。巴黎的社交季节已接近尾声。上流社会的人们都在准备到海滨度假地去，或者到多维尔[46]去，然后各自回祖传的城堡消夏——那些城堡分布于都兰、安茹或者布列塔尼。艾略特通常都是在六月底去伦敦的，可是由于他的家庭观念很强，对姐姐以及伊莎贝尔的感情又是那么诚挚，所以他准备牺牲自己的利益，就是在有头有脸的人都走光的情况下，只要姐姐她们俩想留在巴黎，他也会留下相陪。不过，他发现了一种两全其美的途径，既能够为他人考虑，又方便了自己。他向布雷德利夫人建议，他们三人应该立刻启程到伦敦去。那儿的社交季节正处在高潮，可以参加新的有趣的活动，结交新的朋友，这会转移伊莎贝尔的注意力，使她不再去想她那不幸的遭遇。根据报纸上的报道，专治布雷德利夫人这种病的那位出了名的医生恰好正在英国的首都，找他治病可以成为他们匆匆离开巴黎的一种合理的说法，即便伊莎贝尔不情愿，也会说不出口的。布雷德利夫人同意了这个计划。伊莎贝尔的表现叫她感到困惑。她实在弄不清自己的女儿，不知女儿是不是真的像表面那样一点不在乎，还是心里痛苦、气愤或者伤心，却装出一副英雄相，把打掉的牙往肚子里咽。她只能同意艾略特的说法——结识新的人，游历新的地方，对伊莎贝尔自有好处。

接下来，艾略特打了一通电话。此时的伊莎贝尔正和拉里一同逛凡尔赛宫。等到她回来，艾略特把情况告诉了她，说他已经约好带她的母亲去那位名医处看病，约定的时间是三天后，还说在克拉里奇酒店已订好了房间，他们一家后天便要启程到伦敦去。当艾略特颇有得色地给伊莎贝尔讲述出行计划时，布雷德利夫人留意观察女儿的反应，却见她神色不动。

“啊，亲爱的妈妈，很高兴你能够去找那个医生看病。”伊莎贝尔说道，语调仍像往常那样急火火的，像喘不过气似的，“这个机会当然是不容错过的。到伦敦去一定是段非凡的经历。在那儿待多长时间呢？”

“急着返回巴黎是毫无意义的，”艾略特说，“因为一个星期之内，这里的人都要走光了。我要你们跟我在克拉里奇酒店住完这个社交季节。七月份总会有些别开生面的舞会的，当然还有温布尔登网球公开赛喽。之后，还有古德伍德公园附近举行的赛马会和考斯的赛船。我敢说，埃林厄姆家一定会欢迎咱们坐他们的游艇去考斯看赛船的，而班托克家历来都会在古德伍德赛马时举办一场规模宏大的宴会。”

伊莎贝尔看上去很高兴，布雷德利夫人这才松了口气。伊莎贝尔好像根本没有把拉里往心里放。

艾略特刚给我把情况介绍完，那一对母女就回来了。没见她们的面，已经有超过一年半的时间了。布雷德利夫人比以前瘦了些，脸色也比以前苍白了，倦容满面，气色极差。而伊莎贝尔却容光焕发，脸蛋红扑扑的，一头深褐色的头发，淡褐色的眼睛神采奕奕，肤如凝脂，给人以青春荡漾的印象，乐乐呵呵的，好像活着就是一种幸福。看到她，你心里会不由得充满喜悦，笑出声来。我甚至产生了一个十分荒唐的想法，觉得她就像一枚金黄的熟透了的梨子，香甜可口，只等你来吃呢。她身上散发出阵阵暖意，让你觉得只要伸出手就能感受到温馨。与上次见到她时相比，她看上去高了些，不知道是因为穿了高跟鞋的缘故，还是因为那个聪明的裁缝把她的衣服裁剪得好，遮住了她年轻丰满的躯体，使她的个头显高了些。她的一举一动都显示出自小便习惯于户外运动的女孩子的那种潇洒自如。总之，从性的角度看，她已经出落成了一个非常诱人的年轻女子。我要是她母亲的话，会认为她已经到嫁人的时候了。

我很高兴现在有了机会，总算可以稍稍报答一下布雷德利夫人对我的招待了。我邀请他们三个晚上一块儿去看戏，还为他们三人安排了一次午宴。

“干得好，你约的正是时候，亲爱的老伙计。”艾略特说，“我已经通知了一些朋友，说我们到了伦敦。一两天之内，这个季节我们的日程恐怕就会被排得满满的了。”

听他的话音，像是说他们没有时间陪我这样的人。我只好付之一笑。艾略特看了我一眼，眼神里带着几分傲慢。

“不过，我们每天下午六点钟左右一般都在酒店里，你来我们会很高兴的。”他说话的语气很委婉，意思却很明确——我只不过是个小作家，地位低下。

殊不知兔子急了也会咬人的。

“你应该和圣奥尔弗德家联系一下，”我话中有话地说，“听说他们想卖掉家中的那幅康斯特布尔[47]画的《索尔兹伯里大教堂[48]》。”

“我眼下不想买什么画。”

“这我知道，但我觉得你可以帮他们处理掉嘛。”

艾略特的眼睛里透出了一丝冷冷的光。

“亲爱的老伙计，英国人是一个伟大的民族，可是他们没有绘画的天赋，永远也不会有的。我对英国画派不感兴趣。”

七

这以后的四个星期中，我很少见到艾略特和布雷德利夫人母女。他带着她们四处亮相，去苏塞克斯郡的一个大户人家度一个周末，再到威尔特郡一户更气派的人家过上一个周末。他还带她们坐在皇家包厢作为温莎王室一个年轻公主的客人看歌剧；带她们和大人物们一起共进午餐和晚餐。伊莎贝尔参加了好几次舞会。他在克拉里奇酒店款待了一批批的客人，那些人的名字次日便出现在了报纸上显眼的位置。他还在吉罗酒店和使馆大设晚宴招待四方贵宾。事实上，他为了让伊莎贝尔高兴，该做的都做了——如果是一个涉世不太深的女孩，见了这纸醉金迷、高贵典雅的场面，免不了要感到眼花缭乱的。他可以自诩说他没有一点私心，费尽千辛万苦全都是为了伊莎贝尔，想让她忘掉爱情上的不幸。可我觉得他恐怕别有一番用意，是想让姐姐亲眼看看他跟那些地位高贵的人以及炙手可热的人关系是多么熟稔，从中获得巨大的满足感。他在待人接客方面可称可赞，热衷于展现自己的交际手腕。

他举办的宴会我去参加过一两次，也时常在下午六点钟的时候去克拉里奇酒店他们的房间里坐坐。我发现伊莎贝尔身边老围着一群小伙子，有身材魁梧、衣着漂亮的御林军军官，也有文质彬彬、衣着不太漂亮的外交部官员。一次这样的场合，伊莎贝尔把我拉到了一边。

“我想问你点事。”她说，“你可记得那天傍晚咱们俩去药店喝冰淇淋苏打水的事吗？”

“记得清清楚楚。”

“那次你对我很好，对我很有帮助。能不能再帮我一次呢？”

“愿意效力。”

“我想和你说点事。咱们哪天一起吃顿午饭好吗？”

“你说哪一天都行。”

“找个清静一点的地方。”

“乘车到汉普顿宫，在那儿吃午饭怎么样？花园里正是花开得盛的时候，还可以参观一下伊丽莎白女王的寝室。”

我的建议很合乎她的心意，于是我们约定了日期。可是到了那一天，本来晴暖的天气突然变了脸，空中阴云密布，淅淅沥沥下起了小雨。我打电话给她，问她愿意不愿意在城里吃饭。

“这下子，咱们没法坐在花园里聊天了，室内也黑乎乎的，那些画是看不清的。”我说道。

“花园我去得多了，大师的名画我也看腻烦了。还是按计划去吧。”

“那好吧。”

我去接她，然后我们就乘汽车走了。我知道一家小旅馆，里边提供的饭菜还可以，于是我们便直接去了那里。路上，伊莎贝尔跟平时一样健谈，讲述着她所参加过的宴会以及所遇到的人。她玩得很开心。可是，她对自己所结交的形形色色的人却缺乏好评，认为他们荒唐可笑，这让我觉得她有主见、眼光独到。下雨天，餐厅里没人，只有我们两个吃客。这家旅馆以家常的英国菜最拿手，所以我们点了一块好羊腿，配菜是绿豌豆和新马铃薯，还有用深盘子烘焙的苹果馅饼，上面抹一些德文郡奶油。我们还喝了一大杯啤酒，叫这顿午餐颇显丰盛。饭后，我建议去空咖啡室坐坐，那儿有扶手椅，比较舒服。咖啡室里寒气袭人，不过壁炉里有煤和木柴，于是我擦一根火柴将其点着。火焰让这个阴冷的房间有了宜人的生气。

“言归正传吧，”我说，“把你想对我说的话讲一讲吧。”

“要说的跟上次一样，”她笑嘻嘻地说，“还是拉里。”

“我猜就是这样的。”

“你一定也知道我们解除了婚约。”

“艾略特跟我讲了。”

“妈妈松了口气，而舅舅十分开心。”

说到这里，她犹豫了一下，然后就切入正题，把她和拉里的那场谈话讲述了一遍。关于那场谈话，我已向读者进行了如实的陈述。读者也许会感到奇怪：她为什么会向一个自己了解不深的人倾吐心事呢？我见她也只不过有十来次，除了药店的那次接触，我们从未单独交谈过。其实，我对此并不感到意外。就这一点而论，恐怕所有的作家都有体会——人们不愿随便吐露心事，却愿意向作家敞开心扉。原因不得而知。也许是他们看了某个作家的一两本书，便觉得跟他亲密无间了，要不就是他们将自己戏剧化了，自认为是小说里的主人公，因此愿意像他杜撰的那些人物一样对他推心置腹。还有，我觉得伊莎贝尔认为我喜欢拉里和她，认为他们的青春令我动了恻隐之心，同情他们不幸的境况。她不能指望艾略特有耐心听她倾诉。拉里有过步入社会的绝佳机会，却被他白白放弃了——对于这样的一个年轻人，艾略特是不愿浪费自己的时间的。她母亲也帮助不了她。布雷德利夫人有着自己的处世原则和做事标准。根据她的做事标准，一个人要想在这个世界站住脚跟，就应该按常规行事，而非拒绝听别人的劝告，去做一些不牢靠的事情。她的处世原则使她坚信：一个男人有责任去一家公司工作，靠自身的聪明才智积累一笔财富，按照符合自己地位的生活标准养家糊口，使儿子们受到适当教育，让他们长大后能体面地生活，自己死后能叫妻子过上衣食无忧的日子。

伊莎贝尔记性好，把那次长谈中的许多细节都记得一清二楚。我默默地听她娓娓道来，一直听到最后。中间，她仅仅中断了一次，问了我一个问题。

“勒伊斯达尔是什么人？”

“勒伊斯达尔？他是荷兰的一个风景画家。怎么啦？”

她说拉里在谈话中提到了此人。根据拉里的说法，勒伊斯达尔至少对他关心的问题找到了一个答案。当时，伊莎贝尔曾问此人是谁，拉里的回答却轻描淡写。伊莎贝尔把拉里的回答对我重复了一遍。

“你觉得他是什么意思呢？”

我忽然若有所悟。

“你看他会不会说的是鲁斯布鲁克？”

“也许是吧。他是什么人？”

“是一个生活在十四世纪的佛兰芒神秘主义者。”

“噢，原来如此。”伊莎贝尔有点失望地说。

这一细节对伊莎贝尔倒没有什么，对我却有所启示。我总算找到了一点线索，有益于把握拉里的思想脉络。我一边注意听她讲述，一边琢磨着拉里提及此人究竟意味着什么。我不愿过度解读此事，因为拉里当时提到那位狂热的精神导师，很可能仅仅是借他以引证自己的观点。也许其中自有深意，伊莎贝尔没听出来罢了。拉里回答她的提问时，说鲁斯布鲁克是学校里的一个人，他并不认识，这显然是不想叫伊莎贝尔再追问下去。

“此事你怎么看？”伊莎贝尔讲述完之后问我。

我想了想，然后才说道：

“你还记得他说过自己要逛大街吗？假如告诉你的那些话属实，那么，这种‘逛大街’就是漫长而艰苦的过程了。”

“我敢肯定他说的是实话。但你不觉得他如果把这么大的精力都花在有意义的工作上，就能有可观的收入吗？”

“有些人生性就是那样古怪。一些罪犯苦心经营，机关算尽，结果锒铛入狱，可一出来他们又故态复萌，到头来还是吃牢饭。以他们的勤奋、聪明、意志和耐心，如果干正当的营生，完全可以招财进宝，在社会上占据重要的位置。可是，江山易改，本性难移。他们就喜欢作奸犯科。”

“可怜的拉里。”她咯咯笑了起来，“你不是在说他学习希腊语，目的是为了抢银行吧？”

我也笑了。

“不，我不是这个意思。我是想说有些人做事像走火入魔，不能够自已，不达目的誓不罢休。为了满足内心的渴望，他们什么都可以牺牲。”

“连爱他们的人都可以拿来作为牺牲品？”

“哦，是这么回事。”

“这不明明是自私的表现嘛。除此之外，还会是什么呢？”

“我也弄不清。”我笑笑说。

“拉里学习僵死的语言能有什么用处？”

“有些人追求知识没有功利目的。说来这种欲望也没什么可指责的。”

“学了知识却不打算利用，那有什么意义呢？”

“他的情况也许就是这样的。学习知识也许仅仅是为了心理上的满足，就跟艺术家能创造一件艺术品而感到心里充实一样。或者将其视为阶梯，以后谋求长足的发展。”

“如果他渴望追求知识，那他从战场归来时，为什么不上大学呢？纳尔逊医生和我妈妈就是这样劝他的。”

“我在芝加哥时跟他谈过。学位对他没有用处。我有一种感觉，认为他对自己的目标是胸有成竹的，他觉得上大学实现不了自己的目标。要知道，在求知的道路上，有独行者，也有结伴而行的人。我认为拉里这种人宁愿走自己的独木桥，也不愿走别人的阳光道。”

“记得有一次我问他想不想写作。他付之一笑，说他没有素材可写。”

“若论不情愿写作，那是我所听到过的最站不住脚的理由。”我笑了笑说。

伊莎贝尔动了动身子，显得有点不耐烦。她没心听我说笑，哪怕是最轻松的调侃也不愿听。

“他成了今天这种样子，实在叫人费解。战争爆发前，他跟别的人是没有什么两样的。说出来你也不会相信——他网球打得很好，打高尔夫球也是一把好手。大家干什么，他也干什么，完全是个很正常的孩子。那样的孩子将来不可能不成长为一个正正常常的男子汉。你是个小说家嘛，应该能够解释得清楚。”

“人性极其复杂，我才疏学浅，怎么能解释得清呢？”

“今天我约你来，就是想听听你的见解。”她没理会我的话，自顾自地说道。

“你是不是感到不开心？”

“不，不能说是不开心。拉里不在跟前，我也挺好的。和他在一起，我老觉得自己很软弱。现在我只感到有些不舒服，就好像数月没骑马，这次却骑马跑了很远的路，浑身发硬。这不是那种疼痛感，也并非忍受不了，但是却在折磨着你。我终究会挺过去的。我所无法容忍的是，拉里把他的生活搞得一团糟。”

“也许并非如此。他踏上了一条漫长、艰辛的道路，踽踽而行，但最终他会找到自己所追求的东西的。”

“那是什么呢？”

“你难道没有想到过？从他告诉你的那些话看来，他的意思已经很明显了。他要找的是上帝。”

“上帝！”她叫出了声。可是，她这一句是惊叹语，表达的是意外和难以相信的心情。我们用了同一字眼，但是，意义却完全两样，因此而产生了一种喜剧效果，使得我们都笑了起来。但是，伊莎贝尔立刻又严肃起来。我觉得她的整个表情里带有一种恐惧。“你怎么会想到这个？”

“我只是猜想罢了。你不是要我谈谈自己作为一个小说家的看法嘛。可惜你并不了解，在战争中究竟是什么样的经历深深触动了他。我认为他是突然经受了某种打击，一种出乎他意料之外的打击。依我看，不管他发生了什么事情，反正他因此而感到人生无常，也因此而感到痛苦。他相信总会有一种救世良方，使这个世界摆脱罪恶和痛苦。”

我看得出伊莎贝尔不喜欢我把话头转到这上面，这使得她忐忑不安。

“这恐怕有点太不正常了吧？应该以现实的眼光看待问题才对。既然来到这个世上，就应该想着把日子过好。”

“也许你是对的。”

“老实说，我只是一个普通女孩，一个再普通不过的女孩。我只想把日子过得开心一些。”

“看来你们俩在性情上完全不般配。在结婚之前能发现这一点是非常好的。”

“我想结婚生孩子，生活得……”

“仁慈的上帝很高兴为你安排这样的生活。”我打断她的话，笑着说道。

“哦，这样的生活没有什么不好的，是不是？这是一种愉快的生活，叫我心满意足。”

“你们就像两个朋友要一起去度假期，可是，一个要爬格陵兰的雪山，另一个要到印度的珊瑚礁上去钓鱼。这显然是行不通的。”

“不管怎么说，我去格陵兰爬雪山，说不定能获得一件海豹皮大衣，至于在印度的珊瑚礁上能不能钓到鱼，恐怕就很值得怀疑了。”

“那得等着看了。”

“你为什么这样说呢？”她微微皱了皱眉头问道，“一直以来，你好像说话喜欢留半句。我当然心里有数，知道自己并非唱主角的。唱主角的是拉里。他是个理想主义者，怀揣最美丽的梦想，即便是空梦一场，也会叫追梦人心旷神怡。我的角色是个唯利是图、庸俗不堪的小人。人们一般是不会同情这种人的，对不对？但请别忘了，吃亏的是我。拉里会昂首前行，梦游彩云间，让我跟在后边苦熬岁月。我所需要的是正常的生活。”

“我哪能忘了呢。多年前，当我还年轻的时候，我认识一个医生，医术不错，但他并不开业行医，却经年泡在大英博物馆的图书馆里，隔上一段时间就写出一本厚书来，既不像科学书也不像哲学书，由于没人看，只好自费印刷。离开人世之前，他写了四五本这样的书，没有任何价值。他有个儿子想进军界，可他没有钱送儿子进桑赫斯特军事学院学习，那孩子只好报名入伍，后来战死于疆场。他还有个女儿，长得很漂亮，叫我很是着迷。她是个演戏的，却没有演戏的天赋，只好跟着二流剧团跑江湖，在戏里边演演配角，挣的钱少得可怜。他的妻子操劳多年，干的是牛马活，身体完全崩溃了，女儿只好回家照料她，代替她做她已无力支撑的繁重的家务活。这样的日子苦难接连不断，浪费了大好光阴，最后一无所得。当你决定偏离众人所走的道路，另辟蹊径时，就等于是一场赌博。标新立异者为数不少，成功者寥寥无几。”

“我的决定，妈妈和艾略特舅舅是赞成的。你呢？”

“亲爱的，我怎么看对你有什么关系呢？我对你几乎可以说是个陌生的人。”

“我把你看作是一个不偏不倚的观察者。”她嫣然一笑说，“我还是想得到你的认可的。你觉得我这样做对不对？”

“为了你自己，你算是做对了。”我回答时，深信她不会听出我话中有话。

“那我为什么总觉得良心不安呢？”

“是吗？”

她点点头。她嘴边仍挂着微笑，但那微笑中含着几分悲伤。

“我知道这是合乎常理的。任何有理性的人，都会认为这是我唯一可行的路。不管是从实际情况的角度看，从人情世故的角度看，从道德规范的角度看，抑或是以是非的标准衡量，我的决定都是理所应当的。然而，在我的内心深处，我却有一种惴惴不安的感觉，觉得我如果对拉里好一些，少几分斤斤计较，少几分自私，多一些高尚，我就会和他结婚，过他的那种生活。如果我真的爱他，就会淡视世俗利益。”

“也可以把话倒过来说——如果他真的爱你，他就会毫不犹豫地按你的意思行事了。”

“我也这么想过。可这是行不通的。我觉得与男性相比，女性天生更富于自我牺牲的精神。”她说完嘻嘻一笑，“就像路得到异乡谋生时那样[49]。”

“那你为什么不试一下呢？”

我们的谈话一直是在很轻松的气氛中进行的，语气随随便便的，仿佛在谈论一个双方都认识的熟人，却对那个熟人并不是特别关心在意。伊莎贝尔甚至在向我陈述她跟拉里的那次谈话时，也显得乐呵呵的，时不时还加一些幽默的话语进去，就好像并不想让我把她的话太当真似的。可是现在听我这么一问，她的脸色变了。

“我怕呀。”

我们俩沉默了一会儿，谁都没有吱声。我的脊梁骨起了一阵凉意——每当遇到深刻、真实的感情问题时，我都会有这种奇怪的反应。我觉得这是一个可怕的时刻，一个震撼灵魂的时刻。

“你非常爱他吗？”末了，我问了她这么一句。

“我不知道。我对他很不耐烦，生他的气，但是却渴望和他在一起。”

说到这里，我们又沉默了下来。我真不知道再说什么好。

我们坐的咖啡室面积很小，厚厚的花边窗帘遮住了外面的光线。墙上糊着黄颜色的大理石花纹壁纸，挂着几幅陈旧的游猎图。再加上几件红木家具、寒碜的皮椅和一股霉味，会叫人莫名其妙地联想到狄更斯小说里的咖啡室。我用拨火棍拨了拨壁炉里的火，又添了些煤。这时，伊莎贝尔突然开了口。

“当时，我以为向他摊了牌，他就会服输，因为我知道他是很软弱的。”

“软弱？”我叫出了声，“你怎么会有这种想法？他这种人一旦决定走自己的路，就会义无反顾，根本不理会亲友的反对之声。”

“过去只要我叫他做什么，他就做什么。我能够轻而易举地指挥他。不管干什么事情，他都屈居别人之下，跟在别人的后边转。”

我点着一根烟，吐了个烟圈，看着那烟圈越变越大，最后消失在空气里。

“妈妈和艾略特舅舅认为我绝对不该在解除婚约后还跟着他到处乱跑，像没事人似的。而我觉得这并没有什么大不了的。我一直心怀希望，指望着拉里最终会服输。我不相信，当他那死脑袋瓜意识到我讲的话算数时，他会不让步。”说到此处，她停顿了一下，然后冲我一笑，样子又顽皮又狡黠，“我告诉你一件事情，你不会感到吃惊吧？”

“我想不会的。”

“在我们决定来伦敦之后，我去见了拉里，请他和我一道度过在巴黎的最后一个晚上。当我把此事告诉家里人时，艾略特舅舅说这非常不得体，妈妈则说没这个必要，意思就是她完全不赞成。艾略特舅舅问我究竟想干什么，我说只不过和拉里在一起吃顿饭，然后去夜总会看看。他建议妈妈禁止我去。于是妈妈对我说：‘如果我禁止你去，你会听吗？’我回答说：‘亲爱的妈妈，我不会听的。’她接下来说：‘我猜着你就不会听。既然如此，我禁止你去，好像意义就不大了。’”

“你母亲像是个很有头脑的人。”

“我敢说很少有事情能逃过她的眼睛。拉里来接我时，我到她房间里跟她说再见。当时，我稍微打扮了一下。你知道，在巴黎非得如此不可，不然的话看上去就像光着身子。她看见我身上穿的那身衣服时，把我从头到脚扫了几眼，弄得我局促不安。我怀疑她有一双慧眼，看穿了我的心思。不过，她什么也没有说，只是吻了我一下，说她希望我玩得开心。”

“你有什么心思？”

伊莎贝尔迟疑地望着我，好像决定不了是不是对我应该再坦诚一些。

“我当时感到自己看上去还是挺不错的，觉得那是我的最后一次机会了。拉里在马克西姆饭店预订了一张桌子。我们大快朵颐，吃了很多美味，都是我特别喜欢吃的，还喝了香槟酒。我们海阔天空地谈着——至少我是这样的，引得拉里哈哈大笑。我就喜欢他这一点——一听我说话，他就开心得不得了。然后，我们俩就跳舞，跳够了便跑到马德里堡玩。在那儿碰见几个熟人，大家一起碰杯把盏，喝了些香槟酒。后来，我们又去了金合欢歌舞厅。拉里的舞跳得很棒，我们俩配合默契。大厅里很热，再加上音乐声和酒劲，我感到晕晕乎乎的，心里有些躁动不安。跳舞时，我和拉里脸贴着脸。我知道他想得到我。老天爷清楚，我也想得到他。我心生一计。其实那种想法早就藏在我的心里了。我觉得应该带他回酒店。到了那里，就不可避免地会出现一些插曲。”

“我敢肯定，你这样说是很含蓄的了。”

“我的房间距离艾略特舅舅的房间以及妈妈的房间都隔着一段路，因此我认为没有危险。等我们回到美国之后，我想我可以写信告诉拉里，就说我怀孕了。那时他就只好回去和我结婚了。我敢说把他留在美国并不难，特别是有妈妈患病在身这个理由。我当时心里嘀咕：‘我真蠢，怎么以前没想到这一计。这样一来，所有的问题都会迎刃而解的。’在歌舞厅里，音乐停下来时，我仍依偎在他的怀里。后来我说时间晚了，明天中午我们还要赶火车呢，最好回去吧。我们坐进了一辆出租车。我紧靠在他身上，他用胳膊搂紧我，吻了吻我。他吻了又吻，吻了又吻——啊，那感觉真好。好像没多大一会儿，出租车就停在了酒店门前。拉里付了车费。这时只听他说：‘等会儿我走路回去。’汽车绝尘而去，我伸出胳膊搂紧他的脖子说：‘进去再喝一杯怎么样？’他回答说：‘恭敬不如从命。’他揿了门铃，大门打开了。待我们进了大厅，他把电灯扭亮。我看看他的眼睛——那双眼睛充满了信任，那样诚实，那样天真无邪。显而易见，他丝毫没有觉察到我为他设了个圈套。我觉得自己不能对他玩如此卑鄙的花招，这就像用糖果欺骗一个小孩一样。你猜我后来是怎么处理的？我对他说：‘哦，也许你还是别上去了的好。妈妈今晚不太舒服。如果她睡着了，我不愿把她吵醒。晚安！’我仰起脸让他吻了吻，然后把他推出了门。这就是结局。”

“你感到遗憾吗？”我问。

“既不高兴，也不遗憾。我只是身不由己罢了。我那样做，并非出自我的意愿，而是有一种力量左右了我，驱使着我行事。”她莞尔一笑，“也许你会称之为良心发现吧。”

“我想你可以这样说。”

“那么，我的良心就只好自食其果了。我相信，它以后会倍加小心的。”

我们的谈话实际上就这样结束了。能敞开心扉跟人交谈，这对伊莎贝尔多少是一种安慰。而我帮不上忙，只能听她讲讲而已。我觉得自己有愧于她的信任，想找几句话安慰安慰她。

“要知道，一旦坠入爱河，”我说道，“你会觉得不可自拔，陷入深深的苦恼之中，好像永无摆脱之日。可是，看看大海，你就会心有所悟的。”

“此话怎讲？”她笑着问。

“哦，爱情就像一个很差劲的水手，一旦航行，它便痛苦不堪。可是，如果你抵达大西洋彼岸，跟拉里隔海相望，你会意外地发现启航前那种无法忍受的痛苦突然变得微不足道了。”

“这是你的经验之谈吗？”

“这是一个历尽沧桑的人的经验之谈。一旦情场失意，陷入痛苦之中时，我就立刻乘船远航。”

雨仍在淅淅沥沥下个不停。我们觉得就是不去参观汉普顿宫的那些皇家宫殿，甚至不去看伊丽莎白女王的寝室，伊莎贝尔照样能够活下去，于是我们乘车返回了伦敦城。这以后，我又见过伊莎贝尔两三次面，但都有他人在场。等到在伦敦住了一段时间后，我便启程到蒂罗尔[50]去了。

第三章

一

这以后，有十年的时间我再也没有见过伊莎贝尔和拉里。艾略特我倒是经常见，而且由于某种原因（容我以后向诸位交代）见的次数更多了。从他的嘴里，时不时会听到一些伊莎贝尔的情况。可是关于拉里，他不能提供任何信息。

“根据我了解的情况，他仍住在巴黎，只是不太可能碰上他的面。我们的社交圈子是不一样的。”后边的一句说出来时，他的语气里透出一股自豪感，“他沉沦到今天这种样子，叫人不胜伤感。论出身，他是相当不错的。假如他听我的话，我敢说我可以让他有所作为的。不管怎么说，伊莎贝尔摆脱他，算是吉星高照了。”

我跟艾略特有所不同，并非只跟一定圈子里的人打交道。在巴黎，我有一些熟人，在艾略特看来登不了大雅之堂。我虽然时常经过巴黎，但是待的时间都不太长。我曾经问过一两位熟人是否见过拉里，有没有他的消息。有几个熟人跟拉里是认识的，但没有一个和他是深交，于是无人了解他的近况。我去他常吃晚饭的那家餐馆打听消息，却发现他已经好久不去了，餐馆里的人说他可能搬走了。在附近居民常去的蒙巴纳斯林荫道上的那些咖啡馆，我也没有发现他的踪迹。

在伊莎贝尔离开巴黎之后，他原打算去希腊，后来放弃了。当时的实际情况，他多年以后才亲口告诉了我。不过，为了把事情尽量按照时间顺序排列，读起来方便些，我还是在此处对诸位讲一讲吧。他整个夏天都住在巴黎，苦读不休，直至深秋。

“那时我觉得需要放下书本，休息休息。”他说道，“我每天看八至十个小时的书，已有两年的时间了。于是，我就去了一座煤矿找活干。”

“你去哪里啦？”我失声叫道。

他见我一脸的惊讶，不由哈哈笑了。

“我认为干几个月的体力活对我有好处。我有一种感觉，干体力活能叫我理清思绪，使心情恢复平静。”

我没有吱声。我真不清楚，这是他迈出这出乎人意料之外的一步的唯一原因，还是与伊莎贝尔拒绝嫁给他也有关系。实际上，我也不知道他爱伊莎贝尔究竟有多深。大多数人在恋爱的时候会想出各种理由说服自己，认为按自己的心愿做事是合情合理的。天下婚姻多悲剧，恐怕这就是症结了。这情况就像有些人将自己的事情交给一个骗子去做一样——他们明明知道此人是骗子，却跟他关系很好，于是就不愿意相信他行骗会对朋友下手；他们坚信，他虽然对别人居心叵测，对自己决不会如此。拉里不肯为了伊莎贝尔牺牲自己心仪的生活，其意志相当坚定，可是失掉伊莎贝尔却又给他带来了痛苦，想不到竟如此难以忍受。这可能就是我们通常所说的“鱼和熊掌不可兼得”。

“哦，你继续讲。”我说道。

“我把书和衣服放在两只箱子里，交给美国运通公司保管。然后把一套替换的衣服和一些内衣打了个包，就动身了。我的希腊语教师有个妹妹嫁给了兰斯附近一座煤矿的经理，便写了一封信介绍我去见他。你知道兰斯吧？”

“不知道。”

“在法国北部，离比利时边界不远。我下榻于车站旅馆，在兰斯只待了一个晚上，次日就乘坐当地的火车去了煤矿。你去过矿区吗？”

“在英国去过。”

反正都差不多吧。那儿有煤矿，有经理的房子，还有两层高的矿工小屋，一排一排的，千篇一律，完全是一种模样，单调得让你的心直朝下沉。教堂是新建的，样子很难看。另外，街上还有几家酒吧间。我到达矿区时，天气阴冷，空中飘着毛毛细雨。我找到经理的办公室，把信交给了他。经理是个矮胖子，两颊红红的，看上去像是个贪嘴的人。矿上正缺工人，因为许多矿工都死在了战场上。有不少波兰人在此处打工，大概有两三百人吧。经理问了我一两个问题。他一听我是个美国人，好像觉得来头有些蹊跷。不过，他的小舅子把我夸成了一朵花，他也就乐于雇用我了。他要给我一个地面上的工作，可我说自己想下井。他说如果不习惯，在井下会吃不消的。我说自己已有心理准备。末了，他叫我给一个矿工当帮手。其实，那是童工干的活，只是眼下童工太少，不够用罢了。这位经理是个挺不错的人。他问我找到住处了没有，我说还没有找到。他便拿过一张纸写了个地址，说按这个地址找去，会有一位家庭主妇给我安排睡觉的地方的。那是个寡妇，丈夫是矿工，死于战火之中，她有两个儿子在矿上工作。

我拿起包袱，就告辞了。找到那户人家后，开门的是一个瘦高个女人，头发花白，有一双乌黑的大眼睛。她五官端正，年轻时一定颇有姿色。如果不是因为少了两颗门牙，就是现在也不一定会难看，会如此憔悴。她告诉我，说没有空房间了，但一个波兰人租下的房间里有两张床，我可以睡那张空床。楼上有两个房间，她的两个儿子住一间，她住另一间。她领我看的那个房间在楼下，可能以前是做客厅用的。我倒是想单独住一个房间，但又觉得还是别多事得好。外边毛毛细雨下个不停，雨势有所加大，而我已全身湿透。我不愿再到别处找房子，把自己浇成个落汤鸡。所以我说挺合适的，便住了下来。他们把厨房当作客厅使用，里边放着两把摇摇晃晃的扶手椅。院子里有个贮煤室，也兼作浴室用。她的两个儿子和那个波兰人把午饭带到上班的地方吃，她要我中午跟她一道吃饭。吃过饭，我坐在厨房里抽烟，她则忙家务，一边给我讲述她以及她家的情况。到了下班时间，那几个上班族便回来了。波兰人先回，那两个小伙子接踵而至。波兰人穿过厨房时，房东太太告诉他，说我要和他睡一个房间，而他仅仅冲我点了点头，什么话也没说。随后，他从炉子的铁架上拎起一只大水壶，到浴室里洗脸去了。两个小伙子都身材高挑，尽管脸上有煤污，看上去仍一表人才。他们似乎对我很友好。当得知我是个美国人时，便把我视为怪物。他们俩一个十九岁，退伍还乡才几个月，另一个十八岁。

波兰人洗完回来，两个小伙子就去浴室了。波兰人的名字属于很难叫出口的那一类，大伙儿都简单地叫他考斯迪。他是个大块头，比我要高出两三英寸，虎背熊腰，脸上苍白、多肉，鼻子短而宽，大嘴巴。他的眼睛是蓝颜色的，由于没有能把眉毛和睫毛上面的煤灰洗掉，看上去就像描了眉一样。由于睫毛特别黑，就把他的眼睛衬托得蓝得惊人。这家伙长相丑陋，为人有点粗野。那两个小伙子洗完，换了身衣服就出去了。波兰人坐在厨房里一边抽烟斗一边看报。我口袋里有本书，于是拿出来，也开始看起来。我留意到，他瞥过我一两眼。过了没多久，他放下了手中的报纸。

‘你在看什么书？’他问。

我把书递给他，让他自己看。那是一本《克里夫斯公主》，我在巴黎火车站买的，小版本的，可以放在口袋里。他看看书，又看看我，一副诧异的样子，随后把书还给了我。我注意到他的嘴角浮现出一丝嘲讽的微笑。

‘有意思吗？’

‘我觉得非常有意思，甚至可以说是引人入胜。’

‘我在华沙上中学时读过此书。我觉得味如嚼蜡。’他的法语讲得很好，一点波兰口音也没有，‘现在我除了报纸和侦探小说外，什么都不看。’

勒克莱尔太太（这是我们房东太太的名字）一边留意着炉子上为晚饭煮的汤，一边坐在桌旁补袜子。她告诉考斯迪，说我是煤矿经理介绍来的，把我对她讲过的一席话重复了一遍。波兰人听着，抽着烟斗，用湛蓝湛蓝的眼睛打量着我。那双眼严苛、精明。他问了我几个问题。当我告诉他，说我从来没有在煤矿上干过时，他的嘴角又浮现出了嘲讽的微笑。

‘你都不知道自己在做什么。只要有别的路可走，谁都不愿当矿工的。不过，这是你的事情，你肯定有自己的原因。你在巴黎住在哪里？’

我如实做了回答。

‘有一个时期，我每年都要去巴黎走一走，不过，都是在大街上逛悠。你去拉鲁埃餐馆吃过饭吗？那是我最喜欢去的馆子。’

“我听了觉得有点奇怪，因为那家餐馆的饭菜并不便宜。”

“一点都不便宜。”

他可能看明白了我的心思，因为他的嘴角又浮现出了那种嘲讽的微笑。不过，他显然觉得没必要做进一步的解释。我们东一搭西一搭地扯些咸淡话，直至两个小伙子回来。随后，大家在一起吃晚饭。饭毕，考斯迪问我愿不愿到小酒馆[51]喝一杯。小酒馆设在一个非常大的房间里，有个吧台在房间的一端，屋里摆着几张大理石面桌子，每张桌子旁放几把木椅。酒馆里配有一架自动钢琴，有人往投币孔里塞了一枚硬币，此时钢琴正在弹奏一首舞曲。除掉我们坐的那张桌子外，只有三张桌子旁坐有人。考斯迪问我会不会玩勃洛特牌戏[52]。我曾经跟我的同学学过这种游戏，于是便说自己会玩。他建议我们赌一把，以啤酒为赌注。我同意后，他叫人把纸牌拿了来。我连着输了两局。这时，他提议我们赌钱。他拿的牌好，而我的运气很糟。我们赌的是小钱，但最终我还是输掉了好几法郎。赢了钱，再加上啤酒助兴，他心情很好，打开了话匣子。不一会儿工夫，我就从他的谈吐和行为方式看出他是个受过教育的人。当他重又谈到巴黎时，他就问我认不认识某某人和某某人。他说的是几个美国女人，路易莎伯母和伊莎贝尔住在艾略特家里时，我曾在那儿碰见过。他好像比我跟那些人熟悉得多。我不明白他为什么落到了今天这个地步。此时天色并不算晚，但我们次日天一破晓就得起床呢。

‘走之前，咱们再喝一杯吧。’考斯迪说。

他一面呷着啤酒，一面用他那精明的小眼睛瞅着我。他那样子使我联想到了肥猪，一头脾气暴躁的肥猪。

‘你为什么跑到这个烂煤矿受苦？’他问我。

‘为了体验生活。’

‘你是昏了头了，小伙子。’[53]他说。

‘那你为什么来呢？’

他耸了耸他那厚实、笨拙的肩膀。

‘我小的时候便进了少年军事学校。我父亲是沙皇麾下的一个将军。在上次大战中，我是一名骑兵军官。我无法忍受皮尔苏茨基[54]，我们策划杀死他，却被人出卖了。凡是被捕的，都叫他枪决了。我侥幸逃过了边境。当时摆在我面前的只有两条路：加入法国的外籍军团或者下井挖煤。我选择了后一种罪恶感比较轻的出路。’

之前，我已经告诉过考斯迪我预备在煤矿上做什么工作，他当时没有说什么，这时却见他将胳膊肘在大理石桌面上一架，说道：‘来，试试把我的手掰下去。’

我懂得这是一种老式的角力，于是摊开手，跟他的手握在了一起。他哈哈一笑说：‘用不了几个星期，你的手就不会这么柔软了。’我使出吃奶的气力把他的手朝下扳，可抵不住他的神力。渐渐地，他将我的手朝下压，最终压到了桌面上。

‘你真有劲。’承蒙他这么夸奖我，‘能坚持这么长时间的人是不多的。你听我说，我的助手屁用都不顶，是个三寸丁的法国人，手无缚鸡之力。不如你明天跟我走，我跟工头说叫你做我的助手。’

‘我愿意跟你去。’我说，‘你看工头会同意吗？’

‘这得有见面礼。你拿得出五十个法郎吗？’

“他说完把手伸出来，我从钱包里掏出一张五十法郎的钞票递给他。之后我们便回去睡觉。那一天真够累的，我一躺下便睡得像死猪。”

“你是不是发现挖煤的活十分艰辛？”我问拉里。

“起初，累得人腰酸背痛。”他咧开嘴笑了笑说，“考斯迪打通了工头的关系，让我当上了他的助手。那时，他在一块旅馆浴室那么大的空间里干活，进去时得手脚并用爬过一条非常低的隧道。里面热得像火炉，干活时浑身脱得精光，只穿一条裤子。考斯迪的身子又白又胖，活像一条巨无霸鼻涕虫，看了叫人心生厌恶。在那巴掌大的地方，气动挖煤机发出的声音震耳欲聋。我的任务是把他切下来的煤块装进一个筐子，再拖着筐子爬过隧道，将其拖到隧道口。隔一段时间就有一辆运煤车开过来，煤块便被装进车斗，然后运往电梯那儿。这是我平生第一次下井，不知道这流程是否规范，只觉得不太专业化，简直是牛马干的活。中途，我们停下手休息——吃午饭和抽烟。一天干下来，我的感觉并不糟糕，再洗个澡，舒服极了。我当时觉得自己的脚恐怕永远也别想洗干净了——那双脚黑得像煤炭。我的手磨出了水泡，疼得像刀割，但后来都长好了。渐渐地，挖煤的活我就干惯了。”

“你坚持了多长时间？”

当助手的活我只干了几个星期。话说那些往电梯口运煤的车，它们是靠一辆拖拉机拖拽的。拖拉机驾驶员只会开，不懂机械，而拖拉机的引擎经常出毛病。有一次出毛病，他修理不好，一时不知所措。我可是个呱呱叫的机修工，帮他瞧了瞧，没过半个小时便排除了故障。工头将此事告诉了经理，经理把我找了去，问我懂不懂汽车。结果呢，他给了我一份机修工的工作。当然，那工作单调乏味，可我干起来得心应手。由于汽车一有故障就被排除，他们对我很是满意。

我离开了考斯迪，这叫他窝了一肚子的火。我们俩配合默契，已彼此适应。成天跟他一起干活，晚饭后一起下酒馆，睡觉时分享一个房间，我把他已摸得透透的。他是个古怪的人，叫你一见就会留下印象。他不跟波兰人来往，波兰人去的咖啡馆我们就不去。他总忘记不了自己是贵族，而且当过骑兵军官，所以，他把那些波兰人都看得粪土不如。那些波兰人当然气得不得了，可又奈何不了他——他壮得像头牛，打起架来，不管用不用刀子，五六个人近不了他的身。尽管如此，我还是结识了几个波兰人。他们告诉我，说他在一个很棒的骑兵分队里当过军官是真的，但至于说他是出于政治原因被迫离开了波兰，那是一派胡言——他是被华沙军官俱乐部开除了，并解除了他的军职，理由是他打牌时抽老千，叫人抓了个正着。他们警告我不要跟他打牌，说他老躲着他们是因为他们知道他的底细，不愿跟他在一起待。

我和他打牌老输，但每次输得不多，只不过区区几个法郎，而且他总是争着付酒钱，所以实际上也就算不了什么。我以为自己仅仅是手气不好罢了，或者说自己的牌技不如他。可是，了解了内幕后，我就擦亮眼睛注意观察，百分之百地肯定他在抽老千。可是，即便要了我的命，我也看不出他是怎么捣的鬼。啊，他可真是聪明到家了。我明明知道他不可能老拿到最好的牌，却苦于抓不着把柄。我像猞猁一样紧盯着他不放，而他似狐狸一般狡猾。他可能发现我在提防着他了。一天晚上，我们玩了一会儿牌之后，他看着我，脸上浮现出那种无情、嘲讽的微笑（他只会这种笑法），款款说道：‘想不想让我给你变几个戏法看？’

他把纸牌拿过去，让我说一张牌，然后洗了牌，叫我随便取一张。我取出一张看了看，发现正是我方才说的那张。他又变了两个戏法，然后问我会不会玩扑克游戏，我说会玩。于是他就给我发了几张牌。我看了看，发现手里拿的是四张A和一张老K。

‘愿意不愿意给你手里的牌下一笔大赌注？’

‘我愿意把所有的钱都押上。’我回答说。

‘那你就傻了。’他说完把手里的牌摊在了桌子上——原来是一把同花顺。这叫我一头雾水。他见我一脸的诧异，不由哈哈大笑起来，说道：‘假如我不是个规矩人，我会叫你把身上的衣服都输掉的。’

‘现在你把我赢得也够惨的了。’我笑着说。

‘一点小钱，连去拉鲁埃餐馆打打牙祭都不够。’

我们每晚仍继续打牌，而且兴致很高。我得出的结论是，他抽老千与其说是为了赢钱，还不如说是为了寻乐子。他对自己能够愚弄我而感到一种异样的满足。也许最叫他感到高兴的是：我明明知道他在捣鬼，却弄不清他是怎么捣的。

不过，这只是他的一个方面，而使我最感兴趣的却是他的另一方面。我简直无法把这两方面调和起来。虽则他自夸除掉报纸和侦探小说以外，什么都不看，但其实他是个有学问的人。他很健谈，语言犀利、刻薄，夹枪带棒的，然而却让听者兴奋不已。他是个虔诚的天主教徒，床头挂一个十字架，每逢星期天就去做弥撒。星期六的晚上则以酒为伴。我们去的那个酒馆[55]一到星期六便顾客盈门，屋里空气混浊，烟雾缭绕。客人中有携家人而至的沉默寡言的中年矿工，有结伙而来的喧闹不已的年轻人；一些酒客围在桌旁玩勃洛特牌戏[56]，脸上淌着汗，嘴里大声吆喝着，他们的贤内助则坐在他们身后观战。人群和喧闹声对考斯迪会产生奇特的影响，使他变得深沉。这时的他会谈一些你想不到的话题，会谈神秘主义。至于神秘主义，我在巴黎时仅仅读过梅特林克[57]写的一篇关于鲁斯布鲁克的文章，其他便一无所知了。而考斯迪却大谈普罗提诺[58]、古希腊雅典最高法院的法官丹尼斯、鞋匠雅各布·贝姆[59]以及迈斯特·埃克纳特[60]。听这样一个被自己的社会圈子驱逐出来的大块头游民，一个愤世嫉俗、牢骚满腹、穷困潦倒的人，大谈什么万物的本质以及和上帝合为一体的极乐境界，简直是匪夷所思。这些情况我闻所未闻，让我感到迷茫，也感到激动。我就像一个躺在黑屋子里的人，窗帘的缝隙透进一线光亮，心里知道只要拉开窗帘，眼前就会出现一片沐浴在灿烂曙光里的原野。不过，在没有喝醉酒的情况下，你再跟他扯这个话题，他会生气的，眼睛露出恶狠狠的光。

‘我都不知道自己说了些啥，怎么能给你讲呢？’他会板着脸说。

“可我知道他在睁着眼说瞎话。他完全清楚自己说的是什么。他的知识非常渊博。他当时喝醉了酒固然不错，但他的眼神以及那张丑脸上激昂的表情，就不能仅仅用一句喝醉了的话搪塞过去的。情况并非如此简单。他第一次跟我那般说话，其话语我一直都没有忘掉，因为我当时都惊呆了。他竟然说这个世界并非上帝所创造，说无中不能生有，而是一种永恒的存在。这还罢了，他竟然又说恶和善一样，都直接反映着上天的意志。酒馆里肮脏不堪、人声喧哗，再加上那架自动钢琴弹奏着舞曲，他的话在这种环境中听上去怪兮兮的。”

二

此处我另起一节，好让读者有片刻喘气的机会。这样做，完全是为了读者考虑。拉里的叙述并没有因此而中止。趁此机会，我想说，他叙述时不慌不忙，斟词酌句的。虽然不敢说我能把他的话原封不动再现给诸位，但我做出了努力，不仅努力复述出事情的经过，还努力再现他说话的方式。他的声音圆润，犹如天籁之音，十分悦耳。他说着，一口一口抽着烟斗，时不时会停下来把熄灭了的烟斗再点着，只是说，不加任何手势。他直直望着我，乌黑的眼睛里有一种令人愉快的，并且让人捉摸不透的表情。

后来，春天姗姗而至。在那片平坦而荒凉的乡间，春天来得晚，天气依然寒冷，细雨绵绵。不过，有时会出现一个晴暖天，惹得矿工们都不愿离开地面，坐着摇摇晃晃的电梯（电梯里会挤满身穿肮脏工作服的矿工），钻到数百英尺以下的地球深处去了。春天已经露面，但羞羞答答不敢跨入这片阴冷、肮脏的矿区，好像害怕不受欢迎似的。它宛若一朵鲜花（水仙或百合），开在贫民区住房窗台上的一个花盆里，叫你弄不懂它在那儿干什么。星期天的早晨，我们总是赖在床上不起来。在这样的一个早晨，我正躺在床上看书，考斯迪望着外面的蓝天，对我说道：‘我要离开这儿了。你愿意跟我一起走吗？’

我知道有许多波兰人一到夏天就回他们国家割麦子，而现在还不到收割的季节。再说，考斯迪现在是有国不能回。

‘你要到哪儿去？’我问道。

‘浪迹天涯——穿过比利时到德国，再沿莱茵河朝前走。夏天，就到农场去打打零工。’

我听后，当下便做出了决定，于是说道：‘这主意挺不错的。’

次日，我们告诉工头，说我们不干了。我找到一个人愿意拿旅行背包换我的提包。我把不想要的，或者说不便路上带的衣服，全都给了勒克莱尔太太的小儿子——他跟我的身材差不多。到了第二天，老太婆供我们喝了咖啡，我们就出发了。

一路上我们不慌不忙，因为我们知道起码得等到麦收季节才能在农场找到活干。我们就这样慢慢悠悠从那慕尔和列日穿过法国及比利时，再经由亚琛进入德国境内。我们每天顶多走十英里或十二英里路，遇见中意的村子便歇脚。车到山前必有路——总能找到住宿的客栈和吃肉喝酒的酒馆。总体而言，天气还是不错的。在矿上熬煎了那么多的日月，现在来到开阔的野外，感觉真好。以前真是没有想到绿茵地竟是那么美不胜收；树木尚未长出树叶，而树枝上蒙了一层薄雾般的新绿，竟会那么赏心悦目。后来，考斯迪开始教我学习德语——他的德语和法语讲得一样棒。走在路上，遇见形形色色的景物（或牛或马，或人及其他），他都会把相应的德语告诉我，还会叫我重复简单的德语句子。时间就这样悄然逝去。进入德国境内时，我至少可以用德语问路了。

科隆稍微偏离了一点我们的路线，可是考斯迪硬要到那儿去一趟，说是为了那一万一千名殉道修女[61]。等我们到了科隆时，他便恣意酗酒，一连三天不见人影。我们下榻的地方有点像工人宿舍。待他回到住处，一脸的愠色。原来，他跟人打了一架，眼睛都被打青了，嘴唇有一道血口子，可以说样子很惨。他倒头睡了两天两夜。然后，我们沿着莱茵河的河谷向达姆施塔特进发。他说那儿风光旖旎，而且我们极有可能找到工作。

我从来都没有如此开心过。天气持续晴好。我们走过一个个小镇、一座座村庄。遇见美丽的景色，我们就驻足欣赏。找见住宿的地方，我们便停下来过夜，有一两次睡在稻草堆上。路边有客栈，我们就进去饱餐一顿。进入盛产葡萄酒的地区时，我们就不喝啤酒，以葡萄酒取而代之了。在酒馆里，我们结交了一些朋友。考斯迪粗犷而快活，赢得了酒友们的信任，于是大家一起打司卡特（一种德国的牌戏）。他谈笑风生，一团和气，暗中却抽老千。他满嘴粗俗的玩笑，很得酒友们的喜欢，所以也就不太在意输钱给他了。我则借机练习说德语。在科隆的时候，我买了一本袖珍英德会话手册，学习德语取得了很大的进步。一到晚上，两大盅白葡萄酒落肚，考斯迪便以一种病态的口吻大谈什么从孤独逃离，最后还是孤独，谈灵魂的暗夜，谈生灵与造物主合为一体的极乐境界。可是次日清早，走在明媚的乡野间，青草上露水滴滴，我想让他继续讲下去的时候，他却勃然大怒，差点没动手打我。

‘住口，笨蛋！’他说道，‘乱七八糟的东西，讲那些有什么意思！好啦，还是学德语顶用。’

你是不能跟他犟嘴的——他那汽锤一般的拳头可不是吃素的，说打你就会打你。他发火的样子我可是领教过。他可以一拳把我打昏，将我丢在臭水沟里。趁着我昏迷不醒，他会掏光我的口袋。他这个人真是叫人捉摸不透。当葡萄酒打开他的话匣子，他谈到至高无上的主宰时，他会避开平时讲的那些粗野下流话，就像脱掉下井穿的肮脏的工作服一样，换上一种很文雅的语言，滔滔不绝，口若悬河。要说他缺乏虔诚之意，我是不相信的。可不知怎么我突发奇想，认为他下井干那种艰辛、非人的活儿，只是想折磨自己的肉体。他仿佛憎恨自己那个丑陋、庞大的身躯，渴望叫它受点罪。他抽老千也罢，发脾气也罢，抑或行为残暴，都是他的意志（噢，不知怎么命名这种概念才好）对根深蒂固的神之本性的反抗，是对自己内心欲望的反抗——他渴望见到既让自己害怕又让自己迷茫的上帝。

我们徐徐而行。已到了春末，树上长满了绿叶。葡萄园里的果实越来越丰满。我们一直走的都是土路，路上尘土飞扬。进入达姆施塔特一带时，考斯迪建议找个活儿干，因为身上带的钱都快花光了。我口袋里倒还有六七张旅行支票，但我拿定主意不到万不得已时不取出来使用。后来，我们看见一所农舍样子挺气派，便停下来问他们要不要帮手。当时，敢说我们看上去不太讨人喜欢——风尘仆仆，汗和尘土把我们都弄成了大花脸。考斯迪样子像个土匪，我的样子恐怕也强不到哪儿去。于是，我们屡屡吃闭门羹。有一户农家愿意雇用考斯迪，却不愿用我。考斯迪说我们是好朋友，是不能分开的。我叫他留下干，可他硬是不肯。这叫我感到有点意外。他喜欢我，我是清楚的，其中的原因我想象不来，因为我并不是对他有用处的那种人。可是，至于说因为喜欢我，为了我而放弃一个工作，就是我始料未及的了。离开那户农家后，我感到良心大受谴责，因为实际上我并不喜欢他，甚至很讨厌他。但是，当我想要说几句话，表示我对他这样做感到高兴时，他把我臭骂了一顿。

最后，我们终于时来运转了。话说我们刚刚走出一个山谷里的村庄，便瞧见了一所独门独户的农舍，外表看上去还不错。敲了敲门，开门的是个女人。我们照例介绍了来意，声称不要工钱，只管吃住就行了。想不到的是，她没有当着我们的面砰的一声把门关上，而是叫我们稍候。她冲屋里叫人，很快有一个男子走了出来。此人把我们细细打量一番，问我们从何处来，叫我们出示证件。他发现我是个美国人，便把我多看了一眼，似乎不太乐意用我。不过，他还是请我们进屋先喝杯酒再说。他领我们进了厨房，大家一起坐下。那女人端来一壶酒和几个杯子。男子告诉我们，说他家的雇工被公牛抵伤了，现在医院里，要等到庄稼收割之后才能康复。当地人有许多都战死于疆场，活着的却进了那些在莱茵河畔拔地而起的工厂里做工，于是便使得找个雇工十分艰难。这种情况我们是知道的，并且对此加以利用。长话短说，他最终决定雇用我们。他家的房间倒是不少，但他可能不愿让我们住在他家，于是告诉我们说干草棚里有两张床，我们可以宿在那里。

农场上的活不重，无非就是放牛牧猪什么的。机械坏了，就帮着修修。空闲时间还是有的。我喜欢那些芳香的草地，傍晚时分经常四处游荡，做一做空梦。那是一种十分惬意的生活。

这户人家的家庭成员有贝克尔老夫妇，以及他们那带着几个孩子守寡的儿媳。贝克尔年近五旬，五大三粗，头发花白。他打过仗，腿上负过伤，至今走路仍一瘸一拐的。腿伤叫他疼痛难忍，只好以酒消痛，常在睡觉前喝得酩酊大醉。考斯迪和他相处得很好，晚饭后时常一起去酒馆，打打司卡特牌戏[62]，灌灌黄汤。贝克尔太太原来是家里的女佣，是他们从孤儿院里领来的，贝克尔在妻子死后不久便续娶了她。她比贝克尔小好多岁，也还有点姿色，丰胸肥臀，红红的脸蛋，一头金发，妖妖娆娆的。考斯迪不久便断言那女人是有些风情的。我警告他不要做傻事，说我们有份好工作，不能因此而丢掉。他仅仅只是嘲笑了我几句，说贝克尔满足不了她，是她自己想来一手的。我情知劝他守规矩也是白费口舌，但我还是告诫他三思而后行。贝克尔也许看不出他心怀鬼胎，可是他的儿媳却是个明眼人，任什么都逃不过她的眼睛。

他的儿媳名叫埃莉，是个又高又壮的少妇，年龄不足三十岁，黑眼睛，黑头发，一张蜡黄的方脸老是郁郁不乐的。丈夫阵亡于凡尔登战役，她仍在服丧期。她是个虔诚的教徒，每逢星期天早晨，都要到村子里去做早弥撒，下午又会跑去做晚祷。她有三个孩子，其中一个是遗腹子，是丈夫死后出生的。一家人吃饭时，她除了骂孩子，否则从不开口说话。她很少下地干农活，大部分时间都用来看孩子。一到晚上，她就独自一人坐在客厅里看小说，让客厅的门敞开着，便于听到孩子的哭声。两个女人势同水火。埃莉瞧不起贝克尔太太，嫌她是个弃儿，做过用人。而今，贝克尔太太是一家之主妇，有权发号施令，这叫她气不打一处来。

埃莉是一户富裕农家的千金，嫁过来时带了一笔不菲的嫁妆。她没有在村里上学，而是去邻近的茨温根贝格城，上的是女子高级学校[63]，受过良好的教育。可怜的贝克尔太太十四岁就来到了农场当用人，能够看得懂书、写得了字，对她而言就很不错了。两个女人之间有裂痕，这也是其中的一个原因。埃莉一有机会就卖弄她的学问，会把贝克尔太太气得满脸通红，就问要学问对于一个农夫的妻子有什么用。这时，埃莉会看看自己用钢链套在手腕上的亡夫的身份牌，阴沉的脸上浮现出凶狠的表情，说道：‘不是农夫的妻子，而是农夫的寡妇——只不过，这个农夫是个为国捐躯的英雄。’

“可怜的贝克尔老头放着农活干不成，在她们之间当起了和事佬。”

“插一句，他们是怎么看你的呢？”我打断拉里的话问道。

哦，他们把我当成了美军的逃兵，不敢回到美国去，一回去就要被关进大牢。我不愿意跟贝克尔和考斯迪去酒馆喝酒，他们认为就是因为这个缘故。他们觉得我是不想引起人们注意，不想招来村警盘问我。当埃莉得知我在学德语，便把她用过的旧课本拿了来，说要教我。于是，吃过晚饭后我们俩就会到客厅里去学习，把贝克尔太太一个人丢在厨房里。我大声朗读，埃莉为我纠音。遇到不懂的词，她就给我解释。我猜想她这样做与其说是帮助我，还不如说是在向贝克尔太太传达某种隐晦的意思。

“考斯迪一直都在挖空心思勾引贝克尔太太，但是没有进展。贝克尔太太高高兴兴、乐乐呵呵，跟他插科打诨、谈笑风生，而他是个风月老手，自有一套手段。我猜她知道考斯迪的用心，敢说她为此而感到得意。可是，当考斯迪对她动手动脚时，她呵斥他放规矩些，还扇了他一记耳光。我敢说，那一耳光打得可真是不轻。”

说到这里，拉里犹豫了一下，难为情地笑了笑。

我从来不觉得自己是个有女人缘的人。可是我依稀感到……感到贝克尔太太看上了我。这叫我很不舒服。一是因为她比我大得多，二是由于贝克尔老先生对我们一直都很不错。吃饭时，贝克尔太太管分菜，我暗中注意到她给我的菜总会比别人的多。她好像在找机会同我单独在一起。她冲着我微笑——那种笑容可以说是具有挑逗性的。她问我有没有女朋友，说我这样的小伙子到这种地方来，身边没个女人一定会很痛苦的。她话里边的含意你应该是清楚的。我只带了三件衬衫，而且都穿得很破了。有一次，她说我破衣烂衫的怪丢人，叫我把衬衫交给她补一补。这话让埃莉听去了。一次，她趁旁边没人的时候说，如果我有缝缝补补的活儿，可以交给她做。我胡乱支吾了几句。可是，一两天后，我发觉自己袜子上的洞全补好了，衬衫也打了补丁，放回到了干草棚里的长凳上（我们的物件都摆放在这条凳子上）。这是她们俩哪一个的善举，我不得而知。当然喽，我并没有将贝克尔太太当回事。她心眼好，可我觉得她的情感仅是母性的一种表现。可是有一天考斯迪对我说：

‘告诉你吧，她想要的不是我，而是你。我算是没有戏了。’

‘别胡扯！’我正色道，‘她年龄大得都可以当我的妈妈。’

‘这有什么关系？你只管追她就是了，老弟，我不会碍你事的。她也许不那么年轻了，但身体还是挺有女人味的。’

‘天呀，请你别说了。’

“为什么要优柔寡断呢？但愿不是为了我。我可是个达观者，懂得”天涯何处无芳草的道理。我不怪她，因为你年轻么。我年轻时也风光过。应该趁年轻及时行乐。[64]

“考斯迪那样捕风捉影，样子那般深信不疑，叫我心中有点不悦。出现这种情况，我真不知该怎么对付才好。此时，我想起了一些以前没有重视过的现象，想起了以前从未往心上放的埃莉的一些言语。我大有恍然大悟之感，坚信埃莉是知情的。贝克尔太太和我单独在厨房里时，她会突然闯进来。我觉得她好像在监视我们，这叫我很不高兴。她可能是想捉奸哩。我知道她恨贝克尔太太，有点机会就恨不得生出些事端来。当然，若说捉奸，那是不可能的。可是，这个女人可不是个善茬，谁知道会编出什么谎话来灌进贝克尔老先生的耳朵里呢。我没有脱身良策，只好装痴装傻，假装不知道她们在演什么戏。在这个农场，我日子过得开心，也喜欢这儿的农活，绝不愿意在收麦之前就离开。”

听着听着，我不禁哑然失笑。可以想象得来拉里当时的模样——身穿缀着补丁的衬衣、短裤，脸和脖子被莱茵河的太阳晒得发紫，身体敏捷、苗条，黑黑的眼深嵌在眼窝里。我坚信，这种模样一定会让贝克尔太太这样丰胸肥乳的金发主妇欲火中烧。

“后来怎么样呢？”我问道。

夏日的时光在流淌。我们像牛马般干着活，收割完小麦，将麦秆堆成干草垛。后来樱桃熟了。我和考斯迪就爬上梯子摘樱桃，由两个女人把摘下来的樱桃装进大箩筐，再由贝克尔老先生送到茨温根贝格城里去卖掉。再接下来就是收割黑麦了。这期间，我们始终没忘了放牛牧猪。我们天不亮就起来干活，天黑时才收工。我心想贝克尔太太可能觉得我是个不开窍的榆木疙瘩，不再理会我了。在尽量不得罪她的情况下，我跟她保持着一定的距离。一到晚上，我便困得不行，看不了几眼德文书了，吃完晚饭就回到我们住的干草棚里，倒头便睡。贝克尔和考斯迪晚上一般都要去村里泡酒馆。等到考斯迪从酒馆回来，我早已进入了梦乡。干草棚里很热，我睡觉时脱得精光。

一天夜里，我被弄醒了。开头，我搞不清是怎么回事。就在我半睡半醒之际，只感到一只热乎乎的手捂住了我的嘴，这才发觉有人和我睡在一起。我将捂在我嘴上的那只手推开，接着就有一张嘴贴在了我的嘴上，两条胳膊把我搂紧。我感觉到那是贝克尔太太——她那丰满的胸脯紧紧偎在我身上。

‘别出声！[65]别出声！’她低声说。

“她身体紧紧抵住我，用滚烫、丰满的嘴唇吻我，两只手抚摸我的全身，两条大腿夹在我的大腿中间。”

拉里停了下来。我哧哧笑了几声。

“你是怎么反应的呢？”

他冲我难为情地一笑，甚至脸都有点红了。

“我有什么办法呢？旁边的床上睡着考斯迪，他沉重的呼吸声清晰可闻。约瑟夫[66]的故事我一直都觉得有点可笑。我只有二十三岁呀。反正我觉得不便闹起来将她赶下床。我不愿意刺伤她的感情，于是就依顺了她。”

“完事后，她溜下床，蹑手蹑脚走掉了。可以说，我轻轻舒了口气。要知道，我都快吓死啦。‘老天呀，真是险啊！’我对自己说。我想着贝克尔很可能吃得大醉回来，昏昏沉沉睡着了。可是，两口子睡一张床，他一觉醒来不见了妻子，那该如何是好？另外，还有埃莉。她老说自己睡觉睡不踏实。万一她醒着，听见贝克尔太太下楼走出屋子，那该怎么办呢？就在这时，我突然想起了一个细节——贝克尔太太和我睡在一起时，我觉得有个金属片抵在了我身上。你也知道，在干那种事的时候，这种细节是注意不到的。我也一直没有细想过那究竟是何物。突然，我若有所悟。当时我坐在床沿上，正愁肠百结，担心此事会产生严重后果呢，一个念头闪过我的脑际，惊得我跳了起来。那个金属片其实是埃莉丈夫的身份牌，她历来都是套在手腕上的。原来，和我同眠共枕的不是贝克尔太太，而是埃莉！”

我听了笑得肚子疼，想停也停不下来。

“你可能觉得好笑，”拉里说，“而我并不觉得。”

“你现在回想一下当时的情景，你不觉得其中有几分幽默吗？”

拉里嘴边勉强地露出了一丝微笑。

“也许吧。不过，当时的处境很是尴尬。真不知事情会怎么收场呢。我不喜欢埃莉，觉得她是个非常讨人嫌的女人。”

“问题在于，你怎么会认错人呢？”

当时屋子里黑得伸手不见五指。她除了叫我不要作声外，一句话也没说。她们两个身材都高大、壮实。我认为只是贝克尔太太看上了我，怎么也想不到埃莉也对我起了念头。她一贯心里只有亡夫的呀。我点起一根烟，边抽烟边权衡自己的处境，越想越觉得不妙。三十六计，走为上计！

“平时我老怪考斯迪睡觉太死，叫都叫不醒。下井的那段时间，我常常为了让他按时起床，上班不迟到，非得狠劲摇他不行。而此时他睡觉睡得死，我倒要感谢他了。点亮提灯，穿好衣服，我将自己的用品塞进背包里——东西不多，这一过程很快就完成了。然后，将背包背上肩，穿着袜子走过去，下了楼梯后才把鞋穿上，并吹熄了灯。夜晚漆黑一片，一点月光也没有。好在我认得路，上了大道后便向村子那个方向走去。我走得很快，想趁着人们还未起床赶紧穿过村子。此处距离茨温根贝格城只有十二英里的路程。抵达那儿时，街上刚开始有人走动。那段路程我终生难忘。路上，万籁俱寂，只能听得见脚下沙沙的脚步声，还能听见时不时传来农户人家的公鸡打鸣的声音。后来，天空半明半暗，出现了鱼肚白，再接下来就是曙光初露，太阳冉冉升起。只见百鸟啁啾，那绿油油的田野、草地和树林以及田间的小麦都沐浴在静谧的晨光里，像是披着金裹着银。到了茨温根贝格城里，我喝了杯咖啡，吃了块面包，然后去邮局给美国运通公司发电报，叫他们把我的衣服和书寄到波恩去。”

“为什么要到波恩去？”我打断他的话问。

“我们俩沿着莱茵河畔旅行时，曾在那儿歇过脚，我当时就喜欢上了那座城市。我喜欢看阳光照在千家万户的屋顶上以及河面上，喜欢那古老的窄街、别墅、花园和一排排的栗子树，喜欢高等学府那洛可可式建筑。我觉得那是个挺不错的地方，在那儿住上一段时间是很惬意的。不过，我认为到那儿去，最好先把自己收拾得像个样。我看上去像个流浪汉，到哪户人家找住处的时候，都可能得不到对方的信任。于是，我乘坐火车去了法兰克福，买了个皮包和几件衣服。在波恩，我断断续续住了有一年的光景。”

“你下井挖过煤，在农场干过农活，那样的人生经历你有收获吗？”

“有。”拉里点头笑着说。

不过，他没有说出究竟是什么样的收获。此时的我对他已非常了解，知道他愿意说，就一定会说的，如果不愿意说，那他会开个玩笑将话题引开，你再怎么问也是白搭。在此，我必须提醒读者，这一切都是在事情发生十年之后他才告诉我的。在这以前，也就是我和他重又碰面之前，我不知他身在何方，也不知他在干些什么，亦不知他是生是死。要不是跟艾略特有点交情，从他那儿了解到一些伊莎贝尔的情况，从而回忆起拉里，我肯定早已忘掉有这个人了。

三

跟拉里解除婚约后第二年的六月初，伊莎贝尔就嫁给了格雷·马图林。此时，巴黎的社交季节正在高潮，艾略特要参加许多场规模宏大的宴会，所以他一百个不愿意离开巴黎，但由于他的家族感情异常强烈，容不得他忽略掉在他看来是自己分内的职责。伊莎贝尔的兄长们远在天边，无法抛下那儿的工作回家参加婚礼，于是他只好踏上恼人的旅途，前往芝加哥为外甥女主婚了。他想起那些法国贵族都是穿着盛装上断头台的，所以特地上伦敦购置了一套新晨礼服、一件青灰色双排纽扣的大衣和一顶丝绸礼帽。一返回巴黎，他就把我请去看他试装。他选了一条浅灰色的领带，自认为适合于婚礼上佩戴，可是再用平时的那枚珍珠别针，便不伦不类了，这叫他很恼火。我建议他改用他那枚镶着翡翠和钻石的别针。

“如果我只是个宾客嘛……这也就罢了，”他说，“而我担任主婚人的特殊责任，便感觉到珍珠有一种象征意义。”

他对这门亲事非常满意，认为从各方面看，双方都是门当户对的。一说起来，他便眉飞色舞，就像个孀居的公爵夫人在议论拉罗什富科家族的公子跟蒙特默伦西家族的千金结下的天设地造的良缘。为了明确表示自己满意的心情，他不惜重金买了一幅纳蒂埃为法兰西王室的一个公主画的精美的肖像，准备带去作为结婚礼物。

亨利·马图林好像给小两口在阿斯特街买了一幢房子，靠近布雷德利夫人住的地方，离他自己在湖滨道的那座富丽堂皇的府邸也不太远。说来也巧，购置这幢房子时，格雷戈里·布拉巴宗恰好在芝加哥，房子的内部装饰就交给了他，而我怀疑艾略特和布拉巴宗在这件事上是串通好了的。艾略特返回欧洲时，舍弃了巴黎的社交盛宴，直接取道前往伦敦，给格雷戈里·布拉巴宗带去一些室内装饰的照片作为样本。后者放手大干了一场。客厅的装饰完全是乔治二世时期的风格，显得金碧辉煌。至于书房——格雷将来的小天地，格雷戈里是靠慕尼黑的阿玛利堡宫里一间屋子给他的启发来进行装饰的，除了没有地方放书外，可以说无懈可击。格雷戈里为这对年轻的美国夫妇把寝室装饰得十分舒适（那张双人床不算在内），就是法王路易十五在这里幽会蓬帕杜夫人，也会觉得舒心安逸，而伊莎贝尔的浴室则会叫路易十五大开眼界——那儿完全是玻璃世界，有玻璃墙壁、玻璃天花板、玻璃浴缸；墙根的玻璃鱼缸里有银色的小鱼在金色的水草中游来游去。

“当然，房子是很小的。”艾略特说道，“可是亨利告诉我，说室内装修花了他十万块。对普通人来说，这可是数目很大的一笔钱。”

婚礼很气派，在圣公会教会允许的范围内极尽奢华。

“跟巴黎圣母院里举行的那种婚礼有所不同，”艾略特带着几分自豪告诉我说，“但就新教的婚礼来说，却是别具一格。”

报纸对婚礼高调进行了报道，艾略特剪下几条，做出一副漫不经意的样子丢给我看。他还让我看了新人的结婚照——伊莎贝尔穿着新娘服装，有些胖，然而很漂亮；格雷是个大块头，但身材不错，穿一身结婚的礼服，显得有点不自在。还有一张新婚夫妇和伴娘们的合影，一张小两口跟布雷德利夫人、艾略特一起拍的照片——布雷德利夫人穿一件华贵的衣服；艾略特把他的新帽子拿在手里，风度翩翩，那种高雅的劲儿简直无法比拟。我问他布雷德利夫人的身体状况怎样。

“瘦了许多，脸色不尽如人意，但身体状况还是挺好的。当然，婚事叫她操尽了心，好在现已办完，她总算能彻底休息休息了。”

一年后，伊莎贝尔生了一个女儿，根据当时流行的名字，取名叫琼；隔了两年，她又生了一个女儿，还是根据当时流行的名字，取名叫普里西拉。

亨利·马图林的一个合伙人死了，另外两个合伙人在重压之下不久也退休了。公司原来就由着他独断专行，而今更成了他一人的天下。多年的抱负一朝实现。他让儿子和他一道经营，公司出现了空前繁荣的景象。

“他们赚钱易如反掌，老伙计。”艾略特对我说道，“呵，格雷才二十五岁，一年就能赚五万块。而且，这还只是开了个头。美国的财富是永不枯竭的。这种繁荣并非昙花一现，而是一个伟大国家的常态。”

他的胸中泛起了少见的爱国主义热情。

“亨利·马图林不可能永远活下去。要知道，他患有高血压。格雷到了四十岁时，将坐拥两千万元的资产。那可是富比王侯，老伙计，富比王侯呀。”

艾略特和姐姐之间家书不断。一年一年的时光悄然流逝，他时不时会把姐姐告诉他的事情讲给我听。格雷和伊莎贝尔生活幸福，两个孩子活泼可爱。他们一家的生活方式叫艾略特赞不绝口，说完全合乎他们的社会地位——请客请得风风光光，别人请他们也排场阔气。艾略特非常满意地告诉我，说他们三个月里单独吃饭吃不上一次。后来，由于马图林夫人的离世，这种快活的日子戛然而止。亨利·马图林当初娶那位面无血色、高颧骨的女人，是想利用她的社会关系，好在芝加哥有一席之地，因为他父亲是农村来的乡巴佬，指望不上。为了纪念马图林夫人，小两口儿有一年的工夫，请客吃饭一次顶多只请六个人。

“我一直认为请客请八个人最为合适。”艾略特看问题看的是乐观的一面，于是这样说道，“八个人气氛融和，利于交谈，同时给人的印象是够得上宴会的规模。”

格雷对妻子慷慨得出奇，生第一胎时，送给她一枚四面都经过打磨的钻石戒指，生第二胎，赠给她的是一件紫貂皮大衣。由于太忙，他很少离开芝加哥。中间如果能休息几天，他们全家就会到亨利·马图林在马文的那幢豪宅里度假。亨利爱儿子，有求必应。一次过圣诞节的时候，他把在南卡罗来纳州买的一处农场送给了儿子——这样儿子可以在狩猎季节到那儿去打两个星期的野鸭子。

“当然，我们的商业巨头跟意大利文艺复兴时期靠商业发财的那些伟大的艺术赞助人很相似。就拿美第奇家族来说吧——甚至就连法国的两个国王也放下身段跟这个显赫家族的千金联姻。可以预见，总有一天，欧洲的君主会跑到美国来，向这个金元帝国的公主求婚的。正如诗人雪莱所说：‘世界的伟大时代重又降临，黄金的岁月回来了。’[67]”

多年来，布雷德利夫人和艾略特的投资都交给亨利·马图林打理，姐弟俩对他的眼光深信不疑。亨利从不冒风险搞投机，而是将他们的钱都放在可靠的股票上。由于股票的价值大涨，他们的投资也水涨船高，小小的几笔钱增加了许多，让他们又惊又喜。艾略特告诉我，说他连一根手指头都没有动，一九一八年投进去的钱，至一九二六年便几乎翻了一倍。他已经六十五岁，两鬓霜染，脸上有皱纹，眼睛下面出现了眼袋，但他没有向岁月屈服，仍保持着身材瘦削、腰杆笔挺。他历来都很注意自己的生活习惯，注意自己的外表。只要能够有伦敦最好的裁缝给他做衣服，有自己的特约理发师为他理发修面，有按摩师天天早晨上门按摩，使他的优美体形保持良好的状态，他就绝不会任由时光摆弄自己。他早已欣然淡忘自己已沦落于商贾之流，而倾向于暗示自己年轻时曾在外交界供职，不过他从不把话说得很明白，因为他并不愚蠢，不会就这一点撒谎，免得日后被人戳穿。我得承认，如果我有机会描写一位大使的话，我会毫不迟疑地选艾略特做我的模本。

但是，世道在变。当初对艾略特有提携之恩的显贵女性，有些仍活着，却年事已高。那些英国的贵族夫人，在她们的爵爷去世后，只得把府邸让给媳妇，自己住进切尔滕纳姆的别墅或者摄政公园里的普通房屋。斯塔福德府邸改造成了博物馆，柯曾宅院成了一个机构的办事处，德文郡的衙门如今在出售。艾略特在考斯时经常乘坐的那艘游艇已转手他人。眼下唱主角的那些弄潮儿觉得艾略特老儿已成了无用的废物，认为他是个荒唐可笑的老厌物。他们仍旧愿意参加他在克拉里奇酒店举办的盛大午宴，但艾略特眼光敏锐，看得出他们来赴宴，只是想彼此见见面，而非来看望他。过去，写字台上满是请帖，由着他挑选，而今那样的情形已不复存在。他常常独自一人在酒店房间里用餐，这种丢人的事情他可不愿叫外人知道。在英国，有地位的女人一旦出了丑闻，就会被社交界拒之门外，她们转而会对艺术产生兴趣，召集画家、作家和音乐家围绕于身边。艾略特心高气傲，绝不愿委屈自己，与之为伍。

“遗产税和战争投机商把英国社交界给毁掉了。”他对我说道，“人们好像对于和什么人来往全不在乎。按说，伦敦的裁缝和鞋帽匠还是不错的。我相信我死之前会一直如此。除了这一点好处之外，这座城市便一无是处了。老伙计，圣艾尔斯家要女佣伺候饭桌，这你知道吗？”

这话是他和我在卡尔顿府邸吃完午宴，离开时讲的。就在那天的午宴上，发生了一桩不幸事件。尊贵的东道主在藏画上小有名气，午宴上有个年轻的美国客人，名叫保罗·巴顿，此人提出想看看他的藏画。

“你是不是有幅提香[68]的画？”

“曾经有过。现在，这幅画在美国呢。一个犹太佬出一大笔钱买它，而我们家当时手头正拮据，所以老爷子就把它卖了。”

我注意到艾略特一边支棱起耳朵听，一边把谈笑风生的侯爵狠狠瞪了一眼，于是便猜到那个买画人就是艾略特。他这么个出身于弗吉尼亚，祖先曾在《独立宣言》上签过字的人，竟然听见自己遭到如此奚落，简直都快把肺气炸了。他有生以来从未受过这样的奇耻大辱。最叫他受不了的是，挑起事端的是他恨之入骨的保罗·巴顿。这个年轻人战后不久便来到了伦敦。他二十三岁的年纪，金发碧眼，一表人才，风度翩翩，跳舞跳得好，手里很有钱。他拿了一封信来见艾略特，艾略特素来有善心，就把他介绍给了自己的好多朋友。这还不够，他还为他指点迷津，给了他一些宝贵的忠告。根据自己的亲身经历，艾略特向他传授经验，说只要对年龄大的贵妇人献献殷勤，对显贵人物说的话，不管怎样腻味，都应该洗耳恭听，这样，即便是一个举目无亲的人也能跻身于社交界。

可是，保罗·巴顿步入的社交界和几十年前艾略特·邓普顿费尽千辛万苦才钻进去的社交界完全是两个世界。这个世界只追欢寻乐。保罗·巴顿豪情满怀、仪表堂堂、风度翩翩，没用几个星期便有了效果，其成就不亚于艾略特多年的苦心经营。很快，他便不需要艾略特的提携了，对此他也没有做出样子加以掩饰。两人见面时，保罗·巴顿仍然说些开心的话，但语气却漫不经心，深深刺伤了这位老者的自尊。艾略特请客，不是视自己是否喜欢，而是看对方能不能给宴会增辉，鉴于保罗·巴顿人缘不错，所以每星期设午宴仍旧请他。不过，这个成功的年轻人一般都有约会，有两次到了最后时刻才告知艾略特，给艾略特弄个措手不及。这种事艾略特本人过去也经常做，哪能不知底细——保罗·巴顿显然是刚刚收到了一份更具吸引力的邀请。

“我也不要求你相信我的话，”艾略特气哼哼地对我说，“但事实如此——他竟然想在我面前摆谱。我是谁呀！还谈什么提香不提香。”说到此处，艾略特一副气急败坏的样子，“就是把提香的画放在他面前，他也不见得能认出来。”

我从来没见过艾略特生这么大的气。据我猜想，他之所以动怒，是因为他觉得保罗·巴顿问起这张画是出于恶意；这个年轻人不知从哪儿获悉艾略特买了这幅画，于是就想利用那位贵族老爷的回答拿艾略特开涮。

“他是个厚颜无耻的市侩，天下我最痛恨、最瞧不起的就是这种势利小人。要不是我，他狗屁都不是。相信不相信，他的父亲是做办公家具的。办公家具！”说最后几个字的时候，他的语气十分轻蔑，“我告诫人们，说他在美国是个无名之辈，出身极其寒酸，可是他们好像并不在乎。请记住我的话，老伙计，英国的社交界算是完了，跟渡渡鸟[69]一个样。”

依艾略特看，法国的情形也好不到哪儿去。他年轻时结识的那些贵妇人，即便仍活着，也是沉迷于打桥牌（他最讨厌的一种牌戏）、做祈祷和照料孙辈。如今，工厂主们、阿根廷人、智利人以及那些和丈夫分居或者离了婚的美国妇女，却住进了贵族那富丽堂皇的府邸，请客吃饭，极尽奢华之能事。叫艾略特所不齿的是，在他们举办的宴会上，见到的都是些说起法语俗不可耐的政客、要吃相没吃相要坐相没坐相的记者，甚至还有戏子。侯门家的少爷娶个商店店主的小家碧玉，并不觉得丢人。诚然，巴黎是欢乐之都，但这种欢乐是何等缺乏品味！年轻人们追求的是纸醉金迷、灯红酒绿，认为最有趣的生活莫过于走进一家空间狭小、乌烟瘴气的夜总会，花一百法郎喝一瓶香槟酒，挤在不三不四的人群里跳舞，一直跳到次日凌晨五点钟。烟气、热气、嘈杂声，这些叫艾略特感到头痛。眼前的巴黎不再是他三十年前心目中的精神家园，不再是有品位的美国人渴望在死后升入的天堂。

四

艾略特是个有眼光的人。一位知情人告诉他，说里维埃拉就要重新成为贵族和上层人物的休闲之地了。过去由于在教廷供职，他从罗马回来，途中常要在蒙特卡洛的巴黎饭店住上几天，或者到戛纳去，在哪个朋友的别墅里待一待，所以对那一带海滨相当熟悉。不过，那都是在冬天。近来却听到传言，说那儿正在成为一个非常理想的消夏胜地。那些大旅馆夏天仍旧营业；夏季贵宾的名字登载进了巴黎《先锋报》的交际栏——那一个个熟悉的名字，艾略特看了满心喜悦。

“滚滚红尘，叫人不胜烦恼。”他说，“我已是一把岁数的人了，也该享受享受山水之乐了。”

这话说得没头没尾，有点言不由衷。他一直认为游乐山水是社交生活的一大障碍。有些人眼前明明放着一件摄政时代的古董或者华托的一幅名画不好好欣赏，却跑去游山玩水，这叫他无法容忍。当时，他手头有着一笔数额可观的现金。话说亨利·马图林一方面因儿子力劝，一方面看见那些做证券交易的朋友一夜暴富，不由红了眼，终于向潮流屈服，渐渐放弃了他那套陈旧的保守主义，觉得自己没有理由不搭上这趟顺风车。他写信给艾略特，说他仍旧和过去一样反对赌博，但证券交易并非赌博，而是对祖国坚定的信任，相信祖国有着永不枯竭的财源。他的乐观是有道理的。他认为任何力量都阻挡不住美国前进的步伐。在信的结尾处，他说他凭保证金额度为亲爱的路易莎·布雷德利买进了一些安全股票，而且很高兴告诉艾略特，她现在已经赚入两万块钱了。末了，他说艾略特如果想赚点零钱，让他根据自己的判断行事，保证不会叫艾略特失望。遇到这种事，艾略特总喜欢找些借口搪塞，说什么他抵挡不住眼前的诱惑。多年来，当《先锋报》随着早餐一道送入他的房间时，他都是先看社交界的消息，而自从读了亨利·马图林的来信之后，他首先注意的就是证券市场的报道了。亨利·马图林代表他做的那些交易非常成功，使他不费吹灰之力便拿到了五万块可观的收益。

他决定把这笔钱拿上，在里维埃拉买一幢房子。他选中昂第布作为一处避世的港湾。那地方位于戛纳和蒙特卡洛之间，可进可退，具有战略意义，方便游走于那两地。后来，昂第布没多久便成了上流社会的中心，他的选择不知是出于天意，还是受到内心本能的驱使，谁也说不清。住在一个带花园的乡村别墅里，脱不了城市近郊的那种庸俗气，让讲究品味的他觉得倒胃口，于是他跑到旧城区临海的地方买了两幢房子，再将两幢并为一幢，安装上中央暖气系统、浴室和卫生设备——这些都是顽固的欧洲大陆受到美国影响的产物。当时正流行酸洗，所以他把古老的普罗旺斯家具全都酸洗过，再用现代纺织品蒙上，摆放在屋里，在某种程度上也算赶了赶时髦。对于毕加索[70]、布拉克[71]这类现代派画家，他却仍然难以接受。“不成样子，老伙计，不成样子！”他会这样嗟叹。他觉得这些画家都是缺心眼的评论家制造舆论捧起来的。但是他对印象派画家却青睐有加，并认为自己眼光独到，于是他家的墙上便挂了一些花花绿绿的印象派画作。我记得其中有一张莫奈[72]的人们在河里划船的画；一张毕沙罗[73]画的塞纳河的码头和桥；一张高更的塔希提岛风景；一张雷诺阿[74]画的少女侧像，黄头发从背上披下来，很令人着迷。等到房子修整完毕，真是焕然一新，叫人赏心悦目，不同凡响而又朴素无华——那种朴素，是费尽心思才取得的效果。

自此，艾略特步入了自己一生中最辉煌的时期。他从巴黎把他那位厨艺超群的厨子带了来，不久大家便公认他家的饭菜在里维埃拉口味最好。艾府的管家和男仆全都是一身白装，肩上挂着金带。他请客讲究排场，但有一定的底线，从不庸俗。在地中海沿岸，欧洲各地来的王公贵族处处可见，有的是喜欢这儿的气候，有的是逃亡来的，有的是因为不堪丑闻的纠缠，有的是婚姻出现问题，觉得不如定居于这一片异国的土地。人群中有俄国的罗曼诺夫皇族、奥地利的哈布斯堡王族、西班牙的波旁王族、两个西西里贵族和一个帕尔马贵族，另外还有温莎王室的公主、布拉干萨王室的公主，有瑞典的王室和希腊的王公贵族。对于这些人，艾略特敞开大门欢迎。对于那些从奥地利、意大利、西班牙、俄罗斯、比利时来的没有王室血统的王子和公主，公爵和公爵夫人，侯爵和侯爵夫人，艾略特也都设宴款待。冬季，瑞典国王和丹麦国王来海滨小住，西班牙的阿方索国王也不时地来匆匆一游，艾略特对他们迎迓不及。他鞠躬迎接这些高贵人物不卑不亢的样子历来都叫我佩服有加，因为他既能表现得彬彬有礼，又能保持一个声称人人生来平等的国度里的公民所具有的独立人格。

游荡了几年之后，此时我在费拉角买了幢房屋定居了下来，于是和艾略特见面的机会就多了。我的地位在他眼中很荣幸已经升得很高，所以，他有时候也请我参加他举办的最为盛大的宴会。

“来吧，老伙计，算是帮我的忙了。”他会这样对我说，“当然，你我都清楚，王公贵族在宴会上只会叫人败兴。不过，有些人还是想会会他们的，我觉得自己有责任照顾照顾那些可怜人的面子。只有上天知道，他们是不配的，因为他们是世界上最忘恩负义的人。这些人是要利用你，而一旦你对他们没有用时，便会将你视若敝屣。你给予他们千百种恩惠，他们也不会感恩，哪怕是举手之劳的忙也不会帮你的。”

艾略特绞尽脑汁和当地的权贵搞好关系，因此，区长、教区主教以及主教代理就成了他家常来常往的座上宾。主教在进教会之前是个骑兵军官，第一次世界大战期间指挥过一个骑兵团。他脸色红润，身材胖大，讲话粗鲁、率直，一副军队里的腔调，这叫表情严肃、面容枯槁的主教代理总是如坐针毡，生怕他会说出有伤大雅的话来。主教很喜欢讲故事，这位代理在听的时候，脸上会堆起不以为然的微笑。不过，主教大人在管理教区方面能力过人。他布道时口若悬河、动人心扉，餐桌旁则妙语如珠，给大家带来了欢乐。艾略特对教会的虔诚以及慷慨布施令他很是欣赏，他喜欢艾略特的和蔼可亲以及艾略特提供的美味佳肴。二人成了好朋友。艾略特扬扬得意，说他在天地两世界都游刃有余，而按照我的说法是，他拜上帝和拜金两不误，取得了理想的平衡。

艾略特对自己的房子颇感自豪，急于向姐姐炫耀炫耀。他总觉得姐姐在赞扬他时，肚子里留了三分话。他想让她看看自己如今过得是多么风光，想让她见见自己新结交的朋友。姐姐来了一看，所有的疑惑都会消失的，会承认他干得不错。他写信给她，让她带着格雷和伊莎贝尔一同来——不是住在他的府上，因为府上没有空房间，而是以他的客人身份住进近旁的“海角旅馆”。布雷德利夫人写了回信，说她已经过了旅行的年龄，因为健康欠佳，想想还是待在家里养病好；格雷在芝加哥是怎么也脱不了身的，他生意兴隆，财源滚滚，忙得只好留在国内了。艾略特跟姐姐感情很深，这封信使他慌张起来。他又给伊莎贝尔写了封信。对方回了封电报，说母亲身体虽然很不好，每星期得卧床一天，但目前还没有危险，其实，如果当心一点，完全还能活很长时间；不过，格雷倒需要休息休息，国内的生意有他父亲照看着呢，他自己有理由度一段时间的假；今年夏天算是不行了，明年她和格雷一定来。

一九二九年十月二十三日，纽约证券市场崩溃了。

五

当时，我正在伦敦。我们身处英国，起初没有意识到情况是多么严重，后果会是多么叫人心灰意冷。就我自己而言，虽然对损失了相当大的一笔钱感到烦恼，但损失的大部分是票面利润，等到尘埃落定，我发现自己的现款并无缩水。我知道艾略特买股票下的赌注很大，担心他会受到沉重打击。可是，我一直没有和他见面。直到过圣诞节，我们重返里维埃拉，才得以相见。他告诉我，亨利·马图林死了，格雷破产了。

我对做生意一窍不通，艾略特给我讲述了事件的经过，听得我一头雾水。我只觉得之所以大难临头，一半要怪亨利·马图林一意孤行，一半要怪格雷急躁冒进。亨利·马图林开头不相信事情会那么严重，认为只不过是纽约股票经纪人玩的小把戏，无非是想从别的地方的同行身上榨点油出来，于是咬紧牙关拿出大笔的钱来支撑市场。芝加哥的经纪人们被纽约的那些无赖吓得屁滚尿流，这叫他十分生气。他的那些小客户——有固定进项的寡妇、退伍的军官等，过去听从他的建议，不曾损失过一分钱，他以此而感到自豪，现在为了不使他们受到损失，就自己掏腰包给他们的账户注入资金。他说大不了就是破产么，他还可以东山再起；但是，如果让信任他的小客户蒙受损失，他就永远也无法抬起头来做人了。他自以为有一副侠肝义胆，然而却挽不住狂澜，偌大的家产投进去，顷刻化为乌有。一天夜里，他的心脏病突然发作。他已是六十多岁的人了，平时劳累过度，暴饮暴食，经过几个小时痛苦的挣扎，最终因冠状动脉栓塞而溘然长逝。

只剩下格雷一人独立面对危局。这之前，他在投机生意上广泛涉入，父亲对此一无所知，而今他自己也深陷债务危机。他千方百计想摆脱困境，但最终归于失败。银行不肯贷款给他，交易所里老一辈的人告诉他，说仅有一条路可走了——低头认输。其余的情况我就不太清楚了。可能他无法履行还债的义务，于是便宣告破产了。他家的房子此前早已抵押了出去，这时便乖乖将房子交给了债权人。他父亲在湖滨道的房子以及马文的那套房子均折价卖了出去。伊莎贝尔把首饰也卖了个精光。南卡罗来纳州的那个农场成了他们仅有的财产（此农场过户在伊莎贝尔的名下），想卖也找不到买主。格雷成了一文不名的穷光蛋。

“你的情况怎么样，艾略特？”我问道。

“哦，我倒没什么可抱怨的。”他语气轻松地回答道，“承蒙老天垂怜。”

我没有打破砂锅问到底，因为他的经济情况与我无关。但不管怎样，他跟我们大家一样肯定也蒙受了损失。

经济大萧条的恶潮起初对里维埃拉的冲击还不算大。后来听说有两三户人家损失惨重，许多别墅冬季都关门闭户，有几家还挂出了牌子出售。旅馆冷冷清清，蒙特卡洛的赌场牢骚满腹，说生意惨淡。不过，一直到两年之后，里维埃拉才真正感受到了这场飓风的影响。一个地产商告诉我，说从土伦到意大利边界的地中海沿岸，大大小小有四万八千处房地产要出售。

赌场的股票跌到了谷底。大型旅馆压低价钱以吸引顾客，却无济于事。能看得见的外国游客，全都是些穷得不能再穷的人。他们分文不花，因为他们压根就没有钱可花。商铺的老板们个个都大失所望。而艾略特与别人不同，他既没有辞退自家的仆人，也没有减少他们的工资。他继续用好酒好菜招待那些王公贵族，还买了一辆崭新的大汽车，是从美国进口的，为此付了很大一笔关税。主教大人组织慈善活动，给失业家庭施舍义餐，他为之慷慨解囊。事实上，他一如既往，好像压根没发生经济危机似的，好像半个世界没有因此被冲击得摇摇晃晃似的。

后来，我无意中发现了其中的原因：艾略特此时除掉一年一度去伦敦两个星期购置衣服外，已经不去英国了，然而他仍旧每年秋天回巴黎在自己的公寓里住三个月，五月和六月也在巴黎度过，因为这几个月里他的朋友们是不去里维埃拉的；他喜欢里维埃拉的夏天，部分原因是能洗海水浴，而我觉得主要是因为炎热的天气使他有机会穿上五颜六色的衣服放松一下，平时，为了顾及体统，他是不能这样做的。这时候，他会穿上颜色鲜艳的裤子（红的、蓝的、绿的或者黄的），配上色调形成鲜明对比的汗衫（淡紫色的、蓝紫色的、深褐色的或者杂色的），接受人们对衣服的恭维，神情不以为然，谦虚得就像一个女演员听见人家说她扮演一个新角色演得非常成功一样。

那年春天，在返回费拉角的途中，我在巴黎待了一天，邀艾略特和我一同吃午饭。我们在里茨酒吧见了面。此处一片冷清，不见了从美国跑来寻乐子的大学生，就和一出戏剧初演之夜便砸了锅的情形一样人去屋空。我们喝了一杯鸡尾酒（此为美国人的习惯，艾略特最终还是无奈地接受了），然后点了饭菜。酒足饭饱，他建议一同去逛逛古玩店。我声称自己钱囊羞涩，但愿意舍命陪君子。我们步行穿过旺多姆广场，他问我愿意不愿意跟他到查维特服饰店去一趟——他在那家店里定做了几件衣服，想问问做好了没有。原来，他订的是几件内衣内裤，上面要用手工绣上他的姓名的缩写字母。内衣尚未做好，内裤已完工，店员问他要不要看一下。

“那就看看吧。”他说道。趁着店员去拿内裤的时候，他对我说道：“我让他们缝衣服时加上我的图案。”

内裤拿来了，和我平时在麦西服装店买的一个样子，只不过料子是丝绸罢了。但我注意到，在E.T.两个缩写字母的上方绣着一个伯爵的冠饰。我看了，却一句话也没说。

“非常漂亮，非常漂亮。”艾略特说，“等内衣做好，一同给我送去。”

出了衣服店，离开那儿时，艾略特笑盈盈地转过脸对我说：

“注意到那个冠饰了吗？实话说，我拉你来查维特服饰店的时候，把这个给忘了。我一直没机会告诉你：教皇陛下给我面子，仁慈地恢复了我家古老的头衔。”

“恢复了什么？”我诧异地问，完全忘掉了提问时应该委婉些。

艾略特不满地抬起了眉毛。

“你不知道吗？我母系那一方是劳里亚伯爵的后代，他是随从菲力普二世到英国来的，并且娶了玛丽王后的一个侍女。”

“就是那个血腥玛丽[75]吗？”

“我认为这是异教徒对她的称呼。”艾略特有点尴尬地说，“恐怕我没有告诉过你，一九二九年的九月我是在罗马度过的。我觉得去罗马是件很乏味的事情，因为那儿几乎成了空城。不过，幸亏我的责任感战胜了我追求世俗享乐的欲望。当时，梵蒂冈的朋友告诉我，说经济大崩溃就要来了，力劝我卖掉手头所有美国的股票。天主教会拥有两千年之久的智慧，所以我一刻也没有耽搁，马上拍电报给亨利·马图林，叫他把所有的股票全卖掉，购入黄金。我还发了封电报给路易莎，让她也如此办理。亨利·马图林回电问我是不是疯了，说除非我再发一封电报证实我的指示，否则他什么也不会做。我立刻又发了封电报，以极为强硬的语气，要他按我说的做，然后回电报把结果告诉我。可怜的路易莎没有听我的话，因此栽了跟头。”

“这么说，大崩溃降临时，你毛发未损？”

“这是美式用语，劝你还是别用的好。不过，用它来形容我那时的状况，倒是十分贴切的。我一分钱也没损失，实际上还捡了些便宜（你也许会称之为油水吧）。过了一段时期以后，我只花了很少一点钱就把原来卖掉的那些股票全买回来了。我认为只能把这种现象叫作上帝的直接干预，于是觉得应该做点事情来报答上帝，这样才合乎情理。”

“哦，那你是怎样报答的呢？”

“这个嘛，你知道教廷在蓬蒂内沼泽[76]开垦了大片的土地，他们告诉我，说教皇陛下对那边的居民缺少一个做礼拜的地方深感焦虑。简而言之，我出资在那儿建了一座罗马式教堂，和我在普罗旺斯看到的一座一模一样，每一个部分都异常完美，可以说是一枚灿烂的明珠。教堂是奉献给圣马丁[77]的。说来话长，一次，我有幸发现了一扇古香古色的反映圣马丁事迹的彩色玻璃窗，画面上的圣马丁将自己的长袍割成两半，一半给了一位光身子的乞丐让他遮体。我觉得这幅画很有象征意义，于是把玻璃窗买下，后来镶嵌在了主祭坛的上方。”我没有打断艾略特的话。但我不明白圣马丁的那种世人皆知的善举和艾略特的行为之间有什么联系——他只不过瞅准时机卖掉股票大捞了一把，从中取出一部分小钱贡献给上帝，就像是给代理人的回扣似的。不过，我这种人毕竟是俗胎凡眼，看不透其中的象征意义罢了。艾略特继续说道：

“一次受到教皇陛下的接见，我把教堂和彩色玻璃的照片拿给他看。他圣颜大悦，说他一眼就看出我是个很有品味的人，并且说在这个世风日下的时代能发现一个既忠于教会，又具有如此罕见艺术修养的人，让他感到很高兴。当时的情景叫人终生难忘，老伙计，终生难忘呀。但最让我感到意外的是，过后不久便有人通知我，说教皇陛下有心赐给我一个爵位。我是个美国公民，觉得还是谦虚些好，除非在梵蒂冈，在别的地方就不用这个头衔了。所以我禁止我的仆人约瑟夫称我为伯爵大人[78]。我相信你会尊重我的隐私的。我不想把此事张扬出去。可是，我又不愿让教皇陛下觉得我不珍重他赐给我的荣誉，所以我把冠饰绣在我个人的衬衣上，这完全是出于对他的尊敬。可以这样说：我把爵位的标记不显山不露水地缝在内衣上，既是谦虚的表现，又透露出自豪感。”

我们分手了。艾略特告诉我，说他将于六月底到里维埃拉来。可是他却没有如约而来。原因是这样的：当时他刚刚做好安排把仆人们从巴黎调往里维埃拉，而他本人准备开车过来，消消停停的，这样抵达里维埃拉时，便已万事俱备了；就在此时，伊莎贝尔来了封电报，说她的母亲病情突然加重。我在上文便说过，艾略特喜欢他的姐姐，家族感情非常强。他立刻从瑟堡乘船到了纽约，再从那儿返回芝加哥。他写信告诉我，说布雷德利夫人病得很厉害，瘦得不成人样，着实吓了他一跳。也许她还能活上几个星期，甚至几个月，可是不论怎样，他觉得自己有责任给她送终——不管这种责任是多么痛苦。他说芝加哥的高温比他预计的要容易忍受得多，然而却缺乏惬意的社交活动，不过这也没什么关系，因为这种时刻他反正没有心思与人交往。他说他的国人对经济萧条的反应令他感到失望，因为他原以为国人会以比较平静的心态对待这场灾难呢。看见别人遭难，以泰然的语气说些大话，这是再容易不过了。我觉得艾略特比他一生中任何时候都要富有，恐怕没资格对别人要求这样苛刻。最后，他请我把情况转告给他的几个朋友，并且请我务必记着向所有碰见的人解释，为什么他的府邸今年夏天没有开门迎客。

过了不到一个月的时间，我又收到他的一封信，说布雷德利夫人过世了，词句写得悲痛，充满了深情。我早就认为尽管他为人势利，而且有许多荒唐做作的地方，但他仍不失为一个善良、多情和诚实的人，所以便觉得这样一封真诚、动情和单纯的信是出自于一片真心。他在信中告诉我，说在处理布雷德利夫人的丧事时乱事如麻。布雷德利夫人的长子是个外交官，由于驻日大使离任，他临时代理东京的外交事务[79]，一时抽不出身奔丧。她的次子叫邓普顿，我最初认识布雷德利一家时，他在菲律宾群岛供职，后来调回华盛顿，并在国务院担任要职。母亲病危时，他带着妻子来到芝加哥，但母亲一下葬，便立刻返回了首都。遇到这种情况，艾略特觉得自己应该待在美国把后事料理完再说。布雷德利夫人把财产平均分成三份，给了她的三个孩子。不过，看上去，她在一九二九年经济大崩溃时遭受了重大损失。幸好马文的那个农场有了买主。艾略特在信中把农场说成是“亲爱的路易莎的乡间别墅”。

“一户人家最后落得变卖祖屋，难免令人唏嘘。”他在信中写到，“不过，近年来眼见得许多英国朋友都被迫出此下策，我也就觉得两个外甥和伊莎贝尔必须以同样的勇气以及听天由命的态度接受这种不可避免的后果了。有权利就有义务。[80]”

他们运气好，把布雷德利夫人在芝加哥的房子也处理掉了。其实，早有人计划着要把布雷德利夫人以及其他几户人家住的那排房屋拆掉，在原址上建一幢大型公寓楼，但是，布雷德利夫人非常顽固，坚持要死在自己住的房子里，所以这个计划始终没有实现。布雷德利夫人一断气，就有中间人跑来提出要买房子，布家立刻就接受了。可尽管有了这笔钱，伊莎贝尔还是觉得不够用。

经济大崩溃之后，格雷试图找份工作干，哪怕为那些挺过了灾难的经纪人效力，在办公室当个小职员也可以，但屡屡碰壁。他找老朋友帮忙，想弄个差事做，不管地位多么卑贱，薪水多么低都可以，仍无果而终。为了度过这场灾难，他拼命挣扎，再加上忧虑过度和内心蒙受的屈辱，导致他的神经最终崩溃。他有时头痛欲裂，昼夜不息，头痛症一旦过去，便浑身软绵绵的，像面条一样。伊莎贝尔无奈之中，觉得只好先带着孩子举家前往南卡罗来纳州的那个农场暂住，等格雷恢复了健康再作计较。农场有过兴盛期，一年靠出产大米亦有十万块钱的进项，后来撂荒，成了一片泽国和荒林，对喜欢打野鸭的猎手才能派上用场，想脱手也苦于找不到买主。大崩溃发生后，他们偶尔在那儿住住，现在打算回到农场去，待情况转好，格雷能找到工作再说。

“我不能叫他们过那样的日子，”艾略特在信中写到，“老伙计，那是牲口一样的日子——伊莎贝尔没有贴身女佣，孩子没有家庭教师，只有两个黑种女人料理家务。我提出把我在巴黎的那套公寓让给他们住，等到这个风雨飘摇的国家形势改观之后再说。我将会给他们雇几个用人。其实，我厨房里的女佣烧得一手好菜，可以留给他们用，我自己完全能够再找一个代替她。他们所有的开销都由我负担，伊莎贝尔的那一点点进项，就让她买些衣服以及给家里买点好吃好喝的。当然，这意味着我在里维埃拉的时间要比以前多得多了，希望能多见见你，老伙计。伦敦和巴黎现在成了这个样子，我觉得还是住在里维埃拉自在些。里维埃拉成了唯一的一块净土，在这儿，我可以会会和自己有共同语言的人。巴黎当然也还会去的，偶尔住上几天。不过，即便去了巴黎，我也不在乎在里茨饭店凑合凑合。我可以很高兴地告诉你，我总算不枉费口舌，让格雷和伊莎贝尔接受了我的要求。把必要的事宜安排妥当，我立刻就带他们过来。那些家具和油画非常差劲，老伙计，真伪难辨，再过上一个星期就卖掉它们。我怕他们住在家里伤心，已经把他们带了来，目前和我一道暂住在德雷克饭店。过后去巴黎，我把他们安顿好，就回到里维埃拉去。别忘记替我向你的皇家邻居问好。”

无可否认，艾略特虽然是天字号的势利眼，然而也是最善良、最体贴、最慷慨的一个人！

第四章

一

艾略特把马图林一家安顿在左岸自己的那套宽敞的公寓里，于岁尾返回了里维埃拉。里维埃拉的这套房子在设计上适合于他一人居住，无法再容纳一个四口之家，所以即便他想请那一家子来跟自己住在一起，也是办不到的。对此，他恐怕也并不觉得遗憾。他心里很清楚：凡是请客的，都愿意请一个独居的人，而不愿请由外甥女和外甥女婿相陪的人；至于他自己举办宴会（他在这方面是很费心机的），家里老有两个房客，也别指望能把宴会办得多么出色。

“他们还是住在巴黎要好得多，适应适应文明社会的生活。再说，那两个小姑娘也到了上学的年龄，我找到一所学校，离公寓不远。那是个百里挑一的好学校。”

由于这个缘故，直到第二年春天我才见到了伊莎贝尔。当时，有些事情需要办理，得在巴黎待上几个星期，我便在旺多姆广场近旁的一家旅馆租了两个房间。我是这家旅馆的常客，不仅仅是为了图方便，也是因为这儿弥漫着一种情调。这是一所高门大户、年代悠久的房宅，围成一圈，中心有个院落，作为旅馆接客已有近两百年的历史了。旅馆里的浴室远远称不上奢华，抽水马桶远远不能叫人满意；寝室里放着铁架子床，漆成白色，上面铺着老式的白床罩，还有一面大衣橱，上边镶着镜子，所有的一切都透出一股寒酸气；不过，客厅里的摆设却精致漂亮、古色古香。长沙发和扶手椅是拿破仑三世那个追求奢华时代的产物，不能说舒适，但外观华丽，挺好看的。坐在客厅里，仿佛时光倒流，回到了法国小说家描写的久远岁月里。看一看玻璃罩里的那架帝国式时钟，我联想到了一位美丽女子，头发梳成小发卷，穿一件荷叶边连衣裙，一面望着时钟的长针，一面等候着拉斯蒂涅克的来访——此君是巴尔扎克笔下的一个冒险家，起自贫寒，终成显赫人物。巴尔扎克用几部小说的篇幅描写了他的人生经历。比安松医生也是巴尔扎克塑造的人物，那样栩栩如生，以至于巴尔扎克临死时还说：“只有比安松医生能救我的命了。”那位医生很可能来过这个客厅，为一个外省的贵族寡妇把过脉、看过舌苔——那寡妇来巴黎找律师打官司，偶染微恙，请医生看治。在那张写字台前，也许坐过一个穿撑裙的痴情女子，头发对中分开，正在给她的负心情人写一封情意绵绵的信；或者坐过一个愤怒的老者，穿一件绿颜色的双排扣常礼服，正在写信斥责他那挥霍无度的儿子。

抵达巴黎的第二天，我给伊莎贝尔打了个电话，说我五点钟去看望她，问她能不能请我喝杯茶。我已经有十年没有见过她了。一个脸色凝重的管家把我领进客厅时，她正在看一本法国小说。见了我，她起身迎接，握住我的双手，绽出灿烂、迷人的微笑。我和她过去见面顶多不过十一二次，而且只有两次单独在一起，但她让我立刻觉得我们是老朋友，而非泛泛之交。十年的时光倏然流逝，缩短了一个年轻女子和一个中年男子之间的鸿沟，我不再觉得我们的年龄存在着十分大的差异了。她俨然是一个见过世面的女子，语气委婉地对我说些入耳的话，待我如同龄人一般。没出五分钟，我们便坦坦荡荡，无话不谈了，就好像我们是童年时的玩伴，经常见面，从没有间断过似的。此时的她处事泰然，落落大方，充满了自信。

然而，最叫我感到意外的是她容貌上的变化。在我的记忆中，她是个漂亮、活泼，一不小心就会发胖的女孩子。不知道是她意识到了这一点而不屈不挠地采取措施进行减肥，还是因为生孩子而产生了意想不到的可喜效果，反正她现在有一个人人都渴望具备的苗条身段。她的一身装束更突出了这一点。她穿着一身黑色丝绸衣，既不十分朴素也不十分华丽，我一眼就看出是在巴黎的一家顶级服装店定做的，被她随随便便、漫不经心地穿在身上，那股劲儿就好像她天生应该穿高档服装似的。

十年前，尽管有艾略特为她指点迷津，她的穿着仍不够典雅，而且那样的行头好像老让她觉得不自在。而现在，就是玛丽·路易丝·德·弗洛里蒙在跟前，也不能说她缺乏品味了。如今的她，就连染成了玫瑰色的指甲盖都是有品位的。她出落得更加水灵了。我觉得在我见过的女性中，她的鼻子长得最直、最美。不论在前额上或者在她淡褐色的眼睛下面，都看不见一丝皱纹；她的皮肤虽然失去了几分少女时期的清新光泽，但仍如凝脂一般；也许是由于使用护肤液、乳霜，以及面部按摩的缘故，她的皮肤如今显得滋润光滑、吹弹可破，独具一种魅力。她那清秀的脸庞略施粉黛，芳唇上淡淡涂了点朱色；浅棕色的头发按照当时的风尚剪得很短，并且烫过。她的手上没有戴戒指，这使我想起艾略特说过她把首饰都卖掉了；她的手算不上特别纤巧，但十分匀称。那个时候的女子白天喜欢穿短裙，我发现她那两条穿着香槟酒色长袜的腿十分修长，特别好看。许多漂亮女子坏就坏在腿长得不够好看。记得伊莎贝尔的一双腿在当姑娘时极不入眼，而今一变为异常美观。事实上，在过去，她的魅力来自于大放异彩的健康、高扬的青春气息和亮丽的气色，昔日的那个漂亮小姑娘如今变成了一位如花似玉的美少妇。

至于她的美有几分靠的是素养、训练和修饰容貌，似乎并不重要，反正结果极其理想。也许，经过了苦心经营，她才有了这般绰约的风姿和娴雅的举止，但看上去却自然天成。我有一种感觉：她的美犹如一件艺术品，已着墨数年，而在巴黎居住的这四个月点上了最后一笔，使之脱颖而出。艾略特即便用最苛刻的眼光加以挑剔，恐怕也挑不出毛病来。我本来就不是个吹毛求疵的人，自然觉得她美压群芳。

格雷到莫特芳丹打高尔夫去了，伊莎贝尔说他不一会儿就会回来的。

“我要让你看看我的两个小女儿。她们去杜伊勒里公园了，应该马上就能回家了。她们都很可爱的。”

我们说这说那的，聊个没完。她说她喜欢巴黎的生活，说住在艾略特的公寓里十分舒适。艾略特临行之前，把他的一些这小两口很可能会喜欢的朋友介绍给了他们，现在他们有了一个很开心的朋友圈。艾略特要求他们按照他惯常的那种做法设盛宴待友。

“要知道，我们现在老摆阔，其实一贫如洗，想起来就觉得好笑。”

“真的一贫如洗吗？”

她咯咯笑了，这使我想起十年前她的那种轻松、快活、令人心情愉悦的笑声。

“格雷一个铜板也没有。我的进项很少，差不多跟拉里当年一样。那时候拉里想娶我，我不肯嫁给他，因为我觉得靠那点钱难以维持生计，殊不知我现在多了两个孩子，照样过日子。你说滑稽不滑稽？”

“很高兴你以幽默的眼光看待此事。”

“你有拉里的消息吗？”

“我吗？没有。你上次离开巴黎之前，我就再也没见过他了。他的朋友圈里，有几个我也认识，我还打听过他的情况呢。不过，那都是多年以前的事了。好像没人知道他的下落。他就这么蒸发了。”

“拉里在芝加哥的一家银行开有账户，我们认识该行的经理。经理说他时不时会从哪个怪地方开来一张付款支票——有中国的，有缅甸的，有印度的。他好像在周游世界。”

一个问题已经溜到了嘴边，我便索性说了出来。再怎么样，想了解情况，最好的办法就是开口问。

“你没嫁给他，现在后悔吗？”

她嫣然一笑说道：

“和格雷在一起，我感到十分幸福。他是个‘五好’老公。在经济大崩溃发生之前，我们的日子开心极了。我们喜欢同样的人，喜欢做同样的事情。他对我体贴入微。受到老公的宠爱，那感觉真好。至今，他都对我恩爱如初。在他的眼里，我是天下最棒的女孩子。你无法想象他是多么温柔和体贴。他对我的慷慨大度，简直到了让人觉得荒唐的地步。他认为天下没有我不配得到的东西。结婚多年来，他没有冲我说过一句刺耳或难听的话。啊，我真是太幸运了。”

我暗想她可能觉得这就算回答了我的问题了，于是便转了话题。

“给我讲讲你的两个小女儿吧。”

我话音未落，就听见了门铃响。

“她们来了。你自己看吧。”

一转眼，就有两个小姑娘走了进来，身后跟着她们的保育员。伊莎贝尔先介绍我认识大女儿琼，然后介绍小女儿普里西拉。她们依次和我握手，同时微微鞠躬致意。两姐妹一个八岁，一个六岁，跟同龄人相比个头显高。伊莎贝尔个子就高，我记得格雷也是个大块头。这俩孩子的美仅仅是普通儿童的那种美。她们看上去身子骨比较单薄，有着父亲的黑发以及母亲的浅褐色眼睛。在生人面前，她们丝毫也不害羞，争先恐后地告诉妈妈她们在花园里都做了些什么。她们的目光紧紧盯在伊莎贝尔的厨子端来的可口茶点上——那茶点我们俩谁都还没有碰过。伊莎贝尔允许她们每人挑一块吃，这倒叫二人颇费脑筋，不知挑哪一块好。显然，她们对自己的母亲怀着深深的爱，叫人看了为之感动。母女三人在一起享受天伦之乐，构成一幅美好的图画。两姐妹吃完各自挑选的蛋糕，伊莎贝尔便将她们支走了。她们一声不吭，乖乖走掉了。我所得的印象是：伊莎贝尔把她们管教得十分听话。

她们走后，我又说了几句闲话，无非就是“慈母乖儿”那一类的话。伊莎贝尔听了我的一番恭维显然很受用，但样子有些淡然。随后，我问格雷喜不喜欢巴黎。

“非常喜欢。艾略特舅舅留下一辆汽车给我们，所以他几乎每天都能够去打高尔夫球；他还加入了旅行家俱乐部，在那儿打打桥牌。说起来，艾略特舅舅让出这套公寓供我们住，真是天降洪恩。当初，格雷精神崩溃，至今仍头痛欲裂。就是能找到工作，他也干不了。为此，他把肠子都愁断了。他想工作，也觉得自己应该工作，不能干活养家会叫他无地自容。他认为一个男子汉有责任工作，否则生不如死。一想到自己成了多余的人，他便无法忍受。我好言相劝，说休息休息、换换环境可以使他恢复常态，好说歹说把他劝到了巴黎来。但我清楚，除非他能够东山再起，否则他不会真正开心的。”

“这两年半，你们的日子恐怕是十分艰难。”

“唉，想当初经济大崩溃降临时，我简直不敢相信那是真的。无法想象，我们竟会倾家荡产。要说别人破产，我还能相信，可是至于我们……唉，实在让人意想不到。我一直到最后都心存希望，认为老天会拯救我们的。后来，致命的一击落在了我们身上，我觉得没法再活下去，无法再面对未来，一时间感到天昏地暗。有两个星期的时间，我悲恸欲绝。天呀，所有的家产都离你而去，今后再无欢乐可言，你所喜欢的一切都跟你再也无缘，那种感觉真是可怕极了……两个星期过后，我痛定思痛，对自己说道：‘见它的鬼吧，我再也不去想了！’从那以后，我再也没有发过愁。没有什么可遗憾的。不管昨天多么灿烂，如今过去了，就让它过去吧。”

“显然，住在上等住宅区的一套豪华公寓里，有一个能干的管家和一个厨艺高超的厨子，自己分文不用花，还可以给自己的瘦骨头穿上沙诺尔式女装店缝制的衣服，破产的痛苦是容易忍受的，你说是不是？”

“不是沙诺尔式衣服，而是朗万[81]女装。”她咯咯一笑说，“十年没见，你可是一点都没有变。你是个愤世嫉俗的人，想必不会相信我的话的。也可能，我当初接受艾略特舅舅的邀请，全都是为了格雷和孩子。按说，有我那每年两千八百块的进项，我们一家可以在农场过得很好——种种稻子、黑麦和玉米，再养养猪。再怎么说，我也是在伊利诺伊的一个农场出生和成长大的。”

“任你怎么说吧。”我笑了笑说道。其实，我知道她是在纽约的一家价钱昂贵的产科医院出生的。

就在这时，格雷走了进来。十二年前，我只见过他两三次，这倒是真的，但他的结婚照我还是见过的（艾略特把那张结婚照镶在一个漂亮的镜框里，和瑞典国王、西班牙王后、吉斯公爵签过名的各自的照片一同放在钢琴上面）。他的模样我记得很清楚。这时一见面，我却吓了一大跳。他的鬓角秃得很厉害，头上有一小块秃顶，一张脸又红又胖，都胖成双下巴了。多年来养尊处优的生活以及饮酒过量让他的体重大大增加，只是由于个子高，才没有叫他显得过分臃肿。但最能吸引我注意力的是他的眼神。我记得很清楚，当他前途无量、无忧无虑的时候，那双爱尔兰人的蓝眼睛里充满着信任和坦率，如今在那双眼睛里似乎看到的是迷茫和惶恐。即便不了解内情，恐怕也能猜得到：一定是天降大祸，摧毁了他的自信心以及他对社会秩序的信任。我觉得他有一种自卑感，仿佛做了错事一样，虽则并非出于有意，却仍羞愧难当。显而易见，他的心理世界已经崩溃。他热情、礼貌地跟我寒暄，像是老友重逢一样满脸的高兴，但我却感到他表面的兴奋和开心只是待客的方式，与他的心里感受并不相符。

酒水送来后，他为我们每人调了杯鸡尾酒。他刚刚打完两轮高尔夫球，对自己的球技颇为满意。在谈到其中一次击球进洞的经历时，他大讲特讲自己是如何克服了重重困难，整个叙述过程冗长、啰唆，伊莎贝尔却似乎听得津津有味。又过了几分钟，我跟他们约了个日子请他们吃饭和看戏，便告辞了。

二

我逐渐养成一个习惯，干完一天的工作之后，下午就去看望看望伊莎贝尔，一星期要去三四趟。这个时间，她通常都一个人在家，乐得跟人聊天。艾略特给她介绍的那些人，比她的年纪要大得多，我发现她几乎没有和她年龄相仿的朋友。我自己的朋友大多忙得不可开交，不到吃晚饭是腾不出时间的。再说，我喜欢和伊莎贝尔聊天，而不愿去俱乐部跟那些气哼哼的法国人打桥牌——那些法国佬不太欢迎外人介入他们的圈子。伊莎贝尔把我当作同龄人对待，千娇百媚的，使得我们的谈话轻松愉快。我们谈笑风生、插科打诨，时而谈人生，时而谈朋友们的情况，时而谈书画，时光就这么令人愉快地悄然流逝。我生性有个缺点：总是看不惯其貌不扬的人。一个朋友，不管性格多么好，即便有多年的交情，如果掉了牙齿或歪了鼻子，我便感到不舒服了。另一方面，对于漂亮的人我却百看不厌——对于这样的人，尽管交往已有二十年之久，我仍喜欢看她们那标致的额头或者线条优美的脸颊。因此，我每次见到伊莎贝尔，看着她那完美的鹅蛋脸、凝脂般细腻的皮肤以及淡褐色眼里闪烁着的明快光芒，我都会产生一种心旷神怡的感觉。

后来，一件意想不到的事发生了。

三

在所有大城市里，有着一个个独立的社会圈子，彼此互不交往，在偌大的一个世界上构成了若干小世界，关起门过自己的日子，内部的成员相互依存、抱团取暖，犹如一座座孤岛，岛与岛之间隔着无法通航的海峡。根据我的所见所闻，没有一座城市比巴黎更是如此了。在这座城市里，上流社会很少允许外人涉足圈内；政客们自成一个圈子，过着糜烂的生活；大大小小的资产阶级相互之间你来我往；作家和作家欢聚一堂（在安德烈·纪德[82]的日记里，有一点很突出：他好像很少跟自己行业之外的人交往），画家和画家结伴，音乐家和音乐家为友。伦敦的情况也大致如此，只不过不那么明显罢了。伦敦城内，虽也“人以群分”，但与巴黎相比就不那么讲究了，有那么十几户人家，餐桌上既能看见公爵夫人，也可以遇到演员、画家、议员、律师、服装设计师和作家。

我的人生际遇使得我在不同的时间段里游走于巴黎各类社交圈子，甚至还（通过艾略特）进入过圣日尔曼大街那个封闭的世界，但我最喜欢的是以蒙帕纳司大街为中轴的那个小社会——这个小社会在我心目中的地位要超过那个以现在叫作福煦大道为中心的拘谨保守的小圈子，要超过经常光顾拉鲁埃餐馆和巴黎咖啡馆的那些国际人士，也超过蒙马特尔区的那些吵吵闹闹、蓬头垢面的追欢族。年轻时，我曾经在贝尔福狮子咖啡馆附近的一个小公寓里住过一年。我的房间在五楼，视野开阔，可以眺望到那片公墓。蒙帕纳司在我眼中仍旧具有当初它特有的那种外省乡镇的静谧气息。走过阴暗、狭窄的奥德萨街时，我会怦然心跳，会回想起我们经常聚餐的那家寒碜的餐馆。我们中间有油画家、插图画家和雕塑家，除了阿诺德·班内特[83]偶尔来来外，在座的就我一个作家了。我们在那儿一待就待到很晚，一块儿讨论绘画和文学，一个个情绪激昂，语气激愤，样子荒唐可笑。如今走在蒙帕纳司大街上，看一看那些和我当年一样的年轻人，以他们为蓝本构想几篇故事，仍不失为人生乐事。无事可做的时候，我就搭乘出租车去多姆咖啡店怀怀旧。昔日的景象不复存在，它已不再是放荡不羁的文化人聚会的场所，而成了附近小商小贩的啜饮之地，顾客中也有塞纳河对岸跑来的外乡人，他们怀着一线希望，想看看一个业已消亡的世界留下的痕迹。当然，来的人中间仍有学生、画家和作家，但多为外国人。坐在这里，既可以听到法语，也可以听到俄语、西班牙语、德语和英语。我有一种感觉，他们的话题跟我们四十年前的话题基本是一样的，只不过他们谈的是毕加索而非马奈，是安德烈·布勒东[84]而非纪尧姆·阿波利奈尔[85]。对这些人我有一种亲切的感觉。来到巴黎后，大约有两个星期的时间了。一天傍晚，我去多姆咖啡店小饮，露台上人多，只好在前排找一张桌子坐下。天气晴暖。法国梧桐树上叶子的苞芽待出，空气中飘荡着巴黎所特有的那种闲散、轻松和欢快的气氛。我的内心一片宁静——这不是呆滞的宁静，而是充满了活力的宁静。突然，一个男子从旁边走过时，却停住了脚步，咧嘴一笑，露出一口雪白的牙齿，冲着我打招呼道：“你好！”我白了他一眼。此人瘦高个，没有戴帽子，乱蓬蓬的深棕色头发早就该剪了，上嘴唇和下巴被浓密的棕色胡须遮得严严实实，额头和脖子被太阳晒成了紫红色。他穿一件破衬衫，没有打领带，一件旧旧的棕色外套，下穿一条褴褛的灰裤子。看他的模样像个叫花子，我坚信自己和此人素不相识。在我看来，他就是那种流落于巴黎街头的混混，八成会编出一套落难的故事，从我手中骗几个法郎去吃顿晚饭，找个住宿的地方。他站在我面前，双手插兜，露出雪白的牙齿，黑眼睛里含着笑意。

“你记不得我啦？”他问。

“我从来就没有见过你。”

我准备给他二十法郎把他打发走，可又觉得无法容忍他撒谎，好像我们以前认识似的。

“我是拉里。”他说。

“我的天呀！快请坐！”

他嘿嘿一笑，趋前一步，在我旁边的空椅子上坐了下来。

“来杯喝的！”我冲着跑堂的侍者喊了一声，然后又对拉里说道：“你满脸的胡子，怎么能叫我认出来呢？”

侍者走过来，拉里点了杯橘子水。我仔细打量拉里，想起了他眼睛的特别之处——那虹膜和瞳孔的颜色一样黑，让他的目光显得专注和神秘。

“你来巴黎多长时间了？”我问。

“一个月。”

“预备待下去吗？”

“待一段时间吧。”

我一边问话，脑子却转个不停。我注意到他的裤脚已毛了边，上衣的胳膊肘处有几个窟窿眼，一副落魄相，跟我在东方港口碰见过的流浪汉没什么两样。那些日子，人们对经济大萧条的后果久久难忘，于是我便觉得一定是一九二九年的经济大崩溃使他成了个穷光蛋。我不喜欢绕着圈子说话，此时干脆开门见山地问道：

“你是不是落了难？”

“哪里的话。我挺好的。你怎么会这么想？”

“哦，你看上去像是吃施舍饭的，身上破衣烂衫，还不如扔到垃圾箱里好。”

“有这么糟吗？这我从来没有想到过。其实，我计划着添几件零用品，可就是没有能付诸实施。”

我觉得他是难为情或者放不下架子，所以不愿意再听他支吾下去。

“别充好汉了，拉里。我不是百万富翁，但也不穷。如果你缺钱，就让我借给你几千法郎吧。这不会叫我破产的。”

他哈哈大笑起来。

“多谢。不过，我并不缺钱。我自己的钱都花不完呢。”

“经济大崩溃中没受冲击吗？”

“哦，那次大崩溃没有冲击到我。我把所有的钱都买了政府公债。不知道政府公债是不是也贬值了。我没有打听过，只知道山姆大叔[86]仍一如既往地支付着利息。实际上，这几年我的花销很小，手头宽裕着呢。”

“那么，你是从哪里过来的？”

“从印度。”

“哦，我听说你去了那里，是伊莎贝尔告诉我的。她好像认识你在芝加哥那家银行的经理。”

“伊莎贝尔？你是什么时候见到她的？”

“昨天。”

“她不会在巴黎吧？”

“实际上，她在巴黎呢，住在艾略特·邓普顿的那套公寓里。”

“太好了。我想见见她。”

我们说这些话时，我一直在留意观察他的眼神，发现他的眼睛里有很自然的诧异和喜悦，没有复杂的成分。

“格雷也住在那里。你知道他们结婚了吗？”

“知道。鲍勃大叔，也就是我的监护人纳尔逊医生，曾经写信告诉过我。他几年前过世了。”

我想起纳尔逊医生可能是他和芝加哥以及那边的朋友之间的唯一联系，如今这条线一断，他大概对这几年发生的事情一无所知。于是我告诉他伊莎贝尔生了两个女儿，亨利·马图林和路易莎·布雷德利离开了人世，说格雷已经破产，还讲了讲艾略特的义举。

“艾略特也在巴黎吗？”

“不在。”

四十年来，艾略特第一次不在巴黎过春天。尽管看上去显年轻，他毕竟也是七旬老者了。在这古稀之年，他经常感到周身乏力，身体欠佳。除了散步，他把别的锻炼项目都逐渐放弃了。他对自己的健康状况深感忧虑。他的医生每个星期来探视两次，在他的两边屁股上轮流打针，皮下注射一种当时流行的针剂。每次吃饭，不论在家里或者在外面，他总要从口袋里掏出个小金盒子，取出一粒药片吞下去，就像履行宗教仪式一样郑重其事。医生劝他去蒙特卡蒂尼疗养，那是意大利北部的一个温泉疗养场。这之后，他提出想到威尼斯去寻找一个圣洗池，准备安放在他的那座罗马式教堂里。他对巴黎的钟爱已大不如从前了，原因是他觉得巴黎的社交生活一年不如一年。他不喜欢年纪大的人，遇到有人请客，请的都是他这般年纪的人，他就觉得心中不快。而见了年轻人，他又觉得他们浅薄。装修他出资建造的那座教堂，如今成了他生活中主要的兴趣所在；在这上面，他大量购买艺术品，宣泄自己对艺术的那种根深蒂固的热情，同时感到心安理得，觉得是在为上帝效力。他在罗马找到一座蜜黄色石头砌的基督教早期的祭坛，又在佛罗伦萨花了六个月时间讨价还价，买了一块锡耶纳派[87]的三幅一体的浮雕图，将浮雕图镶嵌在祭坛上方。

随后，拉里问我格雷喜不喜欢巴黎。

“他在这儿恐怕有一种失落感。”

我试图向他描述格雷给我留下的印象。拉里听着，眼睛一眨不眨，死死盯着我的脸，一副若有所思的表情。不知怎么的，我觉得他不是用耳朵在听，而用的是内心深处一种更为敏感的器官。这让我觉得怪兮兮的，感到有点不太舒服。

“不过，你还是自己看看吧。”我末了说。

“好的。我很想见见他们。在电话簿上，我想是能够找到他们的住址的。”

“不过有一点：假如你不想把他们的魂都吓掉，不想吓得孩子们喊起来，劝你先去剃个头，把胡子刮刮。”

他一听笑了起来。

“我正打算这么做呢。显然没有必要使自己这么招眼。”

“除此之外，你还应该给自己弄一套新衣服。”

“我这一身也许真算得上衣衫褴褛了。临离开印度的时候，我才发现自己只有身上的这套行头了。”

拉里说到这里，看了看我穿的衣服，问我是哪家裁缝做的。我告诉了他，但又补充了一句，说这家裁缝在伦敦，可能无法为他效力。我们撇开此事不提，又聊起了格雷和伊莎贝尔来。

“他们俩我是经常见的。”我说道，“他们把日子过得十分幸福。我一直没机会跟格雷单独交谈，其实就是单独交谈，他也不会跟我谈伊莎贝尔的。不过，我知道他对伊莎贝尔的感情非常深。静下来的时候，他表情阴郁、目光茫然，而一看到伊莎贝尔，他的眼睛里便有了柔情爱意，见了令人感动。我有一种感觉，在那些风风雨雨中，伊莎贝尔始终站在他身旁，坚如磐石，此恩此情他终生难忘。见了面，你会发现伊莎贝尔变了样。”我没告诉他，伊莎贝尔现在之美是以前任何时候都无法比拟的。以前的那个漂亮的高个子女孩已经变成了一个端庄典雅、仪态万方的美少妇，这一蜕变的过程谁知道他能不能辨得出来。世间有些男人，他们只喜欢天生的丽质，而不喜欢修饰出来的美。“她对格雷很好，尽了最大的力量帮助他恢复自信心。”我继续说道。

说话间，天色渐晚，我问拉里愿不愿跟我到街上找个地方吃晚饭。

“不了，我就不去了。谢谢。”他回答说，“我得走了。”

他站起来，亲亲热热点了个头，抽身离去，出了咖啡店，走到了人行道上。

四

次日见到格雷和伊莎贝尔，我把巧遇拉里的事跟他们讲了，他们俩和我当初一样，也颇感意外。

“能见见他是件让人开心的事。”伊莎贝尔说，“这就给他打个电话吧。”

我这才想起自己忘记问他住在哪里了。为此，伊莎贝尔把我狠狠埋怨了几句。

“即便我问他，他也不一定会告诉我的。”我笑着辩白，“也许，这是我的潜意识在作怪吧。难道你忘了，他是从来都不喜欢把自己的住处告诉别人的。他怪也怪在这一点上。他随时都可能从哪个地方钻出来。”

“他就是这种人，”格雷说，“过去亦是如此，来无影去无踪，行迹难定，今天在此，明日在彼。你明明看见他在一个房间里，想着过会儿去跟他打个招呼，但一转身他就不见了。”

“他历来我行我素，十分叫人生气。”伊莎贝尔说，“这一点是谁都无法否认的。咱们只好等着了，他愿来的时候自然会来的。”

那天他没有来，第二天也没有来，第三天亦没有见到他的影子。伊莎贝尔抱怨起来，说这件事是我编出来的，纯粹想惹她生气。我信誓旦旦地说自己没有撒谎，并设想出了一些拉里没来的原因向她解释。不过，我说的这些原因都是站不住脚的。我心中暗忖，他可能经过仔细考虑，决定不来见格雷和伊莎贝尔了，于是一走了之，离开巴黎到别的地方去了。我觉得他如闲云野鹤四处游荡，只凭一时高兴、一时兴起，或者说一时心血来潮，便倏忽不见。

最后，他终于露面了。那是个雨天，格雷没有去莫特芳丹打球。我们三个人在一起——伊莎贝尔和我在喝茶，格雷端着一杯掺过毕雷矿泉水[88]的威士忌细啜慢饮。管家打开房门，拉里迈着四方步走了进来。伊莎贝尔欢叫一声像弹簧一样跳了起来，冲上去扑进他的怀里，在他的脸上左亲右亲。格雷的一张红红胖胖的脸比平时更红了，热情地拉住他的手。

“哈，看见你真让人高兴，拉里。”格雷说道，激动得声音都有些哽咽了。

伊莎贝尔咬着嘴唇，看得出她是强忍住才没有哭出声来。

“来喝杯酒，老伙计。”格雷颤抖着声音说。

小两口见到这位浪迹天涯的朋友感到由衷的高兴，这幅场景见了叫人为之动容。一想到自己在他们心中占有如此重要的位置，拉里的心情一定会非常愉快的。只见他开心地绽出了笑容。但我觉得他内心深处是相当冷静的。寒暄间，他一眼看到了桌子上的茶具。

“我想喝杯茶。”他说道。

“啧，啧，怎么能喝茶呢。”格雷嚷嚷道，“咱们喝瓶香槟酒吧。”

“我喜欢喝茶。”拉里笑吟吟地说。

他的冷静对那两口子产生了影响，而这恐怕正是他想看到的。小两口平静了下来，但他们看他的眼神里仍充满了友爱。我并不是说，拉里对别人由衷的喜悦，报以无礼的冷漠；恰恰相反，他表现得异常彬彬有礼、和蔼可亲。但在他的言谈举止中隐约可见一种只能称之为超然的东西，至于那东西有着什么深层的含义我却一无所知。

“你真坏，为什么不早点儿来看望我们？”伊莎贝尔佯怒嗔怪道，“这五天里，我天天都倚在窗口盼你来呢。每次门铃响，我的心都要跳到嗓子眼里了，要费很大的劲才能把它重新咽下去。”

拉里嘿嘿嘿一阵傻笑。

“毛姆先生说我的样子太可怕，像个野蛮人，你们的管家不会叫我进门的。所以，我飞到伦敦购置新装了。”

“你用不着跑那么老远，”我笑笑说，“在春天百货公司或百丽服饰店就可以买到现成的衣服。”

“我觉得既然要购置衣服，就最好弄有格调的。再说，我已经有十年没有在欧洲买衣服了。于是我就去找你的那个裁缝，说我想做套衣服，三天内取货。他说得用两个星期，后来折中定为四天。这不，一小时前，我刚从伦敦飞了回来。”

他穿着一套蓝色哔叽西服，对他瘦削的身材来说极为合体，内穿一件软领白衬衣，系一条蓝色丝绸领带，脚蹬一双棕色的鞋子。他剪了个短发，刮光了脸上的胡子，不仅看上去干净整洁，而且很入时，与以前相比判若两人。由于太瘦，颧骨突出，太阳穴凹陷，深藏在眼窝里的那双眸子比我记忆中的那双更显得大了。尽管如此，他的相貌仍是那般英俊潇洒、风流倜傥，一张晒黑了的、没有皱纹的脸让他显得异常年轻。他和格雷同为三十出头的人（他比格雷只小一岁），但格雷看上去要老十岁，而他则要年轻十岁。由于是个大块头，格雷动作迟缓、笨拙，拉里的一举一动却轻盈、敏捷。拉里像个小男孩一般，欢快和活泼，而我深切感觉到他的内心一片宁静——他已经不再是从前我认识的那个小青年了。谈话在轻松的气氛中进行着，这在老朋友之间是很自然的，因为他们有着许多共同的记忆。格雷和伊莎贝尔不时加几条芝加哥新闻进去，都是些零星花絮，一件连着一件，引得笑声朗朗。我一直有一个印象，就是拉里虽则笑得很爽朗，听伊莎贝尔滔滔不绝讲话时显得很高兴，他的内心却异常落寞。我觉得他并不是假装高兴；他生性纯真，不会弄虚作假；他的高兴显然是真诚的。但我感到在他的内心世界里有一样东西，不知该称之为知性、感性，抑或力量，使得他莫名其妙地有点落落寡合。

两个小姑娘被领了进来，和拉里见过，彬彬有礼地冲着拉里行了个屈膝礼。拉里伸出手来，柔和的眼睛里含着慈祥和仁爱望着她们。小姑娘们握了他的手，两双眼睛天真地看着他。伊莎贝尔喜滋滋地告诉拉里，说她们的功课都很不错，随后给了她们每人一块甜点心，把她们支走了。

“你们睡觉时，我去给你们念十分钟的书。”

此时此刻，伊莎贝尔沉浸在与拉里重逢的喜悦中，不愿意受到打搅。小姑娘们走上前跟她们的父亲道晚安。那个大块头汉子把她们搂在怀里吻了吻，红脸上涌起浓浓的爱意，见了让人感动。谁都看得出他爱她们，为她们感到自豪。女儿走后，他唇边浮起甜蜜的微笑，对拉里说道：

“这俩孩子不错吧，是不是？”

伊莎贝尔深情地望了他一眼。

“要是由着格雷胡来，他会把她们惯坏的。这个大坏蛋，他会把我饿死，也要买来鱼子酱和鹅肝[89]给孩子吃，让她们吃得发撑。”

格雷笑着瞧了瞧她说：“这你就说得不对了，你心里最清楚。我爱你爱得要发疯。”

伊莎贝尔的眼里涌出了会心的笑意。她对格雷的爱心知肚明，并为此感到高兴。多么幸福的一对夫妻！

她提出要留我们吃晚饭，我觉得他们也许愿意和拉里单独说说话，便推说有事，而她坚决不听我解释，说道：

“我去告诉玛丽在汤里多放一根胡萝卜，就够四个人吃的了。还有只鸡，你和格雷可以吃腿，我和拉里吃翅膀。她还会做奶蛋酥的，足够大家享用。”

格雷似乎也想让我留下。我本来就不想走，于是便来了个恭敬不如从命。

等待吃饭的当儿，伊莎贝尔把他们的遭遇从头到尾讲了一遍（他们的情况我曾经给拉里简单介绍过）。那段悲惨的往事她讲起来虽然语调尽可能轻松，但格雷的脸上却布上了一层阴云。她见了，想使格雷高兴起来，便说道：

“现在，一切都过去了。我们栽过跟头，但前途是光明的。到了峰回路转的时候，格雷就找个好工作，挣他个几百万块。”

鸡尾酒送了进来。两杯酒下肚，可怜的格雷情绪有所好转。我看见拉里虽然拿了一杯酒，却碰也没碰。格雷没有注意到这个，要再敬他一杯，被他婉拒了。然后，大家洗了手，坐下来吃晚饭。格雷要来一瓶香槟酒，可是管家给拉里倒酒时，他却说自己不想喝。

“嗨，你必须喝一点。”伊莎贝尔嚷嚷道，“这是艾略特舅舅最好的酒，只用来招待特殊的贵客。”

“实话说，我喜欢喝水。在东方待久了，觉得喝干净水是最好的。”

“今天这是特殊场合嘛。”

“好吧。那我就喝一杯吧。”

饭菜香喷喷的。但我和伊莎贝尔都注意到拉里吃得很少。伊莎贝尔也许觉得她只顾自己说话，拉里只有听的份儿，无机会插话，于是便问他在这十年未见的时间里都干了些什么。拉里回答时语气坦率、真诚，但含糊其词，等于没有告诉我们多少情况。

“哦，瞎转悠呗。在德国待了一年，又到西班牙和意大利待了些时间。后来又去东方游荡了一阵子。”

“你这是刚从哪里来的？”

“从印度。”

“你在印度待了多久？”

“五年。”

“玩得痛快吗？”格雷问，“去打老虎了吗？”

“没有。”拉里笑了笑说。

“你在印度一待就是五年，都做些什么呢？”伊莎贝尔问。

“四处游玩。”拉里回答说，脸上露出一丝玩世不恭的微笑。

“‘绳子魔术’[90]是怎么回事？”格雷问，“你见他们表演过吗？”

“没有，没见过。”

“那你都见到过什么呢？”

“那就多了。”

此时，我向拉里提了一个问题：

“瑜伽修行者是不是真的具有人们所说的超自然的能力？”

“说不上来。我只能告诉你，在印度，人们都普遍这么认为。不过，智者并不看重这种能力，认为它会妨碍修真。记得一位智者给我讲过一个故事，说的是一个瑜伽师来到河边，苦于身上没钱，摆渡的船夫拒绝让他上船，于是瑜伽师踏水而去，如履平地，径直抵达对岸。讲到这里，智者鄙夷地耸了耸肩说：‘这样的雕虫小技不值钱，只顶得上乘渡船用的一个铜板。’”

“你觉得瑜伽师真的能踏水如履平地吗？”格雷问道。

“那位智者是这么说的，显然他相信是真的。”

听拉里说话是一种享受，因为他声音纯美如天籁之音，圆润、轻快，而不低沉，抑扬顿挫恰到好处。饭后，大家回到客厅里喝咖啡。我没去过印度，急切想了解更多的情况。

“你跟作家和思想家有过接触吗？”我问。

“我发现你把作家和思想家分成了两个群体。”伊莎贝尔取笑我说。

“当然要跟他们接触了。”拉里回答道。

“你是怎么和他们交流的？用英语吗？”

“有意思的是，他们即便会说英语，也说得不大好，理解上就更差了。我学了印度斯坦语，后来去南方，又学了泰米尔语，反正足够交流用的了。”

“你现在懂多少种语言呀，拉里？”

“哦，说不准，也就是六七种吧。”

“我还想多了解一点瑜伽师的情况。”伊莎贝尔说，“你和他们有没有关系很熟的？”

“和几位终年苦修的瑜伽师倒是非常熟。”拉里笑了笑说，“我曾在一个苦修林住过两年。”

“两年？苦修林是个什么样的地方？”

“这个嘛，你也可以把它叫作隐居地吧。有些圣人喜欢过独居生活，或在庙里，或在林中，或在喜马拉雅山山麓。还有一些圣人广招门徒。一些乐善好施的人为了积累功德，常常为自己崇拜的瑜伽圣人建造房屋，有大的也有小的，门徒们也随着自己的恩师一块居住，住在晾台上、厨房里（如果有厨房的话），或者栖身于树下。我在这样的苦修林中有一个斗室，刚能放得下我的行军床、桌椅和书架。”

“这地方在哪儿？”我问。

“在特拉凡哥尔。那儿风景如画，青山翠谷，细水蜿蜒流淌。山中有老虎、豹子、大象和野牛，而苦修林位于环礁湖畔，周围椰子树和槟榔树郁郁葱葱。它距离最邻近的城镇也有三四英里远，但人们从镇上或更远的地方纷至沓来，有的步行，有的坐牛车，来听瑜伽圣人宣讲（如果他有兴致的话），或者仅仅坐在圣人的脚下，享受圣人所带来的那一份静谧和吉祥——那份静谧和吉祥犹如花香弥漫在空气中。”

格雷在椅子上不安地扭动着身子。我猜想可能是因为谈话转了弯，让他感到不耐烦了。

“来杯酒吗？”他问我。

“不喝。谢谢。”

“哦，我可要喝一杯了。你喝不喝，伊莎贝尔？”

他把巨大、沉重的身躯从椅子上抬起来，向吧台走去，那儿放着威士忌、毕雷矿泉水以及玻璃杯。

“那地方还有别的白人吗？”

“没有了。只有我一个白人。”

“两年的时间，你怎么能熬得下来？”

“一眨眼就过去了。以前过日子，就是几天好像也要比这两年漫长得多呢。”

“那么长的时间，你都干些什么呀？”

“看书、长距离散步、湖上荡舟，以及冥思。冥思十分耗费精力，两三个小时就会叫你精疲力竭，仿佛开车一口气跑了五百英里的路一样，只想好好休息一下。”

伊莎贝尔微微皱了皱眉头。她心里一片迷茫，恐怕也有点害怕。她可能有一种想法，这个几小时前走进屋来的拉里，虽然表面上没有变化，好像仍和从前一样开朗和友爱，但和她过去认识的那个拉里，那个非常坦率、平易、欢快、任性不听话但讨人喜欢的拉里已经不是一个人了。她曾经失去了他，如今重逢，起先以为他还是昔日的拉里，尽管历尽沧桑，却依旧属于她。然而现在，她好像抓了一把阳光在手里，那阳光从指头缝里溜掉了。这让她有点沮丧。那天晚上，我一直在盯着她瞧（这在我历来都是赏心悦目的事）。我发现她眼里充满着喜悦在看拉里那修剪得很整齐的脑袋（两只小耳朵紧贴着那脑袋壳），当她的目光落在拉里凹陷的太阳穴和消瘦的脸颊上时，眼神由喜转忧。她又望望他那瘦长的手——那双手虽然很瘦，却强壮有力。后来，她的目光移向了他那富于表情的嘴——那张嘴的嘴形好看，丰满但不性感，接着又去看他那平展的额头和端正的鼻子。他穿一身新装，虽没有艾略特的那种整洁、风雅，却落拓不羁、潇洒自如，好像那是一身天天穿的日常衣服似的。我觉得他似乎激起了伊莎贝尔的一种舐犊之情，而这种感情在她和自己的女儿之间并不曾见。她已有了当母亲的经历，而他看上去还像个孩子。她的神情中有一种母性的骄傲，一种为长大成人的儿子而产生的骄傲——那儿子说话有条有理，引得大家侧耳倾听，仿佛他在讲述真理。我觉得她并没有真正理解他话中的含意。

至此，我的话仍未问完。

“你的瑜伽师是个什么样子？”

“你指的是外表吧？这个嘛，个子不高，不胖也不瘦，浅棕色皮肤，脸刮得光光的，一头白发剪得很短，身上除掉一块围腰布外，什么也不穿，但看上去就和布克兄弟男装公司[91]广告牌上的那个年轻男子一样干净利落，一样穿着得体。”

“他究竟有什么特殊之处如此吸引你呢？”

拉里凝神看着我整整有一分钟，最后才做出了回答。他那双深陷在眼窝里的眼睛目光炯炯，好像要射入我的灵魂深处一样。

“圣徒气息。”

他的回答使我感到有点意外。在这个陈设着精美家具、墙上挂着名画的房间里，这句话就像浴缸里溢出的水从天花板上漏下来，啪嗒一声落在了地面上。

“咱们都读过圣徒传，其中有圣佛兰西斯[92]，有十字架的圣约翰[93]，但那都是几百年前的事了。我从未想到过能遇见一个仍活在世上的圣徒。我第一次见到他，就坚定不移地相信他是个圣徒。那是一段美妙的人生经历。”

“你的收获是什么呢？”

“宁静。”他脱口而出，脸上淡淡一笑。随后，他突然站起身说：“我得走了。”

“噢，不要走，拉里。”伊莎贝尔叫了起来，“时间还早呢。”

“晚安。”他说道，脸上仍挂着微笑，丝毫没有理会伊莎贝尔的央求。他在伊莎贝尔的面颊上亲了亲，对她说道：“过一两天我再来看你们。”

“你住在哪里？我给你打电话。”

“哦，劝你别找这个麻烦了。你也知道在巴黎打个电话有多难。再说，我们那儿的电话常常出毛病。”

拉里不愿说出住址，利落地摆脱了窘境，我见了心里不由发笑。隐瞒住址成了他的一个古怪的特征。我提出要请大家后天晚上去布伦园林[94]吃饭。在这样四处飘香的春天，露天坐在大树下面吃饭，确是一大享受。到时候，可以坐上格雷开的汽车一同前往。我跟拉里一同出了门，本想陪他走一段路，可一到街上他就跟我握了握手，快步走掉了。他走后，我坐上了一辆出租车。

五

我们约好在公寓里碰头，先喝杯鸡尾酒，然后出发。我先于拉里一步抵达公寓。我约他们去的是一家很讲究的餐馆，出入那儿的女子一般都穿得光彩照人，所以我觉得伊莎贝尔也一定会盛装打扮。我坚信不疑：她一定不愿输给别的女人。可谁知却见她穿着一件朴素的羊毛长衫。

“格雷的头痛病又发作了。”她说，“他痛苦得不行，我不能丢下他不管。我叮咛了厨娘，让她伺候孩子们吃完饭就可以走了。我必须亲自下厨，给格雷做点饭让他吃下去。你和拉里最好自己去吧。”

“格雷在床上躺着吗？”

“没有。头痛的时候，他从来都不肯躺到床上的。谁都知道病了就应该卧床，可他硬是不肯嘛。他正在书房里呢。”

这是个小房间，镶着棕色和金黄色壁板——壁板是艾略特从一座古堡里弄来的。书籍都放在镀金的格子柜里，上了锁，防止外人翻阅，也许这样做倒好，因为这些书大部分是十八世纪的有插图的淫秽书籍，不过，用摩洛哥皮面装订起来，看上去倒十分正经。伊莎贝尔领我进去时，格雷正弓着身子坐在一张大皮椅子上，脚下乱扔着一些画报。他闭着眼睛，往日的那张红脸呈现出死灰色，显然痛苦万分。他打算站起来，但我拦住了他。

“你给他吃阿司匹林了没有？”我问伊莎贝尔。

“阿司匹林一点用都不顶。我有个美国药方，但是，吃了也不见效。”

“唉，别管我了，亲爱的。”格雷说，“明天我就会好的。”他勉强一笑。“很对不起，成了你们的累赘。”末了，他冲我说道：“你们都走吧，去布伦园林吧。”

“那怎么可能呢。”伊莎贝尔说，“你痛苦得死去活来，你想我能玩得开心吗？”

“可怜的小妇人，看来她是赖上我了。”格雷说完，合上了眼睛。

接着，他的脸突然抽搐起来，看得出他的脑袋里痛如刀割。这时，房门被轻轻推开了，拉里走了进来。伊莎贝尔把情形告诉了他。

“真糟糕。”拉里同情地看了一眼格雷说，“有什么办法能解除他的病痛吗？”

“什么办法都没有。”格雷仍闭着眼睛说道，“只有一个办法，那就是让我一个人待着。你们都走吧，去玩你们的吧。”

我觉得唯有如此才是合乎理性的，却又怕伊莎贝尔心里过意不去不会同意。

“让我来看看能不能帮你一把，好不好？”拉里问。

“谁也帮不了我。”格雷有气无力地说，“头痛起来真能要我的命。有时候希望还不如一死了之。”

“要说我帮你，表达上不准确。我的意思是可以协助你自救。”

格雷慢慢睁开了眼睛，看了看拉里。

“怎么个协助法？”

拉里从口袋里取出一样东西，看上去像枚银币，把它放进了格雷的手心。

“把这硬币握紧，手背朝上。我叫你怎么做你就怎么做。不要用太大的劲，只要把它攥在手心即可。不等我数到二十，你的手就会张开，银币便会落到地上。”

格雷按他的吩咐做了。拉里坐到写字台前，开始数数。我和伊莎贝尔站在一旁观看。一，二，三，四……数到十五时，格雷的手一动不动，后来好像抖了一下。不能说我看见，而只能说有个印象——他那紧攥着的手指慢慢在松开。最先离开拳头的是大拇指。我清清楚楚看见他的手指在颤动。当拉里数到十九时，银币从格雷的手里掉下来，滚到了我的脚边。我拾起来，发现它沉甸甸的，呈不规则形状，银币的一面有一个年轻人的浮雕像，我认出那是亚历山大大帝[95]。格雷望着自己的手，一脸的困惑。

“不是我有意让银币掉落的，”格雷说，“是它自己落下去的。”

他坐在皮椅子里，右臂架在椅子扶手上。

“你坐在这椅子上舒服吗？”拉里问。

“头痛欲裂的时候，只有坐在这儿才感到舒服一点。”

“好，让你自己彻底放松。不要紧张，不要慌，什么都不要做，一切顺其自然。不等我数到二十，你的右胳膊将会从椅子的扶手上抬起，直至你的手举过头顶。一，二，三，四……”

他慢慢数着数，声音优美，如银铃一般。他数到九的时候，我看见格雷的手几乎难以察觉地动了动，从皮面的扶手上抬起了大约有一英寸，然后稍微停顿了一下。

“十，十一，十二……”

起先，手震动了一下，接着是整个胳臂开始向上移动，不再架在椅子扶手上了。伊莎贝尔有点惊恐，抓住了我的手。当时的情形真是奇怪，那胳膊像是在不由自主地移动。我从来没有见过谁梦游过，但可以想象梦游的人走动起来就像格雷的手臂移动一样古怪，看上去不像是靠意志驱动的。我觉得，要是靠意志的力量，是很难把胳膊抬得那么缓慢、那么平稳。这给人的印象是：一种不受大脑控制的潜意识力量在将他的胳膊抬起，动作就像活塞在汽缸里一上一下的，非常缓慢。

“十五，十六，十七……”

那一个个的数字说出来，简直慢极了，就像是盥洗室里的一个没关严的水龙头在滴水，一个水珠一个水珠慢慢地朝下落。格雷的胳臂一点点向上抬，直至把手举过头顶。当拉里说完最后一个数字时，他的胳臂自动落回到了椅子扶手上。

“不是我要抬胳膊的，”格雷说，“是它自己抬起来的，我就是想停也停不下来的。”

拉里淡淡地一笑。

“怎么样都不当紧，主要是想让你对我产生信心。那块希腊硬币呢？”

我把硬币递给了他。

“你把硬币攥在手里。”格雷把硬币接了过去。拉里看着表又说道：“现在是八点十三分。用不了一分钟，你的眼皮就会发沉，那时你会闭上眼，然后入睡。睡上六分钟，到了八点二十，你就会醒来。醒来后，你就不再感到头痛了。”

我和伊莎贝尔都没有说话，眼睛盯着拉里看。拉里不再言语，目光注视着格雷——那目光虽落在格雷身上，却好像不是在看他，而是穿越他的躯体瞟向他方。屋里一片沉寂，出奇的静，就像夜间花园里那般鸦雀无声。突然，我觉得伊莎贝尔抓着我的那只手猛地一紧。我望望格雷，只见他双眼紧闭，呼吸通畅、均匀，已酣然入睡。大家都站在那儿，那段时间似乎永无止境似的。我的烟瘾犯了，却又不敢点烟。拉里一动不动，目光飘向远方不知道哪个地方，木木地睁着眼，仿佛处于恍惚状态。蓦然，他好像松弛了下来，眼睛里的神情恢复了正常。他看了看表。而就在他看表之际，格雷睁开了眼睛。

“哎呀！”他说道，“我肯定是睡着了。”接着，他发了发愣。我注意到他那惨白的脸色不见了。“我的头不痛了。”

“很好。”拉里说，“抽根烟，然后咱们一起出去吃晚饭。”

“这简直是个奇迹。我觉得舒服极了。你这是怎么弄的？”

“不是我弄出来的。奇迹是你自己创造的。”

伊莎贝尔去换衣服。趁此机会，我和格雷喝了杯鸡尾酒。拉里明显不愿再提刚才的事，格雷却不肯罢休，仍在滔滔不绝地讲着。他怎么也弄不明白那一切是怎么发生的。

“起初我并不相信你会有什么办法。”他说道，“我听从你的吩咐，只是因为我懒得跟你斗嘴。”

接下来，他把自己的病情形容了一番，说他头痛如山倒，病去如抽丝，发作之后身体处于崩溃边缘。而这一次，醒来后精力充沛如初，这叫他简直弄不清是怎么回事。伊莎贝尔换衣归来，但见她穿一件我从未见过的拖地长裙，白颜色的，可能是用一种叫罗马坎平绉的布料做的，外镶一圈黑纱边。我不由心想，她打扮得如此漂亮，全是为了叫我们看了高兴。

到了马德里城堡，那儿是一片欢乐的海洋，大家玩得兴高采烈。拉里谈笑风生、趣话连篇（我以前从未见他这么风趣过），引得大伙儿哈哈大笑。我有一种感觉，他这样做是为了转移我们的注意力，免得再询问他那超凡的能力。不过，伊莎贝尔可是个意志坚强的女子。她可以做些顺水行舟的事，但最终好奇心得不到满足的她是不会罢休的。吃过饭后，大家喝咖啡和品酒。这时，伊莎贝尔可能觉得美味佳肴、香醪美酿以及友好的交谈削弱了拉里的防线，于是就将一双明眸盯住拉里，说道：

“给我们讲一讲你是怎么把格雷的头痛病治好的。”

“那个过程你们自己都看见了么。”拉里笑笑说。

“这种妙手回春的本事是在印度学的吧？”

“是的。”

“这病叫他受尽了洋罪。你能不能把他彻底治好？”

“不知道。也许可以吧。”

“这会彻底改变他的生活。他的头痛症一发作，两天两夜都没有行为能力，就是有工作也干不好的。而不干工作，他是绝不会开心的。”

“要知道，我是无法创造奇迹的。”

“可你已经创造了，我可是亲眼所见的。”

“不，那不是奇迹。我只是向他灌输了一种想法，其余的都是他自己完成的。”拉里说到此处，转过头问格雷：“明天你干什么？”

“打高尔夫。”

“我明天六点到你们府上，咱们坐下来谈谈。”拉里说完，冲着伊莎贝尔莞尔一笑，问道：“伊莎贝尔，十年没和你跳舞了，愿不愿看看我是否还能舞起来？”

六

此后，我们和拉里经常见面。在接下来的一个星期里，他天天来公寓找格雷，到书房里把门关上，二人一待就是半个小时。看上去，他在劝说格雷“悬崖勒马”（这是他开玩笑说的），走出沮丧的阴影，而格雷像个乖孩子一样百依百顺。从格雷所说的只言片语中我听得出来，拉里在试图帮助他恢复已经失去的自信心。大约在十天以后，格雷的头痛又发作了，那天碰巧拉里要到傍晚才来。这次的病来势汹汹，而格雷笃信拉里的神力，认为只要把拉里找来，就可以手到病除。可是，他们不知道他的住址，伊莎贝尔打电话问我，我也不知道。最后，拉里终于来了，解除了格雷的病痛。格雷问他住在哪里，以便紧急时可以立刻找到他。他只是笑了笑。

“你打电话给美国运通公司，留下口信就行了。我每天上午都会和他们通话的。”

伊莎贝尔后来问我拉里为什么对自己的住址讳莫如深。她说他以前也是遮遮掩掩的，结果发现他住在拉丁区的一家三流旅馆里，没什么神秘的。

“我不太清楚。”我回答说，“也可能是故作玄虚吧，其实并没有什么大不了的。也许他的精神世界需要隐私，于是产生一种古怪的心理，使得他不愿暴露自己的住址。”

“老天，你这都是在说些什么呀？”她有点急躁地说。

“他和咱们大家在一起的时候，显得平易近人、热情友好，但你会觉得他有些超然，仿佛不愿把自己完全暴露出来，而是将某样东西隐藏在了他灵魂深处的一间密室里。这种现象你难道没注意到吗？究竟是什么使他和咱们拉开了距离就不得而知了，不知是紧张的情绪、某种秘密、一种希冀，抑或是对知识的追求在其中产生了影响。”

“我从小就认识拉里，对他是知根知底的。”伊莎贝尔耐不住性子说道。

“有时候，我觉得他就像个优秀的演员，在一出难登大雅的戏里把角色演得无懈可击，就像《女店主》里的爱琳诺拉·杜丝[96]那样。”

伊莎贝尔沉吟片刻，然后说道：

“你的意思我想我是知道的。有的时候大家在一起玩得很开心，他跟所有的人一样乐悠悠的。可是，突然你会有一种感觉，觉得他好像变成了一缕青烟飘然而去，你想抓都抓不住。你说是什么原因叫他变得如此古怪呢？”

“也许原因平常得不能再平常了，让人都注意不到。”

“比如说呢？”

“比如说天性善良吧。”

伊莎贝尔听了蛾眉紧蹙。

“希望你别说这种话，让人心里边挺不是滋味的。”

“是不是戳得你心窝疼啦？”

伊莎贝尔狠狠地看了我一眼，好像这一眼要把我的心看穿一样。随后，她从身旁的桌子上取过一根烟点着，抽了口，将身子向后一靠，望着自己吐出的烟袅袅升到空中。

“你要我走吗？”我问。

“不。”

我半天没说话，只顾盯着她看，欣赏着她那漂亮的鼻子和精致的下巴。

“你是不是非常爱拉里？”我末了问道。

“看你问的，我这一辈子从来都没有爱过别人。”

“那你为什么嫁给了格雷？”

“男大当婚女大当嫁嘛。格雷爱我爱得发疯，妈妈也想让我嫁给他。那时，人人都说我和拉里分手是明智之举。我喜欢格雷，至今仍不改初衷。你都不知道他有多好。天下谁都不会对我那么温柔，那么体贴。他看上去好像脾气不好，是不是？他对我却总是那么柔情似水。有钱的时候，他为我一掷千金，恨不得把天上的月亮也摘给我。一次，我说要有艘游艇就好了，可以乘游艇周游世界。要不是碰上经济大崩溃，他一定会把游艇给我买来的。”

“你把他说得也太好啦。”我低声咕哝了一句。

“我们曾经有过一段美满的岁月。我一直对他心存感激，是他让我生活得十分幸福。”

我看了看她，却没有说话。

“也许，我对他的感情并非真爱，但没有爱情的生活也是可以过得很好的。在内心深处，我渴望得到的是拉里，不过，既然不得相见，我也觉得没有什么。你曾经说过，情人远隔重洋，中间有三千英里的距离，爱情的痛苦是完全可以忍受的。这话你还记得吗？我当时觉得是无稽之谈，现在则认为这话说得很对。”

“如果见到拉里感到痛苦，比较明智的办法是不是不见他呢？”

“痛苦是痛苦，但这是幸福的痛苦。再说，你也知道他是怎么一个人。哪天太阳落山的时候，他可能会像一道影子消失得无影无踪，多年间再也见不到他。”

“你考虑过和格雷离婚没有？”

“我没有理由和他离婚。”

“你们国家的女子一旦有了离婚的念头，任什么都是阻挡不住的。”

她哈哈笑了。

“依你看，她们为什么要离婚呢？”

“你不知道吗？美国女人要求自己的丈夫十全十美，就跟英国女人要求自己的管家完美无瑕一样。”

伊莎贝尔听了，骄傲地把头向后一甩，我真怕她会把脖子都甩断呢。

“就因为格雷不善于表达感情，你就认为他一无可取之处了。”

“你弄错了。”我急忙打断她的话说，“我觉得他身上有一种叫人感动的东西，能够清楚地表达自己的爱。他看你的时候，谁只要瞧瞧他脸上的表情，就知道他对你的爱有多么深、多么真挚了。他爱孩子比你爱得要强烈得多。”

“恐怕接下来你会说我是个坏母亲喽。”

“恰恰相反，我觉得你是个非常出色的母亲。在你的照料下，她们健康和幸福。你关照她们吃得好、大便正常，教导她们懂得礼仪，要求她们做祈祷，她们生病时为她们及时求医，并精心伺候。只不过，你不像格雷那样有十分心思就把十分心思放在她们身上。”

“没有必要那样做。我是个人，应该以人之道对待她们。为人之母，假如把子女作为自己生活的唯一目标，只会对子女有害。”

“你说的一点不错。”

“事实胜于雄辩——她们崇拜我。”

“这些我也留意到了。你是她们理想中的形象：典雅、美丽、高贵。但是，她们和你在一起不像和格雷在一起时那样适意和随便。她们崇拜你，这是事实，但她们爱格雷。”

“格雷是值得爱的。”

我很喜欢她说话直言不讳。她有个最可爱的优点，那就是直面事实，不愠不怒。

“经济大崩溃之后，格雷一蹶不振。有好多个星期，他在办公室里一直工作到深夜。坐在家里，我吓得胆战心惊，生怕他会寻短见，因为他觉得自己已无地自容。你知道，那些人过去对公司、对他父亲、对格雷都引以为自豪，相信他们正直的人格和准确的判断力。灾难之后，我们倾家荡产这还不算，最叫他过意不去的是，那些对他百般信赖的人们也把投进去的钱损失了个精光。他觉得自己早就应当看出一点苗头。我怎么劝也劝不过来，他老觉得都怪他眼拙。”

伊莎贝尔从化妆袋里取出一支口红，涂了涂嘴唇。

“不过，我想说的并不是这些。当时，我们一无所有，只剩下那片农场。我觉得格雷唯有走出是非之地才是出路。于是，把孩子交给妈妈照料，我们俩去了农场。他一直都很喜欢农场，但我们俩从未单独去过，每次去都拖家带口，在一起大家玩得很开心。格雷的枪法好，可是却没有心思打猎。他常常划一条小船，独自一人到沼泽那儿去，一待就是几个小时，在那儿观察野鸟。他划着船在运河上游荡，两边是郁郁葱葱的灯芯草，头顶上只看见一片蓝天。有些日子，运河里的水跟地中海的海水一样湛蓝湛蓝。他回家后，话却很少，只说风景很美。不过，不用他说我也能看出他心里的感受。我知道他的一颗心被那儿的美丽、辽阔和宁静震撼了。太阳落山之前，有短短的一会儿，沼泽地上洒满夕阳的余晖，美不胜收。他常常站在那儿眺望，心里充满了喜悦。他时常骑马到那些荒凉、神秘的林子里跑得老远。那些树林就像梅特林克一出戏剧里的树林一样，灰暗、沉寂，简直有点叫人毛骨悚然。春天里有一段时间（顶多只有半个月），山茱萸鲜花盛开，橡胶树长出了新叶，鲜嫩鲜嫩的绿叶和灰色的西班牙苔藓相映成趣，奏响了一曲欢乐之歌；地上开遍百合花，又大又白，野生的杜鹃花也争奇斗艳。格雷形容不出内心的感受，但他所受到的影响却是深远的。大自然的美丽让他陶然若醉。啊，真不知怎么才能表达那份心境。我只能告诉你，看见那么大一条汉子竟然有那么纯洁和美好的感情，那么如痴如醉，不能不叫人感动，感动得我差点没哭出声。如果天界有上帝的话，格雷已和他近在咫尺。”

伊莎贝尔追溯往事时，情绪有点激动，掏出一块小手绢，小心地把眼角两边晶莹的泪花揩掉。

“你未免太浪漫了吧？”我笑着说，“我有一种感觉，你是希望格雷有那种思想和感情，于是就把它们硬套在了他的头上。”

“如果他没有那种情感，难道我能瞎编吗？我是什么样的人你该知道。除非走在混凝土人行道上，沿街浏览商店的大橱窗，欣赏橱窗里的帽子、皮大衣、钻石手镯和镶金的化妆盒，否则我就不会真正地感到幸福。”

我笑了。有那么一会儿，双方都没有开口。后来，她回到了我们先前谈的话题上。

“我决不会和格雷离婚的。我们风风雨雨经历得太多了。他是绝对离不开我的。要知道，这叫人感到自己很伟大，于是就有了一份责任心。再说……”

“再说什么？”

她斜睨了我一眼，眼睛里闪出一种调皮的神情。我觉得她很可能想说什么，却吃不准我会怎么看待她。

“他床上的功夫很棒。我们结婚已有十载，而他仍热情似火，跟新婚之夜一般。你在你的一个剧本里不是说过，一个男子爱一个女子，时间不会超过五年么？哦，你这话未免有些武断。格雷爱我，一如初婚一般。在这方面，他使我很快乐。你光看我的样子，不会想到我有这要求。其实，我是个肉欲很强的女人。”

“这你就大错特错了。看看你，我会这么想的。”

“哦，这不是什么坏德行吧？”

“恰恰相反。”我说着，仔细看了她一眼，“十年前你没有嫁给拉里，现在后悔吗？”

“不后悔。那时嫁给他，才是发疯呢。不过，当然喽，假如那时我和现在一样了解风情，那我会跟他远走高飞，和他姘居三个月，然后就离开他，和他永绝情缘。”

“恐怕值得庆幸的是你没有做那样的实验。否则，你也许会发现你和他绑在了一起，连接你们的链条你想斩也斩不断。”

“此话我不能苟同。这只不过是肉体上的吸引力罢了。要知道，克服肉欲的最好办法往往就是让它得到满足。”

“你是个占有欲很强的人，这你想过没有？你告诉过我，说格雷的感情极具诗意，还说他对你激情似火，我完全相信这两点对你有着重大意义。但你没有说过，把他攥在你那美丽但并不太小的手心里，那种感觉比这两点加在一起还要重要得多。而拉里是永远也抓不住的。记得济慈的《希腊古瓮颂》里的一句诗吗？‘大胆的情人，你永远，永远得不到一吻，虽然已接近目标。’”

“你老是以为自己懂得很多，其实远非如此。”她语气有点尖刻地说，“掌控男人，女人有自己的绝招，这你也知道。让我再告诉你一点吧——控制一个男人，决定性因素不在于第一次跟他上床，而在于第二次。一旦将他抓在手里，便可一劳永逸。”

“你掌握的情况真是非同一般哟。”

“我靠的是交游广，眼观六路，耳听八方。”

“能否告诉我，你这一锦囊妙计是从何处学来的？”

她冲我笑了笑，笑容里含着嘲讽。

“在一次服装展览会上，我交了个女友，就是从她那儿学来的。女店员告诉我，说她是巴黎最出名的被人包养的女人。我当时就下定决心要和她结识。她叫阿迪安妮·德·特洛耶。听说过没有？”

“没听说过。”

“你可真是疏于学业呀！她四十五岁，虽无花容月貌，但论风度却远远胜过艾略特舅舅的那些公爵夫人。我一屁股坐到她身旁，拿出我的那种美国小女孩的任性劲，说我必须跟她说几句话，因为我有生以来从未见过她这样典雅的人，简直就像是希腊浮雕画里的女神一样完美无瑕。”

“你的胆子真够大的。”

“起初，她非常冷淡，而我滔滔不绝说个没完，一副天真无邪的样子，最后说得她软了下来。接下来，我俩推心置腹聊了一通。展览会结束时，我提出想请她哪一天去里兹饭店共进午餐。我告诉她，说我一直都很羡慕她那绰约的风姿。”

“你以前见过她？”

“没见过。她不肯去赴宴，说巴黎人喜欢造谣生事、飞短流长，害怕殃及我，不过，对于我的邀请，她还是很高兴的。后来，她见我嘴唇发抖，一脸失望的表情，便提出请我到她家去和她共进午餐。我显出一副受宠若惊的神情，她看在眼里，在我的手背上拍了拍。”

“你去了吗？”

“当然去了。她住在福煦大街旁一幢精致的小房子里，伺候我们的是一个长相酷似乔治·华盛顿的管家。我在那儿一直待到下午四点钟。我们让头发散开，脱掉胸衣，说了一大堆关于女人的秘事。那天下午学到的知识，能够用来写一本书。”

“那你为什么不写？这类稿件适合登在《女士之家杂志》上。”

“你真傻。”她哈哈笑了。

我沉默了一会儿，心里翻江倒海般思索着。

“真不知拉里是不是真的爱过你。”我最后说道。

她不听则已，一听蹭地坐直了身子，脸色大变，一双美眸怒气冲冲。

“你这说的是什么鬼话？他当然爱我。你以为一个女孩子连别人爱她，她都不知道？”

“这个嘛，也可以说他在某种程度上是爱你的。他认识的女孩子，你和他是关系最密切的一个。你们青梅竹马，两小无猜嘛。他指望着自己一定会爱上你的。他有着正常的性欲本能。你们结婚成家似乎是顺理成章的事情。结婚后，你们一同生活，同床共枕，除此之外，与别的夫妻相比，并无什么特殊之处。”

怒气稍微平息了些，伊莎贝尔等着我继续说下去。我知道女人家总喜欢听别人谈爱情，于是便又说道：

“道德家们有一种观点，认为性欲的本能与爱情关系不大。依照他们的说法，性欲的本能似乎仅仅是偶然的冲动。”

“这是什么荒唐理论呀？”

“有些心理学家认为，人的意识伴随着大脑的活动而出现，依赖于大脑的活动，而它本身对大脑不施加任何影响。人的意识犹如水中树影，离开树不能存在，但是对树丝毫没有影响。有人说，没有情也可以有爱，我认为是胡说；他们说即便情消失了，爱仍旧可以存在。其实，他们所谓的情，只是好感、善心、共同的品味、共同的兴趣和共同的习惯。尤其指的是习惯。出于习惯，男女双方可以一直保持性关系，就像一到吃饭时间就感到肚子饿一样。当然，没有爱情，也是可以有肉欲的。肉欲并非激情，而是性欲本能的自然产物，与人的其他动物功能相比并无出众之处。所以说，有些做丈夫的在时间和地点适合时偶尔放纵一下，他们的妻子那样大惊小怪，实在愚蠢。”

“光男人可以放纵吗？”

我笑了。

“如果你硬要问，那我就得承认，男人可以放纵，女人也是可以潇洒一下的。唯一不同的是，对于男人，露水关系并无感情可言，对于女人就不一样了。”

“那要看是什么样的女人了。”

我不想让自己的话被打断，于是继续说了下去。

“爱是有情欲的，否则就不是爱，而是别的东西。这种情欲不是因为得到满足，而是由于遭到阻挠，会变得愈加炽热。济慈曾经对着雕刻在希腊古瓮上的恋人画像，让她不要伤心，你以为他是什么意思？‘你永远在爱着，她永远美丽动人。’为什么？因为她是得不到手的。不管她的情人怎样疯狂地追求，都追不到手。因为二者都被囚禁在了我称之为冷漠艺术品的大理石石面上。你对拉里的爱，以及拉里对你的爱，和保罗与弗兰切斯卡[97]、罗密欧与朱丽叶[98]之间的爱一样，都是那般单纯和自然。幸好你们俩的结局并不悲惨。你嫁入一个富人之家，拉里则浪迹天涯去探寻海妖歌声[99]的秘密。你们之间没有情欲作祟。”

“你怎么知道呢？”

“情欲是不计代价的。帕斯卡[100]曾经说：人之心讲究理智，而理智却有失控的时候。如果我没理解错的话，他的意思是，情欲一旦控制了人心，就会编出理由来，不仅冠冕堂皇，而且好像真实可信，让人们觉得为了爱可以不管天塌地陷。你会觉得，牺牲掉荣誉是值得的，而耻辱仅是很小的代价。情欲是毁灭性的。它毁掉了安东尼与克莉奥佩特拉[101]，毁掉了特里斯坦和伊索尔德[102]，也毁掉了帕内尔和基蒂·奥谢[103]。只要情欲存在，就会有毁人的事情发生。梦醒时，你才发现自己荒废了一生中的大好年华，忍辱负重，经受着嫉妒的痛苦折磨，将所有的苦水一滴滴吞下肚，献给对方的是缱绻温情和灵魂中最宝贵的财富，而对方只不过是个可怜虫、蠢蛋，一个浪费了你许多春梦的饭桶，论价值还不如一块橡皮糖。”

这番议论还未说完，我便发现伊莎贝尔压根就没有听，而是在想自己的心事。而后，她便语出惊人。

“你看拉里是否仍是处男呢？”

“亲爱的，他已经三十二岁了。”

“我敢肯定他还是个处男。”

“何以见得？”

“这种事情，女人凭本能可以感觉得到。”

“我认识一个年轻人，此人在情场上如鱼得水，声称自己是处男，将漂亮的女孩子们一个个骗得晕头转向。据他说，这一招像施魔咒一样灵。”

“不管你怎么说，反正我是相信自己的直觉的。”

天色渐晚，格雷和伊莎贝尔要出去和朋友们吃饭，伊莎贝尔得换衣服。我无事可做，于是步上拉斯帕埃大街，踏着秋天迷人的暮色向前走去。对于女人的直觉我历来都不太相信，认为她们所谓的直觉只是主观的想法，是不可信的。想到和伊莎贝尔这番长谈，自己在末尾说的那段话，我不禁哑然失笑。这使我想起苏姗娜·鲁维埃来，发现自己已有多日未见她了，不知她在做什么事情。如果她闲着没事，也许愿意陪我吃顿饭、看场电影呢。我叫住一辆在街上转悠的出租车，把她公寓的地址告诉了司机。

七

在本书开篇的时候，我曾提到过苏姗娜·鲁维埃。我认识此人已有十一二年了，此时再提起，她恐怕已近不惑之年了。她并不漂亮，其实可以说其貌不扬。在法国女人里面，她个子算是高的，短身躯，长胳臂长腿，笨手笨脚，仿佛真不知如何摆布那么长的四肢才好。她凭着自己的心情将头发染成各种颜色，但多数时间她的头发是红褐色的。她有一张小小的四方脸，颧骨特别高，浓妆艳抹，大嘴巴，嘴唇上涂着厚厚的一层唇膏。这一说，好像她全无动人之处了，但偏偏还是有人看上了她。话又说回来，她皮肤很好，有一口结实的白牙和一双炯炯有神的蓝色大眼睛。眼睛算是她身上最漂亮的部位了，所以她便把睫毛和眼皮都染黑加以渲染。她看上去既精明又和善，像是见过世面的，本性既有宽厚的一面又有强硬的一面。在她的人生中，是不得不强硬的。她父亲是一个政府部门的小公务员，死后母亲守寡，回到安茹州她原来那个村庄，靠抚恤金过活。苏姗娜十五岁那年，被送到邻镇一个服装店里当学徒，那儿离家近，星期天可以回家。十七岁那年夏天，苏姗娜有两个星期假期，就在休假期间被一个来村子里画风景的画家勾引上了。她心里很清楚，家里一分钱的嫁妆也出不起，嫁人的事遥遥无期。所以，在夏天快完时，画家提出要带她到巴黎去，她便欣然答应了。他带她来到巴黎的蒙马特高地，住进一个兔子窝般大小的画室，二人相依相伴，度过了一年快乐的时光。

末了，他告诉她，说自己连一幅画也没有卖出去，再也养不起情妇了。她早就料到会有这一天，没有为之感到慌乱。他问她想不想回老家，她说不想，于是他就说同一个街区有个画家愿意跟她一起生活。他说的那个人曾经勾引过她两三次，被她拒绝了，但没伤和气，没有令对方感到难堪。对那人她并不感到讨厌，所以泰然地接受了这项提议。搬家很方便，用不着花钱叫出租车，提着箱子就过去了。这第二个情人比第一个年龄大许多，但仍像模像样的，让她摆各种姿势为她画像，有穿衣服的，也有裸体的。二人同居，高高兴兴度过了两年的时光。想起来让她感到自豪的是，他的第一张真正成功的画作是以她当模特儿的。她曾经让我看过那幅画，是从一份介绍此画的画报上剪下来的。这幅画后来被美国的一家画廊买了去。这是一幅裸体画，真人一般大小——她呈卧式，姿势和马奈的油画《奥林普》差不多。这个画家敏锐地发现她的身体比例有一种现代情趣，于是采用夸张的手法，将她原本消瘦的身子画得骨瘦如柴，把她的长胳膊长腿画得更长，两个高颧骨更为突出，一双蓝眼睛大得出奇。从剪下来的画上看不出用的是什么色调，但构图相当有看头。此画叫他名声大噪，赢得了一个阔寡妇的敬仰，二人喜结良缘。苏姗娜深知男人得以自己的前程为重，没吵没闹，和他断绝了这段你亲我爱的关系。

此时，她已认识到了自身的价值。她喜欢艺术家的那种生活，喜欢给画家当模特儿。干完一天的活，就去泡咖啡馆，跟画家们、画家的妻子和情妇坐在一起，听画家们谈论艺术，诅咒画商，讲些下流故事，她觉得这种生活很有情趣。在这期间，她已看到了自己与那位画家的关系快到了头，便打起了小算盘。她相中了一个身边没女人的年轻画家，觉得他很有才气。她瞅准机会，一次见这位画家单独坐在咖啡馆里，便向他讲了自己的处境，开门见山地提出想跟他一道过日子。

“我今年二十岁，持家有方，在家务方面能为你省下一笔钱，还能为你省下雇用模特儿的开销。瞧瞧你的衬衫，简直不像个样子，你的画室乱得像鸡窝。你需要有个女人照应你。”

画家早就知道她很能干，听了她的提议，产生了兴趣。她见对方有接受的意思，便接着说道：

“先试试反正也没有害处。万一行不通，咱俩谁也不会有损失的。”

他是个非表现派的画家，给她画像画的全是些四方块和长方块；画她只有一只眼睛，没有嘴；把她画成一幅黑、棕、灰色交织的几何图案；画成一大堆杂乱无章的线条，从中勉强可以看出一张人脸。她和他同居了一年半，后来自动离开了他。

“为什么要走？”我问她，“你不喜欢他吗？”

“喜欢倒是喜欢，他是个挺不错的小伙子，只是觉得他再不会有进步了，老是重复自己。”

没费吹灰之力，她又傍上了一个画家。不管跟谁，她始终都不离开画家圈子。

“我一直都在画界打转。”她说，“我和一个雕塑家待过半年，但不知为什么总觉得没情没趣的。”

每次跟情人分手，从没有出现过叫人不愉快的事情，这让她想起来都感到高兴。她不仅是个出色的模特儿，也是个能干的主妇。不管住进哪个画室，她都喜欢那一方之地，把画室收拾得整整齐齐，并以此而感到自豪。她厨艺精湛，花很少一点钱就能烧出极为可口的饭菜。情人的袜子破了她给补，情人衣服上的扣子掉了她给缝。

“我简直就不明白为什么一个人因为是个画家，就不能穿得整整齐齐的。”

她只有一次日子过不下去的。那是和一个英国小伙子的往事。那人比她以前的任何一个情人都有钱，而且还有一辆汽车。

“不过，我们俩没多久便分手了。”她说，他酗酒成性，一喝醉便叫人心烦。如果他的画好，我也不会在乎的，可是，亲爱的，他的那些画全是涂鸦之作。我跟他说要离开他了，他就哭了起来，说他爱我。

“‘我可怜的朋友，’我对他说，‘你爱不爱我都无关紧要。关键是你没有绘画的天赋。还是回到你们国家去吧，开家杂货铺。你适合干那一行。’”

“他听了后怎么说？”我问。

“他听了勃然大怒，让我赶快滚蛋。你知道，忠言是逆耳的。真希望他能听人劝。他不是个坏人，只是画技太差。”

在风月场上，对于一个风尘女子而言，世情练达、心地善良是有好处的，可以化解一部分困难，但欲海情波中毕竟有许多沉浮，苏姗娜也不例外。她和那个斯堪的纳维亚人的恋情堪为借鉴。她千不该万不该，就不该坠入那张情网。

“他简直就是天神一样的人物，”她告诉我说，“个子特别高，高得就像埃菲尔铁塔，宽肩膀、阔胸脯，腰细得用两只手几乎就可以围过来，肚子扁平，平得和我的手掌一样，肌肉结实得像个职业运动员，一头金黄色的卷发，皮肤细如白瓷。他的画技也不错。我喜欢他的笔触——大胆而有力，他的着色丰富活泼。”

她算计着想和他生个孩子。对方坚决反对，可她说孩子由她负责抚养。

“后来生了个女孩，他爱如掌上明珠。那孩子可爱极了，玫瑰色的皮肤，金色的头发，蓝色的眼睛，酷似她的爸爸。”

苏姗娜和他同居，度过了三年的时光。

“他有点愚蠢，有时候叫人心烦。不过，他十分殷勤，而且长得那么英俊，我也就不太在乎了。”

后来，他接到瑞典的一封电报，说他父亲病危，要他立刻回家。他满口答应一定回来，可是苏姗娜有个预感，觉得他会一去不复返。他把所有的钱都留给了苏姗娜，走后一个月杳无音信。后来，苏姗娜收到他的一封信，说父亲已去世，一大堆乱麻一样的事情需要料理，说自己必须对母亲尽孝，留下来经营木材生意。信中附了一张一万法郎的支票。苏姗娜可不是那种遇事便一蹶不振的人。她当下就做出了判断，认为有个孩子在身边会妨碍她做那半掩门的生意。故而，她将小女儿带到乡下，把女儿连同那一万法郎交给自己的母亲，托她代为抚养。

“我的心都快碎了。我爱那孩子，但过日子得讲求实际呀。”

“以后的情况怎样？”

“唉，混日子呗。我又找到了一个朋友。”

后来，她染上了伤寒。提起那病，她总是说“我的伤寒”，就像百万富翁炫耀自己的度假地时说“我的棕榈滩”或者“我的松鸡泽”一样。那场病差点要了她的命，让她在医院里躺了三个月。出院时，她已骨瘦如柴，弱不禁风，神经脆弱得动不动就想哭。她成了个没有价值的窝囊废，当模特儿吧，身体支撑不下来，口袋里的钱已所剩无几。

“哎呀呀[104]，”她说道，“那是一段艰难的日月。幸亏我还有些好朋友帮忙。不过，你也知道画家的窘境，个个日子都过得紧巴巴的。我从来就不怎么漂亮，只是有点魅力罢了。但毕竟不再是二十岁的青春女子了。后来碰上了那个曾经跟我同居过的立体派画家。自从我们分手之后，他结了婚，随即又离了。他已放弃了立体派画风，秉承了超现实派的衣钵。他觉得可以利用我，于是说自己单身很孤独，提出和我一道生活，给我提供食宿。实不相瞒，我当下就同意了。”

就这样，苏姗娜一直和这位画家生活在一起，直至那位制造商出现。制造商是一个朋友领到画室来的，指望着能买一幅这位前立体派画家的画。苏姗娜一心想促成这笔生意，于是施展出手段来热情待客。制造商不能当场决定买还是不买，但是说过后再来看看。两个星期后，他果然来了。这一次，苏姗娜有个印象：他是来看她的，而非看画。离开时，他仍旧没有买，跟她握手时用了一点劲，显得有些过分亲热。次日，那个领制造商来看画的朋友趁她到菜市场买菜之际，半路截住了她，说制造商看上了她，下次来巴黎时，想请她吃顿饭，到时候有话跟她说。

“你觉得他看上了我什么呢？”她问道。

“他是现代艺术的爱好者，见过你的肖像画，极为倾倒。他是外省人，而且是做生意的。你在他眼中代表着巴黎、艺术、爱情——这些都是他在生活中所缺乏的。”

“他有钱吗？”她理智地问。

“有许多钱。”

“那好，我愿意和他吃饭。他有什么话，听听也无妨。”

制造商带她去马克西姆饭店吃饭，给她留下了好印象。她的穿着十分素雅。瞧瞧周围的女人，相比之下，她觉得自己看起来不错，非常像一个体面的已婚女子。他叫了一瓶女士香槟，让她觉得他很有绅士风度。饭后喝咖啡的时候，他将开出的条件摆在了她面前。她一听，认为对方很是慷慨。他告诉她，说自己每两个星期要来巴黎开一次董事会。晚上吃饭老是孤零零的一个人，想女人就去找青楼女子，日子过得味如嚼蜡。他结了婚，有两个孩子，但以他这种身份的人，过这种日子难以令人满意。他们俩都认识的那个朋友把她的情况如实告诉了他，他觉得她是个识进退的女子。他已不再年轻，不愿跟不懂事的女孩子纠缠在一起。他怎么也算是个现代艺术的收藏家，而她和画界联系紧密，跟他有共同语言。接下来，他讲了具体安排，说准备给她租套公寓，然后装修一下，每月给她两千法郎的零花钱。作为交换，他希望每两个星期能和她共同度过一个良夜佳宵。苏姗娜以前从未有过这许多钱供她私用。她飞快计算了一下，觉得这笔钱不仅够她吃饭穿衣，过衣食无忧的日子，还可以供养女儿，另外能再积攒一些以备不时之需。不过，她还是犹豫了一下。她素来以“画界人”自居，显然还是觉得给一个生意人当情妇未免有些掉价。

“Cest à prendre ou à laisser[105]，”他说，“你可以接受，也可以不接受。”

她并不讨厌他，而且看见了他纽扣孔里镶嵌的玫瑰花状的荣誉胸章，认定他是个有头有脸的人，于是冲他嫣然一笑。

“Je prends[106]，”她回答说，“我接受。”

八

苏姗娜虽说一直住在蒙马特高地，此时却觉得有必要与过去一刀两断，于是就在蒙巴纳斯街区离林荫道不远处的一幢公寓楼里租了一套房，里面包括两个房间、一个小厨房和一个浴室。此房位于六层，不过是配有电梯的。那电梯一次只能搭乘两人，慢得像蜗牛爬，下楼还得步行。但是，浴室和电梯对她而言，不仅代表的是奢华的生活，也是一种时髦。

二人同居的头几个月，阿吉里·高凡先生（此为制造商的名字），每隔两个星期来到巴黎一趟，下榻于一个旅馆，受炽热欲望的驱使，跟苏姗娜做完好事，然后再回到旅馆独眠，次日起床乘火车回去料理事务，享受静谧、愉快的家庭生活。后来，苏姗娜向他指出，说那样糟蹋钱是毫无道理的，完全可以留在公寓里，早晨再走，既省钱又少受点罪。他觉得此话说得有理。苏姗娜这一番知痛知痒的话说得他心里暖洋洋的。说真的，冬夜天气冷，跑上街头拦出租车，可不是件好受的事。至于她不愿让他花冤枉钱，也打动了他的心。一个女人，既懂得自己省开销，也知道为情人节省铜板，这才是好女人。

阿吉里先生对现状感到十分满意。他们俩一般都是下馆子，到蒙巴纳斯街区比较好的餐馆吃饭，但有的时候，苏姗娜也会亲自下厨，留他在公寓里吃饭。她烧得一手好菜，很对阿吉里先生的口味。吃晚饭时，如果天气暖和，阿吉里先生就脱掉外衣，只穿一件衬衫，感觉很有一种无拘无束、放荡不羁的艺术家风范。他一直对画品情有独钟，喜欢买画，但苏姗娜对于自己看不上的画，绝对不允许他买。没过多久，他便发现苏姗娜眼光独到，值得信赖了。苏姗娜不让他和中间人打交道，而是直接把他带到画家的画室里去买，所花的钱只抵在外面买画的一半。阿吉里先生知道她在攒钱，后来她告诉他，说她每年都要在老家的村子里添置一些地产，阿吉里听了为她感到很是自豪。他清楚，在每个法国人的血液里都涌动着拥有土地的欲望，而就是因为苏姗娜拥有了土地，故而对她的敬重又增加了几分。

苏姗娜这一边也是心满意足的。她对阿吉里先生既忠实，也不忠实。这就是说，她留意着不和别的男人保持固定的关系，但如果碰上看得上眼的，也不反对与对方行云雨之欢。但是，她绝不留意中人在家里过夜，这涉及良心的问题。她觉得自己欠那位有钱有地位的阿吉里先生一份情，因为正是阿吉里先生让她衣食无忧，过上了稳定和有尊严的生活。

我是在苏姗娜和一位画家同居时认识她的。这位画家是我的一个相识。苏姗娜在他绘画时为他当模特儿，我时常坐在旁边看。我也只是隔上一段时间偶尔见见她，直至她迁入蒙巴纳斯街区，和她的交往才密切了起来。

事情是这样的——阿吉里先生（她无论是提到还是当面称呼那位制造商都是这么叫的）读了一两本我的小说的法译本，于是，在某天晚上，请我到一家饭馆里和他们一起吃饭。他五短身材，比苏姗娜矮半个头，铁灰色的头发，八字胡修剪得整整齐齐，稍微有点偏胖，肚子突起，但并非大腹便便，仅仅衬托出了他的派头和气质而已。他走路迈着矮胖男人的那种四方步，一副意气风发的样子。这顿饭十分丰盛。他对我非常客气，说很高兴苏姗娜有我这样的朋友。他说一眼就看出我是个好人[107]，对于我如此看得起苏姗娜而感到欣慰。他杂事太多，使他在里尔脱不了身，让可怜的苏姗娜倍感寂寞，多亏有我这等文化人相伴，真是叫人舒心。他虽然是生意人，对艺术家却素有敬仰之心。

“啊，我亲爱的先生[108]，艺术和文学一直是法兰西的一对瑰宝。当然，它的军事实力可与之并驾齐驱。我是个毛织品制造商，不偏不倚，毫不犹豫地会将画家和作家放在与将军及政治家同等的位置。”

他的一席话说得无比入耳。

苏姗娜坚决不愿请女佣料理家务，一半是为了省钱，一半是因为（她自己知道得最清楚）她不喜欢有人插手于纯粹属于她个人分内的事物。那套小公寓被她收拾得干干净净、整整齐齐，而且按照当时最时新的式样加以陈设；所有的内衣都由她自己亲手来缝制。可是，即便如此，由于她不再当模特儿，时间仍多得难以打发。鉴于她是个闲不住的人，不久便心生一念：为那么多画家当过模特儿，她自己也应该画上几笔。说干就干，她立刻买来画布、画笔和油彩等用品，动手画了起来。有时候，我带她出去吃饭，去得早一点，就会看见她穿着罩衫在忙着作画。与胎儿在子宫里重现物种进化的过程基本一样，苏姗娜也重现了她过去所有情人的风格。她画风景像那个风景画家，画抽象画像那个立体派画家，还以风景明信片为参照画了一只停泊的帆船，画风跟那个斯堪的纳维亚人的一样。她的画技很糟，但色彩感不错。即便画得不怎么样，她却从中获得了不少乐趣。阿吉里先生对她大加鼓励。想到自己的情妇是个画家，使他心里有一种满足感。在他的敦促之下，苏姗娜送了一张画去参加秋季沙龙。看见那幅画挂在展厅里，二人都颇为之自豪。阿吉里先生给她提了一条忠告。

“画的时候，不要像男人一样阳刚气十足，亲爱的，”他说道，“而应有女性的温柔。不求笔锋遒劲，但求柔美入眼。画风应该求实。生意场上弄虚作假有时能出奇制胜，但在艺术上求实至上，也是唯一可行之道。”

故事写到此处，他们俩交往已有五年之久，彼此都感到很满意。

“显然，他并非叫我热血沸腾的那种人，”苏姗娜告诉我说，“但他是智慧型的，有着很好的社会地位。我也老大不小了，应该考虑考虑退路了。”

她富于同情之心，明白事理。阿吉里先生很尊重她的意见。他把生意场上的事和家里的事讲给她听时，她会侧着耳朵倾听。他女儿有一次考试落榜，她跟着他一道难过。他的儿子与一个有钱人家的千金订婚，她则和他一起高兴。他本人娶的就是一个同行人家的独生女。两个厂家原来是对头，这一联姻对双方都有好处。现在儿子也懂得了这个道理，知道幸福的婚姻必须有共同的物质利益作为坚实的基础，这叫他感到舒心。他推心置腹地告诉苏姗娜，说他有个野心，想把女儿嫁给贵族。

“她有的是钱，这是顺理成章的事。”苏姗娜说。

阿吉里先生替苏姗娜着想，把苏姗娜的女儿送进了一所女修道院办的学校，让她在那儿接受良好的教育，答应等她女儿到适当的年龄时，由他出钱去学习打字和速记，以便日后靠此谋生。

“她长大后一定是个大美女。”苏姗娜告诉我，“反正受点教育，以后会打字，是没有坏处的。她现在还小，什么事都难以预料，说不定她会变得缺乏气质呢。”

苏姗娜的话藏头露尾，弦外之音由着我去猜想了。我当然是能猜得出来的。

九

大概一个多星期后，我竟然和拉里出人意料地相遇了。一天晚上，我和苏姗娜看了电影，下了馆子，然后到蒙巴纳斯林荫道上的精英酒馆喝啤酒。就在这时，拉里慢慢悠悠走了进来。苏姗娜吃了一惊。令我感到意外的是，她喊住了他。拉里闻声走过来，吻吻她，和我握了握手。我看得出，苏姗娜惊讶极了，简直不敢相信自己的眼睛。

“我可以坐下吗？”他说，“我还没有吃晚饭，得要点东西填填肚子。”

“啊，见到你真高兴，我的宝贝[109]。”苏姗娜说道，眼睛里闪着亮光，“你这是从哪里蹦出来的？怎么这么多年连个人影都不见？天呀，看你瘦得跟个鬼一样！我还以为你死了呢。”

“哦，我没有死。”拉里眨巴了几下眼睛说，“奥德特近来可好？”

奥德特是苏姗娜女儿的芳名。

“好着呢。她现在长成个大姑娘了，很漂亮。她还记着你呢。”

“你从没说过你认识拉里。”我埋怨苏姗娜说。

“我怎么能说呢？我又不知道你认识他。我们是老朋友了。”

拉里给自己要了份鸡蛋和火腿。苏姗娜把女儿的情况以及她自己的情况细细给拉里讲了讲。她讲起来滔滔不绝，拉里则耐心听着，脸上挂着微笑。她告诉拉里，说她有了安定的生活，目前正在作画。她还把脸转向我说：

“我有了长进，你看是不是？我不敢说自己是个天才，但是论才气，与许多我认识的画家相比，我还是巾帼不让须眉的。”

“你的画卖不卖？”拉里问。

“我没必要卖画，”苏姗娜快活地说，“我的生活是有着落的。”

“你运气好呀。”

“错了，这不是运气不运气，而是智慧。你可一定要来看看我的画哟。”

她把自己的住址写在一张纸上，硬逼着拉里一定要去看画。她心情激动，喋喋不休说个没完。后来，拉里叫侍者过来埋单。

“你这就走吗？”她嚷嚷道。

“是的。”拉里微微一笑说。

他付过钱，冲着我们摆摆手，然后飘然而去。我哈哈大笑。他这种派头一直使我觉得很特别——刚才还和你在一起，转眼不见了人影，连句解释的话也没有，来去如风，仿佛消失在了空气里。

“他为什么这么急着走呢？”苏姗娜着恼地问。

“也许有个女孩子在等他吧。”我半开玩笑地说。

“这话说得没名头。”她从包里取出粉盒，往脸上扑了些粉，“哪一个女人爱上了他，算她倒霉。算啦，算啦。[110]”

“此话怎讲？”

她打量了一下我，表情严肃起来（很少见她这么严肃过）。

“在过去，我自己就差点爱上他。爱他，无异于爱水里的倒影、天上的阳光或云朵。幸亏我没有深陷其中。回想起当时的险境，我至今还会吓得打哆嗦。”

好奇心一起，势不可当。换上谁，也都急切想知道中间有什么故事。值得庆幸的是，苏姗娜肚子里藏不住事，是个有话就说的人。

“你到底是怎么和他相识的？”我问道。

“哦，那是多年前的事了。是七年前还是八年前，我记不得了。奥德特那时才五岁。他认识马塞尔，而我和马塞尔住在一起。他常来画室看马塞尔画我，有时候就约我们出去吃饭。你说不准他什么时候就会冒出来。有时候几个星期不见他的面，随后又连着两三天往我们那儿跑。马塞尔喜欢让他来，说有他在跟前，自己的画会画得好些。后来，我染上伤寒住进医院，出院后一下子陷入了困境。”说到此处，她耸了耸肩膀，这些事以前都给你讲过了。一天，我到各个画室里去，想找份工作，却没人愿意要我。整整一天，我只喝了一杯牛奶，吃了一只羊角面包，晚上连住宿费都没有。走到克利希大街，不知怎么却碰上了拉里。他停住脚步，问我日子过得怎么样。我把生病的事给他说了。他听后对我说：‘你看上去得先吃顿饱饭。’他的声音和眼神里有一种东西叫我十分感动，弄得我哭了起来。

我们站的那个地方隔壁就是马里埃特大妈餐馆。他挽起我的胳膊走进去，寻一张餐桌叫我坐下。我肚子饿极了，觉得自己恐怕连整整一头牛都能吞下肚。可是，夹着蔬菜和肉的煎蛋卷端上来时，我却一口也吃不下去了。他逼着我吃了一些，然后给我要了杯勃艮第葡萄酒。一杯酒下肚，我感觉精神了些，然后又吃了点炒芦笋。接下来，我就大倒苦水，把满腹的委屈都告诉了他。我弱不禁风，当不成模特儿；又瘦得皮包骨头，面容憔悴，根本没指望能找个情夫。我问他能不能借给我一点钱，助我回老家去——起码，我还有个小女儿在那里呢。他问我是不是真的想回去，我说当然并非真的想回。妈妈不会愿意接收我的。物价那么高，靠那点抚恤金，她的处境举步维艰；我寄给奥德特的钱已经全部花光。不过，到了家门口，她见我病成这个样子，恐怕也不会将我拒之门外的。拉里看着我，看了好长时间，我以为他会拒绝我，不愿借钱给我呢，然而却听他这样说：‘你愿不愿随我去乡下的一个地方，把你的孩子也带上？我刚好也需要休一段时间的假。’我简直不敢相信自己的耳朵，因为我认识他那么久，没见他对我有过意思。

‘就凭我现在这副模样，你还要我？’我说完，忍不住大笑起来，‘可怜的朋友，我眼下这副惨象，任何男人都不会要我的。’

他听了冲我莞尔一笑。他的笑是那么迷人，你注意过没有？那种笑容甜如蜜糖。

‘别胡扯，’他说，‘我指的不是那档子事。’

“我当时感动得哭成了泪人儿，连话都说不出了。他给我钱，把孩子接出来，我们一起到了乡下。啊，他领我们母女去的那个地方真是美极了。”

苏姗娜对我把那地方描绘了一番，说那儿离一个小镇有三英里远（小镇的名字我记不起来了）。他们乘汽车去了一家客栈。客栈是一幢摇摇欲坠的房屋，位于河畔，房前有一片草坪直达水边。草坪上长着几棵梧桐树，他们就在树荫下吃饭。夏天会有画家到那儿写生，但他们去时，还未到写生季，所以客栈里只有他们几个客人。客栈里的饭菜闻名遐迩。每逢星期天，人们会开着车赶来大快朵颐。但是在别的日子里，他们宁静的生活很少受到打搅。苏姗娜得到充足的休息，享用着好酒好肉，身体逐渐好了起来。而且，有孩子在身边，这叫她感到很幸福。

“他对奥德特非常好，奥德特也很喜欢他。她老缠着拉里，我拦都拦不住，可拉里好像并不介意她的纠缠。他俩在一起，就像两个不懂事的小孩子，常常逗得我大笑不止。”

“你们都做些什么呢？”我问。

“哦，总有事做的。有时划船、钓鱼，有时则把客栈老板[111]的雪铁龙牌汽车借来开着到镇上去。拉里喜欢那个小镇。那儿有古老的房屋和广场[112]，周围异常安静，鸦雀无声，只能听得到你自己走在石板路上的脚步声。镇上有一个路易十四时期的市政厅[113]和一座老教堂；小镇边上矗立着一座城堡和一个勒诺特尔[114]设计的花园。当你坐在广场[115]旁的咖啡店里的时候，你会觉得时光倒流，又回到了三百年前，而马路边停放的那辆雪铁龙好像根本不属于这个世界。”

在一次出游之后，拉里把本书开头时所讲过的那个年轻飞行员的故事告诉了苏姗娜。

“真不明白他为什么给你讲这个。”我说道。

“我也不知道为什么。战争期间，小镇上有所医院和一座公墓，公墓里有一排排的十字架。我们去那儿看过，没有久留。那地方叫我毛骨悚然——那么多可怜的年轻人长眠在那儿。返回的路上，拉里默默无语。他平时就吃得不多，而那天晚饭时几乎粒米未进。我记得非常清楚，那天的夜晚很美，满天的星，我们坐在河沿上，白杨树在黑暗中影影绰绰的，景色很美，拉里抽着烟斗。忽然间，非常突兀地[116]，他讲起了他的那位朋友，说那位朋友为了他而献出了生命。”苏姗娜喝了一口啤酒，又说了下去，“他是个怪人。我永远也理解不透他。他喜欢念书给我听，有时是在白天，我边听边给小家伙缝缝补补，有时是在晚上，在我打发小家伙睡觉之后。”

“他都念些什么？”

“形形色色的，什么都有。其中有塞维尼夫人[117]的《书简集》，也有圣西蒙[118]的《回忆录》。想想看，我以前除了报纸什么都不看，有时偶尔读上一本小说，也是在画室里听别人议论，又不愿让他们把我当白痴看待，才去读的。想不到读书竟能引人入胜。其实，过去的那些作品并非像人们想象的那么枯燥乏味。”

“谁会那么想象呢？”我扑哧笑了。

“后来，他叫我跟他一起念。我们一起念《费德尔》[119]和《贝蕾妮丝》[120]。他念男人的台词，我念女人的台词。你都不知道那是多么有意思。”她天真地补充了一句，“念到催人泪下的台词，我会泣不成声，而他则用不解的目光望着我。当然喽，我的身体还没有恢复过来，才那么多愁善感。实不相瞒，那些书我至今还保留着呢。即便在今日，看看他曾给我念过的塞维尼夫人的《书简集》，似乎仍能听见他那可爱的声音，仍能看见静静流淌的河水以及对岸婆娑的树影。有的时候，拿起书我都看不下去，只觉得心里隐隐作痛。现在我认识到那几个星期是我一生中最快乐的时光。他这个人，真是像天使一样可爱。”

苏姗娜觉得自己有点感情冲动，生怕我会笑她（这是错误的判断）。讲到这里，她耸了耸肩膀，笑着说：

“要知道，我心里也盘算好了，等到我人老珠黄，没有男人愿意跟我睡觉时，我就皈依教门，忏悔自己的罪恶。可是，我和拉里犯下的那些罪恶，我无论如何也不会忏悔的。绝不，绝不忏悔！”

“可是，根据你的描述，实在看不出来你有什么可忏悔的。”

故事的后半截我还没讲呢。你也可以看得到，我的身体素质原本是很好的，那段时间成天在户外待着，吃得好，睡得香，无忧无虑，不出三四个星期，我就跟从前一样健健康康的了，样子也好看了，脸蛋红红的，头发有了光泽，感觉就像二十岁一样。拉里每天早上在河里游泳，我时常在一旁看他。他的身体长得很美，不像我那个斯堪的纳维亚人的运动员型的身体，而是结实有力，非常入眼。

“我身体差的时候，他表现得相当有耐心，现在彻底恢复了健康，就没有理由叫他再继续等下去了。于是，我向他暗示了一两次，表示我已经准备好了，可他好像不明白似的。当然，你们盎格鲁撒克逊人是很怪的，野蛮粗鲁，同时又多愁善感。谈情说爱并非你们的长项，这是无法否认的。我对自己说：‘也许，他比较含蓄吧。他为我做了那么多的事情，还让我把孩子也带了来，可能不愿叫我报答他的恩情。反正他有他的理由。’一天夜里，大家都准备睡觉时，我对他说：‘今天夜里，你要我到你的房间吗？’”

我听了哈哈大笑。

“你说话可有点太直白了，是不是？”

“这个嘛，我又不能让他来我的房间，因为奥德特睡在里边。”她率直地回答说，他用他那双和善的眼睛看了我一下，然后笑眯眯地问：‘你愿意来吗？’

‘你的身体那么诱人，你说我能不愿意吗？’

‘好吧，那你就来吧。’

“我上了楼，脱掉衣服，然后，沿着过道溜进他的房间。他正躺在床上看书，抽着烟斗。见了我，他便放下烟斗和书，挪挪身子，给我腾出点地方。”

说到此处，苏姗娜沉默了一会儿。我也不好意思再朝下问。不过，过了片刻，她又继续说了下去。

“他是个很奇怪的情人，和蔼可亲、感情真挚，甚至可以说是温柔体贴，散发着阳刚之气，却并非激情勃发，希望你能理解我的意思——他的情欲是纯真无邪的。他的那种爱情就像热血沸腾的青年学生的恋情。当时的情形很滑稽，却又令人十分感动。我离开时，觉得应当是我感谢他，而不是他感谢我。当我带上门时，看见他又拿起书，从刚才中断的地方继续看了下去。”

我一听又大笑起来。

“很高兴这能叫你感到开心。”她有点不快地说。不过，她自己也觉得有点滑稽，便也咯咯笑了起来。“我很快就发现，要是等他邀请我，那就等八辈子也等不来。所以，我一旦想干那种事，就溜进他的房间，爬上他的床。每一次他都来者不拒。按说，他也有人的那种自然本能，然而他却像个心不在焉的人，有时会忘记吃饭，当你把丰盛的饭菜摆在他面前时，他则吃得津津有味。一个人爱不爱我，我是清楚的。如果我认为拉里爱我，那我就是个傻瓜。但我认为，这样的生活方式他终究会习惯的。一个人，是必须讲求实际的。我心想，如果回到巴黎，他让我和他一道生活，我会很高兴的。我知道他一定会叫我把孩子留在身边，这一点非常合我的意。我的本能告诫我，只有傻瓜才会坠入情网。你知道女人是很不幸的，一旦坠入情网，就变得不可爱了。我决定让自己时刻保持警惕，绝不栽这个跟头。”

苏姗娜抽了一口香烟，然后把烟从鼻孔里喷出来。时间已晚，许多桌子都已经空了。不过，仍有一些顾客围坐在吧台那儿。

一天上午，吃过了早饭，我坐在河畔做针线活，奥德特在玩拉里给她买的积木。就在这时，拉里走到了我跟前。

‘我是来向你告别的。’他说。

‘你要走了吗？’我诧异地问。

‘是的。’

‘再不回来啦？’我问道。

‘你现在已经完全康复。这里有一笔钱够你这个夏天用的，可以帮你回到巴黎后重新生活。’

一时间，我心里非常难过，都不知道说什么好了。他站在我的面前，笑吟吟的，笑容仍是那般灿烂。

‘我是不是有哪些地方叫你不高兴啦？’我问他。

‘没有的事。千万别这么想。我有工作要做。在这儿，咱们度过了一段美好的时光。奥德特，到这儿来，跟叔叔说再见。’

“孩子太小，不知道是怎么回事。拉里把她抱起来吻了吻，然后也吻了我。随即，他回到了客栈去，不一会儿我就听见了汽车开走的声音。我看了看他塞入我手里的钞票，竟有一万两千法郎之多。事情来得突然，我连反应的时间都没有。‘真是活见鬼！[121]’我对自己这么说了一声。起码有一点得感谢上帝——幸好我没有让自己爱上他。他的所作所为，叫人感到一头雾水。”

我忍俊不禁，笑了起来。

“要知道，过去有个时候，我只是把实情告诉世人，结果给自己赢得了一个幽默作家的美称。大多数人都觉得意外，以为我在说笑话。”

“我看不出你的话跟此事有什么联系。”

“哦，这么说吧——在我认识的人当中，拉里是唯一一个超然物外的人。这让他的行为显得很特殊。有一类人，他们并不相信上帝，所作所为却都是为了上帝之爱，这类人是叫世人看不惯的。”

苏姗娜望着我发呆。

“我可怜的朋友，你的酒喝得太多了。”

第五章

一

我在巴黎写作，三天打鱼两天晒网。此时春光明媚，令人心情愉悦，爱丽舍田园大街上的栗花盛开，大街小巷一片灿烂的光芒。空气中荡漾着欢乐的气氛，那气氛轻快却短暂，使你会产生浪漫但不下流的情绪，令你脚步轻盈、才思敏捷。终日有朋友们陪伴，我感到很快活，心中充满了对往事温馨的回忆，至少在精神上恢复了些许青春的活力。这样的欢乐时光转瞬即逝，恐怕今生今世再也享受不到，我觉得如果用工作加以打扰，那纯粹是愚蠢之举。

伊莎贝尔、格雷、拉里和我常常一同去游览近处的名胜——尚蒂伊[122]、凡尔赛、圣日尔曼和枫丹白露。无论去何处，我们的午饭都吃得好而丰盛。格雷个头大，食量就大，酒也喝得不少。不知是由于拉里的妙手回春，还是由于时间的作用，他的健康状况颇见好转。那种头痛欲裂的感觉已不复存在。以前到巴黎来，跟他有了初交，那时看到他眼里有一种迷茫的神情，令人见了心碎，而今那种神情已经消失。他说话不多，只是偶尔讲上一个故事寻开心，但听见我和伊莎贝尔天南海北的那一通胡扯，他会哈哈大笑，笑声朗朗。和我们在一起，他玩得很开心。他虽然并不风趣，但脾气好，随遇而安，你会不由得喜欢上他。这种人，你不愿意和他度过一个寂寞无聊的夜晚，却很可能会愿意跟他在一起待上半年的时光。

他爱伊莎贝尔，让人见了为伊莎贝尔感到高兴。他崇拜她的美，觉得她是天下最漂亮、最迷人的女子。他忠实于拉里，就像一条小狗忠实于自己的主人，使人颇为感动。拉里似乎玩得也很开心。我有一种感觉：他将眼前的时光看作假日，不管心里有什么打算，都暂时放在一边，静下心来尽情享受。他也少言寡语的，但这无关紧要，有他在跟前，无言胜有言。他态度随和，满面春风，让你觉得这就足够了。我非常清楚，正是由于他在跟前，我们在一起度过的日子才那么充满了欢乐。他虽然没说过一句精彩或幽默的话，但没有了他，我们会感到乏味无聊。

一次出游归来，途中我目睹了一幕场景——那场景吓了我一跳。我们游历了沙特尔，当时正从那儿返回巴黎。格雷开车，拉里坐在副驾驶的位子上。我和伊莎贝尔坐在后排。玩了一天，大家都累散了架。拉里的一只胳膊伸开，搭在前座的椅背上。这个姿势使他的袖口拉了上去，露出瘦长而有力的手腕和微微长了一层茸毛的棕色皮肤的小臂。阳光把那些茸毛染成了黄金色。伊莎贝尔一点声息没有，使我觉得有异，便瞥了她一眼。她一动不动，简直就像是受到了催眠似的。她呼吸急促，眼睛死死盯着那长了金黄茸毛的结实手腕以及那只瘦削、修长而有力的手，脸上一副饿狼似的色相——那色相我在任何人的脸上都没有见到过。她的脸就像是个面具，燃烧着肉欲。我怎么也没想到，她那漂亮的脸上会出现如此荒淫无耻的表情。那是野兽的兽欲，而非人的欲望。她脸上的美不见了，取而代之的是狰狞和恐怖。那情景让人厌恶，使得她就像一只发情的母狗，我看了感到一阵恶心。她无视我的存在，什么都感觉不到了，只盯着那只随随便便搭在椅背上的手，心里升腾起熊熊的欲火。后来，她的脸上掠过了一阵痉挛和抽搐。只见她浑身一哆嗦，闭上眼睛，靠回到了汽车的角落里。

“给我一根烟。”她说道，粗声粗气的，叫我都听不出来是她的声音了。

我从烟盒里取出一根烟，为她点着。她狠狠地抽了一口。在余下的路程中，她始终望着窗外，再也没有说一句话。

回到公寓楼时，格雷请拉里开车送我回旅馆，然后将车停放在车库里。拉里坐到了驾驶员的座位上，我坐到他旁边。只见那两口子在穿过人行道时，伊莎贝尔挽着格雷的胳臂，靠紧他，看了他一眼。我虽然看不清那是什么样的眼神，却也能猜出个八九不离十。我心想，格雷夜里会发现自己的妻子特别狂热，但他永远也不会知道伊莎贝尔是由于良心发现才对他热情似火的。

六月份已接近尾声，我得回里维埃拉去了。艾略特的朋友到美国去，把他们在迪纳尔[123]的别墅借给马图林夫妇住，这小两口准备等孩子们一放暑假就到那儿去。拉里打算留在巴黎工作，但给自己买了一辆二手的雪铁龙汽车，答应八月份上他们那儿去住几天。在我离开巴黎的前夕，我请他们三个人和我一同吃晚饭。就在这天晚上，我们和索菲·麦克唐纳不期而遇。

二

伊莎贝尔突发奇想，想到那些野去处瞧一瞧，鉴于我在那儿有熟人，便请我当向导。我老大不愿意，因为巴黎的这种地方不喜欢叫外人进去参观，他们对此毫不掩饰，十分叫人扫兴。可是，伊莎贝尔非去不行。我提前告诉她，说那种地方非常叫人倒胃口，吩咐她穿着一定要朴素。我们很迟才吃晚饭，饭后去女神影院[124]看了一个小时的短片。接下来，我先带他们到圣母院附近的一处地下室，那儿是流氓恶棍和他们的姘头常来常往之地。我认识此处的老板，他为我们安排位子，让我们坐到一张长条桌旁，同桌的顾客是几个不三不四的人。我为所有的人都要了杯酒，大家相互敬酒。屋子里闷热、肮脏，乌烟瘴气的。后来，我又带他们去了斯芬克斯舞厅，舞厅里的女人们穿着华丽却俗气，袒胸露怀，面对面坐在两张长凳子上，乐队奏舞曲时，她们便到舞池里无精打采地跳舞，一边用眼睛搜索中意的男人——那些男客散坐在舞厅各处的大理石面桌子旁。我们叫了一瓶未冰镇的香槟酒。有些女人经过我们面前时，会给伊莎贝尔抛个眼色，我不知道伊莎贝尔是否明白其中的含意。

随后，我们又去了拉佩街。那是一条脏兮兮、路面狭窄的小街。一到这儿，你就会油然产生污秽下流的印象。走进一家咖啡馆，只见一个面色苍白、沉迷于酒色的年轻人在弹钢琴，另有一个倦容满面的老头在刺刺拉拉地抚琴，还有一个吹萨克斯管的，吹出来的调子杂乱无章。咖啡馆里人满为患，好像一张空桌子都没有了。不过，老板看出我们是肯花钱的主顾，便毫不客气地把一对男女赶到另外一张已经坐了人的桌子去，请我们在空下来的桌旁坐下。被赶走的那两个人很不服气，说了一些让我们难以入耳的话。舞池里有许多人——有帽子上缀着红绒球的水手，还有杂七杂八的男子（他们大多数都头戴帽子，脖子上围着帕巾）；有半老徐娘，也有青春女子，一个个描眉涂唇（她们都没有戴帽子），下穿短裙，上穿五颜六色的罩衣。舞伴的搭配乱七八糟——有大男子和矮胖的小男孩跳（小男孩的眼睛化了妆），有身子干瘦、横眉立目的女人和染了头发的胖女人跳，也有男和女搭配跳。屋里弥漫着烟气、酒味和汗臭味。舞曲没完没了地奏着，人群散发着难闻的气味，在舞池里舞个不停，脸上的汗水闪着亮光，气氛严肃、紧张，有一些可怕的成分在里边。男客里有几个大块头，面相凶狠，但大多数男客都是矮个，显得营养不良。我看了看那三个乐手，觉得他们跟机器人一样，演奏起来死板板的。我怀疑他们是否在起步时怀揣过梦想，梦想着自己有朝一日会成为大音乐家，引得人们从大老远赶来听他们演奏，为他们喝彩。即便提琴拉得不好，也得请人教，也得练习呀！这位提琴手十年磨一剑，末了难道就是为了屈身于这么一个肮脏猪圈里，为人家拉狐步舞曲，一直拉到次日凌晨吗？后来，音乐停止了，钢琴手掏出一块脏手绢揩揩脸。跳舞的人纷纷返回自己的座位，或无精打采，或脚步踉跄，或身子歪斜。突然，我们耳边传来了一声美国口音的叫喊：

“我的老天呀！”

只见屋子另一头有个女子从一张桌子旁站了起来。和她在一起的那个男子想拦她，却被她一把推开，然后她就摇摇晃晃走了过来。她已经有八九分醉了，来到我们的桌前，站在那儿，脚下有点立不稳，傻里傻气咧嘴笑着。她似乎觉得我们这几个人很好笑似的。我偏头望了望我的同伴们。伊莎贝尔木然瞅着她；格雷一脸愠色；拉里目瞪口呆，仿佛无法相信自己的眼睛一般。

“你们好呀！”那女子说道。

“原来是索菲！”

“那你把我当成了哪一个了？”索菲咯咯一笑。她一把扯住了一个从身边走过的侍者，对他说道：“文森特，去给我拿把椅子来。”

“你自己拿去。”侍者挣开她的手说道。

“你个坏东西。[125]”她骂道，朝他啐了一口。

“别担心[126]，索菲，这儿有椅子。”一个油头粉面的大胖子喊了一声。那家伙坐在我们的邻桌，身上只穿了一件衬衣。

“想不到竟在此处碰上了你们诸位。”她说道，脚下仍站立不稳，“你好，拉里！你好，格雷！”她打着招呼，一屁股坐在了那个胖子放在她身后的一把椅子上，“来，咱们一起干一杯。老板！[127]”她扯着喉咙叫了一声。

我留意到那个老板一直在盯着我们，此时闻声走了过来。

“你认识这几个人，索菲？”他问道。他对索菲说话，用的是亲昵的单数第二人称。

“当然认识[128]，”她醉醺醺地大笑着说，“他们是我小时候的朋友。我要请他们喝一瓶香槟酒。你可不要给我们把马尿[129]拿来。拿酒来，别喝了叫我们呕吐。”

“你醉了，可怜的索菲。”老板说。

“咸吃萝卜淡操心。”

老板抽身走掉了，心里乐得卖掉了一瓶香槟酒。我们为了安全起见，只喝白兰地掺苏打水。索菲用呆滞的目光盯着我，把我打量了一会儿。

“伊莎贝尔，怎么不把你的这位朋友介绍一下？”

伊莎贝尔把我的名字告诉了她。

“啊，想起来了。你到芝加哥去过。看你的样子，很有派头呢，是不是？”

“也许吧。”我笑了笑说。

对于她，我却是一点也想不起来了，其实这也并不奇怪，因为去芝加哥是十多年前的事情了，当时及以后我又接触到了许许多多的人。

她的个子很高，站在那儿，由于瘦，就显得更高了。她上穿一件鲜绿的丝绸衣衫，皱巴巴的，上面满是污痕，下穿一条黑短裙，头发染成了亮亮的红褐色，剪得很短，马马虎虎盘了一下，乱得像鸡窝。她把自己打扮得妖里妖气，满脸都搽了胭脂，上下眼皮涂成了深蓝色，眉毛和睫毛上抹了浓浓的睫毛油，嘴唇用口红染成了血红色。她的手脏兮兮的，指甲盖上涂着指甲油。她一看就是个荡妇，比跟前的任何一个女人都显得下流。我怀疑她不仅喝醉了酒，还吸了毒。不过，无可否认的是，她身上有一股狐媚劲；她喜欢风情万种地把头扬得高高的，脸上的脂粉将绿眼珠子衬托得绿得惊人，尽管醉得厉害，却有一种厚颜无耻的荡劲，想象得来是颇受下流男人喜爱的。此时，只听她冲着我们冷笑了一声。

“看来，你们都不太高兴见到我。”她说道。

“听说你来巴黎了。”伊莎贝尔有气无力地说道，脸上浮出的笑容冷冰冰的。

“那你为什么不给我打电话。电话簿上有我的名字。”

“我们来的时间不长。”

格雷赶忙解围问道：

“你来这儿过得好吗，索菲？”

“还好。你破产了，格雷，是不是？”

格雷一听，脸红得跟猪肝一样。

“是的。”

“够你呛的。芝加哥那边恐怕日子都不好过。幸亏我逃了出来。上帝呀，那个天杀的怎么还没有把酒送来？”

“正朝这边走呢。”我瞧见一个侍者手举托盘，上面放着酒杯和一瓶酒，正顺着桌子间的甬道走过来，于是便这样说道。

我的话把她的注意力吸引到了我身上。

“我那慈爱的婆家人把我踢出了芝加哥，说我败坏了他们家的名声。”她说完咯咯一笑，笑得野里野气，“现在我是靠汇款过日子。”

香槟酒送来后，倒进了杯子里。她哆嗦着手端起酒杯，把酒杯举至唇边。

“那些势利小人，去他们的吧。”她说完一仰脖子喝光了杯中的酒，然后望了拉里一眼。“你好像肚子里没有多少话要说的，拉里。”

拉里一直在观察着她，脸上一点表情也没有。自从她露面，他的眼睛一刻也没离开过她。此时听了她的话，他便冲她莞尔一笑。

“我本来话就不多么。”他说。

乐手们又奏起了音乐。一个家伙朝我们这边走了过来，他个子比较高，长得虎背熊腰，大鹰钩鼻，头发油黑发亮，嘴唇厚墩墩的，面容有点像“恶人”萨伏那罗拉[130]。跟屋里的大多数男人一样，他没有戴衣领，上衣的扣子扣得紧紧的，显出他的腰身来。

“来呀，索菲，咱们跳舞去。”

“走开。我忙着呢。你没看见我和朋友在说话吗？”

“我才不管你的什么朋友不朋友呢。[131]叫你的朋友见鬼去吧。你跟我跳舞去。”

他说着一把抓住了索菲的胳膊，却被索菲甩开了。

“松开我，你这个浑蛋！[132]”她勃然大怒，吼了起来。

“妈的。[133]”

“王八蛋。[134]”

格雷听不懂他们的话，但我看出伊莎贝尔却完全能理解他们的意思——奇怪的是，大多数讲究道德修养的女子对污言秽语很敏感，一听就懂。这时，只见她沉下脸来，蛾眉紧蹙，显出一副厌恶的表情。那人举起胳臂，张开他那只长满老茧的工人的手，眼看就要扇在索菲的脸上。就在这时，格雷从椅子上半抬起身子，恶声恶气地大吼一声：

“还不快滚！[135]”

那人住了手，气哼哼地瞥了格雷一眼。

“小心点，可可，”索菲奸笑了一声说，“他会要你的命的。”

那人看了看格雷的个头和体重，看得出他力大无穷，悻悻地耸耸肩膀，冲我们骂了一句脏话，灰溜溜地跑了。索菲醉醺醺地咯咯笑个不停。大家谁都没有说话。我又给她的杯子斟满了酒。

“你住在巴黎吗，拉里？”她喝干杯中的酒，问道。

“只是暂时的。”

跟一个喝醉酒的人说话一般是很吃力的。毫无疑问，没喝酒的与喝醉酒的交谈，总是谈不拢。我们跟索菲说了一会儿话，气氛别别扭扭，很是尴尬。后来，索菲把椅子向后一推，说道：

“我再不回到我的男朋友那儿去，他会气疯的。那是个爱生气的混球。不过，感谢上帝，他床上的功夫很棒。”她说着，摇摇晃晃站了起来，“再见，老乡们。欢迎再来。我每天晚上都在这儿呢。”

她挤进跳舞的人群，然后就消失了。伊莎贝尔那典雅的脸上冷若冰霜，挂着蔑视的表情，我看了差点没笑出声来。有半晌儿，大家谁都没有说话。

“这是个藏污纳垢的地方，”伊莎贝尔突然蹦出了这么一句，“咱们走吧。”

我付了酒水钱，也为索菲的那瓶香槟酒埋了单。随后，我们鱼贯走出咖啡馆。人们仍在舞池里跳个不停，我们却看也不看便离开了。时间已过两点，我觉得应当睡觉了，可格雷说他肚子饿，于是，我建议到蒙马特高地的格拉芙餐馆去吃点东西。汽车启动时，大家都默默无语的。我坐在格雷身旁为他指路，一直把车开到了那家富丽堂皇的餐馆。餐馆的露台上还坐有顾客。我们进了门，要了鸡蛋、火腿和啤酒。至少从表面看，伊莎贝尔已经恢复了平静。她用一种夹枪带棒的口气对我表示祝贺，祝贺我竟然和巴黎那些乌七八糟的地方有来往。

“是你自己提出来要去的。”我抢白道。

“反正我玩得倒是十分开心的，度过了一个美妙的夜晚。”

“糟透了，”格雷说，“想起来就叫人恶心。索菲也真够可怜的。”

伊莎贝尔不置可否地耸了耸肩。

“你能想起来她吗？”她问我，“你第一次到我们家吃晚饭时，她就坐在你身旁。那个时候，她的头发是原色，即浅棕色，没有染成现在这种可怕的红颜色。”

我回想了一下当时的情景，记起了一个年龄不大的小女孩，一双蓝眼睛带点绿色，说话时把脑袋一偏，挺招人喜欢的。她并不漂亮，但活泼、坦率，同时带几分腼腆和唐突，让人觉得很有意思。

“当然能想起来。我当时就喜欢她的名字，因为我有个姑妈也叫索菲。”

“她嫁了一个叫鲍勃·麦克唐纳的小伙子。”

“那小伙子挺不错的。”格雷说道。

“在我见过的极为英俊的小伙子里面，他算其中的一个。我简直不明白他看上了索菲的哪一点。我刚结婚，她也结了婚。她的父母离异，母亲改嫁给了一个在中国工作的美孚石油公司的人。她随父亲一家住在马文，我们经常见面。不过，她结婚之后，便淡出了我们的朋友圈。鲍勃·麦克唐纳是个律师，挣钱却不多。他们住在北区的一座没有电梯的公寓楼里。不过，这也没什么。他们相亲相爱，那种热乎劲真是少见。即便结婚已经有两三年而且生了一个孩子之后，他们上电影院时，还是像一对情侣——他搂着她的腰，而她把头靠在他的肩上。他们一时成了芝加哥谈笑的话题。”

拉里听伊莎贝尔说话，中间未置一词，脸上带着一种叫人捉摸不透的表情。

“后来怎么啦？”我问。

“一天晚间，他们开着自家的敞篷汽车返回芝加哥，孩子也和他们在一起。他们出去总把孩子带上，因为家里没人帮他们照料。反正索菲干什么事都自己来。再说他们也片刻离不开孩子。有几个醉鬼开着一辆大轿车，以每小时八十英里的速度和他们的车迎头相撞。鲍勃和孩子当场死于非命。索菲被撞成了脑震荡，还断了一两根肋骨。大家千方百计瞒着她，不让她知道鲍勃和孩子已经死了。瞒到最后，也只好将实情告诉了她。据说，当时的情景可怕极了。她差点没发疯，哭天喊地，声音能把房子都震塌。不分白天和黑夜，都有人看着她——有一次，她差点跳楼自杀。我们能做的全都做了，但她好像恨上了我们。出了医院之后，又把她送进了疗养院，在那儿疗养了几个月。”

“是个可怜的人呀。”

“一旦放松了监管，她就开始酗酒，喝醉了，谁要她，她就跟谁睡觉。她夫家的人身陷窘境。他们都是些老老实实的本分人，十分痛恨她的丑闻陋行。起初，我们还想帮她一把，但无济于事。你请她吃饭，她来时就已经喝得醉醺醺的了，不等散席便不省人事了。后来，她跟一些不三不四的人交往，我们只好和她一刀两断了。一次，她因醉驾而被捕。车上还有一个人，是她随便勾搭上的一个混混，结果发现此人是警方通缉的逃犯。”

“她靠什么生活呀？”我问。

“有鲍勃的人寿保险呢。和他们撞车的那辆车的车主上了保险，她获得了一些赔偿。但那点钱没多久便花光了。她挥霍无度，花钱如流水，不出两年就一贫如洗了。她的祖母不肯让她回马文去。她夫家的人说，如果她到国外定居，就给她寄生活费。我想，她现在就是靠这笔钱过日子呢。”

“这可真是命运的大轮回呀。”我说道，“想当初，我们国家把害群之马流放到美国去，而今你们美国则将害群之马送到欧洲来了。”

“我真是为索菲感到惋惜呀。”格雷说。

“是吗？”伊莎贝尔冷静地说，“我却不这么想。当然，那是一次沉重的打击。按说，我比任何人都同情索菲。我们俩可是知根知底的。不过，一个正常人总是能够恢复过来的。她一蹶不振，只是因为她有这方面的劣根性。她在本性上是不健全的。就连她对鲍勃的爱情都超过了正常的范围。假如她性格坚强，便可以重新爬起来，继续生活下去。”

“人和人是不同的……你是不是太严苛了些，伊莎贝尔？”我咕哝了一句。

“恐怕并非如此。我觉得应该保持理智，在看待索菲这件事上实在不应该感情用事。上帝知道，谁也没有我对格雷及两个孩子的感情深，如果他们死于车祸，我会发疯的，但迟早会重新振作起来。格雷，你是愿意让我重新振作起来，还是愿意叫我夜夜喝个大醉，然后随便跟巴黎的哪个混混上床睡觉？”

格雷的回答很妙，可以说是我听到他所说的最幽默的一段话：

“当然，我倒愿意让你穿一件莫利纽克斯服装店的衣服跳进我的火葬堆陪葬，只是现在不准这样做了。所以，我想你最好的出路就是打桥牌了。请你一定要记住：不要急于求成，不要一开始就出王牌，而应该等到手中有三叠半到四叠牌再说。”

此时不是时候，我不便向伊莎贝尔指出她对丈夫和孩子们的爱是诚挚的，但并不怎么热烈。也许，她看出了我心里在想什么，于是略带挑战意味地问我：

“你是怎么看的？”

“和格雷一样，我为那女孩子感到惋惜。”

“她不是女孩子了，都三十岁的人了。”

“我想她的丈夫和孩子一死，就等于是世界末日的来临。至于她自己会有什么样的结果，她已完全不在乎了，于是便陷入堕落的泥潭，酗酒和淫乱。她认为命运之神对她过于残酷，于是便借此进行报复。她本来住在天堂，现在天堂失去了，却又住不惯平凡人的平凡世界，因此，绝望之余，一头钻进了地狱。可以想象得来，既然再也喝不上天界的琼浆玉液，那她情愿喝厕所里的小便。”

“这是你们作家在小说里讲的一套大道理。完全是无稽之谈，是瞎胡扯。索菲陷入泥潭，那是因为她喜欢那儿。丧夫丧子的大有人在，谁也不像她。并非一次事故就会叫人变坏；坏并不是由好变过来的，而是本身就存在。车祸冲破了她的防线，于是她就露出了本性。你可不要怜香惜玉，浪费你的感情，她现在这个样子，其实就是她的本来面目。”

在这段时间里，拉里一句话也没说。他似乎在思考着什么，我们的话恐怕并没有听进耳朵里去。伊莎贝尔说完话，一时谁都没有再吭声。后来，拉里开了口，声音古怪、单调，不像是对我们说话，而像自言自语，目光仿佛飘向了如烟似雾般过去的岁月。

“记得她十四岁的时候留着长发，头发从额头朝后梳，在后面打一个黑蝴蝶结，脸上有雀斑，表情沉稳。那时，她是个谦虚、高尚、充满理想的孩子，什么书都喜欢看。我们经常在一起谈诗论文。”

“什么时候呀？”伊莎贝尔把眉头微微一皱，问道。

“哦，就是你和你的母亲出外从事社交活动的时候。我常到她祖父家，我们就坐在他们家的大榆树下读书，有时我给她念，有时她给我念。她喜欢诗歌，写了许多诗呢。”

“那个年龄的女孩子都喜欢写写诗，都是些蹩脚的歪诗。”

“当然，那是许久以前的事了。那时候，我不太懂诗，看不出来优劣。”

“那时候，你顶多也只有十六岁。”

“当然喽，她的诗都是模拟之作，许多地方学的是罗勃特·弗罗斯特[136]。不过，我觉得那么小的孩子能把诗写成那样，相当了不起。她心思细密，写出的诗很有节奏感。乡间的声音和气息——早春柔和的芳香以及干旱土地在雨后散发出的气味，都能引起她的共鸣。”

“我从来不知道她在写诗。”伊莎贝尔说。

“她守口如瓶，生怕你们会取笑她。她比较害羞。”

“她现在可不害臊了。”

“我从战场上归来时，她几乎已长成个大人了。关于工人阶级的生存状况，她读了许多这方面的书，在芝加哥也有所耳闻目睹。她痴迷于卡尔·桑德堡[137]的诗，自己也拼命写自由体的诗，反映穷苦人水深火热的生活以及工人阶级受剥削的情况。依我看，她的诗平淡无奇，然而却感情真挚，满怀同情之心，充满了热忱。那时，她想当一个社会工作者。她那种对公益事业的献身精神让人感动。我觉得她很有能力，头脑一点不糊涂，遇到问题不是感情用事，而给人一种纯洁可爱、心灵高尚的印象。那一年里，我们经常见面。”

可以看得出，伊莎贝尔越听越恼怒。拉里全然不知自己在拿刀子捅她的心窝，每说一句话，就像是用刀子在她的伤口上搅动了一下。不过，轮到伊莎贝尔说话的时候，她的嘴角却挂着笑容。

“她怎么会选中你，对你推心置腹呢？”

拉里用坦荡的目光望了望她。

“我也不清楚。你们都是有钱人，而她家很穷，我和她都不属于你们那个阶层。我到马文去，只是因为纳尔逊叔叔在那儿行医。也许，她觉得我们俩在这方面有共同之处吧。”

拉里举目无亲。一般人都有些堂兄堂妹什么的，虽然并不熟悉，却至少有一种感觉，觉得自己是一个家族的成员。拉里的父亲是独生子，母亲是独生女；他的祖父是教友派教徒，年纪很轻时就在海上遇难，他的外祖父没有兄弟，也没有姐妹。在这个世界上，恐怕数拉里最为孤单了。

“索菲爱你，这些你可曾想到过吗？”伊莎贝尔问。

“从没想到过。”拉里笑了笑说。

“哦，她是爱你的。”

“拉里是战场上负了伤的英雄，当年返回故乡时，半个芝加哥的女孩子都迷上了他。”格雷以他那种坦率的语气说。

“索菲不仅仅是迷恋，还崇拜你。可怜的拉里，她的感情你难道一无所知吗？”

“我当然不知道。我也不相信。”

“也许，你把她想得太高尚了。”

“我仿佛仍能看见那个瘦瘦的小女孩，头发上扎了个蝴蝶结，表情严肃，读起济慈的颂歌来，声音有点发抖，眼里涌出泪水来，因为济慈的诗写得太美了。真不知那个小女孩今在何方。”

伊莎贝尔微微吃了一惊，带着迷惑不解的神情把拉里看了一眼。

“时间太晚了。我累得都不知道怎么样才好了。咱们走吧。”

三

第二天傍晚，我搭乘蓝色列车[138]去了里维埃拉，两三天后前往安提比斯去看望艾略特，把巴黎的新闻告诉了他。他看上去气色很糟，蒙特卡蒂尼的疗养并没有取得预期的疗效，而事后去各处旅行又弄得他精疲力竭。他在威尼斯找到一只圣洗池，然后又到佛罗伦萨去买下那幅经过讨价还价才敲定的三联浮雕画。他急于把这些东西安装在教堂里，便跑到了蓬蒂内沼泽去，下榻于一家条件很差的客栈，屋里热得令人无法忍受。他买的那些宝贝东西要很长时间才能到货，但他下定决心不达目的誓不离开，于是就坚持了下来。最后，一切料理停当，他对效果极为满意。见了我，他就自豪地把拍的照片拿给我看。教堂虽然小，但很有气派，内部装修富于情调，对艾略特高雅的艺术品味是一种佐证。

“我到罗马时，看见一具早期基督教时期的石棺，不由动了心，考虑了好久，想把它买下来，但最后想了想，还是放弃了。”

“你怎么会想到要买一口早期基督教时期的石棺呢，艾略特？”

“是给我自己用的，亲爱的老伙计。这具石棺极为精美，可以和门道另一侧的圣洗池配成一双。不过，早期的基督徒都是些矮胖子，他们的石棺装不下我。我可不愿在最后审判日的号声吹响时，膝盖顶着下巴躺在里面，像个胎儿一样。那种姿势太不舒服了。”

我被逗笑了，而艾略特却是一本正经的。

“我想出了一个比较好的办法，并做出了具体安排，中间遇到了一些困难，但这也是在意料之中的。我死后要葬在祭坛前边的台阶跟前。这样，蓬蒂内沼泽的那些可怜的农民前来领圣餐时，会穿着沉重的皮靴踏着我的遗骨走过去。你不觉得这样很酷吗？那儿只放一块普通的石板，上面刻有我的名字和生卒年月。还刻有Si monumentum quoeris, circumspiece[139]，意思“我懂拉丁语，知道这句被人们广泛引用的铭文是什么意思，用不着你翻译，艾略特。”我有点刻薄地说。

“对不起，老伙计。我惯常跟愚昧无知的上流社会的人打交道，一时竟忘了这是在跟一位作家说话。”

他嘴上不饶人，呛了我这么一句。

“有件事情我想对你讲一讲。”他继续说道，“对于身后之事，我已在遗嘱里写明，只是希望你能监督执行。我可不愿葬在里维埃拉，和那些退役上校以及法国的中产阶级埋在一起。”

“我当然会按你的意愿办理，艾略特。不过，我认为那是多年以后的事了，用不着现在就制订计划。”

“你知道，我也是上了岁数的人了。说实在话，离开人世，我并不为之感到难过。兰多[140]的那几句诗是怎么说的来着？我双手烤着火……”

我对诗文的记性虽则很差，但是，这首诗很短，所以我能背得出来：

我与世无争，和谁争我都不愿；

我爱艺术，仅次于我爱大自然；

我双手烤着火，用生命之火取暖；

火渐熄，我已做好了走的打算。

“是这几句诗。”他说。

我不由心想，艾略特真是想入非非，竟拿这几句诗形容自己的状况，实在牵强。

“这首诗淋漓尽致地表达了我的心情。”却听他这样继续说道，“唯有一点我需要补充进去，那就是我终生与欧洲的上流社会打交道。”

“在一首这么短的四行诗里，把你的人生经历加进去恐怕是件棘手的事。”

“社交界已走进了死胡同。我曾经满怀憧憬，希望美国能取代欧洲的位置，创造一个万民敬仰的贵族阶层，谁料经济大萧条将此化为一场空梦。我不幸的祖国越来越叫人失望，成为一个极其平庸的国度。我说出来你也不会相信，老伙计，上次去美国，一个出租车司机竟然称我为‘兄弟’。”[141]

受到一九二九年经济大崩溃的冲击，里维埃拉已好景不再，仍然没有恢复过来。艾略特却依然如故，照旧举办宴会，并参加别人举办的宴会。他从不跟犹太人你来我往，不过对罗慈吉尔兹家族却是个例外。话又说回来，最为盛大的宴会往往正是这些上帝选中的人举办的。而只要有宴会，艾略特心里就发痒，不得不去。他穿梭于这些聚会，优雅地握握这位先生的手，或者吻吻那位女士的手，表情却忧郁、超然，就像是一个流亡皇族混杂于平民，颇觉尴尬。而那些真正的流亡皇族却审时度势，将结识电影明星视为崇高的愿望。眼下有一种风气，将演艺界的人纳入了社交圈子，艾略特对此是看不顺眼的。可是，一位隐退的女演员在离他家很近的地方建了一座豪宅，敞开门接待四方来宾，内阁部长、公爵、阔太太富小姐在她府上一住就是几个星期，艾略特也成了她的座上宾。

“当然，她的客人形形色色，什么人都有。”他告诉我说，“不过，那些人你不愿意跟他们说话，可以不予理睬。再怎么她也是我的同胞嘛，我觉得自己有义务伸出援手。住在她家的那些法国客人，看见一个会说法语的，心里一定会放松不少。”

有时候看得很明显，他的身体十分不好。我劝他不要把社交活动看得太重。

“老伙计，我这种年龄，只能进不能退。我在上流社会混了快五十年了，此处的道理我哪能不知——你不露面，别人就会把你忘掉。”

真不知他明不明白自己的这一番表白是多么可悲。我都没有心情再去取笑他了，觉得他是一个彻头彻尾的可怜虫。他活着就是为了从事社交活动，而宴会则是他的生命支柱。不邀请他，就是对他的侮辱，无人理睬会叫他丢面子；现在上了年纪，他最怕的就是受冷落。

夏天一溜而过。艾略特在里维埃拉从这头跑到那头，疲于奔命，在戛纳吃午饭，又跑到蒙特卡洛吃晚饭，忽而茶会，忽而鸡尾酒会，使出浑身解数应付场面，不管有多累，他都会强打起精神，装出一副和蔼、健谈和风趣的样子。他知道许多小道消息，对于最近发生的丑闻，除了当事人，恐怕数他了解得最清楚了。假如你向他指出这样的生活毫无价值，他一定会呆呆地望着你，满脸的惊愕，觉得你简直就是个令人扫兴的蠢蛋。

四

秋天来临，艾略特决定到巴黎小住一段时间，一方面是去看看伊莎贝尔、格雷和两个孩子过得怎样，一方面则是为了他所说的“回首都重温旧梦[142]”。之后，他打算到伦敦去定做几件新衣服，再顺便探望一下几个老友。我原计划直接去伦敦，但他邀我和他一同开车到巴黎去。这样的安排挺不错的，所以我就同意了。既然如此，我觉得自己不妨也在巴黎小住一下，起码待上几天总是可以的。这一趟旅途轻轻松松，遇见好的餐馆就停下来又吃又喝的。艾略特肾功能不好，不敢喝酒，只喝维奇矿泉水，但他每次都坚持要亲自选半瓶葡萄酒让我喝。他心眼好，自己虽然不能品尝美酒佳酿，可是见我喝得快活，他也感到由衷的高兴。他非常慷慨，我要费许多口舌才能说服他允许我清付我的那一份开销。他津津乐道于他过去认识的那些大人物，听得我有些心烦，但这趟旅行还是令人开心的。穿行于乡间，初秋的景色美不胜收，叫人心旷神怡。在枫丹白露吃过午饭，下午时分才抵达巴黎。把我送到我所下榻的那家普普通通的老式旅馆，他便驱车绕过街角去里茨饭店了。我们提前通知过伊莎贝尔，说我们要来巴黎，所以见到她留在旅馆里的便条，我并不感到惊讶，叫我觉得惊讶的是便条上写的内容：

见条后速来。出大事了。别把艾略特舅舅带来。看在上帝的分上，快来吧！

我的好奇心之强烈不亚于任何人，但我总得先洗洗，换上件干净衣服呀。整理完毕，我就搭上一辆出租车到圣纪尧姆大街的那幢公寓楼去了。抵达后，我被引进了客厅里。伊莎贝尔见了我，立刻跳起来。

“你这是到哪儿去了？我都等你几个小时了。”

此时是下午五点钟。我还没有来得及回答，管家就把茶具送了来。伊莎贝尔双手紧握在一起，不耐烦地看着管家摆茶具。我想象不出究竟出了什么事。

“我们刚到，中途在枫丹白露吃了顿午饭，耽搁了一下。”

“上帝呀，摆个东西怎么这么慢！快把人急疯了。”伊莎贝尔说。

管家先将托盘连同茶壶放在桌子上，然后摆上糖缸和茶杯，再把一盘盘的面包、黄油、蛋糕、甜饼放在旁边，动作慢悠悠的，的确叫人着恼。做完这一切，他走出客厅，随手关上了门。

“拉里要跟索菲·麦克唐纳结婚了。”

“索菲·麦克唐纳是谁？”

“别装蒜了！”伊莎贝尔大叫一声，眼里喷射出怒火来，“就是你带我们去的那家肮脏咖啡馆里碰见的那个喝醉酒的荡妇。天知道你为什么把我们带到那种地方去。那一趟叫格雷恶心透了。”

“哦，你指的是你们那个芝加哥的朋友吧？”我没理会她的不公正责备，这样问道，“你怎么知道他们要结婚？”

“我怎么知道？拉里昨天下午跑来，是他亲口告诉我的。我都快气疯了。”

“你不妨坐下来，给我倒杯茶，慢慢讲给我听。”

“茶还是你自己倒吧。”

她一屁股坐到茶桌旁，气哼哼地看着我倒茶。倒完茶，我舒舒服服地坐在了壁炉跟前的一张小沙发上。

最近不常见他——我指的是从迪纳尔返回之后。他去迪纳尔待了几天，不肯跟我们住在一起，而是下榻于一家旅馆。那几天，他常到海滩上陪孩子们玩。孩子们十分喜欢他。我们还曾经到圣布里亚克打过高尔夫球。一天，格雷问他再见到过索菲没有。

‘见过，见过好几次呢。’他回答说。

‘为什么要见她？’我问。

‘她是个老朋友嘛。’他说。

‘我要是你，就决不会在她身上浪费时间。’我说。

他听了微微一笑。你知道他是怎么笑的，就好像你说的话很滑稽一样（其实一点也不滑稽）。

‘可是，你不是我呀。’他说。

我当时耸了耸肩膀，转到别的话题上了。之后再也没有多想过。当他跑来告诉我，说他们打算结婚时，你可以想象得出我有多么震惊。

‘你不能跟她结婚，拉里。’我说道，‘你不能这样做。’

‘我已经决定了。’他说道，那股若无其事的劲儿，就像是在点菜，吩咐再来一份炒土豆一样，‘我想让你对她好一些，伊莎贝尔。’

“‘这个要求太过分了。’我说道，‘你发疯了。她是个坏女人，非常坏。’”

“你怎么会这么想？”我打断她的话说道。

伊莎贝尔望着我，眼睛里直冒火。

“她从早到晚喝得烂醉。不管谁让她陪睡，她就跟人家上床。”

“这并不能说明她就是坏人。不少受人尊敬的人也喜欢酗酒，喜欢干一些下流的事情。这是坏习惯，就跟有人喜欢咬指甲一样。我就不知道这样的人能坏到哪儿去。我觉得只有那些坑蒙拐骗、丧尽天良的人才是坏人。”

“你要是一味偏袒她，看我不收拾你。”

“拉里是怎么又和她见的面？”

“他在电话簿上找到她的住址，便跑去看她。她正在生病——这也难怪，她那样糟践自己，哪能不病。他为她请医生，并安排人伺候她。他们就这样来往起来。拉里说她戒了酒。这个笨蛋竟然认为他把她给治好了。”

“你忘了拉里给格雷治病的事了吗？难道不是他把格雷的病治好了吗？”

“那是两码事。格雷渴望被治好，而她没有这个意愿。”

“你怎么知道她没有？”

“因为我了解女人。一个女人堕落到那种地步，就会破罐子破摔，是决不愿走回头路的。索菲今日的堕落，完全是本性使然。你以为她会对拉里忠贞不渝吗？当然不会。迟早有一天她会跟拉里分手。这是由她的本性决定的。她喜欢的是流氓，因为这让她感到刺激，所以她非流氓不要。她会把拉里置于水深火热之中。”

“这种情况很有可能会出现。不过，咱们也只能干瞪眼，爱莫能助。他这是明知山有虎偏向虎山行呀。”

“我是爱莫能助，你却可以帮助他。”

“我？”

“拉里喜欢你，听你的话。只有你能够对他施加影响。你见过世面，不妨去劝劝他，让他不要做傻事，免得毁掉自己的生活。”

“他会叫我少管闲事——他如此说不无道理。”

“可是，你喜欢他呀，至少可以说对他感兴趣呀，总不能袖手旁观，眼睁睁看着他一步步走进泥潭。”

“格雷是他的老朋友，和他的关系最铁。我认为劝说是劝不动的，但如果要劝，格雷恐怕也是最合适的人选。”

“哼，格雷！”她不耐烦地哼了声鼻子。

“话又说回来，事情也不一定像你想的那样一团糟。我认识两三个人——一个是在西班牙，两个是在东方，他们娶了妓女当老婆，小日子过得挺好。那些女子对丈夫感激涕零，因为丈夫给她们提供了一个安乐窝。她们投桃报李，给丈夫带来了那方面的欢乐。”

“你的话叫人听了心烦。你以为我牺牲了自己的利益，就是为了让拉里落入一个不知廉耻的荡妇手中？”

“你是怎样牺牲自己利益的？”

“我放弃拉里只为了一个原因，那就是我不想影响他的前途。”

“得了吧，伊莎贝尔。你放弃他是为了方形钻戒和貂皮大衣。”

我的话刚出口，就有一盘面包和黄油朝着我的脑袋飞了过来。纯粹凭运气，我一把接住了盘子，面包和黄油却啪嗒落在了地板上。我站起身，将盘子放回到桌子上。

“你把艾略特舅舅的皇冠德贝瓷盘[143]打破一只，他可不会饶你的。这些瓷盘当初是特为第三代多塞特公爵烧制的，几乎是无价之宝。”

“把黄油和面包捡起来！”她怒气冲冲地说。

“要捡你自己捡。”我说完又坐回到了沙发上。

她站了起来，一边生着闷气，一边弯腰捡散落了一地的面包和黄油。

“你还自称是英国绅士呢。”她愤怒地嚷嚷道。

“错了，我可从来没有这么称呼过自己。”

“快从这里滚出去。我再也不想见到你了。看见你就叫我讨厌。”

“这太令人遗憾了。我倒是一直都很喜欢见你。不知是否有人告诉过你，你的鼻子跟那不勒斯博物馆里塞姬[144]石像的鼻子一模一样。这座石像是存世的代表少女美的最优秀作品。你的腿非常优美，修长匀称，我见了总是不由得感到惊奇——你当姑娘的时候，两条腿粗壮粗壮的，简直想象不来怎么变得这么漂亮。”

“靠的是坚强的意志和上帝的恩泽。”她怒气冲冲地说。

“不过，要说迷人，还是你的手最迷人了，那么纤细，那么典雅。”

“我有个印象，好像你觉得我的手太大了。”

“就你这样的个头和身段来说，这双手不算大。你的手运作起来，简直优雅极了，令人不胜赞叹。不管是有意还是无意，你的手一举一动都有一种美感。它们有时候像鲜花绽放，有时候似飞鸟展翅，比任何语言都更富于表现力，很像埃尔·格列柯[145]肖像画里主人公的手。实际上，艾略特曾说你家祖上有个人是西班牙贵族，我原来不信，可是看到你的手我就相信了。”

她气恼地瞥了我一眼。

“你在胡扯些什么呀？这我还是第一次听说。”

我把劳里亚伯爵娶玛丽王后侍女的事给她讲了一遍，说那就是艾略特母系一族的先祖。伊莎贝尔一面听，一面自豪地端详着自己的长手指和修剪涂染过的指甲。

“一个人总得有先祖的。”她说完，扑哧一笑，顽皮地看了我一眼，目光里完全没有了怨气。之后，她又娇嗔地说：“你真坏！”

对于女人，只要说话说得得当，很容易叫她明白事理。

“有些时候，我并不是真的讨厌你。”她说道。

随后，她走过来坐到我身旁，挽起我的胳膊，探过身子就要吻我。我急忙将脸扭开。

“我可不愿让脸颊沾上口红。”我说道，“要吻你就吻我的嘴唇吧，这是仁慈的上帝让人们接吻的地方。”

她咯咯笑了几声，然后把我的脸扳过来，将芳唇印在我的嘴唇上，留下了一道细细的口红的痕印。我感觉美滋滋的。

“好啦，心意领了。现在说说你想让我做什么吧。”

“想听听你的锦囊妙计。”

“我十分愿意效力，只怕你一时听不进去。只有一条锦囊妙计献给你：顺其自然。”

她听了又火冒三丈，蹭地将胳膊抽回去，站起身，跑到壁炉的另一侧，一屁股坐回了椅子上。

“我可不能袖手旁观，眼睁睁看着拉里毁掉自己。我要做出一切努力阻止他和那个荡妇结婚。”

“你不会成功的。你可以看到，他已经被感情迷了心窍，而那种感情是人类胸腔里最炽热的感情。”

“你不会是说他爱上她了吧？”

“不是那意思。与这种感情相比，爱情便微不足道了。”

“此话怎讲？”

“你读过《新约全书》没有？”

“读过一些吧。”

“基督曾经受到诱惑走进旷野，一连四十天没有吃饭的故事你还记得吗？就在他饥饿难忍的时候，魔鬼来到他跟前说：‘如果你真是上帝之子，那你不妨将这些石头变为面包。’可是基督顶住了诱惑。接下来，魔鬼把他放在圣殿的屋顶上对他说：‘如果你真是上帝之子，那你不妨从这儿跳下去。有天使的保护，会把你托起来的。’而基督又一次顶住了诱惑。随即，魔鬼把他带到了一座高山上，把世界上的各个王国指给他看，说如果基督愿意跪下来参拜他，就把那些国家赐给基督号令。可是基督正色说道：‘滚开吧，撒旦！’根据善良、单纯的马太的记载，故事的结尾就是这样。实际上，故事并没有结束。魔鬼很狡猾，他又来找基督，对他说：如果你愿意接受羞辱、鞭打，愿意戴上荆棘编的帽冠，最后被钉死在十字架上，那你便可以解救全人类，因为为了朋友牺牲自己的生命，是人所能表现出的最伟大的爱。这次，基督中计了。魔鬼笑得肚子都痛了，因为他知道坏人会假借为人类赎罪的名义来干坏事的。”

伊莎贝尔愠怒地望着我。

“你这段故事到底出自于何处？”

“就出自于这儿。是我临时编出来的。”

“我觉得这故事荒唐、亵渎神明。”

“我只是想向你指出，自我牺牲是压倒一切的情感，连淫欲和饥饿跟它相比都会显得微不足道。它最大程度地使人格高尚化，诱惑人走向毁灭。它无视目的，不管值得不值得它都会这样做。没有一种美酒能令人如此陶醉，没有一种爱情能使人如此心碎，没有一种罪恶能叫人如此无法抵御。一个人一旦牺牲掉自己，顷刻就会变得比上帝还伟大，因为上帝是无限和万能的，怎么能牺牲自己呢？上帝顶多只能牺牲自己唯一的儿子。”

“哎，老天爷，这话说得太乏味了。”伊莎贝尔说道。

我没理会她，继续说了下去：

“拉里目前就是被这种情感左右着。此时对他晓之以理动之以情，你想会有什么效果吗？这些年他在追求什么，你一无所知，我也不知道，只能猜出个一二来。多年的辛勤劳作，多年的经验积累，如果放在天平上与他的愿望相权衡，就轻多了。那不仅仅是愿望，更是一种迫切、热烈的驱动力，要去挽救一个他认识的女人的灵魂——那女人从前是个清纯的孩子，而今成了荡妇。我觉得你言之有理——他一定会无果而终。他过于注重情感，势必会遭受种种磨难。不管他有什么样的事业，什么样的追求，都将功亏一篑。卑鄙的帕里斯一箭射中阿喀琉斯的脚后跟，使他送了命。[146]拉里缺乏的正是这种狠毒劲——即便是圣徒，如欲修得正果，也得有这种狠劲。”

“我爱他。”伊莎贝尔说道，“上帝知道，我对他无所求，无所图。谁都不可能像我这般无私地爱他。我不愿让他的生活过得不幸福。”

说完，她嘤嘤哭了起来。我觉得哭哭对她有好处，所以没加劝阻。在百无聊赖之际，我的心里突然蹿出了一种想法，于是便琢磨、回味起来。我敢断言，看到基督教发动残酷无情的战争，看到基督徒相互迫害、摧残，看到人世间的凶残暴虐、尔虞我诈及鸡肠小肚，魔鬼考虑一下自己的收获，一定会心满意足的；想到基督教给人类背上了一个原始罪恶的痛苦包袱，使美丽的星空黯然失色，在世人及时行乐的心坎上投下了一道邪恶的阴影，魔鬼一定会开心地笑出声，悄然低语说：这就是报应。

伊莎贝尔哭了一会儿，然后从提包里取出一块手帕和一个小镜子，一边照镜子，一边小心翼翼地擦掉眼角的泪水。

“你就没有一点同情之心吗？”她气愤地问。

我若有所思地望着她，却没有回答她的话。她在脸上扑扑粉，在嘴唇上涂了点口红。

“你刚才说猜出了几分他这些年的追求。此话怎讲？”

“只不过是瞎猜罢了，很可能是错的。我觉得他在寻求一种哲学，也可能是一种宗教，一种可以使他身心都获得安宁的人生准则。”

伊莎贝尔沉吟片刻，然后叹了口气说：

“一个伊利诺伊州马文镇的乡下孩子会有这样的想法，你不觉得奇怪吗？”

“卢瑟·伯班克[147]出生在马萨诸塞州的农场，培植出了无核的橘子，亨利·福特[148]出生在密歇根州的农场，却发明了小汽车，与他们相比，拉里就不显得奇怪了。”

“但那两人经营的是实业，符合美国的传统。”

我听了哈哈大笑。

“天下还有什么比学会有意义地生活更能称得上是实业呢？”

伊莎贝尔有气无力地摆了一下手。

“你不想完全失去拉里，对不对？”

她点头称是。

“你知道拉里是个重情感的人。你不愿跟他的妻子来往，他也会跟你井水不犯河水。假如你不痴不傻，倒不如和索菲交朋友。你必须不计前嫌，尽可能善待她。她即将结婚，恐怕得买些衣服。你何不提出跟她一起去采购？我想她肯定会高兴死的。”

伊莎贝尔眯着眼在听我讲话，好像听得十分专注，一面在想着心事。我猜不出她心里在转什么念头。接下来，她的几句话令我颇觉意外。

“能不能由你出面请她吃午饭？昨天我对拉里说了那样难听的话，再让我请，怪不好意思的。”

“如果我请，你能注意自己的言行吗？”

“我会像个光明天使一样。”她说着，绽出了极为迷人的微笑。

“我这就把此事定下来。”

客厅里有电话。我很快就查到了索菲的号码。凡是拨打法国的电话，都要耐着性子等一会儿才能接通。对方总算拿起了听筒，我通报了自己的姓名。

“我刚到巴黎，”我说，“听说你跟拉里要结婚了。我想对你表示祝贺，希望你们幸福美满。”伊莎贝尔站在我身边，把我胳臂上的肉狠狠拧了一下，疼得我差点没叫出声来，“我在这儿只待很短一段时间，不知道你跟拉里后天能不能到里茨饭店和我一起吃午饭。我请格雷、伊莎贝尔和艾略特·邓普顿一道去。”

“让我问问拉里。他就在跟前。”接下来就是一会儿的停顿。“好的。我们将会很高兴的。”

我讲定了时间，又说了几句客套话，然后就把话筒放下了。此时只见伊莎贝尔眼里出现了一种神情，叫我有点担心。

“你在想什么？”我问她，“我不大喜欢你脸上的神情。”

“很遗憾，我原以为你喜欢我这种神情呢。”

“你不是在心里打什么坏主意吧，伊莎贝尔？”

她一听，把眼睛睁得大大的。

“我向你保证没有。事实上，我急切想看看，在经过了拉里的一番改造之后，索菲是否已脱胎换骨。但愿她去里茨饭店时，不要涂成个大花脸。”

五

我举办的这个小宴会还是挺不错的。格雷和伊莎贝尔先到；五分钟后，拉里和索菲·麦克唐纳也来了。伊莎贝尔和索菲亲热地互吻。之后，伊莎贝尔和格雷对她表示了祝贺，祝贺她跟拉里订婚。寒暄间，只见伊莎贝尔飞眼将索菲打量了一遍。索菲的变化叫我看了吃惊。上次在拉佩街的那家咖啡馆见到她时，她浓妆艳抹，头发染成了红色，穿一件亮色的绿上衣，神情放荡，喝得醉醺醺的，浑身上下具有一种挑逗的味儿和狐狸精的媚劲。而现在她一脸的晦气，虽然比伊莎贝尔小一两岁，样子却比伊莎贝尔老许多。她虽然仍旧将头扬得高高的，不知为什么，却叫我觉得可怜。她的头发正在恢复原色，显出染过色的头发和新长出的头发杂在一起的那种邋遢相。除了嘴唇上涂了些口红之外，她什么脂粉都没有搽。她皮肤粗糙，呈现出不健康的苍白色。记得她的眼珠是鲜亮的绿色，而现在却变得暗淡无光了。她穿一件红衣服，簇新簇新的，还配了同色的帽子、鞋子和手提包。对于女装，我不能说自己是个内行，但我总觉得她的这套行头过于招摇和刺眼，不适合今天的聚会。她胸前戴了一件很俗丽的人造宝石首饰，就是里沃利街卖的那种大路货。伊莎贝尔一身黑绸衣，颈上挂一串人工养殖的珍珠，头戴一顶很漂亮的帽子，把她比得廉价和庸俗。

我点了鸡尾酒，不过拉里和索菲都拒绝喝。后来，艾略特姗姗而至。穿过开阔的前厅时，遇见了一个个的熟人，于是他跟这位先生握握手，又在那位女士的手上吻两下，那样子就好像他是里茨饭店的东家，对光临此处的客人们表示热烈欢迎。索菲的事情，我们什么都没有告诉他，只说她丈夫和孩子在车祸中死于非命，现在要跟拉里喜结良缘。当他最终走到我们面前时，他以自己最精通的那一套礼仪对二人表示祝贺，说出的话落落大方、滴水不漏。随后，大家一道步入餐厅。我们共四男二女，于是我让伊莎贝尔和索菲面对面围圆桌而坐，我和格雷分坐在索菲的两边。桌子小，所以谁说话都可以听得清。午宴是提前订好的，专门侍奉酒水的侍者将酒单送了来。

“你压根就不懂酒，老伙计，”艾略特说，“把酒单给我，阿尔伯特。”他一面翻着酒单，一面还说着话，“我自己只喝维奇矿泉水，但看到别人喝劣等酒，我会受不了的。”

他跟侍奉酒水的侍者阿尔伯特是老朋友。二人经过激烈讨论，才把我应当请客人喝什么酒一事决定了下来。随后，他扭过头来问索菲：

“你们准备到哪儿度蜜月呀，亲爱的？”

他瞧了一眼索菲的衣装，几乎不被人察觉地微微皱了皱眉头，于是我判断他对那套行头看法不佳。

“我们打算到希腊去。”

“这十年里我一直都想到那儿去一趟，”拉里说，“可由于各种原因，始终未能成行。”

“这个季节去，景色一定非常迷人。”伊莎贝尔显出一副很感兴趣的样子说。

她和我都记得，当初拉里准备娶她为妻时，提出要带她去的地方正是希腊。对拉里而言，希腊似乎成了度蜜月的必去之地。

席间的谈话进行得并不怎么容易，假如没有伊莎贝尔出面帮衬，我都觉得难以应付当时的场面了。她的表现极其值得称道。一旦冷场的风险出现时，我便绞尽脑汁想发掘出一个新话题，她则站出来捧场，谈笑风生。我对她心存感激。索菲几乎不说话，只有别人跟她讲话，她才勉强回应几句。她已经没有了精气神，似乎一颗心如死灰一般。我心想可能是拉里在改造她时，对她约束过度，令她难以支撑。我怀疑她以前不但酗酒，而且也吸毒，而今突然戒酒戒毒，定会叫她处于崩溃的边缘。有时候，只见二人你看我一眼，我望你一眼。拉里的眼神里含着温存和鼓励，索菲的眼里透露出的则是哀求，令人顿生恻隐之心。格雷天性忠厚，可能本能地觉察到了我所猜测的情况，于是就跟她聊起来，说他以前有头疼病，什么事都做不了，后来拉里治愈了他，还说他现在都离不开拉里了，对拉里感恩不尽。

“如今，我的身体非常棒，”他滔滔不绝地说着，“只要有机会，我就找工作干。目前正在和几个地方接触，希望不久便会有个眉目。啊，能回国去工作，该多么叫人开心呀。”

格雷倒是出于好心，可是他的话也许有些不分场合。我猜想，拉里曾用暗示术（我称之为“暗示术”）医治格雷，并取得了成功，现在又用同样的方法医治索菲酗酒的顽疾，就不知是否能奏效了。

“你现在一点也不头疼了吗，格雷？”

“三个月都没有疼过了。万一出现头疼的苗头，我就紧紧抓住我的护身符，便能转危为安。”他说着，从口袋里掏出了那枚拉里送给他的古币，“这是宝贝，你就是给我一百万块钱我也不会卖的。”

饭后，咖啡端了上来。侍奉酒水的侍者走过来问我们还要不要喝点酒。我们都婉拒了，只有格雷说要一瓶白兰地。酒送来时，艾略特一定要看看是什么牌子的。

“不错，我觉得不错，对你只有好处没有坏处。”

“先生，你也来一小杯吧？”侍者问。

“哎，我是不能喝的。”

随后，艾略特便详详细细地告诉侍者，说他的肾功能不好，医生不准他喝酒。

“这儿有齐白露加酒，喝一点是不碍事的，先生。人人都知道这种酒对肾有好处。我们刚从波兰进了一批货。”

“真的吗？这种酒如今是很难弄到手的。你拿一瓶来我看看。”

这位侍者胖乎乎的，有点气质，颈上挂了长长的一条银项链，一听这话，转身就去拿酒了。艾略特解释说齐白露加酒是波兰的伏特加，各方面都胜似俄罗斯的伏特加。

“当初住在拉齐维尔府上参加打猎时，我倒是常常喝这种酒。你们可是没见那些波兰王子们是怎样豪饮的。真的，我可一点不夸张，他们大杯大杯地喝酒，眼皮都不眨一下。那可都是些金枝玉叶呀，从头到脚都是皇族味。索菲，你一定要尝上几口。伊莎贝尔，你也一样。这种机会失不再来。”

那位侍者把酒拿了来。拉里、索菲和我都不愿沾唇。而伊莎贝尔说她想尝几口。我感到诧异，因为她平时的酒量是很小的，刚才已经喝过两杯鸡尾酒和两三杯葡萄酒了。侍者把那淡绿色的酒液倒了一杯，伊莎贝尔接过来闻了闻。

“啊，酒香扑鼻呀。”

“是不是？”艾略特高声说道，“这是因为他们在酒里加了一种草药，让酒的味道更加醇香。我来陪你喝一杯吧。喝一点点，对身体并无害处。”

“味道美极了，”伊莎贝尔赞不绝口，“真是像琼浆玉液。这样醇香的酒，以前从没有喝到过。”

艾略特把酒杯举到唇边。

“啊，举杯在手，往事历历如在眼前！你们没有在拉齐维尔府上住过，不知道什么是真正的生活。那种风格真是无与伦比。要知道，那是封建社会的回归，仿佛又回到了中世纪。到车站去迎接你的是套着六匹马的马车以及专门的车夫。吃饭时，每个客人身后都站着个身穿制服的家仆伺候。”

他绘声绘色描述着王府纸醉金迷的生活以及豪华奢侈的宴会。我的心里突然冒出一个疑团（显然是毫无根据的疑团），怀疑这是艾略特和那个侍者精心安排的一出戏，只是为了让艾略特有机会吹嘘吹嘘那个王族以及他在王府结识的波兰贵族们的灯红酒绿的生活。他话匣子一打开，想拦都拦不住了。

“再来一杯吧，伊莎贝尔？”

“哎呀，不敢再喝了。不过，这简直像仙酒，喝了叫人心旷神怡。格雷，咱们也应该买几瓶。”

“我叫人送几瓶到你们家去。”

“真的吗，艾略特舅舅？”伊莎贝尔乐不可支地叫了起来，“你对我们太好啦。格雷，劝你尝一尝。这酒闻起来像新割的稻草和春天的鲜花，像百里香和薰香草，味道柔和、爽口。喝这酒，就像在月光下听音乐一般惬意。”

她说话有点语无伦次，跟平时大不相同。我怀疑她喝醉了。筵席散时，我同索菲握手道别。

“你们什么时候结婚？”我问她。

“下下个星期。希望你能来参加婚礼。”

“恐怕那时候我不在巴黎。我明天就到伦敦去了。”

当我和别的客人道别时，伊莎贝尔把索菲拉到一旁，跟她谈了几句话，然后转向格雷说：

“格雷，我现在还不打算回家去。莫利纽克斯服装店那儿有个时装展览，我要带索菲去看看。应该让她看看新式服装。”

“我很乐意去。”索菲说。

大家就此分手。当晚，我带苏姗娜·鲁维埃去吃了顿饭，第二天上午便起程前往英国了。

六

两个星期后，艾略特来到了克拉里奇酒店。他到后不久，我立刻跑去见他。他给自己定做了几套衣服，看到我，便详细地介绍起他选的是什么料子以及出于什么原因，听得我有些不耐烦。最后，我终于找了个空插进话去，问他拉里的婚礼举办得怎么样。

“就没有举办成。”他冷冷地说。

“这话是什么意思？”

“举办婚礼的前三天，索菲失踪了。拉里到处找她。”

“怎么会有这怪事！他们吵架了吗？”

“没有，没有吵架。当时万事俱备，就等着举行婚礼了。我负责把新娘交给新郎。婚礼之后，他们即刻乘东方快车去度蜜月。要是问起来，我倒觉得这样对拉里更好。”

我猜想伊莎贝尔把所有的一切都告诉了艾略特。

“到底出什么事了？”我问。

你肯定记得那天咱们在里茨饭店吃过饭，伊莎贝尔带索菲去了莫利纽克斯服装店。还记得索菲穿的那件衣服吗？简直不能看！你注意那件衣服的肩部了吗？一件衣服剪裁得好不好，全看肩部合不合体。当然喽，莫利纽克斯服装店的衣服，可怜的索菲是买不起的。你也知道伊莎贝尔是个非常慷慨的人，念着她们自小就认识，她提出要送给索菲一件衣服，至少能让索菲在结婚时穿得体面一些。索菲自然高兴得不得了。长话短说，有一天，伊莎贝尔约索菲三点钟到她家里来，二人一同去服装店最后试样。索菲来了，但不幸的是伊莎贝尔要带两个孩子去看牙医，四点钟之后方才回到家，而索菲已经走了。伊莎贝尔以为她等得不耐烦，自己到莫利纽克斯服装店去了，于是急忙往那儿赶，到了那儿才知道索菲压根就没有去。伊莎贝尔只好作罢，又回到了家里。那天，他们约好要在一起吃晚饭的。拉里按时赶来，伊莎贝尔一见他就问索菲在哪里。

“拉里被问蒙了，急忙给索菲的住处挂电话，但没人接，于是他说自己要到那儿去看看。吃饭的人等啊等的，始终没见他俩露面，最后只好自己吃了。你们在拉佩街巧遇索菲之前，她过的是什么日子，这你应该是知道的。最为不幸的是，你竟然能想到把他们带到那种地方去。拉里跑了一整夜，把她常去的地方找了个遍，但一无所获。他往她住的公寓楼跑了一趟又一趟，而看门人总说她没有回来。他花了三天的时间马不停蹄地找，而她像人间蒸发了一样。第四天，他又去公寓楼打听，看门人说她回来了一趟，把东西打了一个包，乘出租车走了。”

“拉里是不是心里非常难过？”

“我没见他人，只是听伊莎贝尔说他感到挺难过的。”

“索菲没留下纸条什么的吗？”

“什么都没有留。”

我沉吟良久，最后问道：

“你是怎么看待这件事的？”

“老伙计，恐怕跟你的看法完全一致。她坚持不下来了，又故态复萌，继续过她那种醉生梦死的日子了。”

这是明摆着的事实，可我仍觉得有点蹊跷，不明白她为何偏偏在这个节骨眼上开溜。

“伊莎贝尔怎样看？”

“她当然心里不好受。不过，她是个理智的孩子。她告诉我说，她一直觉得拉里要是娶了那样的女人，一定会是场灾难。”

“拉里怎么样啦？”

“伊莎贝尔对他体贴入微。她说难就难在他不愿谈及此事。他一定会恢复过来的。伊莎贝尔说他压根就不爱索菲，和她结婚完全是出自于一片侠肝义胆。”

可以看得出，遇到这突发事件，伊莎贝尔表现得如此淡定，内心八成会感到幸灾乐祸。我敢肯定，下次见到她，她一定会说早就知道会有这种后果。

不过，再次见到她，差不多是在一年之后了。那时，我本可以陈述索菲事件的利害关系，叫她三思，可是鉴于当时的处境，我没有了这份情绪。我在伦敦一直住到圣诞节前夕，然后直接回到里维埃拉自己家里，中途没有在巴黎停留。我着手写一部小说，这以后的几个月里都过着与世隔绝的生活。对于艾略特倒是时不时见上一面。他的健康显然在不断恶化。尽管如此，他仍坚持参加社交活动，看了让人心痛。他还是一如既往地不断举办宴会，要我驱车三十英里赶去参加，而我却不肯，这叫他很是气恼。他觉得我不喜欢社交，却喜欢待在家里写作，显得有些太自命不凡了。

“这是一个非凡的季节，让人激动不已，老伙计。”他对我说道，“把自己关在家里闭门谢客，任大好时光白白流淌，简直就是犯罪。你来里维埃拉，偏偏挑了一个死气沉沉的地区居住，我就是活上一百年也弄不懂。”

可怜、善良又有点傻气的艾略特，显然是活不到那把岁数了。

六月份，小说的初稿已经完成。我觉得自己该休息休息了，于是打起行囊，搭乘一只独桅纵帆船（夏天我们经常乘坐此船去福斯湾洗海水浴），扬起风帆，沿着海岸向马赛驶去。由于海风时起时停，我们的帆船大部分路程都靠备用马达突突突地驱动。中途在戛纳港住了一夜，到了圣马克西姆和萨纳里又各住了一夜，然后就到了土伦。我对土伦港素有好感。港湾里法国舰队的船只让你见了立刻产生一种浪漫和亲切的感觉。在土伦古老的街道上溜达，叫你永远也不会厌倦。我流连于这儿的码头，一待就是好几个小时，观看上岸休假的水兵三三两两地闲逛，有的与女友相依相伴，观看平民百姓迈着悠闲的四方步来来往往，就好像除了享受欢乐的阳光外，世界上再没有其他的事可做了。土伦港水域辽阔，各种轮船和渡船将熙熙攘攘的人群分流到各个码头去，于是你就有了一种印象：此处是终点站，包罗万象，是一个融合了大千世界形形色色特征的地方。当你坐在一家咖啡馆里，眼睛被水色天光弄得有点眼花缭乱时，你的幻想会插上翅膀，带你踏上金色的旅途，到天涯海角去。你幻想着自己坐上一条古老的船，在太平洋上远航，来到一片珊瑚海滩，周围长满了椰子树；你走下舷梯，到了仰光的码头上，坐上一辆黄包车；你幻想着你的船抵达了太子港，停泊在码头旁，你从甲板上望去，看见一群黑人站在码头上，又是欢呼，又是挥手致意。

我们的船是在快到中午的时候抵达的。下午的时间刚过了一半，我上岸沿着码头走去，一边走一边东瞧瞧西看看，看那些店铺，看那些从身边走过的路人，看咖啡馆外边坐在遮阳篷下的客人。突然间，我一眼瞧见了索菲。与此同时，她也看见了我。她嫣然一笑，冲我打了个招呼。我停下来和她握手。她独自坐在一张小桌子旁，面前放一只空玻璃杯。

“请坐下来喝一杯。”她说道。

“你也陪我喝吧。”我说着，在一把椅子上落了座。

她上穿一件法国水手的那种蓝白条子海魂衫，下穿一条大红裤子，脚蹬凉鞋，露出几个大脚趾，趾甲盖上涂了红色的指甲油。她没有戴帽子，头发剪得短短的而且烫过，发色是淡金色，近乎银色。她浓妆艳抹，一如当初在拉佩街遇见她时那样。从桌上的小碟可以看出她已经喝过一两杯了，不过并无醉意，好像见到我没有觉得讨厌。

“巴黎的朋友们还好吗？”她问。

“也许都好着呢。自从那天咱们一起在里茨饭店吃过午饭之后，我就再没有见过他们。”

她从鼻孔里喷出一大股烟，哈哈笑了起来。

“最后我还是没有跟拉里结婚。”

“这我知道。为什么？”

“亲爱的，事到临头，我觉得自己不是抹大拉的马利亚[149]，不配得到耶稣基督的化身拉里的拯救。我做不到，先生。”

“是什么原因使得你在最后关头改变了主意？”

她嬉皮笑脸地望着我，脑袋傲然朝起一扬，小奶子、水蛇腰，再加上她的那身装束，俨然就是个小顽童。不过，必须承认，上次见面时，她一身红装，显得有些俗丽，带几分凄惨，而现在却媚人多了。她的脸和脖子被阳光晒成了紫铜色，而这种肤色令涂了胭脂的脸蛋和抹了睫毛油的眉毛显得分外刺眼——她身上的俗气也不乏妩媚之处。

“想听我说一说吗？”

我点了点头。此时，侍者把我为自己要的啤酒以及为她要的白兰地和苏打水送了来。她用刚抽完的一根粗丝卷烟的烟屁股又燃起了一根。

“那三个月里，我滴酒不沾，一口烟也没有抽过。”她见我露出了诧异的神色，哈哈一笑解释说，“我指的不是纸烟，而是鸦片。那感觉简直是活受罪。有时跟前没人，我就可着嗓门吼叫，能把屋子都震塌。我会对自己说：‘我受不了了，再也受不了了！’和拉里在一起的时候，还不是那么糟糕，而他一旦不在跟前，人间就成了地狱。”

我一直在看着她。当她提到鸦片时，就更加注意打量起她来，发现她的瞳孔缩成针眼一样大，说明她又在吸毒了。她的一对眼珠子特别绿，绿得惊人。

“伊莎贝尔要送我一件婚礼时穿的衣服，不知现在那件衣服怎么样了。那件衣服漂亮极了。当时说好我去找她，然后我们俩一块儿去莫利纽克斯服装店。在这方面，我佩服伊莎贝尔，关于衣服的知识，没有她不知道的。我到了她家，管家说她带琼去看牙医了，给我留了话，说她马上就回来。我走进客厅，见咖啡壶和杯子还放在桌子上，于是便请求管家给我煮一杯咖啡。那时，能提神的只有咖啡了。他说这就为我去煮，走时顺手将空咖啡杯和咖啡壶拿走了，盘子里有一瓶酒却没有拿走。我看了看，发现那酒正是你们在里茨饭店热议的波兰货。”

“那是齐白露加酒。记得艾略特说要送几瓶给伊莎贝尔的。”

“你们对那酒赞不绝口，说闻起来赛过仙醪。我起了好奇心，取下瓶塞闻了闻。果真名不虚传，酒香扑鼻。我点起一支香烟。过了几分钟，管家把咖啡送了进来。咖啡的味道也很好。人人都夸法国的咖啡好，那就让他们喝去吧，反正我还是喜欢美国咖啡。在这异国他乡，我唯一思念的东西就是美国咖啡了。不过，伊莎贝尔的咖啡还是挺不错的。我当时感觉很糟，一杯咖啡下肚，精神便好了些。我看看桌子上放的那瓶酒，心里像有个馋虫在拱动。我骂了自己一句，下定决心不受其引诱。我又点起了一支烟，心想伊莎贝尔马上就会回来的，可是左等右等不见她来。我感到发毛，坐立不宁。我最怕等人，而屋里连本书都没有。我走来走去的，欣赏着墙上的画，眼光却不停地瞟向那瓶可恶的酒。后来，我想干脆倒一杯出来，欣赏欣赏吧。倒出来一看，那颜色十分漂亮。”

“是淡绿色的。”

“一点不错。怪就怪在，它的颜色就跟它的酒香一样诱人。那种绿色就像你有时候在一朵白玫瑰花心里看见的绿色一样。我迫切想知道它喝起来是不是味道也同样诱人，觉得反正品上一口也于我无害。我原打算只呷一口，却听见了响动，以为伊莎贝尔回来了，便咕咚将一整杯酒吞下了肚，怕的是被伊莎贝尔瞧见我在喝酒。不过，那不是伊莎贝尔弄出的响动。天呀，一杯酒让我感到飘飘欲仙。自从戒酒以来，我还从未产生过如此美妙的感觉。我感到周身又充满了活力。假如伊莎贝尔及时回来，我恐怕已嫁给了拉里。真不知道是祸是福呢。”

“她没有回来吗？”

是的，没有回来。我很生气，觉得她太看不起人，叫我那样等她。此时，我低头一瞧，见杯子里又斟满了酒，心想可能是自己无意中斟上的。信不信由你，我不知道酒是怎么斟满的。再把酒倒回瓶子里吧，好像怪不值得的，于是我便将它喝了下去。没得说，那酒简直就是琼浆玉液。我喝后觉得自己好像变了个人，直想开怀大笑。三个月来，我从未感到如此惬意过。

“那个老家伙曾说波兰人大杯大杯地喝酒，眼皮都不眨一下，这你还记得吗？我心想，哼，管它的，狗日的波兰人能喝，我也能喝。于是，我把剩下的咖啡倒在壁炉里，给杯子里斟酒，斟得满满的。管它什么琼浆玉液不玉液的，喝他娘的！后来的情况我就记不清了，只记得等我罢手时，瓶子里的酒已所剩不多。这时，我觉得三十六计走为上计。这一走，却差点跟伊莎贝尔撞上。刚出她家的门，我就听见了琼的说话声，于是急忙跑上楼梯。等她们母女进了门，我才连滚带爬冲下楼，钻进了一辆出租车。我叫司机赶快把车开走。司机问我到哪儿去，我却冲着他哈哈大笑不止，觉得自己的行为滑稽到了极点。”

“你回你的公寓了吗？”我这是明知故问，因为我知道她没有回公寓。

“你把我当什么傻瓜了吧？我知道拉里会到公寓楼找我的。那些常去的地方，我一个都不敢去，而是到哈基姆那里去了。我知道拉里是绝不会找到那里的。再说，我想过过烟瘾呢。”

“哈基姆是个什么地方？”

“哈基姆嘛，哈基姆是个阿尔及利亚人。在他那里，只要你出得起钱，他就可以给你搞来鸦片。他很够朋友，要什么人就给你弄来什么人——大人、小孩、女人或者黑人。他手边总有六七个阿尔及利亚人随叫随到。我在那里住了三天，都弄不清自己睡过多少男人了。”说到这里，她咯咯一笑，“高的矮的、胖的瘦的、白的黑的，全都有。我要把失去的时间补回来。可是，我的内心并不踏实，觉得在巴黎不安全，老怕拉里会找到我。而且，我身上的钱都花光了。那些兔崽子，你不给他们钱，他们就不和你上床。所以，我离开哈基姆那里，回到公寓楼，给了看门人[150]一百法郎，让她见有人来找我，就说我已经走了。我当下便打点行装，连夜乘火车来到了土伦。到了这里，我心里的一块石头才算落了地。”

“来了后，你就一直待在这里吗？”

“一点不错，而且我要继续待下去。这儿的鸦片烟要多少有多少，是水手们从东方带来的，上等货色，不是他们在巴黎卖给你的那种烂狗屎。我在旅馆里包了一个房间——就是那家海事商务旅馆。晚上你走进旅馆，过道里全是鸦片烟味。”说着，她风骚劲十足地嗅了嗅鼻子，“那味道香喷喷的，有点刺鼻。大家各在各的房间里抽鸦片，给你一种宾至如归的感觉。旅馆不干涉你的事，你带谁回房间都无所谓。他们会在凌晨五点来敲你的门，提醒水手起床归船，所以你就不用担心会误了行期。”说到这里，她话锋一转，又不停点地说了下去，“我在码头边的书店看见了你的书。早知道要碰见你，我就会买下来，叫你签个名呢。”

刚才路过那家书店，我曾停下来看橱窗，注意到在一堆新书里面有一本我的小说的法译本，是新近出版的。

“你可能不会多么感兴趣的。”我说道。

“我不明白你为什么这样说。我可是会读的。”

“恐怕你也会写呢。”

她飞了我一眼，随即爆发出一串笑声。

“是的，小时候经常写几句歪诗。恐怕都是些涂鸦之作，但我那时的感觉很好。我想这些是拉里告诉你的。”说到此处，她稍微停顿了一下，“生活艰辛，应该学会苦中取乐。有乐不取，就是个大傻瓜。”说着，她倔强地把脑袋朝后一扬，“我把书买来，你能给我签个名吗？”

“我明天就走了。你真要的话，我买一本送你，留在你的旅馆里。”

“那太好了。”

就在这时，一艘海军的摩托艇开到了码头边，一群水手争先恐后上了岸。索菲用眼睛在他们当中搜索着。

“那是我的男朋友。”她向其中的一个挥了挥胳臂，“你可以请他喝一杯酒，然后最好离开我们。他是个科西嘉人，和咱们的老朋友耶和华一样喜欢拈酸吃醋。”

一个年轻人走了过来，看到我，先是迟疑了一下，见索菲向他招手，便来到了我们的桌前。他高高的个子，紫红脸膛，胡子刮得干干净净，黑眼珠神采奕奕，鹰钩鼻，一头卷发乌黑乌黑，看上去还不到二十岁。索菲介绍我时，说我是她童年时代的一个美国朋友。

“他不会说话，但长得漂亮。”索菲用英语对我说。

“你喜欢粗野豪放类型的，是不是？”

“越是粗野豪放越合我的心意。”

“总有一天，你的喉咙会被他们割断的。”

“这一点也不奇怪。”她咧嘴一笑说，“早死早好。”

“你们能不能讲法语呢？”水手厉声说。

索菲冲他微微一笑，笑容里含着几分嘲弄，接下来讲了一通法语，语调流畅，夹杂着一些俗语，美国口音很重，但这样一来，却使她平日使用的下流猥亵语言带有一种滑稽腔调，使人忍俊不禁。

“我在对他讲，说你长得漂亮，怕你不好意思，才用的英语。”随后，她对我说：“他身体很棒，肌肉发达得就像个拳击手。你摸摸看。”

索菲的一番奉承叫水手怒意顿消。他得意地把胳膊一弯，鼓起胳膊上的二头肌。

“你摸摸看。”他说道，“来呀，来摸呀。”

我摸了摸，表示自己羡慕得不得了。我们在一起聊了几分钟。之后，我付了酒钱，起身要走。

“我得告辞了。”

“见到你很高兴。别忘了那本书。”

“不会的。”

我跟他俩握手道别，然后抽身离开了。途中经过书店时，买下了那本小说，在书上写了我和索菲的名字。这时，我突然想起了龙沙[151]那首广为引用的精美小诗，又想不出别的什么可写，便将小诗的第一句写在了书上：

亲爱的，让我们看看这玫瑰花……

我把书留在了索菲的旅馆里。旅馆就靠近码头，我自己也常住在那里。天麻麻亮，你就会被大喇叭吵醒，叫唤人们快起来上班去；阳光如烟似雾，照在港湾平静的水面上，给幽灵一般的船只披上了一层美丽的色彩。次日，我们的船扬帆驶往卡西斯。我准备在那里买些酒，然后到马赛去，在马赛再换乘一艘预订好的船。一个星期后，我回到了家里。

七

我看到艾略特的男仆约瑟夫写来的一封信，说艾略特卧病在床，很想见见我。于是，次日我便驱车去了安提比斯。约瑟夫在领我上楼见他主人之前，告诉我说艾略特突患尿毒症，医生认为病情不容乐观，好在他挺了过来，现在病情好转；不过，他的肾脏有问题，不可能完全康复。约瑟夫跟随艾略特四十年，对他忠心耿耿，可是，尽管表面显得难过，却不难看出内心在幸灾乐祸——仆人们多数如此，一旦主人家祸起萧墙，他们不忧反乐。

“先生真可怜。[152]”约瑟夫叹了口气说，“他有他的怪癖，但归根结底也算是个好人。人迟早都是要死的。”

他说话的口气就好像艾略特眼看就要断气了似的。

“我敢说他把你今后的生活已安排好了，约瑟夫。”我板着脸说。

“但愿如此。”他语气哀痛地说。

他把我领进艾略特的卧房时，我却意外地看到艾略特一副生龙活虎的样子。他固然脸色苍白、面相衰老，但精神头很好。他刮了脸，头发梳得整整齐齐，身穿淡蓝色丝绸睡衣，睡衣口袋上绣着他姓名的缩写字母，而字母上方则绣着他的伯爵冠饰。在翻过来的被单上，也绣有这些字母和冠饰，型号比睡衣上的要大许多。

我问他感觉如何。

“感觉好极了。”他乐呵呵地说，“只不过偶染小恙，用不了几天就可以活蹦乱跳了。我约了迪米特里大公在星期六和我共进午餐。我已告诉了我的医生，让他无论如何要在这之前把我的病治好。”

我陪他坐了半小时，出来时告诉约瑟夫，说如果他的病复发，就来通知我。一个星期后，我到一个邻居家赴午宴，却惊奇地发现艾略特也在那里，穿着礼服，脸色像死人。

“你不应该出来，艾略特。”我对他说。

“胡说什么呀，老伙计。弗里达请了玛法达公主呢。从路易莎在罗马任上的时候起，我认识意大利王室已有多年了。我说什么也不能叫可怜的弗里达失望。”

他年事已高，且身患绝症，对社交活动却始终保持着高涨的热情，真不知是应该敬佩他不屈不挠的精神还是应该可怜他。你绝对不会想到他这个样子，竟然是个病人。他就像一个垂死的演员，脸上涂了油彩，登台表演时，立刻忘掉了病痛。他担任捧场的角色，潇洒自如地将此角色扮演得极其到位，对客人们和蔼可亲、殷勤周到，用他最擅长的手法捧臀啜屁，却妙语如珠，令人开怀。我觉得自己从未见过他把社交艺术发挥到如此高的水平。当公主殿下离开时，艾略特弓腰送行，风度雅致，既表现了对公主崇高身份的尊敬，又表现了一个老人对一个年轻美丽女子的景慕，令人叹为观止。难怪设宴的女主人事后称他为宴会的生命和灵魂。

几天后，他又卧倒在了病床上。医生对他下了禁令，不许他离开房间半步。艾略特为此感到非常窝火。

“早不病晚不病，偏偏这个时候病了。社交季节正如火如荼。”

他列了一长串重量级人物的名单，说他们夏天齐聚里维埃拉。

我每隔三四天都去探望他一次。他有时候躺在床上，有时候穿一件华丽的晨衣坐在一把躺椅上。这种晨衣他似乎备有无数件，记得从未见他穿重过样。八月初的一天，我又去看望他，发现他反常地少言寡语。迎我进门时，约瑟夫曾告诉我，说他病情有所好转，所以见他如此没有精神头，我便觉得有些奇怪了。我把自己得来的一些当地的小道消息讲给他听，想让他高兴起来，他却一点兴趣也没有。他双眉微蹙，脸上有种愠怒的表情，这在他是少见的。

“埃德娜·诺威马里举办宴会，你去参加吗？”他冷不丁这样问道。

“不去。怎么啦？”

“她邀请你了没有？”

“里维埃拉的每个人她都邀请了。”

诺威马里王妃原是美国的一个腰缠万贯的富婆，嫁给了一位罗马的王子，此王子可不是意大利的那种穷得叮当响的普通王子，而是一个伟大家族的族长，一个雇佣兵队长的后代——那个队长在十六世纪曾为自己开拓出了一个公国。诺威马里王妃年已六十，是个寡妇，由于不满意大利法西斯政权对她美国的进项课以重税，便来到法国，在戛纳山背面的一块漂亮的土地上盖了一幢佛罗伦萨风格的别墅。她特意从意大利运来大理石，为她那些大客厅的墙壁镶边，还从国外请来画家给她画天顶画。她的藏画和铜像都异常精美；连素来不喜欢意大利家具的艾略特，也不得不承认她的家具十分华贵。她家的花园美观漂亮，游泳池造价肯定不菲。她请客高朋满座，每次都不少于二十个人。她安排好在八月里月圆时举行一次化装舞会。虽然还有三个星期的时间，里维埃拉已经到处都在谈论这次舞会了。那天晚上要放焰火，她还要从巴黎带一个黑人乐队过来助兴。那些流亡的王公贵族相互谈论时又是羡慕，又是妒忌，认为她这一晚的花费足够他们一年的用度。

“真是气派呀。”有的人说。

“简直是发疯。”有的人说。

“没品位。”有的人说。

“你准备穿什么样的衣服？”艾略特问我。

“我不是告诉你了么，艾略特，我就不打算去。你以为我这把岁数了还会穿得花里胡哨去参加什么化装舞会。”

“她没有邀请我。”他声音嘶哑地说。

说完，他用一双倦怠无神的眼睛望着我。

“哦，她会请的。”我平心静气地说，“请帖肯定还在陆续发着呢。”

“她不会请我的。”他声音有些哽咽地说，“这是故意叫我下不了台。”

“哎，艾略特，这我就不能相信了。中间肯定是有些疏漏。”

“我可不是个容人蔑视的人。”

“再怎么说，你身体不好，反正也去不成。”

“去不成也要去。这是本季节最盛大的一次聚会。我只要还有一口气，就是爬着也要去。我要把我的祖先劳里亚伯爵的那套礼服穿在身上。”

我真不知说什么好了，于是干脆闭上了嘴。

“就在你来之前，保罗·巴顿来看过我。”艾略特突然开口说道。

我不能指望读者还记得这个人，因为我自己也得重温前文看我究竟给了他一个什么名字。保罗·巴顿就是那个由艾略特引进伦敦社交界，后来觉得艾略特派不上用场，就不再理会他的美国青年，艾略特恨他恨得牙根痒痒。此人近来相当引人注目，先是因为他加入了英国国籍，后来又由于他娶了一个报界巨头的千金，而这位巨头已经晋升为贵族了。有了这样的后台，再加上此人八面玲珑，显然前途不可限量。艾略特为此像吃了黄连一样心里感到苦涩。

“夜里一旦醒来，听见老鼠窸窸窣窣在壁橱里爬动，我就心想：‘这是保罗·巴顿在朝上爬。’请相信我的话，老伙计，这家伙早晚能钻进上议院的。谢天谢地，那一天我是看不到了。”

“他来这儿有何贵干？”我问。我和艾略特心里都很清楚，这个年轻人无事不登三宝殿。

“让我告诉你，他有何贵干吧。”艾略特气得咆哮道，“他想借用我祖先劳里亚伯爵的那套礼服。”

“恬不知耻！”

“难道你看不出他的用心？显然，他知道埃德娜没有邀请我，也不打算邀请我。这是埃德娜唆使他来气我的。那条老母狗。没有我，她哪有今日。当初，我特意为她举办宴会，她认识的人都是我介绍的。她和自己的司机睡觉，这个当然你也是知道的。真叫人恶心！巴顿来了告诉我，说她要给花园里张灯结彩，还要放焰火。谁不知道我最爱看的就是放焰火。他说许多人死乞白赖跟埃德娜要请帖，却都一一碰壁，因为埃德娜不愿人多，想把宴会办得别开生面。听他说话的口气，就好像我肯定是在被邀请之列似的。”

“你准备把礼服借给他吗？”

“让他去死吧，恨不得把他送进十八层地狱。我就是死了穿着它下葬也不借给他。”说到这里，艾略特猛地从床上坐起，像个发了疯的女人一样，把身子晃来晃去的，“全都是些狼心狗肺的东西。”他咬牙切齿地说，“我恨他们，我恨他们所有的人。当我能够为他们捧场时，他们无一不围着我转。现在我又老又病，他们就把我弃如敝屣。自从我卧床不起，来探望的人不超过十个。这都一个星期了，只可怜巴巴地送来了一束花。我为他们可以说是尽心尽力。他们吃我的喝我的，我为他们跑前跑后，为他们张罗宴会，鞠躬尽瘁地为他们服务。可是，我得到什么回报了呢？什么也没有，一点回报也没有。没有一个人关心我的死活。天呀，全都是些绝情绝义的坏东西。”说到伤心处，他嘤嘤地哭出了声来，大滴大滴的眼泪顺着皱巴巴的脸颊直朝下滚，“真后悔呀，当初就不该离开美国。”

看见这个不久于人世的老人仅仅因为别人没有请他去赴宴，便像个孩子一样号啕大哭，着实可悲可怜。这样的一幅情景叫人吃惊，也难免会心生恻隐。

“不请你也没有关系，艾略特，”我说，“也许那天晚上会下雨，叫他们放不成焰火。”

他一听，就像人们所说的快死的人抓住了一根救命稻草一样，含着泪花笑了起来。

“我怎么没想到。我祈求上天，无比虔诚地祈求上天，愿到时候天降大雨。你说得不错，叫他们放不成焰火。”

我的几句话让他改变了想法，放弃了那些愚蠢的念头。待我辞别时，他即便不是心情快活，也起码是心平气和了。不过，我还是放心不下，一回到家就给埃德娜·诺威马里挂了个电话，说我次日到戛纳去，问能不能和她一起吃顿午饭。后来，她叫人传话来，说她很高兴请我吃饭，但仅仅是便宴。可是我到达后，却发现除她之外，还有十位客人也在场。她是个挺不错的人，慷慨大方、热情好客，只有一个坏毛病，那就是嘴上不饶人。即便是对好朋友，她也会在背后说人家的坏话。这倒不是说她天性恶毒，而是因为大脑愚钝，再想不出别的方式引起别人的注意了。她说的话传出去，被她中伤的人就不再搭理她了。不过，她举办的宴会总是别开生面，过上一阵子，大多数被她得罪的人就觉得不便跟她斤斤计较了。我觉得一开口就求她邀请艾略特来参加即将举办的盛会，会让艾略特丢面子，想想还是见机行事的好。她对这次盛会兴致很高，吃饭时把话头全集中在了这上面。

“艾略特一定会高兴死的，这下子算是有机会穿他那套菲力普二世时代的礼服了。”我尽量做出一副漫不经心的样子随口说道。

“我没有邀请他。”她说道。

“为什么没邀请？”我装作诧异地问。

“为什么要请他呢？他在社交圈子里已风光不再，纯粹是个老厌物、势利眼，就喜欢传播流言蜚语。”

这一番指控用在她自己的身上倒是挺合适的。我觉得她太刻薄，蠢里蠢气的。

“再说，”她又补加了一句，“我想让保罗把艾略特的那件礼服穿上。保罗穿上一定显得很高贵。”

我不再说话，但决心要替艾略特把他朝思暮想的请帖弄到手，不管用什么样的手段都在所不惜。午饭后，埃德娜把她的朋友们带到花园里去散步。这给了我可乘之机。我曾经有一次在这里做过几天客，所以知道一点她家的情况。我猜想可能还会有些请帖剩下来，保存在秘书的房间里。我悄悄向那儿溜去，打算拿一张请帖塞进口袋，回去后写上艾略特的名字寄给他。我知道他病得厉害，根本无法成行，但能拿到这份请帖对他而言却意义重大。可是一推开房门，我却惊呆了，只见埃德娜的秘书坐在她的办公桌旁。我原以为她还没有吃完午饭呢。秘书是个中年的苏格兰女子，名叫吉斯小姐，沙色头发，雀斑脸，戴一副夹鼻眼镜，显出一副守身如玉的处女气质。我急忙稳定住情绪。

“王妃带客人们到花园散步去了。我没事，想着就到你这儿来抽根烟吧。”

“欢迎你来。”

吉斯小姐说话时带有苏格兰语的那种小舌颤音。和自己喜欢的人在一起时，她会表现出一种“干幽默”，而此时她的小舌颤音就颤得更厉害了，会惹得听者发笑。可是，你禁不住笑出声来时，她则向你投来气恼、诧异的目光，就好像她认为你昏了头，竟然觉得她的话好笑。

“这次举办那宴会肯定给你增加了不少负担，吉斯小姐。”我说道。

“忙得团团转，都分不清东南西北了。”

知道她可以信赖，于是我开门见山地说：

“为什么王妃没有邀请邓普顿先生呢？”

吉斯小姐那不苟言笑的脸上此时浮出一丝笑容，说道：

“你知道她是怎样的人。她跟他有过节。是她亲自从客人名单上把他的名字划掉的。”

“你知道，他已是垂死之人了，这辈子也离不开病床了。受到如此冷落，他心里难过到了极点。”

“如果他不想跟王妃闹翻，他就不应该逢人便说王妃跟自己的司机睡觉。她的司机是有老婆的，还有三个孩子呢。”

“她到底睡了没有？”

吉斯小姐的目光从夹鼻眼镜的上方瞟过来，望了我一眼。

“我当秘书已经有二十一个年头了。我有一个原则，那就是相信自己的雇主像白雪一样纯洁。必须承认，有时候我的某个雇主会发现自己已有三个月的身孕，而老爷去非洲猎狮，去了有半个年头。此时，我对女主人坚信不疑的原则会经受严峻的考验。不过，女主人只要到巴黎去一趟，进行一次极其昂贵的短途旅行，就会化险为夷。我和女主人便如释重负，长长松一口气。”

“吉斯小姐，我并不是想抽烟才到这儿来的。我来是想偷一张请帖亲自寄给邓普顿先生。”

“这样做十分不妥当。”

“我也知道不妥当。行行好，吉斯小姐，那就请你给我一张请帖吧。那个可怜的老人反正也是来不了的，只是给他张请帖叫他高兴高兴。他没有什么叫你感到不痛快的地方吧？”

“没有。他对我总是客客气气的。我敢说他是真正的绅士，比大多数跑到王妃这儿骗吃骗喝的人都要强。”

所有重要人物的身边都有些得宠的下属。这些仰人鼻息的人，你是万万得罪不起的。假如他们觉得自己没有得到应有的尊重，他们就会在主子面前放你的冷箭，挑拨离间。和这些人，你是必须要搞好关系的。艾略特比任何人都更懂得这一点，所以对那些穷亲戚、老年女佣或者受主人信赖的秘书，见了面他总会亲热地寒暄几句，或者热忱地赔个笑脸。我敢说，他肯定经常跟吉斯小姐说开心的话，过圣诞节时不会忘了送给她一盒巧克力、一个化妆盒或者一个手提包。

“求求你，吉斯小姐，发个善心吧。”

吉斯小姐把夹鼻眼镜在她那高鼻梁上固定得更牢了些。

“毛姆先生，我坚信你绝不愿意让我去干对我的雇主不忠实的事情；再说，万一叫那个老母牛发现我违背了她的意愿，必定会炒我的鱿鱼。请帖就在这张桌子上，装在信封里。我现在要到窗户跟前向外瞭望瞭望，一是因为我在一个位置上坐得太久了，腿有点僵，想活动一下；二是因为想欣赏一下窗外美丽的景色。当我将脸转过去的时候，背后发生什么事，不管是老天还是任何人都不能叫我为之负责了。”

当吉斯小姐重新回到她的座位上时，请帖已经进了我的口袋。

“今天见到你，真是叫人舒心，吉斯小姐。”我说着，伸出了手，“化装舞会上你准备穿什么服装？”

“我亲爱的先生，我是牧师的女儿，”她回答说，“这种荒唐的事情就让那些上层阶级的人去做吧。只要把《先驱报》和《邮报》的代表们招待好，让他们酒足饭饱，我的责任就算尽到了。我将回到卧室里去，安安静静地看我的侦探小说。”

八

两三天后，我登门去看望艾略特，发现他满脸喜色。

“瞧，”他说道，“我收到请帖了，是今天上午收到的。”

说完，他从枕头下取出请帖递给我看。

“我不是早就告诉过你了么。”我说道，“要知道，你的姓是以T开头的。显然，秘书写请帖才轮到你。”

“我还没有写回信呢。明天会写的。”

我一听，吓了一大跳。

“愿不愿意让我代笔？我走时可以将回信送到邮局去。”

“哪里的话！为什么要你代笔？我完全能自己写回信的。”

我暗忖，幸亏拆信人将会是吉斯小姐。她又不傻，肯定会把信扣下来的。这时，艾略特摇了摇铃说：

“我想让你看看我的礼服。”

“你不是真的要去吧，艾略特？”

“当然要去。自从去比奥蒙茨家参加过那次舞会之后，这套礼服再没有穿过。”

约瑟夫听见铃声走了进来，艾略特让他把礼服取来。那套礼服放在一个大大的扁平盒子里，用薄棉纸包着。这里面有白绸长袜、带衬里的白锦缎裹边的织金布紧身裤，配一件紧身上衣、一件大氅、一条围在脖子上的绉领、一个平顶丝绒便帽、一条长金链子，链子的一头挂着金羊毛勋章。我认出这套礼服是根据提香所画的菲力普二世穿的那套豪华服装仿制的，而那幅画就在普拉多。艾略特却告诉我，说这套礼服是劳里亚伯爵在参加西班牙国王和英国女王的婚礼时穿过的，这就让我觉得他的想象太离谱了。

次日上午正在吃早饭时，我被叫去接电话。电话是约瑟夫打来的，说艾略特夜间又发病了，他急忙把医生请了来，医生说艾略特恐怕连今天也熬不过去了。我让服务生将汽车开过来，然后驱车前往安提比斯。艾略特正处于昏迷状态。艾略特原先坚决不肯用护士，可是我却看见有个护士在场，是医生从那个位于尼斯与博略之间的英国医院找来的，这令我看了心里感到欣慰。我出去给伊莎贝尔发了封电报。她和格雷带着孩子正在拉波勒的那个比较便宜的海滨度假地消夏，来安提比斯要走很远的路，恐怕来不及为艾略特送终了。她还有两个哥哥，但和艾略特多年不见，所以她算是艾略特在世的唯一亲人了。

不过，艾略特求生的欲望异常强烈，要不然就是医生用的药产生了作用，反正就在这一天他恢复了意识。尽管已是垂危之人，他仍强打起精神说俏皮话，问了几个有关于护士性生活的下流问题。这天下午的大部分时间，我都守在他身旁。第二天又去看他，发现他虽然身体十分虚弱，情绪却很好。护士只允许我在跟前待很短一点时间。发给伊莎贝尔的电报仍未见回音，这让我感到焦虑。由于不知道伊莎贝尔在拉波勒的地址，电报发到了巴黎去。怕就怕门房转送电报时耽搁了时间。两天之后，我才收到了回电，说他们立刻启程。事情很不凑巧，伊莎贝尔和格雷乘汽车到布列塔尼游玩去了，刚刚接到我的电报。我查了一下列车时刻表，发现他们至少要三十六个小时才能赶来。

次日一大早，约瑟夫把电话又打了来，说艾略特夜间病情恶化，提出要见我。我一听，急急忙忙赶了过去。我一到，约瑟夫便将我拉到一旁说：

“先生，如果我说的事情不合时宜，请你原谅我的冒昧。按说，我是不信教的，认为所有的宗教只不过是神父玩弄的阴谋诡计，为的是控制人们的思想。可是，先生也知道，女人们并不这么想。我的妻子和女佣都坚持认为我们的主人应该得到最后的祝福。现在时间已所剩不多。”他用眼睛看着我，一脸难为情的神色，“现在的事情谁也说不清。也许，一个人临死之前，最好还是改善与教会的关系。”

他的心态我很清楚。大多数法国人，不管平时怎样揶揄嘲笑宗教，但宗教毕竟跟他们血肉相连，一旦生命到了终点，他们还是愿意妥协的。

“你是要我向他提出吗？”

“先生如果愿意，那是再好不过了。”

这个差事我并不怎么喜欢，但是，艾略特毕竟多少年来都是个虔诚的天主教徒，所以，履行一个天主教徒的职责也是理所当然的。我上楼走进他的房间，见他平躺在床上，脸色憔悴，瘦得都成了个干巴人，但神志十分清楚。我让护士出去一会儿。

“你的病情恐怕十分危重了，艾略特。”我启口说道，“不知道……不知道你愿不愿意请个牧师来？”

他看着我，半天没说话。

“你的意思是说我就要死了？”

“哦，但愿不是这样。不过，不怕一万就怕万一么。”

“我懂了。”

他一时哑了口。

这是一个令人痛心的时刻——明知此话会刺激艾略特，却又不得不说。我不忍心看他，咬紧牙关，生怕会哭出声来。此时，我坐在床沿上，面向他，伸出一只胳臂撑着身体。

他在我的手背上拍了拍，说道：

“别难过，老伙计。要知道，这是必须走的一步。”

我听了，破涕为笑，说道：

“你真是个奇怪的家伙，艾略特。”

“这就对了。现在打电话给主教，说我要忏悔并且接受涂油礼[153]。如果能把查尔斯神父派来，我将感激不尽。他是我的朋友。”

查尔斯神父是主教的代理人，在前边的一章里提到过。我下楼去打电话，跟主教通上了话。

“很急吗？”他问。

“十万火急。”

“我这就办理。”

医生来时，我把刚才的事情跟他讲了讲。随后，他便带着护士上楼去看艾略特，而我守候在楼下的餐厅里。从尼斯来安提比斯只有二十分钟的车程，所以过了半小时多一点，就有一辆黑颜色的大轿车停在了门口。约瑟夫跑来找我。

“是主教本人，先生[154]，”他慌慌张张地说，“主教大人亲自来了。”

我急忙迎出门去。这次，主教没有像往常那样身旁跟着那位代理人，不知怎么却带来了一个年轻的神父，这位神父手捧一个匣子，我想里面可能装的是施涂油礼的用具。司机紧随其后，手提一只寒碜的黑色旅行箱。主教和我握了手，把同来的神父介绍给了我。

“咱们的那位可怜的朋友怎么样了？”

“恐怕已处于病危状态，主教大人。”

“是不是请你把我们带到哪个房间里去，让我们把法衣换上。”

“这儿是餐厅，主教大人。客厅在楼上。”

“到餐厅里换就很好了。”

我把他领进了餐厅，然后和约瑟夫在过厅里等候。不一会儿，门开了，主教走了出来，后面跟着神父；神父双手捧着一只圣餐杯，杯子上放一个小盘子，里面有一块行圣礼用的圣饼。

这些东西用一块细麻纱餐巾盖着，而麻纱是透明的。之前，我只是在晚宴或午宴上见到过主教，知道他是个大肚汉，喜欢美食美酒，喜欢讲幽默故事，有时甚至还讲些粗俗的笑话。那时候，他给我的印象是一个身体结实强壮的人，只有中等身材。今天他穿上白法衣，披上圣带，看上去不但个头很高，而且庄严肃穆。他的那张红脸，平时总是乐呵呵的，笑容可掬，现在却一副严肃相。从外表上看，过去的那个骑兵军官在他身上找不到一丝痕迹了；此刻，他的面相符合于他在教会的实际地位，一看就知道是个显贵人物。难怪约瑟夫见了肃然起敬，在胸前画了个十字。主教身子微微一躬，点了点头。

“领我去见病人吧。”他说道。

我闪开身子，让他先上楼，而他却叫我走在前边。于是，我们一声不响，一脸严肃地上了楼。我先一步走进艾略特的病房通报道：

“主教大人亲自来了，艾略特。”

艾略特挣扎着坐了起来。

“主教大人亲自光临，我感到不胜荣幸。”

“你别动，我的朋友。”主教叫了一声，然后对我和护士说：“请你们先出去一下。”接着，他又转向那个神父叮咛道：“你也出去，到时候我叫你。”

神父四下里瞧瞧，我猜想他很可能是要找个地方放下手中的圣杯，于是就将梳妆台上的那把玳瑁壳镶背的发刷推开为他腾地方。护士下楼去了，我把神父领进隔壁的房间，此处是艾略特的书房。书房的窗户敞开着，望得见外边的蓝天。他走到一扇窗户前观景。我则坐下来休息。海上正在进行帆船赛，白帆在蓝天的映衬下显得格外耀眼。一条黑壳的大船张起红色的船帆，迎着微风向港口驶来。我认出那是一条捕捞龙虾的船，从撒丁岛那儿满载而归，为赌场提供海鲜，让那些寻欢作乐的赌徒们大快朵颐。艾略特的房门关闭着，却仍能听得见里面有隐隐约约的说话声。艾略特在做忏悔。我烟瘾大发，想点一根烟，却又怕神父不高兴。神父是个身材瘦削的年轻人，一动不动地站在那儿向外眺望，黑黑的头发呈波浪状，一双乌黑的眼睛秀秀气气的，皮肤呈橄榄色，一看就知道是意大利人。他的脸上洋溢着南方人的那种蓬勃的生命力，我不由得心里想到，真不知他有着多么坚定的信仰和燃烧的激情，才使得他放弃了现世开心的生活、青春的欢乐以及世俗人的七情六欲，转而真诚地为上帝服务。

隔壁房间的声音忽然停止了，我抬起头，见门打开了，主教出来了。

“你来吧！[155]”他对神父说道。

屋子里只剩下了我一个人。接着，我听见隔壁房间又传来了主教的声音，情知他在念祈祷词，即教会规定为垂死之人所应该念的祈祷词。随之而至的又是一阵沉寂，我知道艾略特在吃圣餐[156]。恐怕是受到远祖的影响，我虽然不是一个天主教徒，但是每次做弥撒时，听见主的仆人摇着小铃通知人们领圣餐时，总会浑身发抖，产生恐惧感，此时亦哆嗦不已，仿佛寒意传遍全身，心里又害怕又奇怪。书房的门又被推开了。

“你可以进来了。”主教对我说道。

我走进艾略特的房间，见神父正在把细麻纱餐巾盖在圣杯以及盛放过圣饼的那个镀金小盘子上。艾略特的两眼熠熠生辉。

“劳驾你送主教大人上车！”他对我说。

我们一行走下楼去。约瑟夫率三个女佣正等候在过厅里。女佣们热泪盈眶，依次走上前来，跪下亲吻主教的戒指。主教伸出两个指头放在她们头上，为她们祝福。约瑟夫的妻子用胳膊碰了碰他，于是他步上前去，也跪倒在地，吻了吻主教的戒指。主教微微一笑说：

“你是不信教的吧，我的孩子？”

我可以看见约瑟夫在努力保持镇静。

“是的，主教大人。”

“不必介意。你对主人忠心耿耿。上帝对你在认识上的错误会忽略不计的。”

我陪主教到了马路上，为他开了汽车门。他向我弓腰致谢，临上车前冲我仁慈地一笑说：

“咱们可怜的朋友已生命垂危。他表面上是有些缺点的，但内心对自己的同胞宽宏大度、善良慈祥。”

九

想着艾略特刚接受过圣礼，也许不愿见人，我便进了客厅，看起书来。谁知屁股刚坐稳，护士就跑了来，说艾略特想见我。我爬上那串楼梯到了他的房间。他接受圣礼之前，医生曾给他打过一针，叫他振作起来，此时不知是因为这一针的效力，还是因为情绪激动，反正他一副兴奋的样子，眼睛闪闪发光。

“这是莫大的荣誉呀，我的老伙计。”他说道，“这下子，我可以拿着教会一位重要人物的介绍信进天国了。我想，天国里各家各户都会敞开大门欢迎我的。”

“恐怕你会发现那儿什么样的人都有。”我笑了笑说。

“也许你不会相信，我的老伙计，我们从《圣经》上得知，天国和人间一样是有等级区别的。那儿有六翼天使和四翼天使，有天使长和普通天使。在人世间，我游走于欧洲的上流社会，到了天国我毫无疑问也将游走于那儿的上流社会。主曾经说过：‘在我父的家园里有千万住房，分配时应该让众民各得其所。’”

我怀疑艾略特把天国的住房想象成了罗慈吉尔兹男爵的城堡那样的风格——墙上镶有十八世纪的护壁板，有镶嵌细工的桌子、精雕细刻的壁橱以及路易十五风格的器皿，器皿上蒙着路易十五时代的刺绣品。

“请相信我的话，老伙计，”他停顿了一下，然后继续说道，“天国是没有什么绝对平等的。”

说完，他不知怎么昏睡了过去。我坐下来，拿本书看。他一直昏睡不醒。到一点钟时，护士进来告诉我，说约瑟夫把午饭准备好了。见到约瑟夫，发现他一副服服帖帖的样子。

“想不到主教大人竟然亲自大驾光临了，这对我们可怜的主人是莫大的荣幸。你看见我吻他的戒指了吗？”

“看见了。”

“按说，我不会主动去吻的，那样做全是为了让我的妻子见了高兴。”

我在艾略特的房间里待了一下午。这期间，收到伊莎贝尔的一封电报，说她和格雷乘坐蓝色列车第二天上午抵达。我担心他们恐怕赶不上为艾略特送终了。医生来了，见了艾略特的状况直摇头。太阳落山时分，艾略特从昏睡中醒来，可以稍微吃点东西了。肚子里有了食，他似乎暂时有了些气力。他冲我招了招手，我走到了床边。只听他声音极其微弱地说：

“收到埃德娜的请帖，我还没有回信呢。”

“没关系，别管那些了，艾略特。”

“怎么能不管呢？在这个世界，我一直是个懂情理的人，不能因为就要离开这个世界，便置礼节于不顾。请帖在哪儿呢？”

请帖放在壁炉架上，我取来交到他手里，不过我觉得此时他是想看也看不清楚的。

“你去书房找几张信纸来。我口授，由你写回信。”

我走进隔壁的书房，把信纸拿了来，在他的床边坐下。

“你准备好了吗？”

“好了。”

他闭上眼睛，嘴边露出一丝顽皮的微笑。我心里纳闷，不知他会说出什么话来。

“鉴于之前和万能的主有约，恕艾略特·邓普顿无法接受诺威马里王妃善意的邀请。”

他淡淡地狞笑一声，脸色发青，看上去像鬼一样，呼出的气带有一种他这种病特有的恶臭味。可怜的艾略特，平时总是喜欢在身上洒点香水的呀，有时洒香奈儿牌的，有时洒慕尼丽丝牌的。他手里仍旧抓着那张我偷来的请帖。我觉得他那样拿着很不舒服，想从他手里取出来，谁知他紧紧抓住不放，大吼了一声，吓了我一跳。

“老淫妇！”

这是他留在人世间的最后一句话。话一出口，他便陷入了昏迷之中。昨天，护士守在病床旁熬了一夜，看上去疲倦极了，我让她去睡觉，答应在必要时叫她，由我来守夜。其实，守夜是无事可做的，于是我打开一盏带罩子的电灯看起书来，直至把眼睛看得发酸，这才将灯熄灭，坐在黑暗里休息。这是一个闷热的夜晚，窗户都大敞着。灯塔上的探照灯扫来扫去，每隔一段时间就会把光射进屋子里来。月亮隐去了身影，当月圆的时候来临时，就会看到埃德娜·诺威马里的化装舞会那热闹的场面，人声喧嚷却空虚乏味。此时，天空是一片深蓝色，星星多得数不清，一颗颗亮得惊人。我昏昏沉沉的，大概是进入了浅睡之中，但意识还是清醒的。突然，一种急促、愤怒的叫喊吓了我一跳，惊得我彻底醒了过来。那是临死之人发出的叫喊，令人毛骨悚然。我急忙走到病床边，借着灯塔上探照灯的光摸了摸他的脉搏，发现他已经死了。我打开床头灯看看他，见他下巴耷拉着，双目睁开。我静静地望着那双眼，过了一会儿才为他把眼合上。我感到很伤心，觉得有几滴眼泪顺双颊流了下来。一个老朋友，一个善良的老朋友就这么走了。想到他的一生是那么愚蠢、无益和无聊，我不由黯然神伤。他参加过许多宴会，跟王子、公爵、伯爵们举杯同饮，而今一切都化为乌有。那些人已欣然将他淡忘。

我不忍心叫醒那个已经累瘫了的护士，于是就回到窗旁，坐在我的椅子上睡着了。护士在早晨七点钟进来时，我仍在沉睡。醒来后，我丢下护士履行她的职责，自己去吃早餐，然后到车站接格雷和伊莎贝尔。我告诉他们，艾略特已经去世。由于艾略特的家里没有客房，我邀他们到我那儿去住，可他们愿意去住旅馆。我回到自己家中，洗过澡，刮了脸，然后换了身衣服。

这天上午，格雷打电话来，说约瑟夫交给他们一封信，信是写给我的，艾略特生前曾嘱咐由约瑟夫转交。由于这封信只能让我一个人看，于是我答应马上开车过去。不到一小时，我又走进了艾略特的家。那封信的信皮上写着：“我死后即刻转交，内含葬礼的安排。”我知道，他一心一意要葬在他造的那座教堂里，曾把此事对伊莎贝尔讲过。他希望将自己的遗体进行防腐处理，并说出了经营这项业务的公司的名称。“我打听过，”他在信里写道，“人人都说这家公司的防腐术十分高超。我委托你监督此事，一定要做好。下葬时，我要穿上我的祖先劳里亚伯爵的那套礼服，腰挎他的宝剑，胸前佩戴那个金羊毛勋章。至于挑选棺木，交给你决定，不要太招眼，但一定要符合我的身份。为了不给别人增添不必要的负担，遗体的转运事宜由托马斯·库克父子公司承办，让他们派个人护送棺木到下葬地去。”

记得艾略特曾经说过他要穿他那套豪华礼服下葬，当时以为他只是心血来潮，随便说说，没想到他竟然是认真的。约瑟夫坚持要按主人的遗愿办理，也就只好如此了。先是给他的遗体进行了防腐处理，然后我和约瑟夫去给他穿上那套荒唐的礼服。这件差事挺折磨人的。我们给他的长腿套上白绸长袜，再穿上那条金布紧身裤。随后，费了很大的气力把他的两条胳膊塞进紧身上衣的袖管里，给他戴上那浆洗好的宽大轮状绉领，再把锦缎斗篷给他披在肩上。最后，把那个平顶丝绒帽戴在他头上，把金羊毛的领圈围上他的脖子。遗体防腐公司的人在这之前曾给他的脸搽了胭脂，给他的嘴唇涂了口红。他如今骨瘦如柴，礼服穿在身上显得特别大，样子就像是威尔第[157]早期歌剧里的一名歌手，又像是为了没有价值的目标而奋斗的堂吉诃德。当殡葬承办人将他抬进棺材时，我把那柄作为道具的宝剑竖着放在他的两腿之间，让他的手按在剑柄的圆头上——我曾经见一个十字军骑士的墓碑雕塑像就是这种持剑的方式。

格雷和伊莎贝尔一路赶到了意大利去参加葬礼。

第六章

一

在此有必要敬告读者，完全可以跳过这一章，并不影响读者把握本书所叙述的故事脉络，因为这一章的大部分文字记载的基本上都是我和拉里的一次谈话。不过话又说回来，如果没有这次谈话，我觉得写这本书也就没有什么价值了。

二

话说那年秋天，在艾略特辞世两个月后，我前往英国，中途在巴黎逗留了一个星期。伊莎贝尔和格雷到意大利奔丧，之后又回到布列塔尼游览，此时已返回圣纪尧姆大街的公寓楼过起了小日子。伊莎贝尔把艾略特遗嘱的内容详细告诉了我，说他留下一笔钱给他造的那座教堂为他的灵魂做弥撒，另外还捐给教堂一笔维持费。他留给尼斯主教一笔数目可观的钱作为慈善捐献，留给我的则是那些意义暧昧的十八世纪的黄色书刊以及弗拉戈纳尔的一幅画，画面非常漂亮。在弗拉戈纳尔的这幅画里，森林之神在和一个女仙子干那种见不得人的事，由于色情味太浓，不便挂在墙上，而我又不是那种喜欢关上门偷看淫情绘画的人。他对家仆们很是大方，留下的钱不少。他的两个外甥各得一万块钱，余下的家产悉数给了伊莎贝尔。到底余下了多少家产，伊莎贝尔只字未提，我也没问。不过，从她心满意足的表情看来，这笔家产一定不是小数目。

格雷自从恢复健康之后，一直都在想着东山再起，急于返回美国重新工作。尽管伊莎贝尔在巴黎的日子过得很滋润，但格雷焦虑的心情也影响到了她。格雷和生意圈里的朋友沟通已有些时日，但真正的契机是他能够拿出一大笔钱作为资本。按说格雷本人是没有钱的，可是，艾略特给伊莎贝尔留下了一大笔遗产，数目远远超过他所需。所以，在取得伊莎贝尔的同意之后，他和那些人进行了谈判；如果一切进展顺利，他将离开巴黎，亲自实地考察。不过，在成行之前，有许多事情都需要料理。首先，他们必须在遗产税方面和法国财政部达成一项合理的协议。其次，需要处理掉安提比斯的别墅以及圣纪尧姆大街的公寓房。接下来，还得在德鲁奥旅馆筹备一次拍卖，处理掉艾略特的那些家具、藏画和素描。这些东西都是价值连城的宝贝，明智之举是等到来年春天再拍卖——那时，大收藏家们将云集巴黎。在巴黎过冬，伊莎贝尔并不觉得遗憾。两个孩子现在法语说得很棒，跟说英语一样流畅。伊莎贝尔倒是很愿意让她们在法国的学校里再上几个月的课。三年来，她们全长高了，长长的腿，瘦瘦的身体，小家伙们个个活泼可爱，虽然目前还没有母亲的那种天姿国色，却很懂礼貌，有着永不满足的好奇心。

当时的情况就是这样。

三

我和拉里相逢，纯属偶然。我曾经向伊莎贝尔打听过他，伊莎贝尔说自打从拉波勒归来，几乎再也没有见过他的面。她和格雷此时已有了自己的朋友圈，都是同一代的人，经常聚会，比我们四个人时常在一起时的那些快乐日子忙得多。一天傍晚，我去法兰西剧院看《贝蕾妮丝》。这个剧本我当然是读过的，却没看过它在戏台上的表演。由于这是难得一见的盛况，我哪能错过。该剧并非拉辛最优秀的作品，题材太单薄，不足以构成五幕剧，但情节感人肺腑，有几段可以说是脍炙人口。该剧是根据塔西佗[158]短短的一段历史史料虚构的，讲的是提多[159]和巴勒斯坦女王贝蕾妮丝的爱情故事。提多曾情迷贝蕾妮丝，甚至山盟海誓，要娶她为妻，可后来一登基当上皇帝，为了国家的利益，竟然违背自己的心愿，也不顾贝蕾妮丝的感情，将她送出了罗马城。这是因为元老院和罗马的人民都反对自己的皇帝和一个外国女王结合。剧本围绕着提多的心理斗争而展开——他徘徊于爱情和职责之间，难以抉择；贝蕾妮丝知道他爱自己，也理解他的处境，便永远地离开了他。

恐怕只有法国人能够充分欣赏拉辛飞扬的文采和词句里所包含的优美的音律。不过，即便是外国人，一旦熟悉了他那“戴假发”[160]的艺术风格，便不由得会为那种缱绻柔情和高尚情怀所打动。很少有人能像拉辛那样懂得台词里包含着多么感人的戏剧成分。我觉得他的那种流畅的亚历山大体[161]诗句足以弥补情节上的欠缺，剧中人的长篇宏论采用高超的处理手法将剧情推向预期的高潮，和电影里惊险的镜头一样扣人心弦。

第三幕演完后是幕间休息。我走出剧场到大厅里抽烟。那儿耸立着一尊出自于乌东[162]之手的伏尔泰雕像——伏尔泰咧着一张没有牙齿的嘴在讽刺地微笑。突然，有人在我的肩上拍了拍。我转过身去，感到有点气恼，因为我不愿受到打搅，只想独自享受那些精彩的台词给我的心里带来的喜悦。谁知竟是拉里！和往常一样，一见他，我感到由衷的高兴。有一年没见过面了。我提议戏剧散场后去喝上一杯。拉里说自己没吃晚饭，肚子饿了，建议看完戏后去蒙马特高地。剧终，我们俩又见了面，然后一起走到大街上。法兰西剧院有一种特殊的霉味，而这种霉味跟一代又一代女招待员身上的气味混杂在一起。这些女招待员很少洗澡，老是哭丧着脸，把观众领到座位前便赖着不走，硬等着观众给她们小费。从这样的地方走到外边呼吸新鲜的空气，会叫你感到浑身轻松。这是一个美好的夜晚，于是我们漫步走去。歌剧院大街的路灯亮晃晃的，显得傲气十足，天上的群星好像不屑跟它们争奇斗艳，于是便将自身的光华隐匿在了无边无际的黑暗之中。我们一边走，一边谈论着刚才看的戏。拉里感到失望。他倒是希望演戏能演得自然一些，说台词就像平时说话一样，姿势没必要那么过于戏剧化。而我认为他的观点是错误的。该剧以辞藻胜，而且使用华丽的辞藻，所以我觉得说台词就应该拿腔拿调的。我喜欢演员在遇到韵脚时便顿一下加以强调，喜欢他们那格式化的姿势——这种形式有着悠久的历史，是传承下来的传统，似乎很适合于这种偏重形式的艺术格调。我敢说，拉辛一定会愿意让自己的剧本以这种形式加以表演。在重重的限制之下，演员们却能发挥自己的才能，演出了人情味，演出了炽热的感情，真是叫我折服。艺术把传统拿来己用，为的是实现自身的目的——这是艺术之胜利。

我们到了克利希大街，走进格拉夫餐馆。餐馆里人满为患，不过，我们还是找到了一张桌子，点了鸡蛋和火腿。我告诉拉里，说我见到伊莎贝尔了。

“能回到美国去，格雷会非常高兴的。”他说道，“在这儿，他就像是鱼儿离开了水。除非能重返职场，否则他不会快活的。我敢说，他一定能挣很多钱。”

“如果他能成功，也都是亏了你。你不但治愈了他的身体，也治愈了他的心灵。你使他恢复了自信。”

“这是雕虫小技。我只不过向他展示一种方法，让他自我救治。”

“这个雕虫小技你是怎么学来的呢？”

“完全得之于偶然。当时我在印度，正遭受失眠之苦。一次，我把此事给自己认识的一个老瑜伽师随便提了一下，谁知他说马上为我治疗。他的治疗方法就跟你看见我给格雷治病的方法是一样的。结果，那天夜里我睡得很好——我已经很长时间没能睡得那么香了。后来，大概是在一年之后吧，我和一位印度朋友爬喜马拉雅山，他把脚给崴了。跟前找不到医生，他疼得要死。我心想不妨照那个老瑜伽师的办法试一试，谁知竟然奏效了。不管你相信不相信，他的疼痛彻底消失了。”说到此处，拉里哈哈大笑，“我可以向你保证，我当时比任何人都感到意外。其实，没有什么神秘的，你只不过把想法输入到病人的脑子里罢了。”

“说起来容易，做起来难。”

“如果你的胳膊不由自主地从桌子上抬起来，你会感到意外吗？”

“非常意外。”

“情况就是这样。那次回到文明世界后，我的那个印度朋友把我妙手回春的本事告诉了人们，并带了一些病人来。我坚决不愿意出手，因为我压根就不知道那到底是怎么回事，可他们硬缠着我不放。后来，我鬼使神差地竟然把他们全治好了。我发现自己不但能治愈病痛，而且能驱除恐惧。奇怪的是，许多人都患有恐惧症，不是怕幽闭、怕高，而是怕死，更为糟糕的是怕活着。他们往往看上去好像身体健康、事业发达，无忧无虑的，其实深受恐惧症的折磨。有时我心想这恐怕是一种最恼人的心理状况，怀疑它是一种根深蒂固的动物本能，是人类从第一次感到生命战栗的原始生物那儿继承来的。”

他很少说这么多的话，我一边听，一边心里暗暗希望他继续说下去。我有一种感觉——他总算把话匣子打开了。也许，方才看的那出戏剧解除了他的部分戒心，剧中人字正腔圆、抑扬顿挫的台词像音乐一般影响了他的情绪，使得他克服了天生的拘谨。突然间，我感到自己的手发生了变化。刚才对拉里那半开玩笑的提问并没有在意，现在我却觉察到自己的手已不再放在桌面上了，而是不由自主地抬起，离开桌面有一英寸的样子。我吃了一惊，瞧了瞧它，发现它微微有点颤抖。我觉得胳膊上的神经有点发麻，感到它抽搐了一下，随后，手和小臂自己就抬了起来。我干脆听之任之，既不帮助也不抑制。它们离桌面有好几英寸，最后，整条胳膊举过了肩头。

“这真是太奇怪了。”我说道。

拉里哈哈大笑。我稍稍用意志加以控制，那只手便落回到了桌面上。

“雕虫小技，”他说，“不必当真。”

“你刚从印度回来时曾跟我们提到过一位瑜伽师。这一套是不是他教给你的？”

“哦，不是他教的。他才没有耐心理会这种事情呢。一些瑜伽师自称具有神力，我不知他是否也有这种自信心，但有一点是明确的——他觉得这般卖弄是幼稚之举。”

说话间，我们点的鸡蛋和火腿送来了。我们狼吞虎咽吃了起来，一边还喝着啤酒，谁都没有再说话。我不知他在想什么，而我的心里则在思索着他的情况。饭后，我点起一根纸烟，他则抽他的烟斗。

“当初你为什么要去印度？”我冷不丁问道。

“上天的安排。至少我当时是这么想的。现在我倒觉得自己在欧洲多年，到那儿去是一种必然结果。对我影响至深的人，似乎只是偶然相遇，而今回想起来，则好像有着很大的必然性。他们仿佛一直在等着我，等着我在必要的时候和他们相逢。我去印度，是因为我的身心需要得到休息——多年来，我孜孜以求，渴望理清自己的思绪。我登上一艘周游世界的豪华游轮，在甲板上当服务生，开往东方，又穿过巴拿马运河驶向纽约。五年未回美国了，思乡情油然而生。多年前你我初次相遇于芝加哥时，你也知道我当时是多么无知。到了欧洲，我读书破万卷，目睹世间千般变化，但离我上下求索的目标仍相去甚远。”

我原想问问他究竟是什么目标，却又觉得他肯定会付之一笑，耸耸肩，回说不值得一提。

“你也不缺钱，为什么要到游轮上打工呢？”我转而问道。

“我想体验一下生活嘛。一旦心里出现饱和状态，想读书也读不进去时，我发现换换环境大有益处。我和伊莎贝尔解除婚约的那年冬天，我曾到兰斯那儿下煤窑，干了有半年的时间。”

他就是在这个时候讲述了那段经历，此事已在前边的一章里做过交代。

“伊莎贝尔跟你分手，你心里难过吗？”

在回答之前，他打量着我，把我看了一会儿——他的眼睛出奇的黑，似乎不是在看我，而是在看他的内心深处。

“是的。我那时年轻，太重感情。之前，我一门心思要跟她结婚，曾经做出了规划，要和她共度人生，期望生活美满。”说到这里，他淡然一笑，“吵架是一个巴掌拍不响，结婚也是这个道理，得有两个人参与才行。万万没想到，我给伊莎贝尔提供的生活竟会叫她大失所望。我如果懂得一点人情世故的话，就不应该那样做。她年轻，热爱生活。我不能怪她，但我自己也不愿委曲求全。”

读者可能还记得，他和那个农场主守寡的儿媳发生了不干不净的关系之后，便仓皇逃跑，取道去了波恩。我急于听他说下去，却情知必须当心，尽量不问敏感的问题。

“我没去过波恩，”我说道，“小的时候，我倒是在海德堡上过学。那恐怕是我一生中最快乐的时候了。”

我喜欢波恩，在那儿住了有一年的时间。我是住在波恩大学的一个教授遗孀家里，租赁了他们家的一个房间。他们家平时老住着一两个房客。遗孀有二女，均已步入中年，负责烹饪和操持家务。另有一个房客是法国人。起初我有点失望，因为我只想练德语，不愿说别的语言。不过后来发现他是个阿尔萨斯人[163]，操一口德语——他的德语即便不如他的法语说得流畅，其语音语调也胜于他的法语。他的穿着像个牧师。几天后，我意外地得知他竟然是个本笃会[164]修士。他获得修道院的批准，来波恩大学的图书馆搞研究工作。他是个知识渊博的人，但表面上看和我心目中的修士并无两样。他高个子，体格魁梧，沙色的头发，一双蓝眼睛炯炯有神，脸儿又红又圆。他生性腼腆，有点拘谨，似乎不愿意跟我多说话。不过，他非常懂礼貌，处事周到，一道进餐时总是客客气气的。只有在吃饭时，才能见上他的面。午饭一完，他就回图书馆工作；吃过晚饭，他则一头钻进他自己的房间，而我坐在客厅里跟寡妇的一个女儿聊天（另一个女儿在洗碗），练习说德语。

这样至少过了有一个月，一天下午，他问我愿不愿意和他出去散步，这倒叫我颇感意外。他说可以带我在附近走走，有些地方靠我自己找是找不到的。我是个很能走的人，而他更能走，让我甘拜下风。第一次散步，我们走了足足有十五英里。他问我来波恩干什么，我说来学德文，并且想熟悉一下德国文学。他的谈吐充满了智慧。他说他会尽其所能地帮助我。那以后，我们每星期都要出去散两三次步。我得知他是教哲学的，已有些年头了。在巴黎时，我读过一些哲学著作，斯宾诺莎的，柏拉图的，也有笛卡儿的，而德国那些大哲学家的著作我却一本也没有读过。能听他讲讲德国的哲学家，令我喜出望外。一天，我们到莱茵河对岸去散步，坐在一个酒庄里喝啤酒，他问我是不是新教徒。

‘也算是吧。’我回答说。

“他飞快地扫了我一眼，我觉得他的眼睛里闪出一丝笑意。接下来，他便谈论起埃斯库罗斯[165]。你知道我是学过希腊语的，可是他对古希腊悲剧作家的了解之深，是我望尘莫及的。听他谈古论今，叫我茅塞顿开。只是一点令我不解，不知道他为何突然问我是不是新教徒。我的监护人纳尔逊叔叔是个不可知论者，但他照样去做礼拜，因为他的病人期望他这样做。他送我上主日学校，也是出自同样的考虑。我们家的女佣玛莎是一个不折不扣的浸礼会教徒。我小的时候，她老给我讲地狱之火的故事，说罪人将被送进地狱受罚，永无宁日，听得我心惊胆战。她和村里的一些人因为某种原因有了过节，她便诅咒他们，绘声绘色地向我描述那些人在地狱之火里怎样经受痛苦的折磨，从中获得快感。

时至冬日，我对恩斯海姆神父已经有了相当深的了解，觉得他是个十分了不起的人。我从未见他跟谁生过气。他总是那样的温和、善良，胸襟之开阔超出我的想象，待人宽容大度。他博学多闻，我是几斤几两他肯定心中有数，但对待我却好像我跟他一样有学问似的。对我，他从不缺乏耐心，似乎别无所图，只求为我效力。一天，不知怎么，我的腰突然疼了起来。女房东格雷博夫人硬要我上床休息，用热水袋暖一暖。恩斯海姆神父听说我卧病在床，晚饭后跑来看我。除了腰疼得厉害，我感觉身体还是挺好的。你也知道，但凡书虫，对于书都有着特别强烈的兴趣。我原来正在看书，见他进来，就把书放下了。他拿起那本书，看了看书名。那是一本介绍迈斯特·埃克纳特的书，是我在城里的一个书摊买来的。他问我为什么看这种书，我说自己曾经涉猎过一些有关神秘主义的著作，并且和他谈到考斯迪以及考斯迪是怎样引起我对神秘主义产生兴趣的。他用那双炯炯有神的蓝眼睛打量着我，眼睛里有一种神情——那种神情只能被解读为温情。他一定觉得我很可笑，竟然看这种书，但还会照样喜欢我的，绝不会因此而减弱他对我的感情。至于别人是不是把我看得有点蠢，我反正历来都是不在乎的。

‘看这种书，你想寻找什么呢？’他问我。

‘我要是知道的话，’我回答，‘就直接去寻找了。’

‘我曾经问你是不是新教徒，还记得吗？你说你还算是个新教徒，这是什么意思？’

‘我从小就是被当作新教徒教养的。’我答道。

‘你相信上帝吗？’他问。

“我不喜欢别人问我的私事，所以一冲动，想让他别管闲事。可是见他满脸的和善，我就不忍心顶撞他了。我左右为难，不知是该说相信好，还是说不相信好。后来也可能是腰疼让我忘记了自己的底线，要不然就是因为他身上的某样东西感动了我。反正我开口讲述了我的人生经历。”

说到此处，拉里停顿了一下，当他再次拾起话头时，我感觉他不是在对我讲话，而是在向那个本笃会修士陈述了。他忘记了我在跟前。不知是因为时间的关系还是地点的影响，反正他一吐为快，不用我催促，将一直压在心头的事情讲了出来。

鲍勃·纳尔逊叔叔很民主，送我进的是马文中学。后来架不住路易莎·布雷德利伯母的再三劝说，到了我十四岁时，他让我进了圣保罗中学。无论是功课还是体育，我都不怎么行，只是勉强过得去。我觉得自己那时是个十分正常的孩子，对飞行特别着迷。那时候，飞行还处在早期阶段，鲍勃叔叔和我一样，一提起飞行便激动不已。他认识几个飞行员；当我说想要学飞行时，他就说愿意为我想办法。我年纪虽小，个子却长得高，十六岁就完全可以冒充十八岁了。鲍勃叔叔叮嘱我务必保守秘密，因为他明白一旦邻里知道他让我去当飞行员，一定会招来铺天盖地的谴责。其实，是他帮助我跑到加拿大，给我一封介绍信去见他的一位熟人。结果，我十七岁就已经翱翔于法国的蓝天了。

“那时候，我们驾驶的飞机都是些廉价的破烂货，每次飞上天都是玩命。那时的飞行高度，拿现在的标准衡量，简直低得可笑。可我们又不知道这些，只知道那感觉美妙极了。我爱飞行，真不知该如何形容当时的感受，只觉得内心自豪和幸福。在天上，飞得高高的，周围广阔无垠、美不胜收，而自己就是其中的一个部分。不明白是什么原因，反正到了两千英尺的高度，我就感到不再孤独了，不再是一个人独处了，而是有所属了。这话听上去有点蠢，但这的确是我当时的感受。飞翔在高空，脚下有朵朵的白云，那白云就像是一大群绵羊一样。我恬然自得，觉得自己和无限的空间已融为一体。”

拉里停了一下，目光从他那深不可测的眼窝里盯着我。真不知他是看我还是看别处。

“我知道有成千上万的人死于非命，但我没有亲眼所见，故而对我影响不大。后来亲眼见一个人战死，我心里感到非常惋惜。”

“惋惜？”我情不自禁地脱口而出。

“说惋惜，那是因为他是个小伙子，比我才大上三四岁，生龙活虎的，天不怕地不怕。转眼间，一个精力充沛、心地善良的人就变成了一具血肉模糊的躯体，看上去好像从未有过生命似的。”

我没有说什么。我学过医，死人见多了，战争中见的更是多得不计其数。令我沮丧的是，人一死就一钱不值了，没有一丁点人的尊严，就像废弃不用的木偶。

那天夜里我睡不着觉，暗暗地流着眼泪。我并不是为自身的安全感到恐惧，而是觉得气愤，为战争的罪恶感到痛心。战争结束后，我回到了家乡。我一直都很喜欢机械，如果不能再飞行了，我打算进汽车厂工作。我受过伤，所以工作的事不便操之过急。后来，他们要我就业，而我不愿接受他们为我选择的职业。他们的努力无果而终。我曾经花费过大量时间思考问题，不断地问自己，人活着究竟是为了什么？从战争的硝烟中我侥幸活了下来，一心想让自己的人生有意义，但又不知道怎么才能有意义。以前我不太考虑上帝这类问题，而此时我开始苦苦思索。我不明白世界上为什么会有罪恶。我知道自己非常无知，又苦于找不到能够请教的人。我渴望寻找到答案，于是便一头钻进了书堆里。

当我把这些心事讲给恩斯海姆神父听时，他便问我：‘你读书读了有四年了吧？那么你找到答案了吗？’

‘没有找到。’我回答说。

他望着我，神情和蔼、慈祥。我都糊涂了，不知道自己做了什么，竟值得他如此器重。他用手指在桌子上轻轻敲打着，仿佛在考虑着一项决策。

‘我们大智大慧的教会认为，’他启口说道，‘假如你信其有，那才可能成真；假如你祈祷时心存疑虑，但态度虔诚，疑虑便会烟消云散。经许多个世纪的实践证明，礼拜仪式对人的精神影响很大，如果你愿意参加这种仪式，内心一定会感到安宁。我不久就要回修道院去了。何不跟我一起走，在那儿待上几个星期？你可以和修士们一道下地干活，也可以在我们的图书馆里看书。这样的体验恐怕比你下煤窑或者在一个德国农场上务工更有意义。’

‘你为什么提这样的建议？’我问。

‘我观察你已有三个月了，’他说，‘也许，我比你自己更了解你。你和你的信仰之间仅隔着一层纸，一捅就破。’

我对他的建议未置可否。我有一种奇怪的感觉，就好像有人拨弄了一下我的心弦。末了，我说我会考虑的。此话题他搁下不再提起。此后，恩斯海姆神父在波恩又待了一段时间，我们再没有谈及与宗教有关的事情。可是，他临离开波恩时，给我留下了修道院的地址，说如果我打定主意要去，不妨给他写信告知，他将为我做出安排。他走后，我没想到自己会那么思念他。日子一天天过去，转眼便到了仲夏时节。我喜欢在波恩消夏，读了很多人的著作，有歌德的、席勒的、海涅的、荷尔德林[166]的以及里尔克[167]的。可是，从他们的书中，我没有找到答案。期间，我经常考虑恩斯海姆神父的建议。最后，我决定接受他的邀请。

恩斯海姆神父前往车站接我。修道院位于阿尔萨斯的乡间，风光旖旎。他把我介绍给了院长，然后领我去那个拨给我住的小房间。里面有一架狭窄的铁床，墙上挂着耶稣受难像，陈设简陋，只有些生活必需的东西。吃饭铃响时，我向食堂走去。那是一个有着圆顶的大厅。院长率两个修士候在门口，一个修士端一盆水，另一修士手拿一条毛巾。院长在来宾手上洒几滴水，算是洗了手，然后用一位修士递过来的毛巾为之擦干。除了我，另外还有三个来宾——有两个是路过的牧师，留下来吃顿饭，还有一个满腹牢骚的法国老人，是来修道院过隐居生活的。

院长和两个助手，一正一副，在餐厅的上首就座，各自占一张桌子；修士们在沿墙的两边坐，见习修士和勤杂人员以及客人们则坐在餐厅正中。做了感恩祷告之后，大家就吃了起来。一个见习修士在餐厅进口处站定，以一种单调的声音诵读一册训导书。吃完饭，大家又做感恩祷告。院长、恩斯海姆神父、来宾以及负责接待来宾的修士，进入一个小房间喝咖啡，谈了些日常事务。然后，我回到了自己的房间。

“我在那儿住了三个月，日子过得快快活活的。那种生活很适合我。修道院的图书馆很棒，我看了不少书。修士们没有一个企图以任何方法影响我，但是，很高兴和我交谈。他们的学识、虔诚的态度以及超凡脱俗的气质，给我留下了深刻的印象。你不要以为他们过的是一种无所事事的生活。其实，他们时时都在忙碌。他们自耕自种，我偶尔下田相助，叫他们感到由衷的高兴。我喜欢做祈祷时的那种壮观场面，最喜欢的则是晨祷。晨祷是在清晨四点钟进行的。坐在教堂里，周围漆黑一团，修士们身穿神秘的晨祷服，头巾遮在头上，用铿锵的男音唱着礼拜仪式的歌曲，真是动人心弦。修道院的日常生活规律性很强，能起到安神定心的作用。尽管你充满了活力，尽管你的思想一刻也不停止，但你的心里一片静谧。”

说到这里，拉里苦笑了一下。

跟罗拉一样，我可真是生不逢时呀。要是出生在中世纪就好了，因为那时候宗教信仰是铁定的事，我会觉得自己的人生之路清清楚楚，只要加入教会就可以了。现在让我信教便难了。我渴望信仰上帝，但做不到，因为上帝比普通的正人君子强不到哪里去。修士们告诉我，说上帝创造世界是为了彰显自身的荣耀。这在我看来并不是什么值得称道的目标。贝多芬创作交响乐难道是为了彰显自身的荣耀吗？我相信不是的。我认为他创作是因为他内心回荡着音乐，需要他表现出来，而他竭尽其能，努力把这些音乐表现得尽善尽美。

“我常听修士们一遍遍地念主祷文，就不明白他们为什么要苦苦地祈求天父赐给他们每日的口粮呢。难道孩子们还需要祈求他们尘世的父亲给他们提供食物吗？孩子们指望着父亲供养，不会因此而感激他，也没必要那样做。对于一个只生孩子不养孩子的父亲，我们只会加以谴责。在我看来，如果万能的造物主无心给自己创造的众生提供他们赖以生存的物质粮食和精神粮食，那还不如不创造得好。”

“亲爱的拉里，”我说道，“幸好你没有出生在中世纪，否则，你毫无疑问会被处死的。”

他听后笑了。

“你取得了辉煌的成就，”他继续说道，“难道你愿意让别人当面颂扬你吗？”

“那只会叫我尴尬。”

这一点上咱们是英雄所见略同。上帝恐怕也不愿意听奉承话。想当初在空军里服役时，有个家伙对上司溜须拍马，弄上个肥差，结果遭到大家的鄙视。假如靠着阿谀谄媚以求获得‘拯救’，那么，也会遭到上帝鄙视的。依我看来，尽自己的一份力量积德行善最合上帝的心意。

不过，最叫我想不通的还不是这个。对于什么是罪恶有着种种偏见，据我所知，那些修士们就多少带有偏见，而我对他们的看法不能苟同。我在空军里结识了许多人，有的一喝酒就喝个烂醉，有的玩女人，有的满嘴脏话；飞行员里也有害群之马——一个家伙因开空头支票被抓住，判了六个月的刑。也不能全怪那个‘害群之马’——他以前囊空如洗，做梦都想不到能弄到那么多钱，一下子便冲昏了头脑。在巴黎，我遇到过一些坏人，回芝加哥时见到的就更多了。一般来说，他们的劣根性来自于遗传，他们也是身不由己呀；有的则是受到环境的影响而变坏的，这一点上他们是没有选择的——对此，社会恐怕得负更大的责任。如果我是上帝，对于这些坏人，哪怕是罪大恶极的，也不会不分青红皂白地加以惩罚，把他们打入十八层地狱。恩斯海姆神父胸襟开阔，认为所谓的地狱就是失去了上帝护佑的地方。话又说回来，假如下地狱是一种令人难以忍受的惩罚，那么你想想，仁慈的上帝会加以施行吗？归根结底，人类可是他一手创造的。如果说他创造的人类有可能去犯罪，那么，他就难辞其咎。如果有陌生人进我家的后院，我驯养的狗扑上去咬他，而我将狗打一顿，那便有失公允了。

如果说是大慈大悲、无所不能的上帝创造了这个世界，那他何必又要创造出罪恶来呢？按照修士们的说法，一个人只有克服内心的邪念，抵御诱惑，接受上帝的考验，经历痛苦、悲伤和灾难，使自己变得纯洁，才有资格接受上帝的恩典。这就像是派个人去送信，却在路上布一个迷宫，让他难以通过，再挖一条壕沟，逼他泅水而过，最后筑一道高墙，逼他攀爬。我不相信一个大智大慧的上帝会出如此下策。依我之见，还不如信仰一个普通的上帝——这个上帝不是致力于创造世界，而是致力于改善现状；与人类相比，他无比善良、智慧和伟大，和那些并非他创造的罪恶不懈地斗争，最终取得胜利。不过，话又说回来，世人究竟为何信仰现在的这个上帝，我心里也是一本糊涂账。

无论是在理智上还是在感情上，这些问题让我十分纠结，而那些好心的修士却无法为我解答。我和他们显然不是一条道上跑的车。我向恩斯海姆神父辞别时，他满脸慈祥地望着我。他一定认为我在修道院获益匪浅，想问一声，却没有问出口。

‘恐怕我让你失望了，恩斯海姆神父。’我说道。

“‘哪里的话。’他回答，‘你是个宗教修养很深的人，目前不信上帝，而上帝以后会把你挑选出来的。你一定会回来的。至于回到这儿来，还是到别的修道院去，只有上帝能够决断。’”

四

“我到巴黎住下来，在那儿度过了残冬。我对科学知识一无所知，后来觉得该了解了解科学了，至少得掌握一点常识吧。于是，我读了不少相关的书。我也不知道自己学到了多少知识，只觉得自己十分孤陋寡闻。若说这一点，我老早就有自知之明了。春天姗姗来临，我到乡间去，在傍河而建的一个客栈里住下来，不远处有一座美丽的法式古镇——那儿的生活平静如水，似乎两百年没有起过波澜。”

我猜想那年夏天拉里是和苏姗娜·鲁维埃一起度过的。不过，我没有打断他的话。

“后来，我去了西班牙，想看看委拉斯凯兹[168]和埃尔·格列柯的画。我觉得，宗教不能给我提供答案，也许艺术可以为我指出一条路吧。我浪迹天涯，四处游荡，最后去了塞维利亚。我喜欢那地方，打算在那儿过冬。”

我二十三岁那年也去过塞维利亚，也喜欢那地方。我喜欢那弯弯曲曲白颜色的街道，喜欢那教堂以及瓜达尔基维尔河畔一望无际的平原。我还喜欢那些安达卢西亚姑娘，她们一个个风韵十足、活泼可爱，黑色的眸子闪闪发亮，头上插一朵康乃馨，把一头黑发衬托得如乌云一般，而康乃馨显得愈加艳丽。她们美丽的肤色以及诱人、性感的嘴唇令人着迷。是呀，那时候年轻，觉得自己到了天堂。拉里到那儿去的时候，比我当年大不了许多。我不由心想，见了那些迷人的姑娘，他不可能无动于衷。他以下说的话解答了我心里的疑问。

我遇见了一个在巴黎就认识的画家，名叫奥古斯特·科迪特，此人曾经和苏姗娜·鲁维埃同居过。他来到塞维利亚写生，勾搭上一个女孩子，两个人就住在了一起。有天晚上他请我和他们一道去埃里丹尼亚剧院听一位弗拉明戈[169]歌唱家演唱，把他情妇的闺密也带了去。那个闺密有沉鱼落雁的容貌，年仅十八岁。她跟一个小伙子闯了祸，有了身孕，不得不离开了自己的村子。那个小伙子正在服兵役。她将孩子生下来后交给奶妈照料，自己进了一家烟草厂打工。我把她带回了我的住处。她活泼可爱，非常招人喜欢。过了几天，我问她愿意不愿意跟我在一起生活。她回答说愿意。于是，我们在一家旅馆[170]租了两个房间，里面有寝室和客厅。我让她辞去工作，可是她老大不愿意。这倒也好，因为这样一来，白天我可以用来做些事情。我们自己开火做饭。她上班前准备好早餐，中午回来做午饭，晚饭我们则下馆子，吃完饭就去看电影或者跳舞。她把我看作疯子，因为我洗过一次蒸汽浴，而且每天早晨坚持用海绵蘸冷水擦身子。她把孩子寄养在一个村子里，离塞维利亚有几英里的路程，我们常在星期天去看孩子。她跟我同居是想积攒些钱，等她的男友服完兵役回来，他们就租套房，好用这些钱装修房子，对此她毫不隐瞒。她是个招人疼的小可爱，将来一定能成为她的心上人帕克的好妻子。她整天乐呵呵的，性格温和，懂得情意。她把人们讳莫如深的性交视为身体的自然功能，与身体别的功能是一样的。她从性交中获得欢乐，也乐得给别人带来欢乐。在床上，她活像一头小兽，不过却是一头善良、迷人、温和的小兽。

后来，一天晚上，她告诉我，说她收到帕克从西属摩洛哥（他服兵役的地方）寄来一封信，信中说他就要复员了，两天内将抵达加的斯。第二天早上，她把自己的东西打了包，把钱塞在长袜子里，让我送她上车站。当我把她送上车厢时，她热烈地吻了我。一想到就要和自己久别的心上人重逢，她兴奋不已，早已没有心情跟我话别。我很肯定，不等火车开出车站，她就会把我忘到九霄云外。

“她走后，我继续留在塞维利亚，直至秋天来临，然后就踏上了前往印度的旅程。”

五

时间已经很晚了。客人们纷纷离去。只有几张桌子旁还坐着人。那些没有事做来消磨时间的人都回家去了。那些看完戏剧或电影跑来小酌或垫补肚子的人，也已经离去。时不时会有几个夜猫子晃晃悠悠走进来。这时，只见一个高个子（一看就知道是个英国人）和一个小混混走了进来。此人像是个英国的知识分子，有一张马脸，面色苍白，一头鬈发，已开始谢顶。他跟许多人一样有一种幻想症，总以为一到了国外，以前的熟人就认不出他来了。小混混在狼吞虎咽地吃一大盘三明治，而他在一旁观看，脸上带着喜悦和慈祥的神情。真是好胃口呀！在食客中，我看见了一张熟悉的面孔，认出那人在尼斯时和我去同一家理发店理过发。那是个大胖子，上了点年纪，头发花白，有一张虚肿的红脸，眼睛下是两个大眼袋。他是美国中西部的一个银行家，经济大崩溃之后离开了故乡，不愿面对政府部门的调查。不知道他是否犯了罪，即便犯了罪，在法国当局眼里也是小鱼小虾，犯不着引渡他。他摆出一副高傲的架势，像低级政客那样装出君子相，然而眼睛里却含着惊恐和忧郁。他总是浑浑噩噩，一副半醉半醒的样子。他经常跟妓女鬼混，而那些人恨不得榨光他的油水。此刻，有两个涂脂抹粉的中年女子跟他在一起，对他冷嘲热讽，毫不掩饰心里的蔑视。对于她们的话，他也仅仅能听懂一半，只顾嘿嘿嘿地傻笑。这就是风月场上的世态炎凉！他还真不如留在国内，咽下自己酿的苦酒。那些女人总有一天会把他榨干的。到那时候，他将无路可走，只好投河或者服安眠药自杀了。

在深夜两点和三点之间，客人有所增加，大概是因为那些夜总会打烊的缘故。一伙美国小青年大摇大摆走了进来，一个个喝得醉醺醺，又喊又叫，不过，他们坐了一会儿就滚蛋了。离我们不远处有两个胖女人，并排坐在一起，身上紧绷绷地穿着男式衣服，阴沉着脸，一声不吭地在喝闷酒。来了一群穿晚礼服的人——这类人在法语里叫作世界公民[171]。他们显然东游西逛了一天，此刻跑来吃夜宵，给自己的一天画个句号。他们来了，后来又走了。有个小个子男人，穿着朴素，面前放了一杯啤酒，坐在那儿看报有一个多小时了，我见了不由起了好奇之心。他留了一撮整齐的黑胡子，戴着夹鼻眼镜。最后，终于有个女子走了进来，和他坐在了一起。他冲女子点点头，冷冷淡淡的，八成是因为女子叫他久等，惹他生气了。女子年轻，穿着寒碜，浓妆艳抹，倦容满面。过不久，我看见女子从手提包里取出一样东西递给了他，那是一些钱。男子看了看那钱，脸上布满了阴云，随即说了一通话。我听不见他说的是什么，但从女子的表情看，猜想一定是骂她的。而她说了几句话，像是在为自己开脱。冷不丁，男子欠过身去，给了她一记响亮的耳光。她先是惊叫一声，随后抽抽搭搭哭起来。老板听见哭声，急忙跑上前查看情况。他好像在警告他们，叫他们注意自己的言行，否则就赶他们出去。女子冲着这位老板发作起来，嘴里不干不净地骂他，叫他少管闲事，由于嗓门高，每句话都可以听得清清楚楚。

“他扇我耳光，那是我罪有应得！”她高声嚷嚷道。

女人啊，女人！过去我一直认为，要靠女人卖淫吃饭，你必须膀大腰圆，像恶煞神一般，还得讨异性的喜欢，动刀动枪是家常便饭。而眼前的这个家伙又低又矮，看样子像是律师事务所的一个小职员，竟然能在这人满为患的行业里占有一席之地，不能不叫人感到意外。

六

伺候我们这张桌子的侍者要下班，急于拿到小费，便将账单送了过来。我们付了钱，又要了两杯咖啡。

“后来怎么样了？”我问道。

我觉得拉里有意要说，而我有心想听。

“你没有听烦吗？”

“没有。”

后来，我们的船去了孟买，在那儿停留三天，让旅客们上岸游览风光或者做短途旅行。第三天下午，我不值班，于是上岸瞎转悠，东瞧瞧西看看。那儿人山人海，什么人都有——中国人、伊斯兰教徒、印度教徒以及肤色像你的帽子一样黑的泰米尔人。身躯庞大的公牛拉着车行走在大街上，一个个驼着背，头上的犄角老长！我还去了一趟象岛，参观了那儿的石窟。轮船行驶到亚历山大城的时候，曾有一个印度人上了船，是到孟买去的。乘客们都有些瞧不起他。他是个矮胖子，圆脸庞，棕色皮肤，穿一套黑绿两色格子的厚花呢衣服，围一条牧师的领子。有天晚上，我来到甲板上想透透气，他走过来跟我搭话。当时，我不想和任何人说话，只想自己待着。他连珠炮似的问了我一大堆问题，我却爱答不理。我告诉他，说我是个学生，来船上打工，挣点盘缠回美国去。

‘你应该在印度待一待，’他说，‘西方有许多需要向东方学习的东西，多得超出了西方人的想象。’

‘是吗？’我说。

“‘不管怎样，’他继续说道，‘象岛的石窟你是必须要去看的。你一定会不虚此行。’”

拉里讲到此处，停下来问了我一个问题：

“你去过印度吗？”

“没去过。”

后来我就去了象岛，站在那儿观看三头神巨像——那是岛上极为壮观的一景，心里在琢磨着它代表着什么。忽听身后有人说道：‘看来，你接受了我的建议。’我转过脸去，定了定神才认出了说话的人是谁——他就是那个穿厚花呢衣服、戴牧师领子的小个子。此时，他却穿一袭橘黄色长袍——事后我才知道，那是罗摩克里希纳教派[172]的长老所穿的衣服。他已经不再是先前那个滑里滑稽、叽叽喳喳爱说话的小矮子了，而成了一个气宇轩昂的人物。我们俩都在观看那尊巨像。

‘一个是大梵天，司创造；’他说，‘一个是毗湿奴，司护持；还有一个是湿婆，司破坏。这三大神代表的是终极境界。’

‘我怕是听不懂你说什么。’我说道。

“‘这一点也不奇怪。’他嘴角带着一丝笑意回答道，同时挤了一下眼，仿佛在嘲笑我，你要是能吃得透上帝，那他就不是上帝了。谁又能解释得清什么是”无极呢？

他双手合十，微微鞠了一躬，然后便扬长而去了。我待在原地继续观望那三个神秘的头像。我有一种醍醐灌顶的感觉，心里异常兴奋。你知道，有时候你回忆一个人的名字，那名字都到了嘴边了，可你就是叫不出来。我当时的感觉就是如此。出了石窟，我坐在台阶上瞭望大海，在那儿坐了很长时间。关于婆罗门教，我所有的知识都来自于爱默生的几句诗。我绞尽脑汁想把那几句诗背出来，但就是做不到，让我感到很恼火。回到孟买，我钻进一家书店，想看看有哪个诗集收入了那几句诗，结果在《牛津英诗选》里找到了它们。你能背得下来吗？

不把我放在心上，那是痴心妄想；

他们要飞翔，我就是翅膀；

我是怀疑者，也是怀疑的思想，

婆罗门唱圣歌把我颂扬。

我在当地的一家餐馆吃了晚饭。由于只要十点钟之前回到轮船上即可，于是我便信步走上广场溜达，从那儿眺望大海。天上繁星点点，多得前所未见。热了一整天，此时凉爽宜人。我找到一个公园，在长凳上坐下。公园里漆黑一团，不时有白乎乎的身影默默地从我旁边走过。白天的天气晴朗，阳光灿烂，人群熙攘，身着五颜六色服装，空气中弥漫着辛辣而芳香的东方气味，令我心醉神迷。大梵天、毗湿奴和湿婆三头巨像就像是画家的画龙点睛之笔，抹上这一笔色彩，使得画面趋于完整，并带来了一种神秘的气息。我的心狂跳不已——我突然强烈地感受到，印度要赠送给我一件礼物，我必须收下。这是个千载难逢的机会，一旦失去，就永远也不会再有了。我当机立断，决定不回轮船上去了，反正我也没有什么贵重的东西在那儿，旅行包里只装了几件零碎物件。我缓步向居民区走去，想找家旅馆住下。旅馆很快就找到了，我要了个房间。我的财物只有身上的这身衣服、一点零钱、一本护照以及银行信用证。我感到一身轻，自由极了，高兴得哈哈大笑起来。

轮船在十一点钟起航。为保险起见，我一直待在房间里，到了那个时间才走出旅馆，上码头目送它离开。然后，我去了罗摩克里希纳教会，想拜访那个在象岛跟我交谈过的长老。我不知道他的名字，费口舌解释了几句，说要见的那位长老刚从亚历山大城来到此处。和长老会面时，我说自己决定在印度留下来了，问他应该看些什么。我们长谈一番，末了，他说自己当晚要去贝拿勒斯，问我愿不愿跟他同行。我高兴得差点没跳起来。我们乘坐的是三等车厢，里面人满为患，乘客们又是吃又是喝又是说话，空气闷热。我一夜没合眼，次日早晨十分疲倦，而长老却容光焕发、精神抖擞。我问他是怎么保持精力的。他回答说：‘靠的是参究无极，于无限中修心养性。’我吃不透他的话，但眼睛却看得清他精力充沛、神清气爽，就像是在一张舒适的床上睡了一夜好觉一般。

贝拿勒斯总算到了。一个和我年纪相仿的年轻人来迎接我的同伴。长老吩咐他给我找个地方住。这个年轻人叫马亨德拉，是位大学教师，和气、善良、聪慧。我们俩一见如故，彼此产生了好感。傍晚时分，他带我乘船游览恒河，叫我大开眼界。全城的人都拥到了河岸边，场面极其壮观，让人心生神圣的敬畏感。而第二天，他带我去看的景象更叫人叹为观止。天没亮他就到旅馆找我，又带我去了恒河边，让我目睹了令人无法相信的场景——成千上万的人来到河边洗净化浴和祷告。我看见一个瘦高个男子，蓬发虬髯，光着身子，只有一条兜带遮住下体，伸出两只长胳臂，仰着脸，面对冉冉升起的太阳高声祈祷。那场面给我留下的印象简直无法形容。我在贝拿勒斯待了六个月，屡次三番于拂晓时分到恒河边去看那稀有的景象。每次去，都叫我感叹不已。那些人的宗教信仰是全心全意、毫无保留、不掺杂任何疑虑的，那种信仰渗透到他们的每一个细胞里。

“所有的人对我都很好。他们发现我不是来猎虎的，也不是来做生意的，而是来学习的，便不遗余力地帮助我。他们听说我想学习兴都斯坦语，感到由衷的高兴，又是为我找老师，又是帮我借书。对于我提出的问题，他们有问必答。你对印度教了解吗？”

“只知道一点皮毛。”我回答。

“我还以为你会对这门宗教感兴趣呢。印度教认为宇宙无始无终，永远在变化之中，先是到极盛，再从极盛到没落，没落至消亡，然后再复生，循环往复，以至无穷。还有什么样的信仰比这种信仰更为精彩呢？”

“印度教徒认为这种周而复始的轮回，其目的是什么？”

“他们大概认为这就是‘无限’的本质。可以看到，他们的这种生死观认为人生只是一个阶段，应该根据每个人前生前世的作为或惩罚或奖励。”

“这种信仰主张的是生命轮回论。”

“人类社会有三分之二的人都信这个。”

“信的人多并不一定就是真理。”

“不错，但至少值得认真思考。基督教曾经吸收了不少新柏拉图主义[173]的思想，也完全可以将这种学说纳入其中嘛。其实，基督教在初期阶段就有一个流派相信这种生命轮回论，却被视为异端邪说。若非如此，基督教徒们定会笃信这种观点，就像他们相信耶稣复活一样。”

“我觉得这意味着灵魂从一个躯体转向另一个躯体，而这种转换无休无止，根据前生的功与过区分优与劣。你说是不是？”

“我想是的。”

“可是，我不仅有灵魂，也有躯体呀。谁能说得清我之所以是我，我的躯体碰巧在其中起了多大作用呢？如果没有那只畸形足，拜伦还能成为拜伦吗？如果没有癫痫症，陀思妥耶夫斯基还能成为陀思妥耶夫斯基吗？”

“印度人是不会说‘碰巧’的。他们会说是你前生的所作所为，才使你的灵魂投进一个残缺的身体。”拉里说着，用手指轻轻敲着桌子，目光飘向远方。后来，他嘴角浮出一丝笑意，眼里显出若有所思的神情，继续说道：“你可曾想到过，这种轮回论阐述了恶有恶报的道理，却也说明了恶在世间是必然的存在？如果我们受的恶报是我们前生造孽的结果，我们就会乖乖地忍受，并在今世努力行善，使来生少受些苦。自己接受恶报倒还容易，只要挺起胸膛去承受就行了，但最叫人受不了的是目睹他人遭受痛苦，而那种痛苦并非罪有应得。如果你能想得通，就会认为，那是前世造孽的必然报应，你可以同情他们，尽你的力量去减轻他们的痛苦，而且理当如此，但你却没有理由怨天尤人。”

“可是，为什么上帝不在一开始就创造一个没有痛苦和不幸的世界，一个不需要功与过决定人生的世界呢？”

“印度教徒不说什么开始不开始。他们认为人的灵魂与宇宙共存，和日月同生，其本质由前世决定。”

“那么，这种生命轮回学说对信徒的生活有实际影响吗？这才是检验真理的标准。”

我想是有的。我可以告诉你，我认识一个人，这种学说就对他的人生产生了实际影响。话说我到印度的头两三年，一般都住在当地的旅馆里，但有时候也有人会请我去他家住住，其中一两次去土邦主家做客，住的是豪宅。通过贝拿勒斯一个朋友的关系，我被邀请到北方的一个小邦去做客。那个邦的首府让人心情愉悦，是‘一座玫红色的城市，历史悠久’。我被引荐给了该邦的财政部长。他在欧洲求过学，是牛津大学的高才生。与之交谈，你会觉得他是个不乏智慧的进步开明人士，一个颇负盛名的精明强干的部长，一个聪颖、机敏的政治家。他身穿西装，外表整洁，长得一表人才，跟大多数中年印度人一样有点发福，嘴上留一撮胡子，修剪得又短又整齐。他经常请我去他家做客。他家有一个大花园，我们就坐在参天大树的树荫下海阔天空地聊天。他有一个妻子和两个成年的孩子。你会觉得他是个平平常常、普普通通的英国化了的印度人。谁知一年后，也就是他五十岁的时候，他竟然要辞去肥差，将家产交给妻子和孩子，去做一个托钵僧云游四方，这叫我不由得吃了一惊。而最叫人感到意外的是，他的朋友们以及那个土邦主都顺其自然，认为很正常，没有什么可大惊小怪的。

有一天，我跟他说：‘你思想开化，见过世面，又读书破万卷——科学、哲学、文学书无不浏览，难道你真心实意相信灵魂转世一说吗？’

他听后表情大变，换上了一副先知的面孔。

“‘我亲爱的朋友，’他说道，‘假如我不相信，那么，生命对我而言就没有意义了。’”

“你自己相信吗，拉里？”我插话问。

“这个问题很难回答。我认为，西方人不可能像东方人那样从心底里相信。这种信仰已经注入了他们的血液中。对你我而言，它只不过是仁者见仁智者见智的观点。我既相信也不相信。”

他停顿了一下，用手托住下巴，眼睛望着桌面。片刻之后，他把身子又靠了回去。

“我曾经有过一次离奇古怪的经历，我想讲给你听听。当时我在静修处修行，一天晚上在自己的小屋里，正在按印度朋友教给我的方法练习冥想。我点了一支蜡烛，把注意力集中在烛光上。过了一段时间，我在烛光里很清晰地看见了许多人，一个挨一个地排成了一条长龙。为首的是一个年事已高的妇女，戴一顶花边帽，两鬓灰白的头发垂下来盖在耳朵上。她上穿黑色紧身衣，下穿黑绸荷叶边裙（我想就是上世纪七十年代流行的那种款式），面对着我，姿态娴雅、超脱，两臂沿身体下垂，手掌心向着我。她脸上布满了皱纹，表情亲切、和蔼、温柔。紧随其后的是一个瘦高个犹太人，由于侧着身子，只能看见他的侧身像——大鹰钩鼻、厚嘴唇，穿一件黄色宽松长袍，浓密的黑发上扣一顶黄色瓜皮帽。他看上去像个勤奋好学的学者，神情严肃，同时充满了激情。他身后站着个年轻人，面朝着我，眉眼看得很清晰，就好像中间没有隔任何人似的。他面色红润，乐呵呵的，一看就知道是个十六世纪的英国人。他傲然站立，两腿微微分开，一副骄横跋扈的神情。他穿一身红衣，很气派，像朝服一般，脚蹬宽头丝绒鞋，头戴丝绒扁帽。跟在这三人身后的是一条长龙，望也望不到头，就跟电影院外买票排的长队一样，但朦胧模糊，看不清面目，只觉得那些缥缈的身影在移动，像夏风吹拂下起伏的麦浪。过了一会儿，也不知是过了一分钟、五分钟还是十分钟，那些人慢慢消失在了漆黑的夜色里，我眼前只剩下那不摇不晃的烛光。”

拉里说到此处，微微一笑。

“当然喽，这也许是我睡糊涂了，或者做了一场梦。也可能是我盯着那微弱的烛光看，结果进入了催眠状态。而那三个人物，我看得清清楚楚，就像我现在看你一样清楚的三个人物，他们只不过是保留在我潜意识里的一些图像而已。或许可以说，他们是我的前生相。前不久，我也许是新英格兰的一位老太太，而在这以前是勒旺岛的一个犹太人；再往前追溯至塞巴斯蒂安·卡伯特[174]从布里斯托尔启航不久的那段时间，我曾是威尔士亨利亲王宫廷里的一个侍从。”

“你那个玫红色城市的朋友最后怎么样啦？”

两年后我去了南方的一个叫马都拉的地方。一天晚上，在马都拉的寺院里，有人碰了碰我的胳膊，回头一看，见是一个大胡子，长长的一头黑发，光着身子，只在腰间围了一条束带，拿一根手杖和圣徒化缘用的钵子。直到他开口说话，我才认出他就是我的那位朋友。这一惊可是不小，我一时都不知说什么好了。他问我这两年做些什么，我告诉了他。他又问我去何处，我说去特拉凡哥尔。他建议我去见见希瑞·格涅沙，说道：‘他会解答你的问题的。’我让他讲讲那人的情况，他却只是笑笑，说一切见面自知。此时，初见他时的那种惊讶心情已经消失，我问他在马都拉干什么。他说自己正在朝圣途中，准备到印度的各个圣地去参拜。我问他的食宿怎么解决。他说如有人家收留，他就睡在凉台上，否则就睡在树下或寺院里。至于食物，有人施舍就吃，无人施舍便饿肚子。我打量了一下他，说他变瘦了。他大笑，说瘦下来反倒好。随后，他向我告别——听这个腰间只围一块布的人用英语说‘再见，老弟’，真是滑稽。后来，他就进了寺院的内室，那儿是不准我进的。

我在马都拉待了一段时间。马都拉的寺院恐怕是全印度唯一的一个允许白人四处随意走动的寺院，只是院里最为神圣的地方还是不准进的。一到晚上，这儿便人头攒动，男女老少都有。男人们赤裸上身，腰间围一块布，额头上厚厚涂一层牛粪烧剩的白灰（往往有人在胸口上和胳膊上也涂这种白灰）。只见他们拜拜这个神龛又拜拜那个，有时匍匐在地上，脸朝下，行五体投地礼。他们祈祷，诵读连祷经文；他们相互呼叫、寒暄、争吵或激烈地辩论。有人骂出的脏话简直是亵渎神明，而奇怪的是，神明似乎就在跟前，却不闻不问。

“穿过长长的过厅，过厅的房顶由一根根雕刻着图案的石柱支撑，而每根柱子跟前都坐着一个托钵僧，面前放一只化缘的钵，或者一小块席子——时不时会有施主将铜币丢在席子上。托钵僧有的穿衣服，有的几乎赤身裸体；有的目光茫然地望着从跟前走过的人；有的在默默地或出声地诵经；有的在冥想，对川流不息的人群视而不见。我举目望去，要寻找我的那位朋友，却不见其踪影，想来他又踏上了实现自身目标的旅途。”

“什么目标？”

“即免受轮回之苦。根据吠陀经义，真我（他们称为阿特曼，咱们称为灵魂）不同于肉体和感觉，不同于思想和智慧，是‘无限’的一个组成部分；鉴于‘无限’是无边无际的，没有‘部分’之说，所以‘真我’实为‘无限’之本身。它并非创造之物，而是与天地共生之物。一旦摆脱七重蒙蔽，它便会回归它的原始之地——‘无限’。它就像海里蒸发起来的一滴水，在一场雨后坠进水潭，然后流入溪涧，进入江河，通过险峻的峡谷和广袤的平原，迂回曲折，击石穿林，最后抵达它的发源地——无垠的大海。”

“可是，那个可怜的小水滴一旦融入大海，岂不就丧失了个性。”

拉里抿嘴一笑。

“你要尝糖的味道，你并不是要变成糖。何谓‘个性’，还不就是自我主义的一种表现吗？灵魂只有彻底摆脱个性，才能和‘无限’融为一体。”

“你大谈‘无限’，好像很熟悉一样，拉里。这是一个冠冕堂皇的词。你觉得它究竟指的是什么呢？”

“它是一种存在，不能具体地说它是什么或者不是什么。它是无法表达的。印度人称它为大梵天。哪儿都没有它的身影，却无处不在。世间万物都隐含着它的因素，都依赖它而存在。它非人非物，非因非果，超出了‘持久’和‘变化’之范围，超出了‘整体’和‘部分’之范围，也超出了‘有限’和‘无限’的范围。它是永恒的，因为它的完善与时间无关。它就是真理和自由。”

“我的老天！”我在心里叫了一声，但对拉里说出来的话却是：“可是，一种纯理性化的观念又怎么能抚慰受苦受难的众生呢？人们希望有一个人性化的上帝，受苦受难时可以向他寻求安慰和鼓励。”

“也许在遥远的未来，人类会大彻大悟，发现只能在自身灵魂里寻找安慰和鼓励。我个人认为，所谓的崇拜人性化的上帝只是古代朝拜凶残暴虐神祇那种旧信仰的残留。我认为上帝只在我的心中，而不在别的地方。如果是这样，我应当崇拜谁呢？崇拜我自己？人的精神发展是分不同层次的，因此在印度人的想象中，‘无限’就有了几种表现形式——大梵天、毗湿奴、湿婆（另外还有上百种称呼）。‘无限’寓于世界的创造者和统治者‘自在天’之中，也寓于农民在太阳烤焦的土地里放一朵鲜花所供奉的卑微小神之中。印度的那些名目繁多的神只是形式，目的是让人们意识到：‘真我’乃‘我’与上天之合体。”

我望着拉里，思绪万千。

“真不知是什么在吸引着你，使你沉迷于这样的信仰。”我说道。

“这我是可以给你讲一讲的。我一直觉得宗教的创始人有点可悲，他们设置了救赎的条件——那就是你得相信他们。就好像他们缺乏自信心，非得要你的信仰给他们撑面子似的。这会叫人想起古代的那些异教神——那些神必须要信徒烧纸钱供奉，否则便会形容憔悴。不二吠檀多[175]不需要你做任何事情，只要求你怀着炽热的感情去探知‘存在’。它断言，你一定能感受到上帝的存在，就像你能感受到欢乐或痛苦一样。如今，有许多印度人（据我所知人数达成百上千）自认为已经做到了这一点。通过认知了解‘存在’——我认为这种观点很精彩，值得称赞。在后期，印度的圣徒们认识到了人类的弱点，承认通过大爱和勤奋的工作也能得到拯救。但是，他们从不否认，最高级（也是最艰难）的途径仍是认知——认知是人类最宝贵的能力，也是人类理性的形式。”

七

首先我得声明，本人此处无意把笔墨花费在阐述所谓“吠檀多”[176]的哲学思想体系上。对吠檀多我知之甚少，无力为之。即便我能为之，此处也不是我为此挥洒笔墨的地方。我和拉里的谈话是一次长谈，他讲的内容极为丰富，但由于本书的框架为小说，不便一一陈述。我所关心的是拉里本人，马上就会向读者交代他将会采取的一些行动，而他的行动与他的思想以及那些特殊的遭遇有着千丝万缕的联系，所以我觉得应该略加叙述，否则读者会以为他的所言所行缺乏道理。如若不是出于这种考虑，我是不会涉及错综复杂的印度宗教的。他的声音犹如天籁，随便说句话，便可打动人心；他的脸部表情经常随着他的思想在变化，从严肃认真变为轻松欢快，从沉思变为戏谑，就像小提琴在演奏协奏曲的几个曲调时拉出一串动听的音符，钢琴也随之奏鸣。我只恨自己才疏学浅，无法用语言加以展现。尽管说的都是严肃的事情，他却语气自然，似拉家常，也许带几分矜持，但完全不是克制，仿佛在谈天气和收成一样。如果他给读者的印象是迂腐的说教，那都是由于我笔拙所致。他既谦虚又诚恳，这一点显而易见。

此时，饭馆里只剩下零零星星几个客人。那些喝醉了酒闹事的人早已离去，那几个做皮肉生意的可怜虫回她们藏污纳垢的住所去了。时不时会有一个倦容满面的人走进来喝杯咖啡、吃块三明治，或者走进来一个好像还没有完全睡醒的人，喝上一杯咖啡醒神。他们都是些脑力工作者。第一类人是下了夜班回家睡觉去的，第二类则是被闹钟叫醒，不情愿地去上白班的。拉里似乎对时间以及周围的情况全然不加留意。我这一辈子遇到过许多离奇古怪的事情，非止一次和死神擦肩而过，非止一次邂逅爱情，并心里有所感应。我曾经骑着一匹小马穿越中亚，所走的就是马可·波罗当年去神秘的中国走过的那条路；曾经在彼得堡一间整洁的会客室里一面喝俄国茶，一面听一个上穿黑衣下穿条纹裤的矮子细声细气地讲述他刺杀一个大公的经历；曾经坐在英国议会大厦一间客厅里倾听着海顿[177]的恬静、柔和的钢琴三重奏，而窗外却是一片炸弹爆炸的声音。但我觉得以前的那点事情都不如眼前的情况离奇——在一家装饰花哨的餐馆里，我坐在一把红棉绒椅子上听拉里一个小时又一个小时地高谈阔论，大谈上帝和永恒，谈“无限”以及无休无止的生命轮回。

八

拉里沉默了下来，有几分钟没有说话。我不愿意催促他，便耐心地等待着。过了一会儿，他冲我莞尔一笑，就好像突然才意识到我在跟前似的。

“我赶到特拉凡哥尔，发现没必要打听希瑞·格涅沙的下落。说起他，路人皆知。起初，他进入深山，在一个山洞里隐居，一住就是好多年。后来，有人劝说他移居平原，一位施主舍出一块地，给他盖了座土坯房。那儿离首府特里凡得琅路途遥遥，我花了一整天的时间，先是乘火车，后又坐牛车，终于到了他的静修处。在院子的入口处，我碰见一个年轻人，问他能不能拜谒静修者。此行，我带来了一篮子水果作为见面礼。几分钟后，那个年轻人走回来，把我领到了一个狭长的大厅里，四下里开着一扇扇的窗户。在大厅的一角，只见希瑞·格涅沙端坐于一个蒙着虎皮的台子上，正在冥想。‘正在恭候你的到来呢。’他启口说道。我先是感到诧异，继而心想一定是马都拉的那个朋友说起我来着，于是便向他提到了那位朋友的名字，谁知他摇头表示不认识。我把水果呈上，他吩咐那个年轻人收走。大厅里只剩下我们俩，他一句话也不说，默默地望着我。不知道这种沉默的局面持续了有多长时间，大概有半个小时吧。以前我对你说过他的情况，但是却没有提到他的气质——他浑身散发出的气息是宁静、善良、平和以及无私。我一路赶来，觉得又热又累，而后来逐渐静下来，感到出奇地放松。没等他再说任何话，我就意识到他正是我寻找的人。”

“他会说英语吗？”我插话问道。

不会。不过，你知道，我学语言是相当快的。那时我已经掌握了一些泰米尔语，在南方能听得懂别人的话，别人也知道我说的是什么。在沉默了许久之后，他终于开了口。

‘你来这儿有何贵干？’他问道。

我向他讲述了自己来印度的经历，讲述了我在印度三年来的遭遇。我说自己四处打听智者和圣贤，然后逐一拜访，结果发现无人能够解答我心中的疑问。讲到此处，他打断了我的话说道：‘这些我都知道，不必再讲。你来这儿有何贵干？’

‘是想请你做我的导师。’我回答。

‘只有婆罗门才能为人导师。’他说。

他一直在盯着我看，神情古怪、专注，后来他的身体突然变得硬挺挺的，眼睛似乎转为内视，看得出他已进入印度人所说的入定状态。进入这种状态，一个人会物我两忘，成为‘认知’和‘无限’。我席地盘膝而坐，面向着他，心里怦怦直跳。过了不知有多长时间，他轻轻发出一声叹息，我情知他已恢复了常态。他望了我一眼，目光柔和，里面包含着慈悲和爱。

‘那就住下来吧。’他说道，‘他们会告诉你歇宿的地方。’

“分给我的下榻处就是希瑞·格涅沙最初来到平原上时所住过的那间土坯房。他现在住的厅堂（他不分日夜都待在此处）是后来门徒越来越多，慕名赶来参拜的人络绎不绝的时候，特意为他建造的。为了不至于引人注目，我改穿了舒适的印度服装，把皮肤晒得黝黑，不注意看，你会把我当成本地人呢。我读了许多经卷，静下心来冥想。希瑞·格涅沙有谈兴的时候，我便聆听他的教诲。他不太爱说话，但回答你的提问，他会乐此不疲。听他的教诲，你会茅塞顿开。他的话语如音乐般悦耳。他年轻时严于律己，过着清苦的生活，但对弟子却不刻意要求，只是劝导他们要摆脱私心、情欲、声色的奴役，教导他们应该静修、克制、谦虚、超脱，一心一意、孜孜以求地追求自由，最终得到解脱。人们纷纷从三四英里开外的一个临近小镇赶来参拜（那个镇上有座名寺，逢年过节都会有大量徒众进寺烧香磕头）；也有人从特里凡得琅以及天涯海角赶来见他，向他倾诉自己的苦难，寻求良方妙策，聆听他的教诲。那些人来时忧虑重重，走时心情舒展，内心一片祥和。他的教诲言简意赅。他告诉我们，说人之伟大超出人之想象，修得智慧之身，便可获得解脱。他说要脱离苦海并不一定要出家，只需去掉一个‘我’字；做事不怀私欲，便会获得纯洁之心，舍弃小我，成就大我，就能畅行天下。不过，令人感触最深的还不是他的教诲，而是他的为人，是他的慈祥、气度和圣洁。和他相遇，真是上天的赐福。同他在一起，我感到十分幸福。我觉得自己如愿以偿，实现了人生目标。日月如梭，光阴似箭，一个星期接着一个星期，一个月接着一个月倏忽而逝。我打算住到他圆寂（他说他不准备久留于这个臭皮囊之中），或者说住到一朝大彻大悟，意即冲破愚昧的藩篱，深信不疑地感到自己已与‘无限’融为一体。”

“以后会怎么样呢？”

“以后嘛，如果他们所言不虚，一切就不复存在。灵魂在尘世的旅途结束，一朝逝去，永不复返。”

“希瑞·格涅沙圆寂了吗？”

“据我所知，尚未圆寂。”

他说完，意识到我的问话别有深意，于是淡然一笑。犹豫片刻之后，他又接着说了下去，不过语气有所不同，让我一开始以为他一定是不愿回答我很可能会问到的第二个问题，也就是问他是否已大彻大悟。

我并没有一直住在静修处。我有幸结识了一个当地的森林管理员，此人住在山脚下一座村庄的外边。他是希瑞·格涅沙的崇拜者，一旦从工作中抽出空来，就跑来和我们在一起住上两三天。他是个大好人，我们俩常促膝长谈。他喜欢找我练习英语。在相识了一段时间之后，他告诉我森林管理所在山上有间小屋子，什么时候我想一个人上山去住住，他就把钥匙交给我。后来，我每隔一段时间就到那儿去一趟。路上要跋涉两天——先坐长途汽车到森林管理员的村子，下边的路便需要步行了。不过，到了那里，就别有洞天——环境优雅、景色壮观。我把所能携带的东西装在一只背袋里自己背着，雇了个脚夫替我担食物。在那儿我一住就是多日，直至将食物吃完。那是一个木头小屋，后边带一间厨房，屋里有一张架子床，上面可放铺盖，还有一张桌子和两把椅子，再没有别的家具了。山上很凉爽，有时夜间生一堆篝火倒是挺惬意的。后来得知方圆二十英里渺无人烟，不由心惊胆战。夜间常听到虎啸或者野象群穿过丛林时发出的吼叫。我经常进森林里远足，最喜欢的是找个地方坐下，眺望远远近近的群山，眺望湖泊——黄昏时分，野生动物们纷纷聚在湖边饮水，其中有野鹿、野猪和野牛，也有大象和豹子。

“来静修处满两年时，我又一次到森林小屋里去，原因说出来恐怕会惹你发笑——我想在那儿过生日。我提前一天抵达那儿，次日天未亮就醒来了，心想还不如到我刚才提及的那个观景点看日出去。那地方我闭着眼睛也摸得到。到了观景点，我坐在一棵树下等日出。此时仍是黑夜，但天上的星光已趋于暗淡，白日即将降临。我满怀期待，心里有一种特殊的感觉。曙光神不知鬼不觉地悄悄摸来，慢慢地刺破了黑暗，就像一道神秘的身形蹑足穿过林子。我的心一阵狂跳，就好像有危险在接近似的。太阳升了起来！”

拉里打住话头，嘴角浮出一丝苦笑。

只恨我的表达力不强，不善于用语言描述景色，找不到合适的字眼向你形容破晓时展现在我眼前的那幅壮丽的景观。青山满目，丛林青翠，晨雾仍缭绕于树梢间，远处山脚下铺展着深不见底的湖泊。阳光从山巅间的空隙射进来，把灿银一般的光芒洒向湖面。好一幅美丽的景观，真叫我陶然若醉。一种从未有过的喜悦，一种超然物外的欢乐，荡漾在我的心间。我有一种异样的感觉，感到一阵战栗从脚后跟传到了头顶；我觉得就好像自己的灵魂突然升华，脱离了躯体，感受到从未有过的心旷神怡。一种醍醐灌顶的感觉油然而生——模糊不清的概念得到了澄清，令人困惑的疑难问题得到了解答。我高兴到了极致，乃至于心口发痛，于是便努力想摆脱这种状况，生怕这样下去会死去。然而，这种欢乐又是如此诱人，我宁肯死去也不愿将其放弃。那种感觉，我怎么能说得清呢？任何语言都无法表达我那种欣喜若狂的感受。末了恢复常态后，我已经精疲力竭，浑身发抖。最后，我懵懵然进入了梦乡。

“我醒来时，已是中午。返回小屋的途中，心里轻松愉快，脚下有腾云驾雾之感。我给自己弄了些吃的（天呀，我真是饿坏了），然后点上了烟斗。”

说到这里，拉里把手中的烟斗也点着了。

“我真不敢相信，别人经年累月清心寡欲地苦苦修行，尚未大彻大悟，而我，伊利诺伊州马文镇的拉里·达雷尔，竟然做到了。”

“你不觉得那只是一种催眠状态，是由你当时的心情，再加上孤独感、拂晓时分的神秘气氛以及灿银一般的湖水而造成的吗？”

“我深切地感受到那一切都是真实的。不管怎样，千百年来，全世界的神秘主义者都有类似的体验。印度的婆罗门、波斯的苏非派、西班牙的天主教徒以及新英格兰的新教徒，只要描述那种难以形容的境界，所用词语都差不多。这种境界的存在是无可否认的，难就难在不好解释其原因。至于我当时是和‘无限’融为了一体，还是普通的精神向往（这种向往人人皆有）在潜意识上的一种表现，这我就说不清了。”

拉里停了一下，嘲弄地看了我一眼。

“我问你，你能用拇指碰到你的小指头吗？”他问道。

“当然能。”我笑着回答，并且当场做给他看。

“你可知道这只有人类和灵长目动物能够做到？由于拇指能接触到另外的几个手指，所以手才能成为称心如意的工具。也许，这种灵巧的拇指，当它还在雏形时，只为人类个别的祖先以及大猩猩所拥有，后来经过世世代代的进化才成了人类共同的特征。至于和‘无限’的融合，是许多人都有过的体验，这也许预示着人类意识中的第六感觉进化的方向，后者也许在极其遥远的未来会成为人类共同的特征，使得人类能够直接感受到‘无限’，就像咱们现在感受周围的事物一样容易。至少存在着这种可能性吧？”

“你觉得那会对人类产生什么影响呢？”我问道。

“这就说不清了。当初，人类的祖先能将拇指碰到小指，他们也不知道那一细小的动作后来竟会产生如此重大的影响。至于我自己的那段体验，我只能说，在那如痴如醉的时刻，我的心里一片宁静、欢乐和怡然，看到世界上那极为美丽的景观，不禁眼花缭乱。当时的情景至今仍历历在目。”

“话又说回来，拉里，你们那样看待‘无限’，势必会导致你们认为这个世界及其美景只不过是幻觉，是摩耶一手编织出来的。”

“若是以为印度人将这个世界视为幻觉，那就大错特错了。这并非他们的观点。他们只是说，世界之真实与无限”之真实在意思上是不同的。所谓摩耶，仅仅是狂热的思想家们虚构出来的，借此解释‘无穷’怎样创造‘有穷’。‘轮回’是诸多学说中最具智慧的一种，断定这是永远也解决不了的谜团。婆罗门是真我、极乐和智慧，是亘古不变的，与天地共存，无所缺、无所求，有为也无为，是完善至美的。既然如此，为什么还要创造世界呢？这就难以解答了。如果你提出这个问题，他们一般会回答，‘无限’创造世界只是随意而为之，并没有任何目的。可是，当你想到洪水和饥馑，想到地震和飓风，想到折磨人体的一切疾病，你的正义感就会油然而生，为这许多骇人听闻的灾难被随意创造出来而感到愤慨。希瑞·格涅沙有一副大慈大悲的心肠，不相信这样的学说。他认为这个世界是‘无限’的表现形式，充满了‘完美’。他教导我们说，天神造物是一种责任，而这个世界体现了天神慈悲的心性。我问道：既然这个世界体现的是十全十美天神的慈悲心性，为什么却如此可恨——非得设定目标，要众生摆脱它的束缚才能跳出苦海？希瑞·格涅沙回答，尘世间的完满都是暂时的，只有达到‘无穷’的境界，才可获得持久的幸福。不过，时间的无穷并不能改变事物的本质，不能使善更加善，也不能使白颜色更加白；如果说玫瑰花在中午不再娇艳，而它的美在清晨时却是真实的。世间万物没有一样是永恒的，只有蠢人才会要求事物永不消亡，而更蠢的做法则是放着眼前的欢乐不去享受。如果说变化是事物的本性，明智之举则是将其视为哲学的一种命题。谁也不会在同一条河里反复涉水，而这条河的河水依然潺潺流淌，走到另外一条河，那儿的河水同样清凉沁人。

雅利安人初来印度的时候，把人类已知的世界仅仅看作未知世界的一种表象，但他们喜欢这个世界，觉得它风光旖旎、绚丽多彩。只是经过了若干世纪之后，当征伐的劳累和耗人的气候消磨掉他们的活力，使得他们成为异族大举入侵的俎上肉时，他们方才看到了人生的丑恶一面，并且渴望从轮回中解脱出来。不过，咱们西方人，尤其是美国人，为什么要畏首畏尾，害怕什么衰朽、死亡、饥渴、疾病、衰老、悲伤和幻象呢？咱们充满了旺盛的生命力。那时，我坐在自己的小木屋里抽着烟斗，觉得浑身精力充沛，比以往任何时候都精神抖擞，体内有一种力量急切地要爆发出来。要我远离尘世，过一种与世隔绝的生活，显然是不行的。相反，我要置身于尘世之中，欣赏世间的万物——其实并非欣赏事物的表象，而是欣赏其内含的‘无穷’。假如在那我曾经历过的极乐时刻，我果真与‘无限’融为了一体，他们所言不虚，我已脱离了轮回之苦，今世的孽债已经还清，那我就不回到尘世来了。这种念头叫我感到沮丧。其实，我渴望一次次地投生，愿意接受各种各样的生活，不管是体验痛苦还是忧伤。我觉得只有一次接一次地投生，才能实现我的愿望，倾注我的活力，满足我的好奇之心。

第二天早上，我动身下山，于次日来到了静修处。希瑞·格涅沙见我一身西装，不由觉得奇怪。这身衣服是我上山时在森林管理员那个小屋里换上的，因为山上冷，下山时也没有想起要换掉。

‘师傅，我是来告别的，’我说，‘我打算回家乡去了。’

他没吱声，仍和平时一样盘膝坐在虎皮台子上，面前的香炉里燃着一炷香，使得空气里香气氤氲。跟头一天见面时一样，他依然是独自一人在修行。他目不转睛地盯着我看，目光犀利，似乎能看透我的五脏六腑。我知道，他对一切都已心中有数。

‘这样好，’他说，‘你离家太久了。’

“我跪倒在地，接受了他的赐福，再站起来时，早已热泪盈眶。他是一个高尚、圣洁的人，我将永远以认识他为荣。之后，我和静修者们依依惜别——他们中有些已静修多年，有些则是在我之后来的。我把自己的几件衣物和书籍留下，觉得说不定对他们有用，然后背上行囊，身着我来时穿的旧长裤和棕色上衣，头上扣一顶破破烂烂的遮阳帽，步行回到镇上。一星期后，在孟买搭上一条船，在马赛上了岸。”

我们两人沉默了，各自都陷入遐思冥想。尽管我已非常疲倦，但心里仍有谜团，需要问个清楚，于是便开了口。

“拉里老弟，”我说，“你多年来孜孜以求，起初就是为了探清恶的源头。正是这一命题，才催促你不断前行。你刚才讲了半天，却只字未提是否已找到答案，哪怕是不确定的答案也可以。”

“也许这一命题压根就没有答案，或者我不够聪明，没有找到答案。罗摩克里希纳把创造世界看作是天神的一种游戏。他说：‘这就犹如玩游戏，其中有喜也有忧，有美德也有失德，有智慧也有愚昧，有善也有恶。如果将罪恶和痛苦去除掉，游戏便无法再进行下去了。’对这一观点，我持坚决反对的看法。充其量也只能说，‘无限’在这个世界上的表现形式是善与恶并存。没有地壳变化那种叫人无法想象的可怕的灾难，你就不可能欣赏到喜马拉雅山的壮丽景色。中国烧瓷的匠人能够把花瓶烧得像蛋壳一样薄，造型优美，图案漂亮，色彩鲜艳夺目，上的釉精致美观，但就其本质而言，它是易碎的，掉到地上就会成为许多碎片。同样的道理，我们在这个世界上所珍视的一切美好事物都是与丑恶的事物并存的，你说是不是呢？”

“这是一种独到的见解，拉里。但我觉得这样的回答难以叫人满意。”

“我也不满意。”他笑了笑说，“当你断定必须发表看法时，那就尽其力而为之，这就是我的解释。”

“你现在有什么打算？”

“眼前有件事需要了结，之后便回美国去。”

“回去干什么？”

“过日子呗。”

“怎么个过法？”

他回答时语气极其冷静，但眼睛却闪出一丝顽皮的光，因为他知道自己的回答会叫我意想不到。

“不急不躁，宽宏大度，大慈大悲，无私无欲，不近女色。”

“高标准！”我说，“那么，为什么要不近女色呢？你还年轻，女色和吃饭一样是人这个动物最强的本能，你这样抑制它是否明智呢？”

“所幸的是对我来说，接近女色只是寻欢作乐，而不是出于生理需要。根据我个人的经验，印度的那些哲人主张不近女色可以大大增强精神的力量，这话说得再正确不过了。”

“我倒觉得明智之举是在肉体需要和精神需要之间保持一种平衡。”

“印度人觉得这恰恰是西方人所没有做到的。他们认为，西方人发明创造无数，又是建工厂又是造机器，创造了大量财富，总想把幸福建筑在物质上，岂不知幸福与否并非由物质决定，而取决于精神。他们认为西方人选择的道路最终会导致毁灭。”

“你认为要实现自己的精神追求，美国是理想之地吗？”

“为什么不是？你们欧洲人一点不了解美国。你们以为我们积聚了大量的财富便钻进了钱眼里，岂不知我们视金钱如粪土，一有钱就花掉，有时花得好，有时花得糟，但不做守财奴。金钱对我们算不上什么，只是一种成功的象征。我们是天下最地道的理想主义者，也许在某些方面将理想放在错误的目标上罢了。依我之见，一个人最高的理想应该是自我完善。”

“这不失为一种崇高的理想，拉里。”

“是不是值得为实现这一理想而努力呢？”

“可你想过没有，以你一己之力，对焦躁不安、忙忙碌碌、目无法纪、极端个人化的美利坚民族，会产生什么影响呢？这无异于妄想要赤手空拳阻挡住滔滔的密西西比河河水。”

“我可以试试嘛。车轮的发明是靠一己之力完成的，万有引力的发现也靠的是一己之力。所有的努力都会产生一定的影响。哪怕你把一粒石子投入池中，宇宙也会产生一点变化的。如果认为印度的那些圣人过的是无益于众生的日子，那就错了。他们宛若黑暗里的明灯，代表的是一种理想，能滋润众生的心灵。普通人可能永远也无法企及，但他们心怀崇敬之感，从而终身受益。一个人一旦变得纯洁、完美，就会产生广泛的影响，而那些追求真理的人自然而然会受到他的吸引。也许，如果我按照自己的规划去生活，便能对他人产生影响。这种影响也许就跟投石入池一样，激起了一圈涟漪，没什么大不了的，但第一圈涟漪会引起第二圈涟漪，第二圈涟漪又会引起第三圈涟漪。很可能会有一些人从我的生活方式中学到了满足和平静，他们就会将其传授给其他人，于是一传十，十传百。”

“你可知道你在跟什么人作对吗，拉里？要知道，那些庸人曾经用严刑拷打和火刑镇压令他们感到害怕的思想家，虽然那些刑罚早已放弃不用了，现在却发明了一种更为致命的毁灭性武器——泼脏水。”

“我可是个非常坚强的人。”拉里笑了笑说。

“好吧，我只能说你有点进项算你的福气。”

“这笔钱帮了我不小的忙。要是没有它，我就不可能了结我的心愿。不过，我的学徒期现已结束，它对我就只能是负担了，我将弃之不用。”

“这可是极其非理性的打算。你想过闲云野鹤般的生活，就必须在物质上不依赖别人。”

“恰恰相反，在物质上不依赖别人，会让那样的生活变得毫无意义。”

我实在按捺不住，不由露出了不耐烦的神色。

“对于印度的那些浪迹天涯的托钵僧而言，这倒没有什么，他们可以露宿于树下，而善男信女们为了积德，会把他们化缘的钵子装满食物。可是，美国的气候对露宿是很不适宜的，虽然我不敢说自己非常了解美国，但有一点我是知道的——你们的国人有一种共识：不劳动者不得食。可怜的拉里呀，恐怕不等你踏上旅途，就会被人当作流浪汉抓到教养院去的。”

他听了大笑。

“这我知道。入乡随俗嘛，我当然是要劳动的。到了美国，我将想办法在汽车修配厂找个活干。我是个相当棒的机修工，想来不会有什么困难的。”

“这是不是有点大材小用，白白浪费精力呢？”

“我喜欢干体力活。每当书看不下去的时候，我就干干体力活，可以借此振奋精神。记得有一次读斯宾诺莎的传记，了解到他为了糊口曾经为人打磨镜片，而那个传记作家竟视其为可怕的磨难，岂不愚蠢。我敢说，打磨镜片有助于缓解他的智力活动，最起码可以转移他的注意力，使得他暂停劳神的哲学思考。冲洗汽车或者修理汽化器时，我的大脑是放松的；把活干完，我会心情愉快，有一种成就感。当然，我可不是想干一辈子的修理工。离开美国已有多年，我得重新认识它。我将设法找一个卡车司机的工作。开卡车，我能四处跑，把美国跑个遍。”

“也许，你把金钱的一个最重要的用途给忘了——它可以节省时间。生命苦短，百事纷繁，必须只争朝夕。举例来说，你徒步走到哪个地方去，不知会浪费多少时间。在此，坐公共汽车胜似徒步，而搭乘出租车又胜似坐公共汽车。”

拉里嘿嘿一笑。

“此话不假，我却没有想到这一点。不过，我可以拥有自己的出租车，这一问题便迎刃而解了。”

“你这话是什么意思？”

“最终，我将在纽约定居，不为别的，只因为那儿图书馆多。我所需的生活费用不多，在何处过夜全不在乎，每日一餐便可果腹。把要看的地方全都去过之后，我将会攒下一笔钱买辆出租车，当一名出租车司机。”

“真该把你关起来，拉里。你简直就是个疯子。”

“一点不疯，而是很理智，也很实际。有自己的出租车，我开车挣的钱只要够食宿和汽车的折旧费就行了。其余的时间可以用在别处。到哪儿有急事，就开自己的车去。”

“不过，拉里，汽车跟政府公债一样也是财产哟，”我逗趣地说，“有辆汽车，你岂不成资本家了。”

他听了哈哈一笑。

“差矣。我的出租汽车只不过是我的劳动工具而已，相当于托钵僧的打狗棍和化缘钵。”

这一番打趣之后，我们的谈话中止了。我早已留意到来餐馆进餐的顾客越来越多。一个身穿晚礼服的男客在离我们不远的位子坐下，点了一份丰盛的早餐。他看上去很疲倦，却心满意足，猜得到他一夜风流，此刻仍余兴未消。几位老者，由于年纪大睡觉少，所以起得早，一边不慌不忙喝着牛奶咖啡[178]，一边透过厚厚的镜片读着晨报。年轻的食客，有的衣冠楚楚，有的不修边幅，狼吞虎咽吃一个面包，急急忙忙吞几口咖啡，便匆匆赶往商店或办公室上班去了。一个干瘪老太婆拿了一捆报纸进来，走到各个餐桌前兜售，但看上去好像一份也没卖掉。从硕大的玻璃窗望去，发现天已大亮。一两分钟后，所有的电灯都熄灭了，只有这家大餐馆后堂的灯仍开着。我看了看表——已经过七点钟了。

“来点早饭怎么样？”我说。

我们吃了些羊角面包，刚烤出来的，又热又脆，还喝了点牛奶咖啡[179]。我疲倦不堪，无精打采的，样子一定很难看。拉里却精神抖擞，神采奕奕，光滑的脸上一道皱纹也没有，看上去顶多只有二十五岁。一杯咖啡落肚，我才有了几分精神头。

“愿不愿听我进几句忠言，拉里？我可是不经常给人提忠告的。”

“我也是不经常接受别人的忠告的。”他咧嘴一笑，回答道。

“至于处理掉你那一丁点财产，你能不能三思而后行？一旦脱手，就永远回不来了。万一你自己或别人急需要用钱，那时你将追悔莫及，怪自己做了件蠢事。”

他回话时，眼睛里有一丝讥笑的神情，但那讥笑没有丝毫的恶意。

“相比较而言，你可是比我看重金钱。”

“对此我不否认。”我坦率地回答说，“要知道，你口袋里老有钱花，我却不然。有钱就不用求人，而这正是我最为珍视的。你哪里懂得，最叫我感到开心的就是想骂谁，叫他见鬼去，那我就骂谁。”

“我并不想骂任何人，不想让任何人见鬼去。即便我想骂人，也不会因为银行里没有存款就骂不成。这样说吧，金钱对你意味着自由，对我则是束缚。”

“你真是块臭硬臭硬的顽石，拉里。”

“惭愧，惭愧，生性如此。不过，不管怎么样，时间还早着呢，如果要改变主意，还来得及。要说回美国，得等到来年春天。我的画家朋友奥古斯特·科迪特把萨纳里的一座度假屋借给了我，我打算在那边过冬。”

萨纳里是里维埃拉一个名不见经传的海滨度假地，位于邦多勒和土伦之间。画家和作家们对圣特罗佩斯花里胡哨的环境看不上眼，就会跑到这儿来休憩。

“那地方就像一潭死水般缺乏生气，如果你愿去，那你就去吧。”

“我去那儿是有事做的。我收集了许多资料，准备写本书。”

“什么内容？”

“出版后你就知道了。”他笑了笑说。

“写完后，如果你愿意把书稿寄给我，我可以找人为你出版。”

“不用劳驾你了。我有几个美国朋友在巴黎办了一家小型出版社，已经谈妥为我出版此书。”

“以这种途径出版书，别指望销路好，也别指望有谁给你写书评。”

“写不写书评我不在乎，也不指望销路好。印几本够送人就行了——我要寄给印度的朋友以及法国的几个熟人，他们也许会感兴趣的。此书也没有什么大的价值。我写书，只是想给手头的那些材料找个用途，出版书则是觉得应该把心里的想法变为白纸黑字。”

“这两条理由我都理解。”

说话间，我们已吃完了早餐。我喊侍者过来结账。账单送来时，我把它递给了拉里。

“既然你打算把你的钱扔进下水道，那就不妨先替我把饭钱付了吧。”

他大笑一声，把钱付了。由于坐的时间长，我的身子都僵了。走出餐馆时，只觉得腰发酸。秋天早晨的空气洁净、新鲜，令人神清气爽。天空湛蓝，夜间显得邋里邋遢的克利希大街此时有了一些活泼的生气，就像是一个涂脂抹粉的憔悴妇人换上了姑娘家轻快的脚步在走路，看了并不让人感到讨厌。我向一辆驶过的出租车招了招手。

“送你回住处怎么样？”我问拉里。

“不用了。我到塞纳河边走走，然后找个浴场游游泳，再进图书馆里查资料。”

跟他握了握手，然后我目送他迈开长腿悠闲地走过了马路。我可不像他是个铁打的人，于是就坐上出租车，回到了我的旅馆。进了客厅，我发现已经八点多了。

“一个上了年纪的人真不该这个时候才回家。”我冲着钟表玻璃罩里的裸体女子自嘲地说了一声——那女子自从一八一三年起就侧卧在钟表的顶端，姿势在我看来极其不舒服。

那女子眼睛盯着一面镀金铜镜在照镜子，望着镜子中她的那张镀金的铜脸。那种表一个劲地发出嘀嗒、嘀嗒的响声。我放了一浴盆热水开始泡澡，一直泡到水渐渐变温，才出来把身子擦干，然后吞了片安眠药。接下来，我拿起放在床头柜上的那本瓦勒里[180]写的《海滨墓园》，躺到了床上，看看看着便昏然睡着了。

第七章

一

半年后，那是一个四月的早晨，我在费拉角自家房屋顶层的书房里正忙着写东西，仆人进来说隔壁圣让村的村警在楼下要见我。受到外来的干扰，我心里没好气，吃不透他们找我有什么事。我又没做什么亏心事，而且还慷慨解囊，交了慈善基金。作为回报，他们给了我一张卡片，时时放在汽车上，万一因超速行驶或者违规停车被警察抓住，我便可以在出示驾驶执照时，把这张卡片也拿出来，警察就会叮咛我下次小心，对我免于处罚。我心想可能是我的哪个用人遭到了匿名举报（这在法国是很正常的），说她的身份证件有问题。平时，我和当地的警察相处得不错，他们每次登门，都要请他们先喝上一杯才放他们走，所以觉得不会有什么大不了的事情。不过，一次来两个警察，情况就大不相同了。

我和他们握了手，彼此问好。然后，年长的一个从口袋里掏出个本子，用脏兮兮拇指翻着——此人绰号叫“将军”，蓄着威风凛凛的大胡子（这样的胡子我以前从未见过）。

“索菲·麦克唐纳这个名字你听说过吗？”他启口问道。

“我认识的人有叫这个名字的。”我小心地回答。

“我们刚和土伦的警察局通电话，那边的警察总长要你去一趟（Vous prie de vous y rendre[181]），立刻就去。”

“为什么？”我问，“我和麦克唐纳太太并不太熟。”

我立刻想到索菲一定出事了，很可能和鸦片有关系，但弄不懂为什么会把我牵连进来。

“这个不归我管。毫无疑问，你和这个女人是有过交往的。她好像五天没有回家，后来港口从海里捞出一具女尸，警方觉得可能是她，要你去认一下。”

一股寒意传遍了我的全身。不过，这样的结局也是意料之中。她过着今日有酒今日醉的生活，早晚会走投无路，结束自己的生命。

“她穿着衣服，身上带着证件，凭这些是可以辨认出来的呀。”

“她一丝不挂，喉咙被人割断了。”

“我的老天！”我吓得失声叫道。我略加思索，觉得识时务者为俊杰，警方反正是可以强迫我去的，倒不如顺从的好。“好吧，我马上搭乘火车去。”

我看了看火车时刻表，发现可以搭乘五点至六点之间的一趟车到土伦去。“将军”说他将通知土伦的警察总长，让我一到土伦就直接去警察局。那天上午，我没有再写稿子，把一些必需品塞进行李箱，吃过午饭便开车去了火车站。

二

我到了土伦警察局，立即被领进了警察总长的办公室。警察总长是个粗汉，坐在办公桌旁，一张脸黑不溜秋，面色阴沉，看上去像个科西嘉人。也许是出于职业习惯吧，他狠狠地扫了我一眼，目光疑神疑鬼的。可是看见我的纽扣孔里挂着荣誉军团勋章（那是我以防万一临时挂上去的），他便满脸堆起笑容，急忙请我坐下，说了一篓子道歉的话，声称惊动我这样一个有身份的人，实在不得已。我对他也以礼相待，说能为他效犬马之劳，我感到不胜荣幸。接下来，我们言归正传。他又恢复了先前的那种严厉、粗暴的神情，眼睛看着桌子上的材料对我说：

“真是伤风败俗。这个叫麦克唐纳的女人好像名声很坏，是个酒鬼、瘾君子、野鸡。她不但和上岸的水手睡觉，还同城里的地痞流氓上床。以你这样的年龄，以你这样的身份，怎么跟这种人搅和在了一起？”

我本来想告诉他这不关他的事，可是，根据我钻研几百本侦探小说的经验，觉得对待警察还是客气点好。

“我和她并不太熟。初次在芝加哥见她时，她还是个孩子。后来，她嫁了个有头有脸的人。大概在一年前吧，通过她和我共同认识的几位朋友，我才又一次见到了她。”

我一边说话一边纳闷，不知道这位警察总长到底是怎么把我和索菲联系在了一起。此时，只见他把一本书推到了我面前说：

“这是在她的房间找到的。你看看上面的题词，恐怕就不能说你和她不太熟了。”

此书就是我的那本法译版小说，索菲在书店看到过，想请我签名题词。我签了名，并在下面题了词：“亲爱的，让我们看看这玫瑰花……”题词是当时随便想出来的，语气的确有点太亲热了些。

“假如你怀疑我是她的情人，那你就大错特错了。”

“是不是情人不关我的事。”他回答说，眼睛里闪闪发着亮光，“我无意冒犯你，但此处必须补充一句，根据我所了解到的她的喜好，你不是她的意中人。可是，有一点得弄清楚：你绝不会把一个自己不太熟悉的人称为‘亲爱的’。”

“这是龙沙的一首名作中的头一行诗，总长大人[182]。像你这样有文化修养的人对龙沙的诗肯定是很了解的。我当时引用这句诗，是觉得她知道这首诗，会联想到下面的诗行，从而感到愧疚，至少能意识到自己的生活有失检点。”

“当然，龙沙的诗我上学的时候是读过的，可现在乱事如麻，你刚才提到的诗句早已忘掉了。”

接下来，我把那首诗的第一段背诵了出来。我断定他以前对龙沙的名字连听也没听说过，所以不怕他知道后边的诗句并不包含劝人改邪归正的内容。

“她显然是读过一些书的。我们在她的房间里找到了许多本侦探小说和两三本诗集。一本诗集是波德莱尔[183]写的，还有一本是兰波[184]的诗集。另有一本英文诗集，是一个叫艾略特[185]的人写的。他的名气大不大？”

“名气非常大。”

“我没时间读诗。再说，我也看不懂英语。可惜呀，如果他是个好诗人，何不用法语写诗，这样可以让法国有文化的人拜读拜读嘛。”

想到这位警察总长阅读《荒原》的情景，我的心里觉得好笑。突然，他把一张照片推到了我面前。

“对这个人你了解吗？”

我立刻认出是拉里，穿着游泳裤，是最近才拍的一张照片。拍摄的时间大概就是去年夏天——当时他和伊莎贝尔及格雷在迪纳尔避暑。我一急，想说不认识，因为我不愿让拉里也陷于这件麻烦事中，可是细细寻思，觉得既然警方知道了他的身份，我再推说不认识，只会叫人以为里面有不可告人之处。

“他是个美国公民，叫劳伦斯·达雷尔。”

“在那个女人的物品中，这是唯一的一张照片。他们之间是什么关系。”

“他们都是芝加哥附近一个村子里的人，从小就认识。”

“不过，这张照片可是在前不久拍的，我想大概是在法国北部或者西部的一个海滨疗养地拍的吧。要确定位置不会是难事。他是干什么的？”

“是个作家。”我大着胆子说。警察总长的两撇浓眉稍稍抬起来了一点，大概是认为干我们这一行的人，行为都是不大检点的。“不过，他不是靠撰稿为生的。”我又补充了一句，想让拉里的身份显得体面一些。

“他现在何处？”

我又想推说不知道，可还是觉得那样会叫事情更为尴尬。法国的警务也许有各种弊端，但他们有一张网，立刻就能查出一个人来。

“他住在萨纳里。”

警察总长抬头看了看我，显然对我的回答很感兴趣。

“地址呢？”

拉里曾告诉过我，说奥古斯特·科迪特把他的乡间小屋借给了他。我圣诞节回家时，给那个地址写过信，请他来我家做客，住上几天，可不出所料，他谢绝了我的邀请。此时见总长问起，我就把他的地址说了出来。

“我会给萨纳里那边打电话的，让他到这儿来一趟。从他嘴里也许能问出些情况来。”

我心中暗想，警察总长一定把拉里当成了嫌犯，于是觉得心里好笑。我断定，拉里很容易就可以证明自己与此事一点关系都没有。我所关心的是索菲的惨剧，想了解更多的细节，可是总长告诉我的情况并不比我已经了解到的多多少。尸体是两个渔民打捞出来的。至于我们那儿的村警说死者一丝不挂，纯粹是夸大其词。凶手没有剥掉她的内裤和乳罩。如果索菲死时还是我以前见过的那身装束，那么，凶手只是扒掉了她的长裤和运动衫。起初，由于查不出她的身份，警方曾在当地报纸上登了一则告示，描述了她的特征，结果引来了一位女子。此人在一条背街上经营地下出租屋，法语称作妓院，经常有男人带女人或男孩去出租屋鬼混。其实，她是警方的耳目。警方询问了她，问她有什么人到出租屋去，都干了些什么。我上次碰见索菲时，她刚被码头跟前的那家旅馆赶了出来，因为她的行为过于寡廉鲜耻，就连一向宽容的旅馆老板都忍无可忍了。于是，她就到旁边的地下出租屋去，就是刚才提到的那位女子经营的出租屋，想租一套带小客厅的房间。按说，临时把房间租出去，一夜出租两三次，是有利可图的。但索菲按月租，出的价钱更高，于是女房东就答应租给她了。女房东这个时候来警察局，说她的房客几天都没见踪影了。原先她并没有在意，以为索菲到马赛或者维尔弗朗什去了——最近，英国海军的舰队抵达那两处港口，像磁石一样把海岸线一带许多的女人（年轻的以及年老的）都吸引了去。后来，她看了报上登的关于死者的描述，觉得很符合女房客的特征。被领去辨认死尸时，她几乎没有犹豫，立刻便认定死者就是索菲·麦克唐纳。

“既然尸体已经得到了辨认，又何必叫我来呢？”

“贝莱夫人品德高尚，诚实可信，”总长说道，“但她也许出于某种不得而知的原因认错人。不管怎么说吧，我觉得应当找一个和死者关系比较密切的人来证实一下。”

“你认为有可能抓住凶手吗？”

总长耸了耸他那宽厚的肩膀。

“当然，我们正在找线索，曾经到她常去的酒吧询问过几个人。她可能被哪个吃醋的水手杀害，而水手的船已经离开了港口，或者是遇到了一个图财害命的恶棍。她好像身上老带着钱，免不了叫歹徒见财起意。也许有人了解些线索，知道何人是凶手，但她那个圈子里的人，除非利益相关，否则没人会说话的。她跟那些坏蛋鬼混，早晚都会落到这种下场的。”

我一时无语。总长要我次日上午九点钟再来一趟，那时他应当接见过“照片中的这位男子”。然后，由一位警察领我们去认尸。

“死者怎么安葬呢？”

“辨认完尸体，如果你们认定死者是你们的朋友，同时愿意负担丧葬费，就可以得到相关的授权。”

“我敢肯定，我和达雷尔先生都愿意获得授权，越快越好。”

“我完全理解。这是一件叫人伤心的事情。应该让那个可怜的女人尽早入土为安，越快越好。这让我想起我这儿有一张殡葬承办人的名片。此人办事周到，收费合理，会为你们把事情打理好的。我在名片上批几个字，他一定会重视的。”

我敢打包票，他一定会从殡葬费里吃回扣的，但还是对他表示了感谢。他送我出门，一举一动都表现得毕恭毕敬。按照名片上的地址，我即刻前去找殡葬承办人。对方是个爽快人，一副公事公办的样子。我挑了一口棺材，价钱适中，既不是最便宜的，也不是最贵的。他主动提出替我从他熟识的一家花店订购两三只花圈，我接受了他的建议。“这样可以免去先生一些麻烦事，也可以表达我对死者的敬意。”他解释说。我们约定好让柩车于次日两点钟到达太平间。他叫我不必为坟地操心，一切都由他代办，还说“想来死者是新教徒”，如果我同意的话，他将找一位牧师等在公墓那边，于下葬时为死者祈祷。对于他的办事效率，我不得不佩服。不过，鉴于我们素不相识，我又是个外国人，所以他提出我最好预先给他开一张支票，希望我不会介意。他说出的钱数比我预料的要多一点，显然是等着我还价。可是，我二话没说，掏出支票本来，开了一张支票给他。只见他脸上现出了意外的表情，那样子甚至可以说有点失望。

我在一家旅馆要了个房间住下来，次日早晨又去了警察局。等了一小会儿，就有人把我领进了警察总长的办公室。拉里也在那儿，表情凝重、悲伤，坐在我昨天坐过的那把椅子上。总长高兴地跟我打招呼，仿佛我是他失散多年的兄弟似的。

“很好，亲爱的先生[186]，你的朋友极其坦率地回答了我有责任问他的所有问题。他说已经有一年半的时间没见那个可怜的女人了，对此我没有理由不相信。至于他上星期身在何处以及他的照片为什么出现在了那个女人的房间，他解释得清清楚楚，令人十分满意。照片是在迪纳尔拍的，有一天，他和那女人吃午饭时，刚好放在他口袋里，就送给了她。我从萨纳里已经收到了报告，对这个年轻人评价很好。再说，不是我吹牛，我是个很有眼光的人，坚信他不可能干那种伤天害理的事情。那女人是他童年时的朋友，在一个气氛健康的家庭长大，有着种种优越环境，竟会落得如此悲惨的下场，对此我深表同情。不过，这就是人生呀。现在，亲爱的先生们，我的一个下属将陪二位到太平间去，在确定了死者的身份之后，你们的责任就算尽到了。好好去吃一顿。我这儿有一张餐馆的名片，那是土伦最好的餐馆。我在上面批几个字给老板，你们一定会受到最优惠的待遇。辛苦了这么一通，喝上一瓶美酒，对你们会大有好处。”

说话时，他满脸喜色，样子显得很开心。随即，我们跟着一个警察去了太平间。此处的生意很不景气，停尸床上只停放着一具尸体。我们走过去，工作人员揭开了蒙在死者头上的遮布，现出的场景惨不忍睹——死者那染成了银灰色并烫过的卷发已被海水泡直，湿漉漉地贴在脑壳上；面部肿得不像样，看上去似鬼脸一般可怕。尽管如此，一看就知道是索菲无疑。工作人员把遮布又朝下拉了拉，露出了一条刀口——那刀口切穿了喉管，从一个耳朵根切到了另一个耳朵根，让我们俩不忍再看下去。

我们回到了警察局。总长抽不出空接见我们，于是我们就把事情对他的助手说了，助手让我们等了一会儿，便拿来了所需的证件。

我们把证件拿走，给了殡葬承办人。

“好啦，咱们去喝一杯吧。”我说道。

刚才从警察局去太平间，拉里在返回的路上曾说他一眼就认出死者是索菲·麦克唐纳。除此之外，他再也没说过一句话。我领着他向码头走去，到了一家咖啡店——我和索菲曾在这家店里喝咖啡。外边北风呼啸，平时平静的港湾此时白浪翻滚。渔船随着海水在轻轻地摇晃。阳光亮晃晃的。每次刮北风，视野里的一景一物都异常清晰，就像是用聚焦望远镜看到的一样，在刺激着人们的神经，使人们的心灵颤抖。我喝了一杯苏打水白兰地，而拉里碰也没碰我给他要的那杯酒。他一语不发，心情沉痛，木然呆坐着。我没有去打搅他。

过了一会儿，我看了看表说：

“咱们走吧，吃点东西去。两点钟还得到太平间去呢。”

“我饿得肚子咕噜叫，早晨没吃东西。”

从那位警察总长的外表看来，我断定他是个美食专家，于是便将拉里带到了他推荐的那家餐馆。我知道拉里很少吃肉，所以点了煎蛋卷和烤龙虾，又让侍者把酒单拿来，仍按照警察总长的建议挑了一瓶葡萄酒。酒送来时，我给拉里倒了一杯。

“劝你喝下去，”我说道，“杯酒可以解千愁，让你把心里的话说出来。”

他顺从地照我的话做了。

“希瑞·格涅沙常说，沉默也是一种交谈。”他喃喃地说。

“这倒叫我想起了剑桥大学教师们的一次别开生面的社交聚会，有着异曲同工之妙。”

“至于这次的丧葬费，你恐怕得一个人承担了，”他说道，“我现在已囊空如洗。”

“我十分乐意承担。”我答道。把他的话又回味了一下，我接着又说道：“你不会真的那样做了吧？”

他一时没有回答我的话。我注意到他的眼里闪出一丝古怪、戏谑的光。

“你不会仗义疏财，把钱都送人了吧？”

“除了一点钱够我在轮船来之前用，其余的全都送了人。”

“什么轮船？”

“我在萨纳里居住，隔壁有个邻居是一家货轮公司在马赛的代理人，货轮的航线是往返于近东和纽约之间。他们从亚历山大城发电报给他，说一条开往马赛的船有两个水手生病，在亚历山大城上了岸，叫他找两个替工。他是我的好朋友，答应把我弄上船。我要把我的那辆旧的雪铁龙送给他作为纪念。这样，一旦登船，除了身上的一身衣服以及包里的几件日用品，我就一无所有了。”

“钱是你自己的。你是个白种人，已满二十一岁，作为成年人你可以自由支配你的财产。”

“自由这个词用得很恰当。以前我从未感到如此快乐和自在过。到纽约下船，他们会给我一些报酬，够我花一阵子，直至我找到工作。”

“你的书写得怎么样了？”

“哦，已完稿，并印了出来。我开了一张赠书的名单，你在一两天内当会收到。”

“多谢。”

接下来再无话可说，我们俩默默地在友好的气氛中吃完了饭。然后，我要了杯咖啡。拉里点着烟斗，我则燃起一支雪茄。我一边想心事一边望着他。他感觉到我在盯着他瞧，便扫了我一眼，目光里闪出一丝顽皮。

“如果你心里想骂我是个大傻瓜，尽管骂出口好啦，我一点都不会介意的。”

“我心里并没有这种念头。我只是在想，你要是像其他人一样结婚生子，日子过得岂不是比现在美满一些。”

他听后笑了。他的笑容很美，我以前说过足有二十遍了——这种笑容恬适、真诚、迷人，反映出了他那坦率、诚挚、令人舒心的天性。此处有必要再谈及他的笑容，因为这次的笑容除了包含以上成分之外，还有些许凄婉和柔情。

“现在太迟了。我碰到的女子，唯一可婚可娶的只有可怜的索菲。”

我愕然地望了望他。

“发生了那许多事情，你还能这么说吗？”

“她有一颗可亲可爱的灵魂，满怀热情，有追求，慷慨大方。她的理想是高尚的。即便她寻求自我毁灭，最后以悲剧告终，里面也蕴含着高尚的因素。”

我哑口无言，对这种奇怪的论断真不知怎么说才好。

“那你当初为什么不娶她？”我末了问道。

“她那时还是个孩子。当时我常到她祖父家，和她一同在榆树下读诗，说实话，我没想到那个瘦巴巴的丫头正孕育着美丽的精神世界。”

我不由感到奇怪，在结婚这件事上，他竟然只字未提伊莎贝尔。他曾经和伊莎贝尔订过婚，此事不可能已淡然忘却。我只能推想，他也许把他俩的订婚视为两个不明事理的年轻人干下的荒唐事，只能是无果而终。我觉得，若说伊莎贝尔一直在苦苦暗恋着他，这样的想法在他的脑海里恐怕连个影子都没有出现过。

该去料理丧事了。我们到了广场上，那儿停放着拉里那辆破旧不堪的汽车，然后驱车前往太平间。殡葬承办人所言不虚，果真办事效率很高，把所有的事情均已办妥。天上一片亮晃晃的光，狂风大作，把公墓的柏树吹弯了腰，给葬礼增添了几分恐怖的气氛。葬礼结束后，承办人客气地跟我们一一握手。

“但愿两位先生能够满意。一切都进行得非常顺利。”

“的确非常顺利。”我说道。

“请先生记着，如果有什么差遣，我将随时准备效力，路远路近不在话下。”

我对他表示了谢意。走到公墓门口时，拉里问我还有什么事情需要他做。

“没有什么别的事了。”

“我想尽快赶回萨纳里去。”

“把我送到旅馆，好吗？”

汽车启动后，我们谁都没有再说一句话。到旅馆后，我下了车。然后，我们握了握手，他就把车开走了。我在旅馆结了账，拿上行李箱，乘出租车去了火车站。我和拉里一样，也想赶快离开这个地方。

三

几天之后，我启程前往英国。起初我打算直达彼地，但经过了这一通变故之后，特别想见见伊莎贝尔，于是决定在巴黎停留二十四小时。我给她发了封电报，希望能在下午晚一些时候去她家坐坐，并留下来吃晚饭。到了旅馆，我看见她留的一张便条，说她和格雷晚上有饭局，提出欢迎我在下午五点半之前去，因为她去赴宴前需要更换衣服。

天气寒冷，下着大雨，下一阵停一阵。这样的天气，格雷不大可能去莫特芳丹打高尔夫了。这对我不是件好事，因为我想单独见见伊莎贝尔。不过，到了他们家的公寓，伊莎贝尔一见我就说格雷到旅行者俱乐部打桥牌去了。

“我对他说，如果想见你，就不要回家太晚。不过，我们的那个晚宴推迟到了晚上九点钟，九点半赶去就行。所以，咱们有的是时间好好聊一聊，我有许多事情要告诉你呢。”

他们已经把公寓转租出去。艾略特的藏画将在两星期内拍卖。拍卖时他们要到场，所以正准备搬到里茨饭店去住。此事一完，他们就乘船回美国。伊莎贝尔打算把能卖的都卖掉，只留下艾略特在安提比斯家中挂的那些近代画。她虽然并不是十分喜欢这些画，但明智地判断，将来搬到新家，这些画可以起到提高品味的作用。

“遗憾的是，可怜的艾略特舅舅不是很前卫。你知道，毕加索、马蒂斯[187]以及鲁奥[188]的画是很时尚的。艾略特舅舅的画自有其精彩之处，不过怕是过时了些。”

“我要是你，就不操这份心。用不了几年，又会出现一些新的画家。到那时，毕加索和马蒂斯的作品与你的这些印象派画作相比较，也就不见得前卫了。”

格雷和一家生意兴隆的企业在谈判，目前已接近尾声。有伊莎贝尔的钱作为资本，他将会荣任副总裁。这家企业的业务与石油有关，所以他们准备举家迁居达拉斯[189]。

“我们要做的第一件事情就是找一座合适的住房，有漂亮的花园，好让格雷下班回家后有个地方务花弄草，还必须有一个大大的客厅招待客人。”

“真不知你为何不把艾略特的家具也带走。”

“我觉得这套家具很不合适。我想要的是摩登家具，也许带一点墨西哥情调加以点缀。一到纽约我就去打听，看哪一家装饰公司当下最吃香。”

此时，男仆安托万端着个托盘走了过来，上面放着几个酒瓶。伊莎贝尔历来善于察言观色，知道男人十个有九个都觉得自己调鸡尾酒比女人技高一筹（情况的确如此），故而请我调两杯。我把杜松子酒和一种法国酒倒出来一些，掺上少量的苦艾酒。这种苦艾酒可以将干马丁尼从没名堂的酒化为仙露，就连奥林匹斯山上的神仙也肯定愿意舍弃山上自酿的酒，跑来一品为快。我自己倒是一直觉得这种酒的口感更像是可口可乐。我把调好的酒递给伊莎贝尔时，注意到桌上有一本书。

“哈！这是拉里写的书！”我说道。

“是的，今天上午寄来的。我忙得焦头烂额，手头乱事如麻。中午有饭局，下午又去了一趟莫利纽克斯服装店。真不知何时才有闲空看这书呢。”

一个作家成年累月地写一本书，也许呕心沥血才写成，却被人随手放在一旁，等到实在无事可做时才看上两眼，想起来便叫人心寒。拉里的这本书共三百页，印刷质量好，装帧精美。

“你可能也知道拉里一冬天都住在萨纳里。你见过他的面吗？”

“见过。前两天我们俩还去了趟土伦呢。”

“是吗？去土伦干什么？”

“为索菲办丧事。”

“难道她死了不成？”伊莎贝尔惊叫了一声。

“如果她没死，我们又有什么理由为她办丧事呢？”

“这种事可开不得玩笑。”她打住话头，停了一下才又说道，“不过，也没有什么伤心的。她一定是酗酒和吸毒过量导致的死亡。”

“不是的。她是被人割了脖子，赤身裸体抛到了海里。”

我的感觉大概和圣让的那位“将军”警察一样，认为有必要稍加渲染索菲赤身裸体的状况。

“太可怕了！可怜的人儿。她那样放浪形骸，必然会有这种悲惨的结局。”

“土伦的警察总长也是这么说的。”

“他们知道凶手是谁吗？”

“不知道，但是我知道。我认为是你杀了她。”

她一听，惊愕万状地望着我发呆。

“你在胡说什么呀？”她说完，阴阳怪气地扑哧一笑，“随你胡扯去吧。我可是能证实自身清白的，证实我没有去过犯罪现场。”

“去年夏天，我在土伦碰见了她，和她进行了一次长谈。”

“她没有喝醉吧？”

“没有，脑子很清楚。想当初她准备嫁给拉里，可就在举行婚礼的前几天，她却莫名其妙地不见了踪影。她把前因后果都告诉了我。”

我注意到伊莎贝尔脸上的肌肉变得僵硬。接下来，我便将索菲的话一五一十复述了一遍。她侧耳倾听着，神情专注。

“后来，我把她的遭遇想了许久，越想越觉得蹊跷。我来你家吃午饭足有二十次了，从未见你午饭喝过酒。那天你一个人吃午饭，为什么放咖啡杯子的盘里有一瓶齐白露加酒呢？”

“那是艾略特舅舅叫人刚送来的。我想尝几口，看是不是和我在里茨饭店喝的那样合口味。”

“不错，记得你曾交口称赞那酒。我当时有点奇怪，因为你是从不喝那种甜酒的——你非常注意自己的身材，怕喝甜酒会坏了身段。那时候我有个印象，觉得你不怀好意，是在引诱索菲上钩。”

“承蒙夸奖。”

“一般来说，你和人约会是很守时的。你既然约索菲去试衣服——这对她很重要，对你则很有趣，那你为什么不在家等她呢？”

“这是她跟你说的吗？琼的牙齿叫我很担心。牙医忙得不得了，只能按他约的时间去。”

“看牙医，一般都是在看病时就约好下一次去的时间。”

“我知道。可是，他早上打电话给我，说不能按以前约好的时间看病，建议改为下午三点钟，我当然接受了他的建议。”

“难道就不能叫保姆带琼去吗？”

“那可怜的孩子吓得要命，我觉得亲自陪她去，她心里会踏实些。”

“你回来的时候，看见那瓶齐白露加酒有四分之三都被人喝掉了，索菲也不见了，你难道不感到奇怪吗？”

“我以为她等得不耐烦，自己去莫利纽克斯服装店了。我赶到那儿一问，才知道她并没有去，一时觉得莫名其妙。”

“那瓶齐白露加酒怎么解释？”

“哦，我的确看出酒被喝掉许多，还以为是安托万偷喝的呢，差一点责问他。后来觉得他的工资是艾略特舅舅付的，他又是约瑟夫的朋友，所以没有加以追究。他是个很尽职的仆人，即使偶尔偷点嘴，我也犯不着责备他。”

“你可真会撒谎，伊莎贝尔。”

“你不相信吗？”

“根本不相信。”

伊莎贝尔起身，走到了壁炉架跟前。壁炉里炉火熊熊，在这阴冷天叫人感到惬意。她把一个胳膊肘支在壁炉板上，姿态优雅——这是她最为迷人的一种天赋，既仪态万方，又不露任何做作的痕迹。多数有身份的法国女子白日喜欢穿一身黑色的素装，她也一样。这样的装束和她那凝脂一般的肤色相得益彰。这次她穿的衣服款式简单，质料贵重，充分凸显了她那窈窕婀娜的身段。她不停地抽烟，抽了好一会儿。

“无论怎么说，我都应该对你无所隐瞒。那天我有事外出，实属不幸。安托万实在不应当把齐白露加酒和咖啡饮具留在房间里。我出门后，就应该将那些东西撤掉。我回到家，见那瓶酒几成空瓶，当然知道是怎么回事。后来索菲失踪，我猜想她一定故态复萌，纵酒狂欢去了。我之所以只字未提此事，是怕雪上加霜，徒增拉里的烦恼。拉里为此事牵肠挂肚，已经够心烦意乱的了。”

“你敢说那瓶酒不是你故意放在那儿的吗？”

“我敢说。”

“我不相信。”

“不相信就不相信呗。”她一甩手，恶狠狠地把纸烟扔进了炉火里，一双美目怒火燃烧，“那好吧，既然你想了解真相，那我就告诉你吧，然后你就给我滚蛋。是我着意那样做的，而且绝不后悔。我告诉过你，说我会不惜一切代价阻止她嫁给拉里。你和格雷只会袖手旁观，不关心拉里的痛痒。你们只会耸耸肩膀，事后会说他们的婚姻是个弥天大错。你们不关心，可我关心。”

“如果你不加以阻挠，她现在还活着呢。”

“她嫁给拉里，会将拉里抛入痛苦的深渊。拉里想入非非，以为如此可以叫她脱胎换骨、重新做人。男人全都是些傻瓜！我知道她迟早都会再次堕落——这是明摆着的。那次在里茨饭店聚餐，你也看到了她是多么焦躁不安。她喝咖啡时，我留意到你在看她——她的手抖得厉害，一只手不敢拿杯子，只好用两只手捧到嘴边喝。我看到侍者给咱们倒酒时，她的眼睛贪婪地跟着瓶子转，就像一条蛇盯着一只羽毛方满的小鸡拍翅似的。我知道她哪怕出卖灵魂，也会弄一杯喝的。”

伊莎贝尔把脸直对着我，眼里射出两道光来，声色俱厉，加快语速说了下去。

“当艾略特舅舅把那难喝的波兰酒大吹特吹的时候，我心里就有了一计。我觉得那酒味道像马尿，然而我却对其大加赞扬，说我从未喝过这样味道棒到了极点的美酒。我当时就断定，索菲一旦接触到这酒，便难以抵挡住诱惑。于是我就依计行事，又是带她去看时装展览，又是提出要送她一套结婚礼服。约她最后试样的那天，我告诉安托万，说我午饭后要喝齐白露加酒，后又说我约了一位女士来，女士来后让她等一等，喝上一杯咖啡，把酒也留下，她想喝就让她喝。我的确把琼带到了牙医那里，但没有预先约好，医生不能为琼看病。离开诊所，我带琼去电影院看了场纪录片。我打定主意，如果索菲没有碰那波兰酒，我便真心实意和她交朋友。这是真的，我发誓。可是，我回家一看那酒瓶，便知道自己的判断是正确的。她不见了踪影，我敢拿生命打赌，她这一去将永不回头。”

伊莎贝尔说完，已娇喘吁吁。

“我早就猜想到是这么回事。”我说道，“瞧，我刚才所言不虚。你这样做就跟亲手用刀抹她的脖子没什么两样。”

“她是个可恶、邪恶的坏女人，她死了大快人心。”她说着，猛地一屁股坐在了一把椅子上，“给我一杯鸡尾酒，你这浑蛋。”

我走过去，又调制了一杯。

“你是个卑鄙的坏蛋。”她从我手里接过鸡尾酒时说。随后，她挤出了一个笑容，就像是一个做了错事的孩子一样，装出一副天真无邪的样子蒙骗你，想叫你不要生气。“你不会告诉拉里吧？”

“我想都不会往这方面想。”

“你能对天发誓吗？男人说话是靠不住的。”

“我发誓绝不告诉他。即便我想告诉他，也不会有这个机会的，恐怕我今生今世再也见不上他了。”

她一听，立刻坐直了身子。

“这话是什么意思？”

“此时此刻，他已登上了一艘货轮，或者当船员或者当司炉，正在向纽约进发。”

“此话当真？他真是个怪人！几个星期前，他还来了一趟这里，为他那本书上公共图书馆查资料，却没听他说一句要到美国去的话。这样倒好，我们可以在美国相见了。”

“对此我表示怀疑。他的美国跟你们的美国相去甚远，要隔上十万八千里呢。”

接下来，我就把拉里的所作所为以及他的抱负叙述了一番，听得她目瞪口呆，一脸的惊愕，时不时打断我的话，连声说“他疯了，他疯了”。我说完之后，只见她垂头丧气，两行热泪滚滚而下。

“这下子，我真的失去了他。”

她转过身去，脸抵着椅背嘤嘤哭了起来。她毫不掩饰内心的悲伤，一场痛哭让美丽的脸都变了形。我一时束手无策。她究竟怀着怎样缥缈、矛盾的希望（而在我的叙述之后那些希望全都化为了泡影），便不得而知了。我朦胧觉得，她原以为只要能偶尔见见拉里，最起码知道他仍是她生活的一个组成部分，这便可以将他们联系在一起，不管这种联系是多么薄弱，而今拉里斩断了这一联系，使她觉得自己永远失去了他。我感到纳闷，不知她是否觉得自己白费了一番心机，留下的只是满肚子的懊悔。就让她哭吧，哭出来也许心里会好受一些。我拿起拉里的书，将目录浏览了一眼。我离开里维埃拉时，他寄给我的书还没有收到，估计几天内是拿不到手的。书写得完全出乎我的意料，是一本论文集，篇幅和里顿·斯特拉奇[190]的《维多利亚女王时代名人传》相仿，论述了若干名人。书中所选的内容叫我百思不得其解。有一篇是写古罗马独裁者苏拉的——苏拉在独揽大权之后，退位归隐；还有一篇写蒙古征服者阿克巴尔——此人缔造了一个大帝国；一篇写鲁本斯[191]，一篇写歌德，一篇写查斯特菲尔德勋爵[192]。显而易见，每写一篇论文都必须阅读大量的资料，难怪拉里用了那么长的时间才把书写完。我真不明白他为什么舍得花大把的时间写这本书，也不明白他为何要选这些人物作为研究对象。我突然产生了一种想法，觉得拉里可能认为这些人在自己不同的领域取得了辉煌的成就，于是便有了研究的兴趣。他有心弄个水落石出，研究一下他们的成就究竟产生了什么样的影响。

我粗粗浏览了一页，想看看他的文笔如何，发现他用的是学术文章的那种风格，但措辞简洁、语气明快，全然没有刚入门新手的那种咬文嚼字、卖弄辞藻的生涩气。看得出，他非常熟悉那些优秀作家，就跟艾略特·邓普顿熟悉达官贵人一样。我的思绪被伊莎贝尔的一声叹息打断了。只见她苦着脸将杯中由热变温的鸡尾酒一饮而尽。

“我不能再哭了，会把眼睛哭肿的，晚上还有个饭局呢。”她从包里取出一个小镜子，担心地左照右照，“随他去吧。我只想有个冰袋敷在眼上，敷个半小时。”接下来，她在脸上扑了粉，涂了口红。之后，她若有所思地望着我问道：“我做了那种事情，你不会因此对我有不好的看法吧？”

“你在乎我的看法吗？”

“你也许会奇怪，我在乎。我希望你对我有好的看法。”

我笑了笑，说道：

“亲爱的，我是一个极没有道德观念的人。我一旦喜欢上一个人，即便不赞成他干下伤天害理的事情，也还会照样喜欢他。你是个不错的女人，自有你的风采——仪态万方、魅力四射。我不会因为你的行为稍稍看低你的美丽，因为我十分清楚你的美丽完美地综合了高雅的品味以及残酷无情的意志。你只需要一样东西，就可以使你的魅力趋于完善。”

她嫣然一笑，等待着我说下去。

“那就是温柔。”

她唇边的笑意倏然不见了踪影，横扫了我一眼，目光里没有一丝一毫的善意。她定了定神，正要回话，却见格雷摇摇晃晃走了进来。在巴黎住的这三年，他增加了好多磅的体重，脸色比以前更红了，头发秃得厉害，但健康状况良好，情绪高涨。看见我，他简直掩饰不住内心的高兴。他说话时夹带着许多口头禅，明明是用滥了的词语，他却深信不疑自己是第一个使用者。什么“不做亏心事不怕鬼敲门”啦，“屋漏偏逢连阴雨”啦，以及“路遥知马力，日久见人心”什么的。不过，他心地善良，为人无私、正直、可靠，没一点架子，叫你不可能不喜欢他。我对他有一种发自于内心的真情实感。谈到即将回到祖国，他又兴奋又激动。

“万事俱备，只欠东风了。”他说道，“我已整装待发。”

“是否已万事俱备了呢？”

“已是板上钉钉的事了，只剩下在合同上签字了。我未来的合伙人是我大学时的一个舍友，一个挺不错的人，绝对不会叫我吃亏的。不过，一抵达纽约，我还是要即刻飞往得克萨斯落实细节，拿着伊莎贝尔的钱，我可要不见兔子不撒鹰。”

“谁都知道，格雷做生意是有一套的。”伊莎贝尔说。

“我可不是个只知道种田的乡巴佬。”格雷笑了笑说。

接下来，他就滔滔不绝地讲起了他将要涉足的生意，一讲就收不住口了。可是，我对这种事情一窍不通，只听明白了一点——他将时来运转、财源滚滚。他越说兴致越高。过了一会儿，他扭过头对伊莎贝尔说：

“依我看，咱们把今晚那讨厌的饭局推掉算啦，咱们三个到银塔餐厅消消停停地吃饭岂不痛快。你觉得呢？”

“这可不行，亲爱的，不能这样做事。这个饭局是他们专门为你我而设的。”

“你们去吧，反正我也是抽不出身的。”我插嘴说，“一听说你们有饭局，我就打电话约了苏姗娜·鲁维埃，和她一起出去吃饭。”

“苏姗娜·鲁维埃是谁？”伊莎贝尔问。

“哦，是拉里的一个女朋友。”我故意逗她说道。

“我早就怀疑拉里金屋藏娇，瞒着咱们呢。”格雷说完，咯咯咯地笑个不停。

“没影儿的事。”伊莎贝尔打抱不平地说，“拉里的性生活我是很清楚的。他身边压根就没有女人！”

“好的，大家再干一杯，然后各自准备去吃饭。”格雷说。

我们举杯喝了酒，我向他们说了再见。小两口送我进门厅。我穿外套时，见伊莎贝尔挽起了格雷的胳膊，偎在他身上，望着他的眼睛，脸上露出我曾经指责她所缺乏的温柔表情。

“格雷，请你坦率地告诉我，你是不是觉得我是个铁石心肠的人？”

“不是，亲爱的，不沾边的话。怎么，难道有人这么说你吗？”

“没有。”

她把头掉过去，使格雷看不见她的脸，朝我吐了吐舌头。这种样子，要是让艾略特看见，肯定会说她不像个有身份的人。

“那是两码事。”我胡乱支吾了一句，然后出了门，随手把门带上。

四

当我再次路过巴黎时，马图林一家已经走了，艾略特的公寓房里有了新的住户。我还是蛮想念伊莎贝尔的——她有闭月羞花的容貌，又非常健谈。她善于体察人意，没有什么坏心眼。可惜我再也没有见过她。我不爱写信，也懒得写信，而伊莎贝尔则从不写信。如果不能给你通电话或发电报，那就会彻底跟你失掉联系。那年圣诞节，我倒是收到她一张贺卡，上面有张漂亮的照片，照的是一幢房屋，房屋的门廊是殖民地时期的，周围长着郁郁葱葱的橡树。这恐怕就是农场上的那幢房屋，他们缺钱时曾想卖卖不掉，现在大概准备留下来自家住了。邮戳表明贺卡是从达拉斯寄来的，由此可以断定那桩生意已经成功，他们已在达拉斯定居。

我没去过达拉斯，但可以想象得来那儿跟美国其他的城市别无二致——从住宅区开车去商业中心和乡间俱乐部都很方便；富贵人家住豪宅，有大花园，从客厅窗户可望见风景优美的山丘或峡谷。伊莎贝尔肯定会住这样的小区，住这样的豪宅，从地窖到阁楼都是由纽约最时髦的屋内装饰师按照最时新的式样布置。我只希望她的那些画——雷诺阿的画、马奈的花卉、莫奈的风景以及高更的画，挂在她家墙上，不要显得太过时。餐厅无疑会不大不小，正适合伊莎贝尔隔三岔五请女友们来吃午饭，好酒好菜地招待她们。她在巴黎长了不少见识，一眼就可以看出客厅合不合适，客厅不如意她是不会住的。眼见两个女儿一天天长大，她还指望在客厅为女儿举办交际舞会呢——这可是为人母的一项惬意的职责。现在，琼和普里西拉恐怕已到了谈婚论嫁的年纪。她们姐妹肯定有令人钦羡的教养，上的是最好的学校；伊莎贝尔准会叫她们学习琴棋书画，让门当户对的小伙子们一见倾心。格雷想必脸色更红，心情更愉快，头更秃，体重也大大增加了。若说伊莎贝尔，我坚信不会有什么变化。她会依然光彩照人，美貌不输她的两个千金。马图林一家在社区里一定很有分量。我坚信，他们一定人缘好，颇受欢迎。伊莎贝尔风趣幽默、彬彬有礼、殷勤好客、识分寸知进退，而格雷出类拔萃，是人之佼佼者。

五

我仍然时不时去看望看望苏姗娜·鲁维埃。后来，她的境遇发生了意想不到的变化，使她离开巴黎，也从我的生活中消失了。那是一天下午，大致在我叙述的那些事件发生两年之后，我在奥德昂大剧院走廊的书摊前浏览书籍，很惬意地消磨了一个小时，后来觉着闲得无事可做，就想起去看望一下苏姗娜。我已有半年时间没有见她了。她开门时，手端调色板，嘴里衔着一支画笔，穿一件罩衫，上面满是油彩。

“啊，是您，亲爱的朋友。请进，请您进来。[193]”

她这样客气使我有点诧异，因为我们之间一般只是以你我相称。我跨进那个既当客厅又做画室的小房间，见画架上放了一幅油画。

“我忙得不可开交，简直都晕头转向了。你请坐吧，我得继续工作了，一会儿都耽搁不得。说来你也不信，我要在迈耶海姆画廊办个人画展，必须准备三十幅画参展。”

“在迈耶海姆画廊？这真了不起。你是怎样做到的？”

迈耶海姆画廊可不是塞纳路上的那些靠不住的小画廊——那些野画廊门面小，一缺钱付不起房租，就会关门大吉。迈耶海姆画廊是一个很体面的画廊，位于塞纳河畔有钱人的地区，享有国际声誉。一个画家一旦被这家画廊看中，就会走上通向成功的康庄大道。

“阿吉里先生带迈耶海姆先生来看过我的画，迈耶海姆先生认为我很有才气。”

“别吹了，老伙计。[194]”我回了一句。我觉得这句话最好翻译为：“鬼才会相信你的话，老伙计。”

她瞥了我一眼，随即扑哧笑出了声。

“我要嫁人了。”

“嫁给迈耶海姆吗？”

“别犯傻！”她放下了画笔和调色板说，“我画画画了一整天，也该休息一下了。咱们不妨来杯波特酒，容我细细道来。”

法国人的生活中也有令人不爽的一面——他们常常在最不恰当的时候逼你喝下一杯酸不拉叽的波特酒。此时，你必须乖乖地从命。苏姗娜取出一瓶酒和两只杯子，把杯子斟满，坐下来如释重负地叹了一口气。

“今天画画，一连站了几个小时，站得我静脉曲张、腿发痛。情况是这样的。阿吉里先生的妻子今年年初去世了。她是个好人，也是个好天主教徒。不过，阿吉里先生娶她并非出于本意，而是出于对生意的考虑。他固然敬重她，但若说她的死令他痛不欲生，那就言过其实了。他儿子的婚姻门当户对，事业也干得风生水起；他女儿的婚事亦安排妥当，要嫁给一位伯爵——那伯爵虽说是比利时人，却是货真价实的贵族，在那慕尔附近有一座非常漂亮的城堡。阿吉里先生认为，他妻子的在天之灵绝不愿因为自己的缘故耽搁了一双儿女的幸福，于是决定不等服满丧期，只要安排停当就举办婚礼。里尔的房子那么大，只剩下了阿吉里先生一个人，孤零零的，显然需要一个女人在身边，照顾他的起居，料理事务——他那么有身份的人，势必有重要的事务需要关照。长话短说，他请求我代替他妻子的位置。他说的话入情入理：‘我第一次结婚是为了消除两家对立公司的竞争，为此我毫不后悔，但第二次婚姻就要合自己的心意，选自己喜欢的人了。’”

“恭喜，恭喜。”我说。

“代价是失去自由。我喜欢无拘无束的生活，但前途却是不得不考虑的。不瞒你说，我马上就要步入不惑之年了。阿吉里先生正在危险的年龄段，万一他突发奇想，去追求一个二十岁的大姑娘，那该如何是好？我还得为我的女儿想一想。她今年十六岁，水灵灵的，越长越像她爸爸。我让她接受了良好的教育固然不错，但残酷的现实摆在你面前不容忽视：她既没有当演员的天赋，也没有她可怜母亲的那种气质去当妓女。那我问你，她有什么盼头呢？末了只好给人家当秘书，或者在邮局里谋个差事。阿吉里先生极其慷慨，同意让她和我们住在一起，并且答应给她一笔丰厚的奁资，使她能嫁个好人家。请相信我，亲爱的朋友，不管别人怎么说，婚姻仍是女人最实在的职业。于是，考虑到女儿的幸福，我毫不犹豫地接受了阿吉里先生的求婚，即使牺牲某种满足也在所不惜——再说，一年一年地过去，这种满足愈来愈不容易获得了。有一点我必须告诉你：一旦结婚，我将绝对恪守妇道（dune vertu farouche[195]）。根据多年的经验，我深信夫妻双方必须绝对忠实，才能使幸福的婚姻固若金汤。”

“这是多么崇高的情操啊，我的美人儿！”我说，“阿吉里先生还会和从前一样每两个星期来一趟巴黎洽谈生意吗？”

“哎呀呀，你把我当成傻瓜了不成，我的小宝贝？阿吉里先生向我求婚，我提的第一个条件就是：‘亲爱的，请听我说，你来巴黎开董事会，我也跟着来。让你一个人来，我是不放心的。’他回答说：‘请放心，我都这把岁数了，不会做出蠢事来的。’我则说：‘阿吉里先生，你正当生命力旺盛的年龄，我比谁都清楚你充满了激情，而且相貌堂堂、气宇轩昂，举手投足都让女人动心。总而言之，我怕你经不起诱惑。’最后，他答应把董事会的位置让给儿子，由儿子代替他来巴黎开会。阿吉里先生假装不快，好像我不通情理似的，其实心里像灌了蜜一样甜。”说到此处，苏姗娜满足地长出了一口气，“对我们可怜的女人来说，假如男人没有这种难以捉摸的虚荣心，日子就如雪上加霜。”

“这样的结局非常好。但这和你在迈耶海姆画廊办个人画展有什么联系呢？”

“我可怜的朋友，今天你可真是有点不开窍了。多少年来我不是告诉你，说阿吉里先生是一个聪明绝顶的人吗？他得考虑自己的社会地位，得考虑里尔的人喜欢评头论足。他是个重要人物，而我作为他法定的妻子，按他的愿望应该在社会上占有一席之地。你也知道外省人的那种德行，他们喜欢管别人的闲事。他们势必会问，苏姗娜·鲁维埃是何许人？他们将得到这样的回答：‘苏姗娜·鲁维埃是一位出类拔萃的画家，最近在迈耶海姆画廊的个人画展取得了巨大成功，真是实至名归。’‘苏姗娜·鲁维埃是殖民步兵团一位军官的遗孀，多年靠卖画为生，含辛茹苦抚养一个早早便丧失父爱的娇女，表现出了一个法国妇女的刚毅性格。令人快慰的是，善于发现人才的迈耶海姆画廊将为她举办个人画展，公众不久便可大饱眼福，欣赏到她细腻的笔触和娴熟的技法。’”

“这是胡扯些什么呀？”我竖着耳朵听后，启口问道。

“亲爱的，这是阿吉里先生设计的广告语，将会在法国的各大报纸登出。他做事滴水不漏。迈耶海姆提的条件非常苛刻，但阿吉里先生却认为是小事一桩，予以全盘接受。画展的开幕式上，将会喝香槟酒表示庆祝，美术部长（此人欠阿吉里先生的人情）将要发表精彩的致辞，将会盛赞我作为女人的情操以及作为艺术家的天赋，最后宣布国家有责任、有义务奖励人才，已经买下我的一幅画由国家收藏。巴黎各界人士都将到场。迈耶海姆将亲自关照那些评论家，确保他们的评论文章不仅要大加赞誉，而且篇幅要长。评论家们是很可怜的，挣的钱实在太少了。给他们一个捞外快的机会，也算是积德行善了。”

“这都是你应该得到的，亲爱的，”我说道，“好人有好报嘛。”

“Et ta soeur[196]，”她答道，这句话很难翻译，“还不止这些呢。阿吉里先生又用我的名字在圣拉斐尔海边买了一幢别墅，这样，我在里尔的社交界便有了自己的位置，一是因为我是个杰出的艺术家，二是由于我还是个有产业的女人。再过两三年他就要退休了，那时，我们将像上流人士（comme des gens bien[197]）那样在里维埃拉住下去。他可以在海上划船、捕捞海虾，我则专心于艺术创作。我先让你看看我的画再说吧。”

苏姗娜画画已有多年。深受诸多画家情人的影响，她广采众长，最后形成了自己独特的风格。她的线条仍画不好，但色彩感相当强。她让我看了几幅风景画，有一幅是她随母亲在昂儒省居住时画的，一幅画的是凡尔赛宫花园的小景，一幅画的是枫丹白露森林，还有一幅画的是巴黎近郊她所喜欢的街景。她的画朦朦胧胧，似海市蜃楼，却有一种鲜花般的美和一种非刻意雕琢的雅致。我对其中的一幅画产生了兴趣，同时为了取悦她，便提出想花钱买下。记不清那幅画是叫《林间空地》还是叫《白围巾》，时至今日也弄不清名称。我问了价钱，要价也很合理，于是决定购买。

“你真是个天使！”她乐得叫出了声，“这是我的第一笔交易。当然，画展结束后你才能拿到手。我要让此事上报纸，说你买下了这幅画。反正造造声势对你也没有害处嘛。很高兴你选中了这一幅——它恐怕是我最得意的作品了。”她拿起一面镜子，从镜子里端详这幅画。“很有情调，”她一边眯起眼睛欣赏一边说道，“这是谁都否认不了的。这几块绿色青翠欲滴，多么精致呀！中间点一笔白色，起到了画龙点睛的作用，将全部画面连接为一个整体。这不是才气是什么？！毫无疑问，这是地地道道的才气。”

看得出来，她朝着专业画家目标已走出了很远。

“哎呀，我的小宝贝，咱们聊得太久了，我得赶快干活去了。”

“我也得走了。”我说。

“顺带问一句[198]，那个可怜的拉里是不是仍然和那些红皮肤的人在一起？”

每次提到神的国度里的居民，她总是喜欢用这种鄙薄的口气。

“据我所知，情况的确如此。”

“拉里和蔼可亲、温文尔雅，他那种人和野蛮人在一起处境一定很艰难。如果电影里的情节可信的话，那些土匪、牛仔和墨西哥人可不是好惹的。倒不是说牛仔缺乏让你动心的吸引力。哎呀呀，可是，你上纽约的大街上去，口袋里不藏把枪，好像是极其危险的。”

她把我送到门口，在我的两颊上吻了吻。

“你我相处，开开心心的。日后多想着我点。”

六

我讲的故事到这里就结束了。拉里那边音讯全无，其实我也没指望能听到他的消息。他历来我行我素，由着自己的性子干事。想必他回到阔别多年的美国，先是在汽车修理厂找了份工作干，后来便当了个卡车司机四处跑，直至把这个国家了解个透。这一目标实现之后，他很可能会把他那奇怪的想法付诸实施——开出租车。那原本是在和我喝咖啡时开玩笑的一句话，但他如果当真做起来，我一点都不会感到稀奇。那以后我每次在纽约搭乘出租车，都要把司机扫一眼，想着说不定会看见拉里的那双深陷的庄重而含笑的眼睛，却始终没有看见过。后来第二次世界大战爆发，他年龄太大，当不成飞行员，但他很可能又去开卡车了，在国内或海外运输物资，要不然就是进工厂做工，尽自己的一份力量。有了闲暇时间，他很可能会著书立传，讲述自己的人生经验，向自己的同胞传经送宝。不过，对他而言，要完成一部书稿得花很长的时间。反正他有的是时间——岁月在他的身上没有留下印痕，不管从哪一方面说，他都仍然是个青年。

他没有野心，无意追名逐利。要他蝇营狗苟以成为社会名流，只会叫他大倒胃口。他按自己选择的道路生活，心安理得、随遇而安。他是个谦谦君子，不图为人之榜样。但他觉得可能有一些人会受到他的感召，和他具有同样炽热的激情和信仰——人生最大的满足感只能在精神生活中获取。他无私无欲、严于律己，走的是一条不断完善自我的道路，对旁人产生的影响无异于著书立传或传经布道。

我毕竟是个凡夫俗子，对于他的胸怀只能揣度一二。对于普通的饮食男女，我还是比较了解的。但对于拉里这样光彩夺目的人之翘楚，我只有敬仰的份儿，他之情怀及内心世界却不甚了了。拉里如其所愿，融入了喧嚣激荡的人海中——这茫茫的人海为错综复杂的利益和矛盾所纠缠，迷失于风雨飘摇的大世界，人们渴望美好的生活，外表笃定而内心彷徨，有善者也有恶者，有守财奴也有仗义疏财者。这，就是美利坚合众国的人民！关于拉里的故事，我只能讲这许多了，深知不足，却也只好如此了。完稿后，我觉得读者阅读此书，可能会迷茫，对故事的主旨有些摸不着头脑，于是便将这部长篇小说重温一遍，看能不能设计一个令人满意一点的结局。这一重温不当紧，我突然有所感悟，万分惊讶地发现，我虽无写“成功”之意，但此书却的确是一部关于“成功”的小说。书中跟我有关的主人公无不如愿以偿——艾略特成为社交界名流；伊莎贝尔有雄厚的经济基础，在一个生机勃勃、文化气氛浓郁的社区占有稳固的一席之地；格雷找到一个稳定而赚钱的职业，早晨九点上班，下午六点下班；苏姗娜·鲁维埃过上了衣食无忧的日子；索菲以死亡解脱；拉里寻觅到了幸福的归宿。那些自命不凡的人也许会吹毛求疵，但普通大众打心眼里还是喜欢“成功”小说的。就这一点而论，本故事的结局还算令人称心吧。

The sharp edge of a razor is difficult to pass over；

thus the wise say the path to Salvation is hard.

——KATHA UPANISHAD

CHAPTER TWO

1

I did not see Elliott till he came to London towards the end of June in the following year. I asked him whether Larry had after all gone to Paris.He had.I was faintly amused at Elliott's exasperation with him.

“I had a kind of sneaking sympathy for the boy. I couldn't blame him for wanting to spend a couple of years in Paris and I was prepared to launch him.I told him to let me know the moment he arrived, but it was only when Louisa wrote and told me he was there that I knew he'd come.I wrote to him care of the American Express, which was the address she gave me, and asked him to come and dine to meet some of the people I thought he ought to know；I thought I'd try him out first with the Franco-American set, Emily de Montadour and Gracie de Château-Gaillard and so on, and d’you know what he answered?He said he was sorry he couldn’t come, but he hadn’t brought any evening clothes with him，”

Elliott looked me full in the face to see the stupefaction with which he expected this communication to fill me. He raised a supercilious eyebrow when he observed that I took it with calm.

“He replied to my letter on a sheet of nasty paper with the heading of a café in the Latin Quarter and when I wrote back I asked him to let me know where he was staying.I felt I must do something about him for Isabel’s sake, and I thought perhaps he was shy-I mean I couldn’t believe that any young fellow in his senses could come to Paris without evening clothes, and in any case there are tolerable tailors there, so I asked him to lunch and said it would be quite a small party, and would you believe it, not only did he ignore my request to give me some other address than the American Express, but he said he never ate luncheon.That finished him as far as I was concerned.”

“I wonder what he's been doing with himself.”

“I don't know, and to tell you the truth I don't care. I'm afraid he's a thoroughly undesirable young man and I think it would be a great mistake for Isabel to marry him.After all, if he led a normal sort of life I'd have run across him at the Ritz bar or at Fouquet’s or somewhere.”

I go sometimes to these fashionable places myself, but I go to others also, and it happened that I spent several days in Paris early in the autumn of that year on my way to Marseilles, where I was proposing to take one of the Messagerie ships for Singapore. I dined one evening with friends in Montparnasse and after dinner we went to the Dôme to drink a glass of beer.Presently my wandering eye caught sight of Larry sitting by himself at a little marble-topped table on the crowded terrace.He was looking idly at the people who strolled up and down enjoying the coolness of the night after a sultry day.I left my party and went up to him.His face lit up when he saw me and he gave me an engaging smile.He asked me to sit down, but I said I couldn’t as I was with a party.

“I just wanted to say how d'you do to you，”I said.

“Are you staying here?”he asked.

“Only for a very few days.”

“Will you lunch with me tomorrow?”

“I thought you never lunched.”

He chuckled.

“You've seen Elliott. I don't generally.I can't afford the time, I just have a glass of milk and a brioche, but I'd like you to lunch with me.”

“All right.”

We arranged to meet at the Dôme next day to have an apéritif and eat at some place on the boulevard.I rejoined my friends.We sat on talking.When next I looked for Larry he had gone.

2

I spent the next morning very pleasantly. I went to the Luxembourg and passed an hour looking at some pictures I liked.Then I strolled in the gardens, recapturing the memories of my youth.Nothing had changed.They might have been the same students who walked along the gravel paths in pairs, eagerly discussing the writers who excited them.They might have been the same children who trundled the same hoops under the watchful eyes of the same nurses.They might have been the same old men who basked in the sunshine, reading the morning paper.They might have been the same middle-aged women in mourning who sat on the free benches and gossiped with one another about the price of food and the misdeeds of servants.Then I went to the Odéon and looked at the new books in the galleries and I saw the lads who like myself thirty years before were trying under the petulant eyes of the smock-frocked attendants to read as much as they could of books they could not afford to buy.Then I strolled leisurely along those dear, dingy streets till I came to the Boulevard du Montparnasse and so to the Dôme.Larry was waiting.We had a drink and walked along to a restaurant where we could lunch in the open air.

He was perhaps a little paler than I remembered him and this made his very dark eyes, in their deep orbits, more striking；but he had the same self-possession, curious in one so young, and the same ingenuous smile. When he ordered his lunch I noticed that he spoke French fluently and with a good accent.I congratulated him on it.

“I knew a certain amount of French before, you know，”he explained.“Aunt Louisa had a French governess for Isabel, and when they were at Marvin she used to make us talk French with her all the time.”

I asked him how he liked Paris.

“Very much.”

“D'you live in Montparnasse?”

“Yes，”he said, after a moment's hesitation which I interpreted into a disinclination to tell exactly where he lived.

“Elliott was rather put out that the only address you gave was the American Express.”

Larry smiled but did not answer.

“What do you do with yourself all the time?”

“I loaf.”

“And you read?”

“Yes, I read.”

“Do you ever hear from Isabel?”

“Sometimes. We're neither of us great letter-writers.She's having a grand time in Chicago.They're coming over next year to stay with Elliott.”

“That'll be nice for you.”

“I don't believe Isabel's ever been to Paris. It'll be fun taking her around.”

He was curious to know about my journey in China and listened attentively to what I told him；but when I tried to get him to talk about himself, I failed. He was so uncommunicative that I was forced to the conclusion that he had asked me to lunch with him merely to enjoy my company.I was pleased, but baffled.We had no sooner finished our coffee than he called for the bill, paid it, and got up.

“Well, I must be off，”he said.

We parted. I knew no more of what he was up to than before.I did not see him again.

3

I was not in Paris in the spring when, sooner than they had planned, Mrs. Bradley and Isabel arrived to stay with Elliott；and again I have to eke out my knowledge or what passed during the few weeks they spent there by the exercise of my imagination.They landed at Cherbourg, and Elliott, always considerate, went to meet them.They passed through the customs.The train started.Elliott with some complacency told them that he had engaged a very good lady's maid to look after them and when Mrs.Bradley said that was quite unnecessary, since they didn't need one, he was very sharp with her.

“Don't be tiresome the moment you arrive, Louisa. No one can be well turned out without a maid, and I've engaged Antoinette not only for your sake and Isabel's but for mine.It would mortify me that you shouldn't beperfectly dressed.”

He gave the clothes they were wearing a disparaging glance.

“Of course you'll want to buy some new frocks. On mature consideration I've come to the conclusion that you can't do better than Chanel.”

“I always used to go to Worth，”said Mrs. Bradley.

She might as well not have spoken, for he took no notice.

“I've talked to Chanel myself and I've made an appointment for you tomorrow at three. Then there are hats.Obviously Reboux.”

“I don't want to spend a lot of money, Elliott.”

“I know. I am proposing to pay for everything myself.I'm determined that you shall be a credit to me.Oh, and Louisa, I've arranged several parties for you and I've told my French friends that Myron was an ambassador, which, of course, he would have been if he'd lived a little longer, and it makes a better effect.I don't suppose it’ll come up, but I thought I’d better warn you.”

“You're ridiculous, Elliott.”

“No, I'm not. I know the world.I know that the widow of an ambassador has more prestige than the widow of a minister.”

As the train steamed into the Gare du Nord, Isabel, who was standing at the window, called out：

“There's Larry.”

It had hardly stopped when she sprang out and ran to meet him. He threw his arms around her.

“How did he know you were coming?”Elliott asked his sister acidly.

“Isabel wirelessed him from the ship.”

Mrs. Bradley kissed him affectionately, and Elliott gave him a limp hand to shake.It was ten o'clock at night.

“Uncle Elliott, can Larry come to lunch tomorrow?”cried Isabel, her arm in the young man's, her face eager and her eyes shining.

“I should be charmed, but Larry has given me to understand that he doesn't eat lunch.”

“He will tomorrow, won't you, Larry?”

“I will，”he smiled.

“I shall look forward to seeing you at one o'clock then.”

He stretched out his hand once more, intending to dismiss him, but Larry grinned at him impudently.

“I'll help with the luggage and get a cab for you.”

“My car is waiting and my man will see to the luggage，”said Elliott with dignity.

“That's fine. Then all we've got to do is to go.If there's room for me I'll come as far as your door with you.”

“Yes, do, Larry，”said Isabel.

They walked down the platform together, followed by Mrs. Bradley and Elliott.Elliott's face bore a look of frigid disapproval.

“Quelles manières，”he said to himself, for in certain circumstances he felt he could express his sentiments more forcibly in French.

Next morning at eleven, having finished dressing, for he was not an early riser, he sent a note to his sister, via his man Joseph and her maid Antoinette, to ask her to come to the library so that they could have a talk. When she appeared he closed the door carefully and, putting a cigarette into an immensely long agate holder, lit it and sat down.

“Am I to understand that Isabel and Larry are still engaged?”he asked.

“So far as I know.”

“I'm afraid I haven't a very good account to give you of the young man.”He told her then how he had been prepared to launch him in society and the plans he had made to establish him in a fit and proper manner.“I even had my eye on a rez-de-chaussée that would have been the very thing for him.It belongs to the young Marquis de Rethel and hewanted to sublet it because he’d been appointed to the embassy at Madrid.”

But Larry had refused his invitations in a manner that made it quite clear that he did not want his help.

“What the object of coming to Paris is if you're not going to take advantage of what Paris has to give you is beyond my comprehension. I don't know what he does with himself.He doesn't seem to know anybody.Do you know where he lives?”

“The only address we've ever had is the American Express.”

“Like a travelling salesman or a school-teacher on vacation. I shouldn't be surprised if he was living with some little trollop in a studio in Montmartre.”

“Oh, Elliott.”

“What other explanation can there be for the mystery he's making of his dwelling place and for his refusal to consort with people of his own class?”

“It doesn't sound like Larry. And last night, didn't you get the impression that he was just as much in love with Isabel as ever?He couldn't be so false.”

Elliott by a shrug of the shoulders gave her to understand that there was no limit to the duplicity of men.

“What about Gray Maturin?Is he still in the picture?”

“He'd marry Isabel tomorrow if she'd have him.”

Mrs. Bradley told him then why they had come to Europe sooner than they had at first intended.She had found herself in ill-health, and the doctors had informed her that she was suffering from diabetes.It was not serious, and by attention to her diet and taking moderate doses of insulin there was no reason why she should not live for a good many years, but the knowledge that she had an incurable disease made her anxious to see Isabel settled.They had talked the matter over.Isabel was sensible.She had agreed that if Larry refused to come back to Chicago at the end of the two years in Paris they had agreed upon and get a job, there was only one thing to do and that was to break with him.But it offended Mrs.Bradley's sense of personal dignity that they should wait till the appointed time and then come to fetch him, like a fugitive from justice, back to his own country.She felt that Isabel would put herself in a humiliating position.But it was very natural that they should spend the summer in Europe, where Isabel had not been since she was a child.After their visit in Paris they could go to some watering-place suitable to Mrs.Bradley's complaint, then on to the Austrian Tyrol for a while and from there travel slowly through Italy.Mrs.Bradley's intention was to ask Larry to accompany them, so that he and Isabel could see whether the long separation had left their feelings unchanged.It would be manifest in due course whether Larry, having had his fling, was prepared to accept the responsibilities of life.

“Henry Maturin was sore with him for turning down the position he offered him, but Gray has talked him round, and he can go into the business the moment he comes back to Chicago.”

“Gray's a very nice fellow.”

“He certainly is.”Mrs. Bradley sighed.“I know he'd make Isabel happy.”

Elliott then told her what parties he had arranged for them. He was giving a big luncheon on the following day and at the end of the week a grand dinner party.He was taking them to a reception at the Château-Gaillards and he had got cards for them to a ball that the Rothschilds were giving.

“You'll ask Larry, won't you?”

“He tells me he hasn't any evening clothes，”Elliott sniffed.

“Well, ask him all the same. After all, he is a nice boy, and it wouldn't help to give him the cold shoulder.It would only make Isabel obstinate.”

“Of course I'll ask him if you wish it.”

Larry came to lunch at the appointed time, and Elliott, whose manners were admirable, was pointedly cordial to him. It was not difficult, since Larry was so gay, in such high spirits that it would have needed a much more ill-natured man than Elliott not to be charmed with him.The conversation dealt with Chicago and their common friends there, so that there was not much for Elliott to do other than to look amiable and pretend to be interested in the concerns ofpersons whom he thought of no social consequence.He did not mind listening；indeed, he thought it rather touching to hear them tell of this young couple's engagement, that young couple's marriage, and another young couple's divorce.Who had ever heard of them?He knew that the pretty little Marquise de Clinchant had tried to poison herself because her lover, the Prince de Colombey, had left her to marry the daughter of a South American millionaire.That was something to talk about.Looking at Larry, he was obliged to admit that there was something peculiarly attractive in him；with his deep-set strangely black eyes, his high cheekbones, pale skin, and mobile mouth he reminded Elliott of a portrait by Botticelli, and it occurred to him that if he were dressed in the costume of the period he would look extravagantly romantic.He remembered his notion of getting him off with a distinguished Frenchwoman and he smiled slyly on reflecting that he was expecting at dinner on Saturday Marie Louise de Florimond, who combined irreproachable connexions with notorious immorality.She was forty, but looked ten years younger；she had the delicate beauty of her ancestress painted by Nattier which, owing to Elliott himself, now hung in one of the great American collections；and her sexual voracity was insatiable.Elliott decided to put Larry next to her.He knew she would waste no time in making her desires clear to him.He had already invited a young attaché at the British embassy whom he thought Isabel might like.Isabel was very pretty, and as he was an Englishman, and well off, it wouldn’t matter that she had no fortune.Mellowed by the excellent Montrachet with which they had started lunch and by the fine Bordeaux that followed, Elliott thought with tranquil pleasure of the possibilities that presented themselves to his mind.If things turned out as he thought they very well might, dear Louisa would have no more cause for anxiety.She had always slightly disapproved of him；poor dear, she was very provincial；but he was fond of her.It would be a satisfaction to him to arrange everything for her by help of his knowledge of the world.

To waste no time, Elliott had arranged to take his ladies to look at clothes immediately after lunch, so as they got up from table he intimated to Larry with the tact of which he was a master that he must make himself scarce, but at the same time he asked him with pressing affability to come to the two grand parties he had arranged. He need hardly have taken so much trouble, since Larry accepted both invitations with alacrity.

But Elliott's plan failed. He was relieved when Larry appeared at the dinner party in a very presentable dinner-jacket, for he had been a little nervous that he would wear the same blue suit that he had worn at lunch；and after dinner, getting Marie Louise de Florimond into a corner, he asked her how she had liked his young American friend.

“He has nice eyes and good teeth.”

“Is that all?I put him beside you because I thought he was just your cup of tea.”

She looked at him suspiciously.

“He told me he was engaged to your pretty niece.”

“Voyons, ma chère, the fact that a man belongs to another woman has never prevented you from taking him away from her if you could.”

“Is that what you want me to do?Well, I'm not going to do your dirty work for you, my poor Elliott.”

Elliott chuckled.

“The meaning of that, I presume, is that you tried your stuff and found there was nothing doing.”

“Why I like you, Elliott, is that you have the morals of a bawdy-house keeper. You don't want him to marry your niece.Why not?He is well bred and quite charming.But he's really too innocent.I don't think he had the least suspicion of what I meant.”

“You should have been more explicit, dear friend.”

“I have enough experience to know when I'm wasting my time. The fact is that he has eyes only for your little Isabel, and between you and me, she has twenty years advantage over me.And she's sweet.”

“Do you like her dress?I chose it for her myself.”

“It's pretty and it's suitable. But of course she has no chic.”

Elliott took this as a reflection on himself, and he was not prepared to let Madame de Florimond get away without a dig. He smiled genially.

“One has to have reached your ripe maturity to have your chic, dear friend，”he said.

Madame de Florimond wielded a bludgeon rather than a rapier. Her retort made Elliott's Virginian blood boil.

“But I'm sure that in your fair land of gangsters[votre beau pays d'apaches]they will hardly miss something that is so subtle and so inimitable.”

But if Madame de Florimond carped, the rest of Elliott's friends were delighted both with Isabel and with Larry. They liked her fresh prettiness, her abounding health, and her vitality；they liked his picturesque appearance, his good manners, and his quiet, ironic humour.Both had the advantage of speaking good and fluent French.Mrs.Bradley, after living so many years in diplomatic circles, spoke it correctly enough but with an unabashed American accent.Elliott entertained them lavishly.Isabel, pleased with her new clothes and her new hats, amused by all the gaiety Elliott provided, and happy to be with Larry, thought she had never enjoyed herself so much.

4

Elliott was of opinion that breakfast was a meal that you should share only with total strangers, and then only if there was no help for it, so Mrs. Bradley, somewhat against her will, and Isabel, far from displeased, were obliged to have theirs in their bedrooms.But Isabel, when she awoke, sometimes told Antoinette the grand maid Elliott had engaged for them, to take her café au lait into her mother’s room so that she could talk to her while she had it.In the busy life she led it was the only moment of the day in which she could be alone with her.One such morning, when they had been in Paris nearly a month, after Isabel had done narrating the events of the previous night, most of which she and Larry had spent going the rounds of the night clubs with a party of friends, Mrs.Bradley let fall the question she had had in mind to ask ever since their arrival.

“When is he coming back to Chicago?”

“I don't know. He hasn't spoken of it.”

“Haven't you asked him?”

“No.”

“Are you scared to?”

“No, of course not.”

Mrs. Bradley, lying on a chaise longue, in a modish dressing-gown that Elliott had insisted on giving her, was polishing her nails.

“What do you talk about all the time when you're alone?”

“We don't talk all the time. It's nice to be together.You know, Larry was always rather silent.When we talk I think I do most of the talking.”

“What has he been doing with himself?”

“I don't really know. I don't think anything very much.I suppose he's been having a good time.”

“And where is he living?”

“I don't know that either.”

“He seems very reticent, doesn't he?”

Isabel lit a cigarette and, as she blew a cloud of smoke from her nostrils, looked coolly at her mother.

“What exactly do you mean by that, Mamma?”

“Your uncle Elliott thinks he has an apartment and is living there with a woman.”

Isabel burst out laughing.

“You don't believe that, do you?”

“No. I honestly don't.”Mrs.Bradley looked reflectively at her nails.“Don't you ever talk to him about Chicago?”

“Yes, a lot.”

“Hasn't he given any sort of indication that he intends to come back?”

“I can't say he has.”

“He will have been gone two years next October.”

“I know.”

“Well, it's your business, dear, and you must do what you think right. But things don't get any easier by putting them off.”She glanced at her daughter, but Isabel would not meet her eyes.Mrs.Bradley gave her an affectionate smile.“If you don't want to be late for lunch you'd better go and have your bath.”

“I'm lunching with Larry. We're going to some place in the Latin Quarter.”

“Enjoy yourself.”

An hour later Larry came to fetch her. They took a cab to the Pont St.Michel and sauntered up the crowded boulevard till they came to a café they liked the look of.They sat down on the terrace and ordered a couple of Dubonnets.Then they took another cab and went to a restaurant.Isabel had a healthy appetite and she enjoyed the good things Larry ordered for her.She enjoyed looking at the people sitting cheek by jowl with them, for the place was packed, and it made her laugh to see the intense pleasure they so obviously took in their food；but she enjoyed above all sitting at a tiny table alone with Larry.She loved the amusement in his eyes while she chattered away gaily.It was enchanting to feel so much at home with him.But at the back of her mind was a vague disquiet, for though he seemed very much at home too, she felt it was not so much with her as with the surroundings.She had been faintly disturbed by what her mother had said, and though seeming to prattle so guilelessly she observed his every expression.He was not quite the same as when he had left Chicago, but she couldn’t tell in what the difference lay.He looked exactly as she remembered him, as young, as frank, but his expression was changed.It was not that he was more serious, his face in repose had always been serious, it had a calmness that was new to her；it was as though he had settled something with himself and were at ease in a way he had never been before.

When they had finished lunch he suggested that they should take a stroll through the Luxembourg.

“No, I don't want to go and look at pictures.”

“All right then, let's go and sit in the gardens.”

“No, I don't want to do that either. I want to go and see where you live.”

“There's nothing to see. I live in a scrubby little room in a hotel.”

“Uncle Elliott says you've got an apartment and are living in sin with an artist's model.”

“Come on then and see for yourself，”he laughed.“It's only a step from here. We can walk.”

He took her through narrow, tortuous streets, dingy notwithstanding the streak of blue sky that showed between the high houses, and after a while stopped at a small hotel with a pretentious façade.

“Here we are.”

Isabel followed him into a narrow hall, on one side of which was a desk and behind it a man in shirt-sleeves, with a waistcoat in thin black and yellow stripes and a dirty apron, reading a paper. Larry asked for his key, and the man handed it to him from the rack immediately behind him.He gave Isabel an inquisitive glance that turned into a knowing smirk.It was clear that he thought she was going to Larry's room for no honest purpose.

They climbed up two flights of stairs, on which was a threadbare red carpet, and Larry unlocked his door. Isabel entered a smallish room with two windows.They looked out on the grey apartment house opposite, on the ground floor of which was a stationer's shop.There was a single bed in the room, with a night table beside it, a heavy wardrobe with a large mirror, an upholstered but straight-backed armchair, and a table between the windows on which were a typewriter, papers, and a number of books.The chimney-piece was piled with paper-bound volumes.

“You sit in the armchair. It's not very comfortable, but it's the best I can offer.”

He drew up another chair and sat down.

“Is this where you live?”asked Isabel.

He chuckled at the look on her face.

“It is. I've been here ever since I came to Paris.”

“But why?”

“It's convenient. It's near the Bibliothèque Nationale and the Sorbonne.”He pointed to a door she had not noticed.“It’s got a bathroom.I can get breakfast here and I generally dine at that restaurant where we had lunch.”

“It's awfully sordid.”

“Oh no, it's all right. It's all I want.”

“But what sort of people live here?”

“Oh, I don't know. Up in the attics a few students.Two or three old bachelors in government offices and a retired actress at the Odéon；the only other room with a bath is occupied by a kept woman whose gentleman friend comes to see her every other Thursday；I suppose a few transients.It’s a very quiet and respectable place.”

Isabel was a trifle disconcerted and because she knew Larry noticed it and was amused she was half inclined to take offence.

“What's that great big book on the table?”she asked.

“That?Oh, that's my Greek dictionary.”

“Your what?”she cried.

“It's all right. It won't bite you.”

“Are you learning Greek?”

“Yes.”

“Why?”

“I thought I'd like to.”

He was looking at her with a smile in his eyes and she smiled back at him.

“Don't you think you might tell me what you've been up to all the time you've been in Paris?”

“I've been reading a good deal. Eight or ten hours a day.I've attended lectures at the Sorbonne.I think I've read everything that's important in French literature and I can read Latin, at least Latin prose, almost as easily as I can read French.Of course Greek's more difficult.But I have a very good teacher.Until you came here I used to go to him three evenings a week.”

“And what is that going to lead to?”

“The acquisition of knowledge，”he smiled.

“It doesn't sound very practical.”

“Perhaps it isn't and on the other hand perhaps it is. But it's enormous fun.You can't imagine what a thrill it is to read the Odyssey in the original.It makes you feel as if you had only to get on tiptoe and stretch out your hands to touch the stars.”

He got up from his chair, as though impelled by an excitement that seized him, and walked up and down the small room.

“I've been reading Spinoza the last month or two. I don't suppose I understand very much of it yet, but it fills me with exultation.It's like landing from your plane on a great plateau in the mountains.Solitude, and an air so pure that it goes to your head like wine and you feel like a million dollars.”

“When are you coming back to Chicago?”

“Chicago?I don't know. I haven't thought of it.”

“You said that if you hadn't got what you wanted after two years you'd give it up as a bad job.”

“I couldn't go back now. I'm on the threshold.I see vast lands of the spirit stretching out before me, beckoning, and I'm eager to travel them.”

“What do you expect to find in them?”

“The answers to my questions.”He gave her a glance that was almost playful, so that except that she knew him so well, she might have thought he was speaking in jest.“I want to make up my mind whether God is or God is not. I want to find out why evil exists.I want to know whether I have an immortal soul or whether when I die it's the end.”

Isabel gave a little gasp. It made her uncomfortable to hear Larry say such things, and she was thankful that he spoke so lightly, in the tone of ordinary conversation, that it was possible for her to overcome her embarrassment.

“But Larry，”she smiled.“People have been asking those questions for thousands of years. If they could be answered, surely they'd have been answered by now.”

Larry chuckled.

“Don't laugh as if I'd said something idiotic，”she said sharply.

“On the contrary I think you've said something shrewd. But on the other hand you might say that if men have been asking them for thousands of years it proves that they can't help asking them and have to go on asking them.Besides, it's not true that no one has found the answers.There are more answers than questions, and lots of people have found answers that were perfectly satisfactory for them.Old Ruysbroek for instance.”

“Who was he?”

“Oh, just a guy I didn't know at college，”Larry answered flippantly.

Isabel didn't know what he meant, but passed on.

“It all sounds so adolescent to me. Those are the sort of things sophomores get excited about and then when they leave college they forget about them.They have to earn a living.”

“I don't blame them. You see, I'm in the happy position that I have enough to live on.If I hadn't I'd have had to do like everybody else and make money.”

“But doesn't money mean anything to you?”

“Not a thing，”he grinned.

“How long d'you think all this is going to take you?”

“I wouldn't know. Five years.Ten years.”

“And after that?What are you going to do with all this wisdom?”

“If I ever acquire wisdom I suppose I shall be wise enough to know what to do with it.”

Isabel clasped her hands passionately and leant forwards in her chair.

“You're so wrong, Larry. You're an American.Your place isn't here.Your place is in America.”

“I shall come back when I'm ready.”

“But you're missing so much. How can you bear to sit here in a backwater just when we're living through the most wonderful adventure the world has ever known?Europe's finished.We're the greatest, the most powerful people in the world.We're going forward by leaps and bounds.We’ve got everything.It’s your duty to take part in the development of your country.You’ve forgotten, you don’t know how thrilling life is in America today.Are you sure you’re not doing this because you haven’t the courage to stand up to the work that’s before every American now?Oh, I know you’re working in a way, but isn’t it just an escape from your responsibilities?Is it more than just a sort of laborious idleness?What would happen to America if everyone shirked as you’re shirking?”

“You're very severe, honey，”he smiled.“The answer to that is that everyone doesn't feel like me. Fortunately for themselves, perhaps, most people are prepared to follow the normal course；what you forget is that I want to learn as passionately as-Gray, for instance, wants to make pots of money.Am I really a traitor to my country because I want to spend a few years educating myself?It may be that when I'm through I shall have something to give that people will be glad to take.It's only a chance, of course, but if I fail I shall be no worse off than a man who's gone into business and hasn’t made a go of it.”

“And what about me?Am I of no importance to you at all?”

“You're of very great importance. I want you to marry me.”

“When?In ten years?”

“No. Now.As soon as possible.”

“On what?Mamma can't afford to give me anything. Besides, she wouldn't if she could.She'd think it wrong to help you to live without doing anything.”

“I wouldn't want to take anything from your mother，”said Larry.“I've got three thousand a year. That's plenty in Paris.We could have a little apartment and a bonne à tout faire.We’d have such a lark, darling.”

“But, Larry, one can't live on three thousand a year.”

“Of course one can. Lots of people live on much less.”

“But I don't want to live on three thousand a year. There's no reason why I should.”

“I've been living on half that.”

“But how！”

She looked at the dingy little room with a shudder of distaste.

“It means I've got a bit saved up. We could go down to Capri for our honeymoon and then in the fall we'd go to Greece.I'm crazy to go there.Don't you remember how we used to talk about travelling all over the world together?”

“Of course I want to travel. But not like that.I don't want to travel second-class on steamships and put up at third-rate hotels, without a bathroom, and eat at cheap restaurants.”

“I went all through Italy last October like that. I had a wonderful time.We could travel all over the world on three thousand a year.”

“But I want to have babies, Larry.”

“That's all right. We'll take them along with us.”

“You're so silly，”she laughed.“D'you know what it costs to have a baby?Violet Tomlinson had one last year and she did it as cheaply as she could and it cost her twelve hundred and fifty. And what d'you think a nurse costs?”She grew more vehement as one idea after another occurred to her.“You're so impractical.You don't know what you’re asking me to do.I’m young, I want to have fun.I want to do all the things that people do.I want to go to parties, I want to go to dances, I want to play golf and ride horseback.I want to wear nice clothes.Can’t you imagine what it means to a girl not to be as well dressed as the rest of her crowd?D’you know what it means, Larry, to buy your friends’old dresses when they’re sick of them and be thankful when someone out of pity makes you a present of a new one?I couldn’t even afford to go to a decent hairdresser to have my hair properly done.I don’t want to go about in street-cars and omnibuses；I want to have my own car.And what d’you suppose I’d find to do with myself all day long while you were reading at the Library?Walk about the streets window-shopping or sit in the Luxembourg Garden seeing that my children didn’t get into mischief?We wouldn’t have any friends.”

“Oh, Isabel，”he interrupted.

“Not the sort of friends I'm used to. Oh yes, Uncle Elliott's friends would ask us now and then for his sake, but we couldn't go because I wouldn't have the clothes to go in, and we wouldn't go because we couldn’t afford to return their hospitality.I don’t want to know a lot of scrubby, unwashed people；I’ve got nothing to say to them and they’ve got nothing to say to me.I want to live, Larry.”She grew suddenly conscious of the look in his eyes, tender as it always was when fixed on her, but gently amused.“You think I’m silly, don’t you?You think I’m being trivial and horrid.”

“No, I don't. I think what you say is very natural.”

He was standing with his back to the fireplace, and she got up and went up to him so that they were face to face.

“Larry, if you hadn't a cent to your name and got a job that brought you in three thousand a year I'd marry you without a minute's hesitation. I'd cook for you, I'd make the beds, I wouldn’t care what I wore, I’d go without anything, I’d look upon it as wonderful fun, because I’d know that it was only a question of time and you’d make good.But this means living in a sordid beastly way all our lives with nothing to look forward to.It means that I should be a drudge to the day of my death.And for what?So that you can spend years trying to find answers to questions that you say yourself are insoluble.It’s so wrong.A man ought to work.That’s what he’s here for.That’s how he contributes to the welfare of the community.”

“In short it's his duty to settle down in Chicago and enter Henry Maturin's business. Do you think that by getting my friends to buy the securities that Henry Maturin is interested in I should add greatly to the welfare of the community?”

“There must be brokers and it's a perfectly decent and honourable way of earning a living.”

“You've drawn a very black picture of life in Paris on a moderate income. You know, it isn't really like that.One can dress very nicely without going to Chanel.And all the interesting people don't live in the neighbourhood of the Arc de Triomphe and the Avenue Foch.In fact few interesting people do, because interesting people generally don't have a lot of money.I know quite a number of people here, painters and writers and students, French, English, American, and what not, whom I think you'd find much more amusing than Elliott’s seedy marquises and long-nosed duchesses.You’ve got a quick mind and a lively sense of humour.You’d enjoy hearing them swap ideas across the dinner table even though the wine was only vin ordinaire and you didn’t have a butler and a couple of footmen to wait on you.”

“Don't be stupid, Larry. Of course I would.You know I'm not a snob.I'd love to meet interesting people.”

“Yes, in a Chanel dress. D'you think they wouldn't catch on to it that you looked upon it as a sort of cultured slumming?They wouldn't be at their ease, any more than you would, and you wouldn't get anything out of it except to tell Emily de Montadour and Gracie de Château-Gaillard afterwards what fun you’d had meeting a lot of weird bohemians in the Latin Quarter.”

Isabel slightly shrugged her shoulders.

“I dare say you're right. They're not the sort of people I've been brought up with.They're not the sort of people I have anything in common with.”

“Where does that leave us?”

“Just where we started. I've lived in Chicago ever since I can remember.All my friends are there.All my interests are there.I'm at home there.It's where I belong and it's where you belong.Mamma's ill and she’s never going to get any better.I couldn’t leave her even if I wanted to.”

“Does that mean that unless I'm prepared to come back to Chicago you don't want to marry me?”

Isabel hesitated. She loved Larry.She wanted to marry him.She wanted him with all the power of her senses.She knew that he desired her.She couldn't believe that when it came to a showdown he wouldn't weaken.She was afraid, but she had to risk it.

“Yes, Larry, that's just what it does mean.”

He struck a match on the chimney-piece, one of those old-fashioned French sulphur matches that fill your nostrils with an acrid odour, and lit his pipe. Then, passing her, he went over and stood by one of the windows.He looked out.He was silent for what seemed an endless time.She stood as she had stood before, when she was facing him, and looked in the mirror over the chimney-piece, but she did not see herself.Her heart was beating madly and she was sick with apprehension.He turned at last.

“I wish I could make you see how much fuller the life I offer you is than anything you have a conception of. I wish I could make you see how exciting the life of the spirit is and how rich in experience.It's illimitable.It's such a happy life.There's only one thing like it, when you're up in a plane by yourself, high, high, and only infinity surrounds you.You're intoxicated by the boundless space.You feel such a sense of exhilaration that you wouldn’t exchange it for all the power and glory in the world.I was reading Descartes the other day.The ease, the grace, the lucidity.Gosh！”

“But Larry，”she interrupted him desperately，“don't you see you're asking something of me that I'm not fitted for, that I'm not interested in and don't want to be interested in?How often have I got to repeat to you that I’m just an ordinary, normal girl. I’m twenty, in ten years I shall be old, I want to have a good time while I have the chance.Oh, Larry, I do love you so terribly.All this is just trifling.It’s not going to lead you anywhere.For your own sake I beseech you to give it up.Be a man, Larry, and do a man’s work.You’re just wasting the precious years that others are doing so much with.Larry, if you love me you won’t give me up for a dream.You’ve had your fling.Come back with us to America.”

“I can't, darling. It would be death to me.It would be the betrayal of my soul.”

“Oh, Larry, why d'you talk in that way?That's the way hysterical, highbrow women talk. What does it mean?Nothing.Nothing.Nothing.”

“It happens to mean exactly what I feel，”he answered, his eyes twinkling.

“How can you laugh?Don't you realize this is desperately serious?We've come to the cross-roads and what we do now is going to affect our whole lives.”

“I know that. Believe me, I'm perfectly serious.”

She sighed.

“If you won't listen to reason there's nothing more to be said.”

“But I don't think it's reason. I think you've been talking the most terrible nonsense all the time.”

“I?”If she hadn't been so miserable she would have laughed.“My poor Larry, you're as crazy as a coot.”

She slowly slipped her engagement ring off her finger. She placed it on the palm of her hand and looked at it.It was a square-cut ruby set in a thin platinum band and she had always liked it.

“If you loved me you wouldn't make me so unhappy.”

“I do love you. Unfortunately sometimes one can't do what one thinks is right without making someone else unhappy.”

She stretched out her hand on which the ruby was resting and forced a smile to her trembling lips.

“Here you are, Larry.”

“It's no good to me. Won't you keep it as a memento of our friendship?You can wear it on your little finger.Our friendship needn't stop, need it?”

“I shall always care for you, Larry.”“Then keep it. I should like you to.”

She hesitated for an instant, then put it on the finger of her right hand.

“It's too large.”

“You can have it altered. Let's go to the Ritz bar and have a drink.”

“All right.”

She was a trifle taken aback that it had all gone so easily. She had not cried.Nothing seemed to be changed except that now she wasn't going to marry Larry.She could hardly believe that everything was over and done with.She resented a little the fact that they hadn't had a terrific scene.They had talked it all over almost as coolly as though they had been discussing the taking of a house.She felt let down, but at the same time was conscious of a slight sense of satisfaction because they had behaved in such a civilized way.She would have given a lot to know exactly what Larry was feeling.But it was always difficult to know that；his smooth face, his dark eyes were a mask that she was aware even she, who had known him for so many years, could not penetrate.She had taken off her hat and laid it on the bed.Now, standing before the mirror, she put it on again.

“Just as a matter of interest，”she said, arranging her hair，“did you want to break our engagement?”

“No.”

“I thought it might be a relief to you.”He made no reply. She turned round with a gay smile on her lips.“Now I'm ready.”

Larry locked the door behind him. When he handed the key to the man at the desk he enveloped them both in a look of conniving archness.It was impossible for Isabel not to guess what he thought they had been up to.

“I don't believe that old fellow would bet much on my virginity，”she said.

They took a taxi to the Ritz and had a drink. They spoke of indifferent things, without apparent constraint, like two old friends who saw one another every day.Though Larry was naturally silent, Isabel was a talkative girl, with an ample fund of chit-chat, and she was determined that no silence should fall between them that might be hard to break.She wasn't going to let Larry think she felt any resentment towards him and her pride constrained her to act so that he should not suspect that she was hurt and unhappy.Presently she suggested that he should drive her home.When he dropped her at the door she said to him gaily：

“Don't forget that you're lunching with us tomorrow.”

“You bet your life I won't.”

She gave him her cheek to kiss and passed through the porte cochère.

5

When Isabel entered the drawing-room she found that some people had dropped in to tea. There were two American women who lived in Paris, exquisitely gowned, with strings of pearls round their necks, diamond bracelets on their wrists and costly rings on their fingers.Though the hair of one was darkly hennaed and that of the other unnaturally golden they were strangely alike.They had the same heavily mascaraed eyelashes, the same brightly painted lips, the same rouged cheeks, the same slim figures, maintained at the cost of extreme mortification, the same clear, sharp features, the same hungry restless eyes；and you could not but be conscious that their lives were a desperate struggle to maintain their fading charms.They talked with inanity in a loud, metallic voice without a moment's pause, as though afraid that if they were silent for an instant the machine would run down and the artificial construction which was all they were would fall to pieces.There was also a secretary from the American Embassy, suave, silent, for he could not get a word in, and very much the man of the world, and a small dark Rumanian prince, all bows and servility, with little darting black eyes and a clean-shaven swarthy face, who was for ever jumping up to hand a teacup, pass a plate of cakes, or light a cigarette, and who shamelessly dished out to those present the most flattering, the most gross compliments.He was paying for all the dinners he had received from the objects of his adulation and for all the dinners he hoped to receive.

Mrs. Bradley, seated at the tea table and dressed to please Elliott somewhat more grandly than she thought suitable to the occasion, performed her duties as hostess with her usual civil but rather indifferent composure.What she thought of her brother's guests I can only imagine.I never knew her more than slightly and she was a woman who kept herself to herself.She was not a stupid woman；in all the years she had lived in foreign capitals she had met innumerable people of all kinds and I think she summed them up shrewdly enough according to the standards of the small Virginian town where she was born and bred.I think she got a certain amount of amusement from observing their antics, and I don't believe she took their airs and graces any more seriously than she took the aches and pains of the characters in a novel which she knew from the beginning（otherwise she wouldn't have read it）would end happily.Paris, Rome, Peking had had no more effect on her Americanism than Elliott's devout Catholicism on her robust, but not inconvenient, Presbyterian faith.

Isabel, with her youth, her strapping good looks, and her vitality, brought a breath of fresh air into that meretricious atmosphere. She swept in like a young earth goddess.The Rumanian prince leapt to his feet to draw forward a chair for her and with ample gesticulation did his shift.The two American ladies, with shrill amiabilities on their lips, looked her up and down, took in the details of her dress, and perhaps in their hearts felt a pang of dismay at being confronted with her exuberant youth.The American diplomat smiled to himself as he saw how false and haggard she made them look.But Isabel thought they were grand；she liked their rich clothes and expensive pearls and felt a twinge of envy for their sophisticated poise.She wondered if she would ever achieve that supreme elegance.Of course the little Rumanian was quite ridiculous, but he was rather sweet and even if he didn't mean the charming things he said it was nice to listen to them.The conversation which her entrance had interrupted was resumed, and they talked so brightly, with so much conviction that what they were saying was worth saying, that you almost thought they were talking sense.They talked of the parties they had been to and the parties they were going to.They gossiped about the latest scandal.They tore their friends to pieces.They bandied great names from one to the other.They seemed to know everybody.They were in on all the secrets.Almost in a breath they touched upon the latest play, the latest dressmaker, the latest portrait painter, and the latest mistress of the latest premier.One would have thought there was nothing they didn't know.Isabel listened with ravishment.It all seemed to her wonderfully civilized.This really was life.It gave her a thrilling sense of being in the midst of things.This was real.The setting was perfect.That spacious room with the Savonnerie carpet on the floor, the lovely drawings on the richly-panelled walls, the petit-point chairs on which they sat, the priceless pieces of marquetry, commodes and occasional tables, every piece worthy to go into a museum；it must have cost a fortune, that room, but it was worth it.Its beauty, its discretion struck her as never before because she had still so vividly in her mind the shabby little hotel room, with its iron bed and that hard, comfortless chair in which he had sat, that room that Larry saw nothing wrong in.It was bare, cheerless, and horrid.It made her shudder to remember it.

The party broke up and Isabel was left with her mother and Elliott.

“Charming women，”said Elliott when he came back from seeing the two poor painted drabs to the door.“I knew them when they first settled in Paris. I never dreamt they'd turn out as well as they have.It's amazing, the adaptability of our women.You'd hardly know now they were Americans and Middle West into the bargain.”

Mrs. Bradley, raising her eyebrows, without speaking gave him a look which he was too quick-witted not to understand.

“No one could ever say that of you, my poor Louisa，”he continued half acidly and half affectionately.“Though heaven knows, you've had every chance.”

Mrs. Bradley pursed her lips.

“I'm afraid I've been a sad disappointment to you, Elliott, but to tell you the truth I'm very satisfied with myself as I am.”

“Tous les goûts sont dans la nature，”Elliott murmured.

“I think I ought to tell you that I'm no longer engaged to Larry，”said Isabel.

“Tut，”cried Elliott.“That'll put my luncheon table out for tomorrow. How on earth am I going to get another man at this short notice?”

“Oh, he's coming to lunch all right.”

“After you've broken off your engagement?That sounds very unconventional.”

Isabel giggled. She kept her gaze on Elliott, for she knew her mother's eyes were fixed upon her and she didn't want to meet them.

“We haven't quarrelled. We talked it over this afternoon and came to the conclusion we'd made a mistake.He doesn't want to come back to America；he wants to stop on in Paris.He's talking of going to Greece.”

“What on earth for?There's no society in Athens. As a matter of fact I never thought so much of Greek art myself.Some of that Hellenistic stuff has a certain decadent charm that's rather attractive.But Phidias：no, no.”

“Look at me, Isabel，”said Mrs. Bradley.

Isabel turned and with a faint smile on her lips faced her mother. Mrs.Bradley gave her a scrutinizing stare, but all she said was，“H'm.”The girl hadn't been crying, that she saw；she looked calm and composed.

“I think you're well out of it, Isabel，”said Elliott.“I was prepared to make the best of it, but I never thought it a good match. He wasn't really up to your mark, and the way he's been behaving in Paris is a pretty clear indication that he'll never amount to anything.With your looks and your connexions you can aspire to something better than that.I think you've behaved in a very sensible manner.”

Mrs. Bradley gave her daughter a glance that was not devoid of anxiety.

“You haven't done this on my account, Isabel?”

Isabel shook her head decidedly.

“No, darling, I've done it entirely on my own.”

6

I had come back from the East and was spending some time in London just then. It was perhaps a fortnight after the events I have just related that Elliott called me up one morning.I was not surprised to hear his voice, for I knew that he was in the habit of coming to England to enjoy the fag end of the season.He told me that Mrs.Bradley and Isabelwere with him and if I would drop in that evening at six for a drink they would be glad to see me.They were, of course, staying at Claridge's.I was at that time living not far from there, so I strolled down Park Lane and through the quiet, dignified streets of Mayfair till I came to the hotel.Elliott had his usual suite.It was panelled in brown wood like the wood of a cigar box and furnished with quiet sumptuousness.He was alone when I was ushered in.Mrs.Bradley and Isabel had gone shopping and he was expecting them at any minute.He told me that Isabel had broken her engagement to Larry.

Elliott with his romantic and highly conventional sense of how people should comport themselves under given circumstances had been disconcerted by the young people's behaviour. Not only had Larry come to lunch the very day after the break, but he had acted as though his position were unchanged.He was as pleasant, attentive, and soberly gay as usual.He treated Isabel with the same comradely affectionateness with which he had always treated her.He seemed neither harassed, upset, nor woebegone.Nor did Isabel appear dispirited.She looked as happy, she laughed as lightly, she jested as merrily as though she had not just taken a decisive and surely searing step in her life.Elliott could not make head or tail of it.From such scraps of their conversation as he caught he gathered that they had no intention of breaking any of the dates they had made.On the first opportunity he talked it over with his sister.

“It's not decent，”he said.“They can't run around together as if they were still engaged. Larry really should have more sense of propriety.Besides, it damages Isabel's chances.Young Fotheringham, that boy at the British Embassy, is obviously taken with her；he's got money and he's very well connected；if he knew the coast was clear I wouldn’t be at all surprised if he made her an offer, I think you ought to talk to her about it.”

“My dear, Isabel's twenty and she has a technique for telling you to mind your own business without offensiveness which I've always found very difficult to cope with.”

“Then you've brought her up extremely badly, Louisa. And besides, it is your business.”

“That is a point on which you and she would certainly differ.”

“You're trying my patience, Louisa.”

“My poor Elliott, if you'd ever had a grown-up daughter you'd know that by comparison a bucking steer is easy to manage. And as to knowing what goes on inside her-well, it's much better to pretend you're the simple, innocent old fool she almost certainly takes you for.”

“But you have talked the matter over with her?”

“I tried to. She laughed at me and told me there was really nothing to tell.”

“Is she cut up?”

“I wouldn't know. All I do know is that she eats well and sleeps like a child.”

“Well, take my word for it, if you let them go on like this they'll go off one of these days and get married without saying a word to anybody.”

Mrs. Bradley permitted herself to smile.

“It must be a relief to you to think that at present we're living in a country where every facility is afforded to sexual irregularity and every obstacle put in the way of marriage.”

“And quite rightly. Marriage is a serious matter on which rest the security of the family and the stability of the state.But marriage can only maintain its authority if extra-conjugal relations are not only tolerated but sanctioned.Prostitution, my poor Louisa—”

“That'll do, Elliott，'interrupted Mrs. Bradley.“I'm not interested in your views on the social and moral values of promiscuous fornication.”

It was then he put forward a scheme that would interrupt Isabel's continued intercourse with Larry, which was so repugnant to his sense of what was fitting. The Paris season was drawing to a close and all the best people were arranging to go to watering places or to Deauville before repairing for the rest of the summer to their ancestral châteaux in Touraine, Anjou, or Brittany.Ordinarily Elliott went to London at the end of June, but his family feeling was strong and his affection for his sister and Isabel sincere；he had been quite ready to sacrifice himself and remain in Paris, ifthey wished it, when no one who was anyone was there；but he found himself now in the agreeable situation of being able to do what was best for others and at the same time what was convenient to himself.He proposed to Mrs.Bradley that the three of them should go to London immediately, where the season was still in full swing and where new interests and new friends would distract Isabel’s mind from her unfortunate entanglement.According to the papers the great specialist on Mrs.Bradley’s disease was then in the British capital and the desirability of consulting him would reasonably account for their precipitate departure and override any disinclination to leave Paris that Isabel might have.Mrs.Bradley fell in with the plan.She was puzzled by Isabel.She could not make up her mind whether she was as carefree as she seemed or whether, hurt, angry, or heartsick, she was putting on a bold front to conceal her wounded feelings.Mrs.Bradley could only agree with Elliott that it would do Isabel good to see new people and new places.

Elliott got busy on the telephone and when Isabel, who had been spending the day at Versailles with Larry, came home, he was able to tell her that he had made an appointment for her mother to see the celebrated doctor three days from then, that he had engaged a suite at Claridge's and that they were starting on the next day but one. Mrs.Bradley watched her daughter while this intelligence was being somewhat smugly imparted to her by Elliott, but she did not turn a hair.

“Oh, darling, I'm so glad you're going to see that doctor，”she cried with her usual rather breathless impetuosity.“Of course, you mustn't miss the chance. And it'll be grand going to London.How long are we going to stay?”

“It would be useless to come back to Paris，”said Elliott.“There won't be a soul here in a week. I want you to stay with me at Claridge's for the rest of the season.There are always some good balls in July and of course there's Wimbledon.And then Goodwood and Cowes.I'm sure the Ellinghams will be glad to have us on their yacht for Cowes and the Bantocks always have a large party for Goodwood.”

Isabel appeared to be delighted and Mrs. Bradley was reassured.It looked as though she were not giving Larry a thought.

Elliott had just finished telling me all this when mother and daughter came in. I had not seen them for more than eighteen months.Mrs.Bradley was a little thinner than before and more pasty-faced；she looked tired and none too well.But Isabel was blooming.With her high colour, the rich brown of her hair, her shining hazel eyes, her clear skin, she gave an impression of such youth, of so much enjoyment of the mere fact of being alive, that you felt half inclined to laugh with delight.She gave me the rather absurd notion of a pear, golden and luscious, perfectly ripe and simply asking to be eaten.She radiated warmth so that you thought that if you held out your hands you could feel its comfort.She looked taller than when I had last seen her, whether because she wore higher heels or because the clever dressmaker had cut her frock to conceal her youthful plumpness I don't know, and she held herself with the graceful ease of a girl who has played outdoor games since childhood.She was in short sexually a very attractive young woman.Had I been her mother I should have thought it high time she was married.

Glad of the opportunity to repay some of the kindness I had received from Mrs. Bradley in Chicago, I asked them all three to come to a play with me one evening.I arranged to give a luncheon for them.

“You'll be wise to get in at once, my dear fellow，”said Elliott.“I've already let my friends know we're here and I presume that in a day or two we shall be fixed up for the rest of the season.”

I understood by this that Elliott meant that then they would have no time for the likes of me and I laughed. Elliott gave me a glance in which I discerned a certain hauteur.

“But of course you'll generally find us here about six o'clock and we shall always be glad to see you，”he said graciously, but with the evident intention of putting me, as an author, in my humble place.

But the worm sometimes turns.

“You must try to get in touch with the St. Olpherds，”I said.“I hear they want to dispose of their Constable of Salisbury Cathedral.”

“I'm not buying any pictures just now.”

“I know, but I thought you might dispose of it for them.”

A steely glitter came into Elliott's eyes.

“My dear fellow, the English are a great people, but they have never been able to paint and never will be able to paint. I am not interested in the English school.”

7

During the next four weeks I saw little of Elliott and his relations. He did them proud.He took them for a week-end to a grand house in Sussex and for another week-end to an even grander one in Wiltshire.He took them to the royal box at the opera as guests of a minor princess of the House of Windsor.He took them to lunch and dine with the great.Isabel went to several balls.He entertained at Claridge's a series of guests whose names made a fine show in the paper next day.He gave supper parties at Ciro's and the Embassy.In fact he did all the right things and Isabel would have had to be much more sophisticated than she was not to have been a trifle dazzled by the splendour and elegance he provided for her delectation.Elliott could flatter himself that he was taking all this trouble from the purely unselfish motive of distracting Isabel's mind from an unfortunate love affair；but I had a notion he got besides a good deal of satisfaction out of letting his sister see with her own eyes how familiar he was with the illustrious and fashionable.He was an admirable host and he took a delight in displaying his virtuosity.

I went to one or two of his parties myself and now and again I dropped in at Claridge's at six o'clock. I found Isabel surrounded by strapping young men in beautiful clothes who were in the Household Brigade or by elegant young men in less beautiful clothes from the Foreign Office.It was on one of these occasions that she drew me aside.

“I want to ask you something，”she said.“Do you remember that evening we went to a drugstore and had an ice-cream soda?”

“Perfectly.”

“You were very nice and helpful then. Will you be nice and helpful again?”

“I'll do my best.”

“I want to talk to you about something. Couldn't we lunch one day?”

“Almost any day you like.”

“Somewhere quiet.”

“What d'you say to driving down to Hampton Court and lunching there?The gardens should be at their best just now and you could see Queen Elizabeth's bed.”

The notion suited her and we fixed a day. But when the day came the weather, which had been fine and warm, broke；the sky was grey and a drizzling rain was falling.I called up and asked her if she wouldn't prefer to lunch in town.

“We shouldn't be able to sit in the gardens and the pictures will be so dark, we shan't see a thing.”

“I've sat in lots of gardens and I'm fed to the teeth with old masters. Let's go anyway.”

“All right.”

I fetched her and we drove down. I knew a small hotel where one ate tolerably and we went straight there.On the way Isabel talked with her usual vivacity of the parties she had been to and the people she had met.She had been enjoying herself, but her comments on various acquaintances she had made suggested to me that she had shrewdness and a quick eye for the absurd.The bad weather kept visitors away and we were the only occupants of the dining-room.The hotel specialized in homely English fare and we had a cut off a leg of excellent lamb with green peas and new potatoes and a deep-dish apple pie with Devonshire cream to follow.With a tankard of pale ale it made an excellent lunch.When we had finished I suggested that we should go into the empty coffee-room where there were armchairs in which we could sit in comfort.It was chilly in there, but the fire was laid, so I put a match to it.The flames made the dingy room more companionable.

“That's that，”I said.“Now tell me what you want to talk to me about.”

“It's the same as last time，”she chuckled.“Larry.”

“So I guessed.”

“You know that we've broken off our engagement.”

“Elliott told me.”

“Mamma's relieved and he's delighted.”

She hesitated for a moment and then embarked upon the account of her talk with Larry of which I have done my best faithfully to inform the reader. It may surprise the reader that she should have chosen to tell so much to someone whom she knew so little.I don't suppose I had seen her a dozen times and, except for that one occasion at the drugstore, never alone.It did not surprise me.For one thing, as any writer will tell you, people do tell a writer things that they don't tell others.I don't know why, unless it is that having read one or two of his books they feel on peculiarly intimate terms with him；or it may be that they dramatize themselves and, seeing themselves as it were as characters in a novel, are ready to be as open with him as they imagine the characters of his invention are.And I think that Isabel felt that I liked Larry and her, and that their youth touched me, and that I was sympathetic to their distresses.She could not expect to find a friendly listener in Elliott who was disinclined to trouble himself with a young man who had spurned the best chance a young man ever had of getting to society.Nor could her mother help her.Mrs.Bradley had high principles and common sense.Her common sense assured her that if you wanted to get on in this world you must accept its conventions, and not to do what everybody else did clearly pointed to instability.Her high principles led her to believe that a man's duty was to go to work in a business where by energy and initiative he had a chance of earning enough money to keep his wife and family in accordance with the standards of his station, give his sons such an education as would enable them on reaching man's estate to make an honest living, and on his death leave his widow adequately provided for.

Isabel had a good memory and the various turns of the long discussion had engraved themselves upon it. I listened in silence till she had finished.She only interrupted herself once to ask me a question.

“Who was Ruysdael?”

“Ruysdael?He was a Dutch landscape painter. Why?”

She told me that Larry had mentioned him. He had said that Ruysdael at least had found an answer to the questions he was asking, and she repeated to me his flippant reply when she had inquired who he was.

“What d'you suppose he meant?”

I had an inspiration.

“Are you sure he didn't say Ruysbroek?”

“He might have. Who was he?”

“He was a Flemish mystic who lived in the fourteenth century.”

“Oh，”she said with disappointment.

It meant nothing to her. But it meant something to me.That was the first indication I had of the turn Larry's reflection was taking, and while she went on with her story, though still listening attentively, part of my mind busied itself with the possibilities that reference of his had suggested.I did not want to make too much of it, for it might be that he had only mentioned the name of the Ecstatic Teacher to make an argumentative point；it might also have a significance that had escaped Isabel.When he answered her question by saying Ruysbroek was just a guy he hadn't known in college he evidently meant to throw her off the scent.

“What do you make of it all?”she asked when she had come to an end.

I paused before replying.

“D'you remember his saying that he was just going to loaf?If what he tells you is true his loafing seems to involve some very strenuous work.”

“I'm sure it's true. But don't you see that if he'd worked as hard at any productive form of work he'd be earning a decent income?”

“There are people who are strangely constituted. There are criminals who'll work like beavers to contrive schemes that land them in prison and they no sooner get out than they start all over again and again land in prison.If they put as much industry, as much cleverness, resource, and patience into honest practices they could make a handsome living and occupy important positions.But they're just made that way.They like crime.”

“Poor Larry，”she giggled.“You're not going to suggest that he's learning Greek to cook up a bank robbery.”

I laughed too.

“No, I'm not. What I'm trying to tell you is that there are men who are possessed by an urge so strong to do some particular thing that they can't help themselves, they've got to do it.They're prepared to sacrifice everything to satisfy their yearning.”

“Even the people who love them?”

“Oh, yes.”

“Is that anything more than plain selfishness?”

“I wouldn't know，”I smiled.

“What can be the possible use of Larry's learning dead languages?”

“Some people have a disinterested desire for knowledge. It's not an ignoble desire.”

“What's the good of knowledge if you're not going to do anything with it?”

“Perhaps he is. Perhaps it will be sufficient satisfaction merely to know, as it's a sufficient satisfaction to an artist to produce a work of art.And perhaps it's only a step towards something further.”

“If he wanted knowledge why couldn't he go to college when he came back from the war?It's what Dr. Nelson and Mamma wanted him to do.”

“I talked to him about that in Chicago. A degree would be of no use to him.I have an inkling that he had a definite idea of what he wanted and felt he couldn't get it at a university.You know, in learning there's the lone wolf as well as the wolf who runs in the pack.I think Larry is one of those persons who can go no other way than their own.”

“I remember once asking him if he wanted to write. He laughed and said he had nothing to write about.”

“That's the most inconclusive reason for not writing that I've ever heard，”I smiled.

Isabel made a gesture of impatience. She was in no mood even for the mildest jest.

“What I can't make out is why he should have turned out like this. Before the war he was just like everybody else.You wouldn't think it, but he plays a very good game of tennis and he's quite a decent golfer.He used to do all the things the rest of us did.He was a perfectly normal boy and there was no reason to suppose he wouldn't become a perfectly normal man.After all you're a novelist, you ought to be able to explain it.”

“Who am I to explain the infinite complexities of human nature?”

“That's why I wanted to talk to you today，”she added, taking no notice of what I said.

“Are you unhappy?”

“No, not exactly unhappy. When Larry isn't there I'm all right；it's when I'm with him that I feel so weak.Now it's just a sort of ache, like the stiffness you get after a long ride when you haven’t been on a horse for months；it’s not pain, it’s not at all unbearable, but you’re conscious of it.I shall get over it all right.I hate the idea of Larry making such a mess of his life.”

“Perhaps he won't. It's a long, arduous road he's starting to travel, but it may be that at the end of it he'll find what he's seeking.”

“What's that?”

“Hasn't it occurred to you?It seems to me that in what he said to you he indicated it pretty plainly. God.”

“God！”she cried. But it was an exclamation of incredulous surprise.Our use of the same word, but in such a different sense, had a comic effect, so that we were obliged to laugh.But Isabel immediately grew serious again and I felt in her whole attitude something like fear.“What on earth makes you think that?”

“I'm only guessing. But you asked me to tell you what I thought as a novelist.Unfortunately you don't know whatexperience he had in the war that so profoundly moved him.I think it was some sudden shock for which he was unprepared.I suggest to you that whatever it was that happened to Larry filled him with a sense of the transiency of life, and an anguish to be sure that there was a compensation for the sin and sorrow of the world.”

I could see that Isabel didn't like the turn I had given the conversation. It made her feel shy and awkward.

“Isn't all that awfully morbid?One has to take the world as it comes. If we're here, it's surely to make the most of life.”

“You're probably right.”

“I don't pretend to be anything but a perfectly normal, ordinary girl. I want to have fun.”

“It looks as though there were complete incompatibility of temper between you. It's much better that you should have found it out before marriage.”

“I want to marry and have children and live—”

“In that state of life in which a merciful Providence has been pleased to place you，”I interrupted, smiling.

“Well, there's no harm in that, is there?It's a very pleasant state and I'm quite satisfied with it.”

“You're like two friends who want to take their holiday together, but one of them wants to climb Greenland's icy mountains while the other wants to fish off India's coral strand. Obviously it's not going to work.”

“Anyway, I might get a sealskin coat off Greenland's icy mountains, and I think it's very doubtful if there are any fish off India's coral strand.”

“That remains to be seen.”

“Why d'you say that?”she asked, frowning a little.“All the time you seem to be making some sort of mental reservation. Of course I know that I'm not playing the star part in this.Larry's got that.He's the idealist, he's the dreamer of a beautiful dream, and even if the dream doesn’t come true, it’s rather thrilling to have dreamt it.I’m cast for the hard, mercenary, practical part.Common sense is never very sympathetic, is it?But what you forget is that it’s I who’d have to pay.Larry would sweep along, trailing clouds of glory, and all there’d be left for me would be to tag along and make both ends meet.I want to live.”

“I don't forget that at all. Years ago, when I was young, I knew a man who was a doctor, and not a bad one either, but he didn't practise.He spent years burrowing away in the library of the British Museum and at long intervals produced a huge pseudo-scientific, pseudo-philosophical book that nobody read and that he had to publish at his own expense.He wrote four or five of them before he died and they were absolutely worthless.He had a son who wanted to go into the army, but there was no money to send him to Sandhurst, so he had to enlist.He was killed in the war.He had a daughter too.She was very pretty and I was rather taken with her.She went on the stage, but she had no talent and she traipsed around the provinces playing small parts in second-rate companies at a miserable salary.His wife, after years of dreary, sordid drudgery, broke down in health and the girl had to come home and nurse her and take on the drudgery her mother no longer had the strength for.Wasted, thwarted lives and all to no purpose.It's a toss-up when you decide to leave the beaten track.Many are called but few are chosen.”

“Mother and Uncle Elliott approve of what I've done. Do you approve too?”

“My dear, what can that matter to you?I'm almost a stranger to you.”

“I look upon you as a disinterested observer，”she said, with a pleasant smile.“I should like to have your approval. You do think I've done right, don't you?”

“I think you've done right for you，”I said, fairly confident that she would not catch the slight distinction I made in my reply.

“Then why have I a bad conscience?”

“Have you?”

With a smile still on her lips, but a slightly rueful smile now, she nodded.

“I know it's only horse sense. I know that every reasonable person would agree that I've done the only possible thing.I know that from every practical standpoint, from the standpoint of worldly wisdom, from the standpoint ofcommon decency, from the standpoint of what's right and wrong, I've done what I ought to do.And yet at the bottom of my heart I've got an uneasy feeling that if I were better, if I were more disinterested, more unselfish, nobler, I’d marry Larry and lead his life.If I only loved him enough I’d think the world well lost.”

“You might put it the other way about. If he loved you enough he wouldn't have hesitated to do what you want.”

“I've said that to myself too. But it doesn't help.I suppose it's more in woman's nature to sacrifice herself than in a man's.”She chuckled.“Ruth and the alien corn and all that sort of thing.”

“Why don't you risk it?”

We had been talking quite lightly, almost as if we were having a casual conversation about people we both knew but in whose affairs we were not intimately concerned, and even when she narrated to me her talk with Larry, Isabel had spoken with a sort of breezy gaiety, enlivening it with humour, as if she did not want me to take what she said too seriously. But now she went pale.

“I'm afraid.”

For a while we were silent. A chill went down my spine as it strangely does when I am confronted with deep and genuine human emotion.I find it terrible and rather awe-inspiring.

“Do you love him very much?”I asked at last.

“I don't know. I'm impatient with him.I'm exasperated with him.I keep longing for him.”

Silence again fell upon us. I didn't know what to say.The coffee-room in which we sat was small, and heavy lace curtains over the window shut out the light.On the walls, covered with yellow marbled paper, were old sporting prints.With its mahogany furniture, its shabby leather chairs, and its musty smell, it was strangely reminiscent of a coffee-room in a Dickens novel.I poked the fire and put more coal on it.Isabel suddenly began to speak.

“You see, I thought when it came to a showdown he'd knuckle under. I knew he was weak.”

“Weak?”I cried.“What made you think that?A man who for a year withstood the disapproval of all his friends and associates because he was determined to go his own way.”

“I could always do anything I wanted with him. I could turn him round my little finger.He was never a leader in the things we did.He just tagged along with the crowd.”

I had lit a cigarette and watched the smoke ring I had made. It grew larger and larger and then faded away into the air.

“Mamma and Elliott thought it very wrong of me to go about with him afterwards as though nothing had happened, but I didn't take it very seriously. I kept on thinking up to the end that he'd yield.I couldn't believe that when he'd got it into his thick head that I meant what I said he wouldn't give in.”She hesitated and gave me a smile of roguish, playful malice.“Will you be awfully shocked if I tell you something?”

“I think it very unlikely.”

“When we decided to come to London I called Larry and asked him if we couldn't spend my last evening in Paris together. When I told them, Uncle Elliott said it was most improper and Mamma said she thought it unnecessary.When Mamma says something is unnecessary it means she thoroughly disapproves.Uncle Elliott asked me what the idea was and I said we were going to dine somewhere and then make a tour of the night clubs.He told Mamma she ought to forbid me to go.Mamma said，‘Will you pay any attention if I forbid you to go?'‘No, darling，'I said，‘none.'Then she said，‘That is what I imagined.In that case there doesn't seem to be much point in my forbidding it.’”

“Your mother appears to be a woman of enormous sense.”

“I don't believe she misses much. When Larry called for me I went into her room to say good night to her.I'd made up a bit；you know, you have to in Paris or else you look so naked, and when she saw the dress I had on, I had an uneasy suspicion from the way she took me in from top to toe that she had a pretty shrewd idea what I was after.But she didn't say anything.She just kissed me and said she hoped I'd have a good time.”

“What were you after?”

Isabel looked at me doubtfully, as though she couldn't quite decide how frank she was prepared to be.

“I didn't think I was looking too bad and it was my last chance. Larry had reserved a table at Maxim's.We had lovely things to eat, all the things I particularly liked, and we had champagne.We talked our heads off, at least I did, and I made Larry laugh.One of the things I've liked about him is that I can always amuse him.We danced.When we'd had enough of that we went on to the Château de Madrid.We found some people we knew and joined them and we had more champagne.Then we all went to the Acacia.Larry dances quite well, and we fit.The heat and the music and the wine-I was getting a bit light-headed.I felt absolutely reckless.I danced with my face against Larry’s and I knew he wanted me.God knows I wanted him.I had an idea.I suppose it had been at the back of my mind all the time.I thought I’d get him to come home with me and once I’d got him there, well, it was almost inevitable that the inevitable should happen.”

“Upon my word you couldn't put it more delicately.”

“My room was quite a way from Uncle Elliott's and Mamma's, so I knew there was no risk. When we were back in America I thought I'd write and say I was going to have a baby.He'd be obliged to come back and marry me, and when I'd got him home I didn’t believe it would be hard to keep him there, especially with Mamma ill.‘What a fool I am not to have thought of that before，’I said to myself.‘Of course that’ll settle everything.’When the music stopped I just stayed there in his arms.Then I said it was getting late and we had to take the train at noon, so we’d better go.We got into a taxi.I nestled close to him and he put his arms around me and kissed me.He kissed me, he kissed me-oh, it was heaven.It hardly seemed a moment before the taxi stopped at the door.Larry paid it.

“‘I shall walk home，'he said.

“The taxi rattled off and I put my arms round his neck.

“‘Won't you come up and have one last drink?'I said.

“‘Yes, if you like，'he said.

“He'd rung the bell and the door swung open. He switched on the light as we stepped in.I looked into his eyes.They were so trusting, so honest, so-so guileless；he so obviously hadn't the smallest idea that I was laying a trap for him；I felt I couldn't play him such a dirty trick.It was like taking candy off a child.D'you know what I did?I said，‘Oh well, perhaps you'd better not.Mamma’s not very well tonight and if she’s fallen asleep I don’t want to wake her up.Good night.’I put my face up for him to kiss and pushed him out of the door.That was the end of that.”

“Are you sorry?”I asked.

“I'm neither pleased nor sorry. I just couldn't help myself.It wasn't me that did what I did.It was just an impulse that took possession of me and acted for me.”She grinned.“I suppose you'd call it my better nature.”

“I suppose you would.”

“Then my better nature must take the consequences. I trust in the future it'll be more careful.”

That was in effect the end of our talk. It may be that it was some consolation to Isabel to have been able to speak to someone with entire freedom, but that was all the good I had been able to do her.Feeling I had been inadequate, I tried to say at least some small thing that would give her comfort.

“You know, when one's in love，”I said，“and things go all wrong, one's terribly unhappy and one thinks one won't ever get over it. But you'll be astounded to learn what the sea will do.”

“What do you mean?”she smiled.

“Well, love isn't a good sailor and it languishes on a sea voyage. You'll be surprised when you have the Atlantic between you and Larry to find how slight the pang is that before you sailed seemed intolerable.”

“Do you speak from experience?”

“From the experience of a stormy past. When I suffered from the pangs of unrequited love I immediately got on an ocean liner.”

The rain showed no sign of letting up, so we decided that Isabel could survive without seeing the noble pile of Hampton Court or even Queen Elizabeth's bed, and drove back to London. I saw her two or three times after that, but only when other people were present, and then, having had enough of London for a while, I set off for the Tyrol.